<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>mental Archives - Serve and Volley Tennis</title>
	<atom:link href="/tag/mental/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/tag/mental/</link>
	<description>Your secret weapon on the court.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 11 Jul 2019 12:20:49 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	

<image>
	<url>/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/cropped-ted_svt_favicon-32x32.png</url>
	<title>mental Archives - Serve and Volley Tennis</title>
	<link>/tag/mental/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>Mental Toughness In Tennis – 9 Easy Ways To Conquer Your Fears</title>
		<link>/mental-toughness-in-tennis-9-easy-ways-to-conquer-your-fears/</link>
					<comments>/mental-toughness-in-tennis-9-easy-ways-to-conquer-your-fears/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chad Walner]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 16 Nov 2018 14:58:32 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Theory]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mental]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1338</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Tennis is the type of game that requires a sound mind to win. Being mostly an individual sport, the mind can often make or break a player. With no teammates to rely on, the tennis player is left bare, exposed &#8230; <a class="kt-excerpt-readmore" href="/mental-toughness-in-tennis-9-easy-ways-to-conquer-your-fears/" aria-label="Mental Toughness In Tennis – 9 Easy Ways To Conquer Your Fears">Read More</a></p>
<p>The post <a href="/mental-toughness-in-tennis-9-easy-ways-to-conquer-your-fears/">Mental Toughness In Tennis – 9 Easy Ways To Conquer Your Fears</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Tennis is the type of game that requires a sound mind to win. Being mostly an individual sport, the mind can often make or break a player. With no teammates to rely on, the tennis player is left bare, exposed to battle his mental demons at every turn.</p>
<p>The mental side of tennis has been discussed endlessly. We’ve seen professional players crumble under pressure like sand castles washed over by a raging tide. On a world stage, we’ve witnessed this time and again on the mens&#8217; and womens&#8217; professional tours.</p>
<p>We’ve also seen players rise to the occasion with ice in their veins. These players are seemingly impervious to distractions, getting the job done under the most difficult circumstances. We marvel at these players and herald them as heroes.</p>
<p><strong>Building up a sound mind that is determined and disciplined takes time. While physical prowess comes and goes, the mind is the one thing in tennis you can always control. Your outlook, expectations and mindset are entirely determined by you alone.</strong></p>
<p>In this post, you’ll learn 9 easy ways to maximize your mental prowess in tennis. These tips will strengthen your mental resolve and better your play.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Stay Positive</h2>
<p><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" class="alignright wp-image-1358 size-full" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/agree-2952558_960_720.jpg" alt="" width="400" height="413" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/agree-2952558_960_720.jpg 400w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/11/agree-2952558_960_720-291x300.jpg 291w" sizes="(max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" />When playing a match, you’ll undoubtedly be faced with adversity. When it hits you, you’ll need to deal with it effectively. Doing so will give you the best odds of winning the match.</p>
<p>The most effective way to deal with adversity is to stay positive. Staying positive means positive self-talk and positive body language. I know this is easier said than done, but it’s entirely possible.</p>
<p>The next time you go into a match, try to be positive on every point, from beginning to end no matter what. You’ll notice a big difference in your outlook and play afterwards.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>You can remain positive by not criticizing yourself for mistakes. Instead let go of them and constantly repeat positive phrases to yourself. You also need to stand tall in your posture and avoid moping, sulking, and other negative body language.</p>
<p>I know this is a tall task for some people, but the more you practice it, the easier it will become. When I first started playing tennis, I was not very positive at all. I was John McEnroe without any talent.</p>
<p>However, once I began to shift into being a positive person and player, the differences were so stark that I realized it was the only way going forward. Today, even if I’m playing my worst, I stay positive knowing that it will afford me the greatest chance of winning the match.</p>
<p>The next time you play a match, go into it with a positive mind set. Even if it’s totally against how you usually think, it can’t hurt to try. You may just be surprised at the results.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Avoid Distractions</h2>
<p>This is a big mental demon that many tennis players suffer from. While it’s true tennis players are more finicky than most other athletes about surrounding conditions, those distractions need to be put out of mind to win.</p>
<p>Any time you play tennis, there will always be distractions. Those distractions come in two forms. Either they are internal, as in something negative in your personal life. Or they are external and happening during play – such as noise, bad weather, others playing next to you, etc.</p>
<p>If you really want to win in tennis, you need to be single-mindedly focused and in the present. Thinking about personal situations (internal distractions) during play will only hinder your performance.</p>
<p>This is where meditation can be very helpful. By meditating on one thing only, you can train your mind to block out all distractions.</p>
<p>Meditation can also be applied on the tennis court. By training my mind through meditation, I’m so focused during my matches, I totally forget about everything else in my life. I feel like I’m completely immersed in tennis when I play. It really does work.</p>
<p>External distractions are different, as they are typically unexpected. Sometimes you never quite know how the weather will be, who will be playing next to you, or what kind of noises will be present during the match.</p>
<p>Through the years, I’ve experienced a lot on the tennis court. I’ve seen strong-minded players block out the toughest of distractions. And I’ve also seen weak-minded players driven to tears over the smallest of distractions. Who do you think plays better?</p>
<p>Before your next match, resolve to leave internal distractions at home. And when you arrive to the court, make a deal with yourself that just for this match, you’re not going to pay any attention to external distractions. If you don’t see a positive difference in your play afterwards, I’d be surprised.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Hit The Delete Button</h2>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1363" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/photo-1538758414587-f5e9255b9a13.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/photo-1538758414587-f5e9255b9a13.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/11/photo-1538758414587-f5e9255b9a13-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/11/photo-1538758414587-f5e9255b9a13-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" />When playing a match, mistakes are inevitable. Sometimes those mistakes are forced by our opponent and we can’t be too hard on ourselves for that. But sometimes they’re unforced and just blatantly bad shots on our part.</p>
<p>When we hit a bad shot, we can’t be hard on ourselves either. Instead we need to “hit the delete button” and forget about it. A friend of mine, named Leon, (who I play doubles with) always tells me to “hit the delete button” after I make a bad shot.</p>
<p>At first this seems like it could be difficult to do. Some people really like to hark on their mistakes and use negative self-talk and body language to reinforce their errors. Does McEnroe come to mind? However, I find that most mistakes are technical and cannot be easily corrected during a match.</p>
<p>As a result, it’s best to accept your mistakes and forget about them. We’re all trying our best on the tennis court. 99 percent of us are not professional players who have the time to practice every day. Realize that tennis is a difficult sport and mistakes are part of the game.</p>
<p>Once you understand that, you can let go of them and move on. The worst-case scenario of making too many mistakes, is you lose the match. In the grand scheme of your life, one lost match at the club level is not very important.</p>
<p>By putting mistakes or losses into that context, it’s easier to let them go. Additionally, you’re bound to play better the next point if you forget the previous one.</p>
<p>This took me a while to learn, but it’s so true. Only focus on the point at hand. By “hitting the delete button” I was able to raise my game and feel better while I played. I recommend you do the same. Thanks, Leon.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Sportsmanship</h2>
<p>While winning is the primary goal of competitive athletes, many recreational players compete for the fun and exercise. When bad sportsmanship creeps into match play no matter what the intentions are, it ruins the experience for everyone.</p>
<p>For this reason, good sportsmanship should be a part of your play in every match. This means, not antagonizing other players or boasting of your play. It also means not cheating or arguing over close calls.</p>
<p>I play in a very competitive singles league, and I see bad sportsmanship every week, as well as good sportsmanship from time-to-time. It always seems like the same players are either good sportsman or bad sportsman. And there’s a reason for it.</p>
<p>If you’re a bad sport, people see that. Those people will judge you negatively and won’t want to include you in future matches or social events. Additionally, they’ll view you as a cheater, sore loser, and complainer.</p>
<p>I know some of you are very competitive and want to win badly but do it inside the rules and protocols of tennis. Remember, if you ostracize yourself, you’ll have a very small pool of players to hit with. If you consistently vex people with your attitude and actions, nobody will want to play with you.</p>
<p>If you watch the top professional players in the world like Rafael Nadal and Roger Federer, you’ll see that 99% of the time they hold themselves to the highest value of good sportsmanship. It’s not a coincidence they’re also the best players.</p>
<p>A great player doesn’t need to do all the things bad sportsman do to win a match. The great player wins because of his ability alone. Resorting to bad sportsmanship is a dead-end road that only fosters negativity and poor play.</p>
<p>During future matches, resolve to give the benefit of doubt to your opponent on close line calls, especially on their side of the court &#8211; where it’s truly their call. Don’t say things to your opponent that will incite them, and don’t play mind games.</p>
<p>Petty tricks like that are best left in other sports, not tennis. Let your tennis be pure. Be the better man or woman on the court. The other players will respect and like you a lot more.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Pre-Game Routine</h2>
<p>Pre-game routines are used by many professional athletes across all sports. By doing the same things before every match, it creates an atmosphere of comfortability and soothes the nerves.</p>
<p>Pre-match routines also put you into the right mind-frame for a match. By performing the same rituals repeatedly before you play, your mind automatically switches into a competitive mode. It’s like Pavlov’s dog experiment. A stimulus produces a conditioned response.</p>
<p>Players like Rafael Nadal use the pregame ritual to psych themselves up and control their environment. By limiting the variables that happen just before and during a match, athletes like Nadal can more easily stay focused on the competition and avoid distractions.</p>
<p>An example of pre-match routine is packing your tennis bag the same way for every match. Others might include stretching a certain way, visualizing the match, or even eating the same food.<br />
These habits or rituals provide a feeling of comfort before the stress of the match. Such rituals also increase confidence. The reason is simple. Previous such routines led to winning. Therefore, present and future routines will lead to winning as well.</p>
<p>If you don’t currently use a pre-match routine, try to create one for yourself. It doesn’t need be complex. I like to pack my tennis bag the same way, warm up in the same way, and wear the same clothes (I have several of the same sneakers, socks, shirts, and shorts).</p>
<p>By the time I start playing a match, I feel comfortable and in the right mind-set for competitive play. Pre-match routines eliminate randomness and distractions, so if you don’t currently use one, I highly recommend starting one.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Focus In Between Points</h2>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1361" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/photo-1531323386183-43890b5c766d.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/photo-1531323386183-43890b5c766d.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/11/photo-1531323386183-43890b5c766d-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/11/photo-1531323386183-43890b5c766d-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p>When playing a match, there’s often more time in between points and games then actual time playing. While focusing during the actual point is critical for success, how and what you focus on between points is just as important.</p>
<p>I already mentioned staying positive and putting errors out of mind. So what should a player think about between points? What’s best to focus on during these junctures to provide the best chances of winning?</p>
<p>I personally focus on one of three different things. First is positive self-talk/visualization. Second, I think about strategy. And third, I use a meditation technique where I focus all my attention on one object (like the strings of my racket).</p>
<p>I’ll elaborate on each one so they’re clear. I’ll say this first. You can select one of these techniques and stick with it for the whole match. Or you may decide to vary them during play. Either will work fine.</p>
<p>During those moments between points, positive self-talk and visualization are great ways to spend your time. They make you feel better about your game and keep you on the right track.</p>
<p>In my own experience, I clearly play better when engaging in positive self-talk and visualization. Keep in mind, these are only tools to be used between points. While playing points, you must be in the moment, reacting and responding with a still mind.</p>
<p>The second technique is to think about strategy. By doing so, you reinforce your game plan. You can also boost confidence, knowing you have a good battle plan to follow.</p>
<p>During the heat of battle, it’s easy to lose sight of the plan. This is especially true for one-on-one sports like tennis. For this reason, it’s good to draw up a plan of attack before the match and focus on it between points and games.</p>
<p>The last mental technique I use is more like a pure meditation. I’ll pick one object to look at (like my tennis strings) and eliminate all other thoughts. This keeps my mind centered and still, which usually carries over into the point.</p>
<p>I first learned of this one in college. My college coach mentioned it to me and I saw other players doing it. Often they would adjust their strings will meditating on them.<br />
Give these proven techniques a try the next time you’re in a match. At the least, use positive self-talk during the match. This alone will improve your results without doing anything more.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Anchors</h2>
<p>An anchor is a particular action a player performs to trigger a specific feeling. For example, a fist pump, a beating of the chest, or a raising a finger to the sky are all actions that produce corresponding feelings.</p>
<p>I’ll use Nadal as another example. Often before matches he’ll do a host of OCD type things, capping it off with a sprint from the net to the baseline. I’m sure these things pump him up for the coming contest. At this point, you may be wondering how this differs from a pregame ritual?</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignright size-full wp-image-1365" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/anchor-tattoo-designs-28.jpg" alt="" width="400" height="400" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/anchor-tattoo-designs-28.jpg 400w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/11/anchor-tattoo-designs-28-150x150.jpg 150w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/11/anchor-tattoo-designs-28-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" />The pregame ritual is done exclusively before the match begins. An anchor can be used any time before or during the match. For example, when playing a match, an anchor could be a certain word or phrase you say to yourself that triggers strong emotions. Or it might be a physical action you do, like clapping your hands or holding your racket in a certain way. Anchors need to be programmed before use. I’ll elaborate on this soon.</p>
<p>As a personal example of an anchor, when I’m facing adversity in a match and I need motivation and energy, I tell myself, “I’m the best” and I tap my chest twice with a closed fist.</p>
<p>Sometimes I’ll speak the words out loud to myself. Other times I internalize them. My opponent often has no idea I am performing an anchor. The anchor immediately elicits a strong emotion in me that I use to play better. It also raises my energy levels.</p>
<p>All anchors need to be correlated with an experience or feeling. Otherwise they are just empty actions and ineffective. For example, my anchor correlates with hard work and difficult practice sessions.</p>
<p>Every time I practice hard and put in the work, I’ll perform my anchor (tell myself “I’m the best” and tap my chest twice). When I then execute the anchor during the match, it harkens memories of my very hard practice sessions.</p>
<p>That then triggers a positive cascade of thoughts.</p>
<ul>
<li>The first one is, “I worked hard to prepare for this match, so there’s no question of my conditioning or work ethic.” Check.</li>
<li>The second is that my competitor probably hasn’t worked as hard as me, so I therefore deserve the win. Check.</li>
<li>The last thought I have is that I will prevail, and my opponent will fade down the stretch. Check.</li>
</ul>
<p>Using this anchor has proved to be surprisingly effective for me against competition around my level.</p>
<p>Just by using an anchor alone, you’ll be a leg up on the competition. Most of your opponents don’t even know what an anchor is. Try creating your own and use it during the match. See how powerful it can be!</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Win or Lose – Play Your Best</h2>
<p>This one could have easily been titled “focus on the process, not the results”. If you want to play your best tennis, you must be willing to let go of the idea of winning.</p>
<p>I know it sounds contradictory to success, but it will take the pressure off during the match. If you are so tied up in winning or losing, you’ll certainly be tight and not play your best.</p>
<p>Instead your goal during the match should be to play your best on every shot. To play your best, you need your body to be loose and free-flowing. Instead of tightening up and controlling the ball, you’re better off hitting out and taking the risk of making mistakes.</p>
<p>If you make too many mistakes during the match, just realize your technique is the culprit. You’ll need to improve your technique (during practice, not during the match) to cut down on those mistakes. You can still hit out on the ball during matches if you add more spin and less drive to keep it in play.</p>
<p>I often see club level players berating themselves after mistakes. Soon after, they are playing as tight as a drum, afraid to make more mistakes. What these players don’t understand is that their technique is the main issue. The sad part is they never work to correct their technique and so they’re play never improves.</p>
<p>Playing tight may win you a match here or there, but in the long run you’ll never reach your potential. If you watch the professional players, you’ll see them hitting out on every ball no matter if it’s the first point of the match or the last.</p>
<p>It used to surprise me that the pros would simply go for every shot, even when facing match point. I couldn’t understand why they wouldn’t hit softer and keep the ball in play? The answer is when you reach a certain level of play, controlling the ball to win doesn’t work.</p>
<p>Believe me, I’ve been playing at the 4.5-5.0 level for a long time. I can tell you that controlling the ball and keeping it in play by hitting safely does not work against good players. It’s even more so at the pro level. Imagine trying to play safely against a guy like Dominic Thiem? He’d rip your head off!</p>
<p>While this mental strategy is good for adults, it’s especially pertinent to children and beginners. Children are in a phase where they’re developing their games physically and technique-wise. Beginners are in a development stage too. Thinking only about winning should be way off the radar of young and beginner players.</p>
<p>Such players should focus exclusively on their technique and their growth. Matches should be viewed as intense practice sessions, where winning or losing makes no difference. This is the way all great players started.</p>
<p>The next time you play a match, think about the worst thing that will happen if you lose. Nobody really cares if you win or lose. And hardly anyone is going to remember the score weeks, months, or years later.</p>
<p>Just go out and play your best game and forget about the score. Try it for at least one match and see how it makes a difference in your play. Keep in mind, you’re not playing carelessly. You’re playing care-free &#8211; and that’s a big difference.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Be Accountable</h2>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignright wp-image-1373 size-full" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/accountable.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/accountable.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/11/accountable-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/11/accountable-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p>Everyone in this world has an ego. We all have our ups and downs and want people to view us in the best possible light. For this reason, we often don’t like to take the blame for things – even if they’re our fault.</p>
<p>It’s the same in tennis when we lose. It’s so easy to blame distractions and other people rather than ourselves. For most people, it makes them feel better to place the blame on anything or anybody but themselves.</p>
<p>While this is a short-term strategy for feeling better, in the long term it hurts us. People who don’t take accountability for their actions are in denial of their flaws. And if you’re in denial of your flaws, you’ll never improve and grow up.</p>
<p>All great athletes and leaders take ownership of their mistakes and shortcomings. Only by doing so, can you honestly see them and begin to improve. All the great athletes in sports history took accountability of their play. When they spotted a weakness in their game, they immediate sought to work on it.</p>
<p>You should as well. The next time you lose a match, determine why you lost. Maybe it’s because of a weak second serve or a poor backhand. Whatever the reason, own up to it, take full responsibility for the loss, and resolve to work on your weakness.</p>
<p>This is the way of a mature individual and the only path to true growth as a player. Even if you have several weak points in your game, you need to own up them. If so, work on them all and seek to improve.</p>
<p>The point of playing tennis at the club/recreational level is to have fun, get exercise, socialize a bit, and become better. You’ll undoubtedly become a better person and player when you take full responsibility for all your losses while working to shore up the shortcomings.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Final Thoughts</h2>
<p>The mental side of sports and tennis is a huge component to their success. At the club level, your biggest priority should be on improving, not winning. By taking ownership of your faults and working on them, the winning will gradually take care of itself.</p>
<p>Don’t just read this post and do nothing. Use the information in here to enhance your game. Your mental framework is so important in tennis. Whatever the mind conceives, it achieves.<br />
Trust me, I’ve been there and done that when it comes to mind set in tennis. I know what works and what doesn’t after 25 years of play. I’ve also read Winning Ugly, The Inner Game of Tennis and Vic Braden’s Mental Tennis more times than I care to say.</p>
<p>Use the tips in this post to grow better – not just in tennis but in life. I can guarantee you they work. They sure have for me and for the thousands of athletes who’ve been using them through the years.</p>
<p>If you have any questions about the mental game of tennis, just ask me in the comment section below. Thanks for reading!</p>
<p>The post <a href="/mental-toughness-in-tennis-9-easy-ways-to-conquer-your-fears/">Mental Toughness In Tennis – 9 Easy Ways To Conquer Your Fears</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/mental-toughness-in-tennis-9-easy-ways-to-conquer-your-fears/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>4</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>How To Truly Master The Mental Game Of Tennis</title>
		<link>/how-to-truly-master-the-mental-game-of-tennis/</link>
					<comments>/how-to-truly-master-the-mental-game-of-tennis/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chad Walner]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 15 Sep 2018 07:40:22 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Theory]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mental]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=252</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>You’ve heard that old cliche many times in sports: it’s 10% physical and 90% mental. To me, those numbers look lopsided. I believe you need both in equal proportions to excel at your chosen sport, and tennis is no different. &#8230; <a class="kt-excerpt-readmore" href="/how-to-truly-master-the-mental-game-of-tennis/" aria-label="How To Truly Master The Mental Game Of Tennis">Read More</a></p>
<p>The post <a href="/how-to-truly-master-the-mental-game-of-tennis/">How To Truly Master The Mental Game Of Tennis</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>You’ve heard that old cliche many times in sports: it’s 10% physical and 90% mental. To me, those numbers look lopsided. I believe you need both in equal proportions to excel at your chosen sport, and tennis is no different.</p>
<p>It irks me when I see articles titled “The Secrets To Mastering The Mental Game”. I’ll tell you right now, there are no secrets – only common sense information you need to do and think about before every match.</p>
<p><strong>I’m going to show you how to truly master the mental game of tennis – and it comes from proper preparation, knowledge of yourself, knowledge of your opponent, past experience and adapting to conditions.</strong></p>
<p>Has anyone told you to “just be confident”? Have you noticed that this advice doesn’t work? Why? I believe it’s because confidence only comes from successful experiences. If you don’t have successful experiences, there can be no confidence. Small wins over time equate to confidence. Like building our physical skills, the mental game takes time to build as well. No secret tip is going to change your outlook overnight.</p>
<p>So how do we achieve small wins for yourself? It starts at the lower levels of our sport (tennis) and grows from there. Everyone starts at the bottom and works their way up. In this post I am going to reveal how to truly master your mental game, including my personal journey from virtual scrub to a player with over 1,000 wins under my belt coming at the college, club and tournament levels. This win amount spans 25 years.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Proper Preparation</h2>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-989" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/woman-hands-1207952_960_720.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/woman-hands-1207952_960_720.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/woman-hands-1207952_960_720-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/woman-hands-1207952_960_720-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p>Everything with the mental game starts with proper preparation. If you’re not physically prepared for battle, no amount of confidence, visualization or prayer will work. It should go without saying that you are playing regularly, practicing often and always thinking of ways to improve your game. If this is not the case, I’m afraid the rest of this post will not apply to you.</p>
<p>You see, physical preparation is a given in sports. If you consider yourself a player and care enough to improve your game (and you do or you wouldn’t be reading this article right now) then you’ll at least be willing to put in the hard work to maintain your conditioning and skills on the court. Right? If you are not doing this, then spend a month doing so, work your tail off, and then come back to this article and start from here.</p>
<p>When I started playing tennis, I had no lessons, no coach, no instructional youtube videos and no knowledge of how to hit a ball other than watching tennis on TV. I tried to learn tennis by watching the pros hit, but even after two years of playing my strokes were fair at best and technically flawed. I didn’t know proper footwork, how to construct points or the many things I know now. This caused a severe lack of confidence and I was unsure of myself on court.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Small Win</h2>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignright size-full wp-image-1175" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/IMG_0061smallwins.jpg" alt="" width="400" height="414" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/IMG_0061smallwins.jpg 400w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/IMG_0061smallwins-290x300.jpg 290w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" />When I was a junior in college, a buddy of mine convinced me to try out for my college tennis team (a division II school). I had never played on a tennis team before, much less a tennis tournament or an organized match. My entire tennis resume up until that point (I was 21-years old) was casually hitting the ball around with a few friends from time-to-time. I thought my buddy was crazy but he knew the coach and promised to get me into tryouts. He said the team lost several good players to graduation the previous semester and they could use me now. I really thought he was putting me on.</p>
<p>So my buddy walked me down to tryouts on the last day they were being held. I could see him pleading with the coach. After a minute. the coach reluctantly consented and allowed me to try out. I had to beat two players that day to make the team. I played each one and to my surprise won both quite easily. I thought for sure I was going to get creamed, but sometimes life surprises you.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>With that mission accomplished, the coach walked up to me and asked what size shirt I wear. “Medium,” I chirped. “You made the team. Our first match is Friday in Boston,” the coach told me. I again couldn’t believe I so easily beat those two guys. I did it purely by using my physical gifts of speed and stamina plus my dogged determination. I had forced them to miss over and over just by being consistent.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>The Will To Win</h2>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-282 alignleft" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/preparation.jpg" alt="" width="400" height="273" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/preparation.jpg 400w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/preparation-300x205.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" /></p>
<p>From my earliest childhood memories playing sports, I had no quit in me. I wanted to win at all costs. If I lost, I would cry and sulk all day. To this day, I haven’t met a single person in my 27 years of playing tennis that wanted to win more than I do. I know it sounds like hyperbole, but I’m willing to die on the court. That’s how passionate I am about tennis and winning.</p>
<p>I’ll do whatever it takes within the rules to ensure victory. In a way, and all by itself, that degree of thinking is true mental toughness – the ability to fight through pain and fear in the face of uncertainty to earn victory. But only a very small percentage of the population possesses it. You’ll find this mentality in the Michael Jordans, Kobe Bryants and John McEnroes of the world.</p>
<p>I’ve played points that would make Rafael Nadal proud. In some of those points, my opponents have called me “insane” because I ran down shots that no other mere mortal would retrieve. I’ve played day matches in 95-degree heat in the middle of the Florida summer with no quit. Several times opponents on those days ending up stopping on me, saying, “It’s not worth it”.</p>
<p>I’d rather first be taken to a hospital than quit. I bring the warrior’s code to every match: I fight to the death – of either me or my opponent. By death, I mean the winning or losing.</p>
<p>On many occasions, I’ve played 4-5 matches in one day with few breaks in between. I did this to improve my skill and conditioning and because I love tennis. By playing so much, I quickly earned many small wins. I love the famous quote by Thomas J. Watson:</p>
<blockquote><p>“If you want to succeed faster, double your rate of failure”.</p></blockquote>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Small Wins Are Good, But Not Enough</h2>
<p>At the time I made the tennis team, I had no offensive weapons to speak of; I was all defensive with a less-than-stellar serve. My volleys and overheads were no better.</p>
<p>Instead, I relied on my opponents to make unforced errors. But if they were skilled and could place the ball out of my reach, I could not contend. Yet, the two wins in tryouts gave me a confidence I never had before. I took that confidence and those two small wins on the road trip to Boston, where I’d play my first collegiate matches. The coach put me at the #6 spot &#8211; the last spot on the starting roster.</p>
<p>The moment had come to play my first official college tennis match. In warm-ups, I knew I was in trouble. My opponent wasn’t big in stature but he had a powerful forehand with excellent topspin. Handling the high shots was always my weakness in tennis. I like to hit flat and feel much more comfortable hitting low shots.</p>
<p>Still, I was mentally prepared to do battle. I’d fight to the end no matter how badly I was getting beat. And that’s what I did. I fought with all my heart like my life depended on the outcome. Funny, but I still play like that today. In the end, I lost in straight sets but had managed to secure at least a couple of games in the match. I thought I might get shut out. Glad I didn’t.</p>
<p>The next two matches in Boston went the same way. I lost both contests but felt I had a chance to win them. If I just had a little more skill, I could beat those guys.</p>
<p>The only reason I lost was that my technique was not quite up to speed. Everything else was in place – my determination, my speed, my conditioning. Even though I lost all three matches in Boston, I returned home with a sense of hope, believing I could make that needed improvement in technique.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Knowledge Of Yourself</h2>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1173" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/IMG_0054knowlegeofself.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/IMG_0054knowlegeofself.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/IMG_0054knowlegeofself-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/IMG_0054knowlegeofself-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p>When you play tennis, it’s important to know your level of fitness, level of skill and how much you want it. Some people play to have fun, get exercise and socialize. I’d be willing to bet money they’re not the type of people to read this post. The information here is for the hardcore players. You know, the ones who are tired of losing and want to beat their rivals. This post is for those players serious about tennis and making improvements.</p>
<p>It’s so important to know your capabilities when you step on the court. I know exactly where I’m at in terms of my playing ability, conditioning and confidence at all times. I tailor my game around it. If I’m playing an opponent up to the task and my ability is low that day, I’ll tone down the offense and make them earn the victory by forcing them to hit more-and-more shots.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>If my conditioning is not there for some reason, I’ll force the issue and get to the net to end the point quickly. And if my confidence is low, I’ll start the match cautiously, play my way into it and remind myself of all the small wins.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<blockquote><p>At times, when I’m not playing well, I’ll utter the mantra “I’m the best” or “this is my match” through the competition. I visualize myself winning at the end, even as the match goes on. So many times this strategy has worked for me. This is how a mentally strong mind thinks in tennis.</p></blockquote>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Knowledge Of Your Opponent</h2>
<p>If you want to win in tennis, you need to know your opponent. Have you ever played someone new and unfamiliar? You have no idea of their tendencies, strengths and weaknesses until you begin playing them. If you know your opponent’s game, you can expose their weaknesses. Often, just being familiar with your opponent’s game will make you feel more comfortable during the match.</p>
<p>When I play someone new, I like to assess them as much as possible before the match, primarily in the warm-ups. When the match begins, I like to hit up the middle, be consistent and take few unnecessary risks. In my mind, I’m taking note of how my opponent reacts to various shots. Here are some questions to consider when playing someone, especially a new player:</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<ul>
<li>Which is their stronger/weaker wing – forehand or backhand?</li>
<li>How do they handle high shots (those hit with topspin that they have to catch up high)?</li>
<li>Where do they like to serve? Can I consistently attack their second serve?</li>
<li>Do they volley well? How are their overheads?</li>
<li>How do they react to my slice shots?</li>
<li>How do they react to pace? What about the slow looping shots?</li>
<li>How is their conditioning? How quick are they? What is their footwork like? Can they get to my drop shots?</li>
<li>Do they approach the net on short balls or retreat back to the baseline?</li>
<li>Does my opponent hit with various spins or are they primarily a flat hitter?</li>
<li>How good or poor is their mental attitude?</li>
</ul>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>I try to find the answer to as many of these questions as possible, as soon as I can. I have a tennis mind, so I can quickly analyze and sum a player up quicker than most. In every point of the match against an unfamiliar player, take note of what’s happening. Once you see a weakness, attack it often without being predictable. Almost every club player has at least one serious weakness if not two or more.</p>
<p>There is so much I can talk about in regard to this. On occasion, I’ll play a very good junior or former college player. These players can hit all the shots and possess excellent, textbook groundstrokes and serves. From the outside, it looks like there’s no weakness in their game. But if you probe further, you’ll find that their mental game is often suspect. Once this makes itself evident, I’m positive I’ll soon break my opponent’s will. Doing so gives me strength and before long most completely crack under the pressure. I’ll give you an example.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Exposing Your Opponent</h2>
<p>I live, train and teach here in South Florida. On occasion, I used to give lessons at a famous resort hotel on the beach. It’s a fancy establishment with two Har-Tru clay tennis courts. I was called by the hotel one day to play with a “boy”. That’s all I knew when I drove there. I wasn’t expecting much other the usual teaching lesson. Well that boy was 17-years-old, 6’3” tall and had been playing since he was a kid.</p>
<p>His family was wealthy and he had been given expertly coached since being a child. His strokes were no different than any tour pro. I could see it in the first minute of hitting with him. I know I shouldn’t admit this, but I was a little jealous. If I had been afforded the same luxury growing up, I certainly would have been a tour level player (at least in my mind).</p>
<p>We started hitting and after a couple of minutes he asked to play a set. I thought, “Cool, I get to play an excellent player and get paid for it.” If I lost to him, nobody would know anyway. It would be my secret.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-287 alignleft" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/Mental4.jpg" alt="" width="400" height="266" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/Mental4.jpg 400w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/Mental4-300x200.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" /></p>
<p>I had played young men of his pedigree before and did very well against them. Why? Not because my strokes are better or that I am more decorated. Just the opposite. But it all comes down to the mental game when you reach a certain level in tennis. Yes, I can run down many shots and neutralize my opponent’s power with slice and placement. At the same time, I know they can hit me off the court if I give them anything short. I had to play smart to win this match – that was my only chance.</p>
<p>The first few games were tough, but I was gauging his play and analyzing his game on every point. I decided that being consistent was my best option for victory; I wasn’t going to hit him off the court. After 15 minutes of play, I took a 3-1 lead. I saw he was flustered but he still retained hope of beating me. 15 minutes later the set was over and I had won it 6-1. I could see he was surprised by the result but thinking it might be a fluke, he asked to play another set. Now that I knew his weaknesses (conditioning and the mental game), I quickly beat him 6-0 in the second set.</p>
<p>I could see and feel the quit in him up 2-0 in the second. For the remainder of the set the fight was taken out of him and he chalked it up to not being used to the hot conditions. Being I was paid to play and was the club pro, I encouraged the kid and really didn’t hit that many winners in the match. He beat himself. I don’t think he expected to play someone like me. Someone who runs down every ball (proper preparation). Someone who knows his capabilities and limits (knowledge of yourself). And someone who could dissect his game and quickly key in on his weaknesses to the point of breaking him mentally and physically (knowledge of your opponent).</p>
<p>I went home very content that day, but I felt for the kid too. I told him to his face that he merely beat himself that day and needed to be more consistent. I encouraged him by saying he had a great game, should learn from playing someone like me and keep playing tournaments.</p>
<p>I thought I’d never see the kid again. I was wrong. The next day I got a call from the hotel. The kid and his father requested I come back to play him one more time. The next day I returned to the hotel and this time his father was there to watch the whole match.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>I’ll spare you the detailed play-by-play of the match. All you need to know is that it was a repeat of the first match except this time I won 6-0, 6-0. His father was a nice man and applauded the great shots I hit. After the match, the kid looked disgusted. I asked him what’s wrong. The only thing he said to me was this: “It’s extremely annoying playing you. You get everything back.” That was the last day the hotel ever called me. My competitive spirit would not allow me to lose even one game. I guess that was looked on badly by the hotel. Still, I’ll take those two decisive wins even if it meant the end of my stint.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Past Experience</h2>
<p>If you don’t have experience, you’re going to lack confidence – no matter who you are. I elaborated on that earlier in this post. You’ve got to build up your experience by playing matches. There’s no other way.</p>
<p>I know a ton of players who only want to hit. They’re afraid of playing matches because they might lose or don’t like the stress of playing a match. Some even shun competition. If you’re one of those players who just want to have fun and stay in shape, then great. But if you’re looking to get into competitive tennis, there’s no substitute for actual match play, whether in tournaments, leagues or recreational matches.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-288 alignleft" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/Mental10.jpg" alt="" width="400" height="225" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/Mental10.jpg 400w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/Mental10-300x169.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" /></p>
<p>I’ve built my game from the bottom up by playing hundreds of matches. In the beginning, I would play anyone that could hit the ball over the net. I played players of all styles, ages and levels. It was fun beating the players I could out-hit. But many times in those early days I got my ass handed to me and was torn asunder.</p>
<p>After a humiliating loss on the court, I cried by myself &#8211; literally. I vowed to quit tennis and never return more than three dozen times in my life. But I kept coming back to it, thinking I would be better the next time.</p>
<p>In his book, “Open”, Andre Agassi admitted he quit tennis “a thousand times”. So if the great Andre Agassi quit tennis, we probably have all felt that way once or twice in our lives too. It’s normal. However, if you really decide to quit, you’ll never be a winner. That’s the way of the coward. And if you’re a reader of this blog, I won’t allow it!</p>
<p>What I love about experience is that I can draw on it before and during the match. If I’m in a tough match, I can say to myself, “I’ve beaten better players dozens of times before. Just stay with it and be consistent. He’ll fold in the end like most of them do.” If I had not beaten dozens of good players in the past, there is no way I’d have that level of confidence. Instead, I’d probably be thinking, “Wow, this guy is good. He’s getting to all my shots. He’s the best guy I’ve ever played. I don’t think I can win this.”</p>
<p>It’s amazing how experience and positive self-talk can so drastically change the outcome of a match. During the match, sometimes you need to remind yourself of all the great wins you had in tennis to keep up your fighting spirit.</p>
<p>The bottom line here is that you need to play matches.</p>
<p>Please don’t fear losing. It happens to all of us. Some professional tennis players have never won a single pro tournament – even in their entire playing career. It doesn’t stop them from competing. A great man once said, “You miss every shot you don’t take.”</p>
<p>Play as many matches against as many different players as you can. At the end of the match, talk with your opponent if possible. Tell them something positive about their game and then ask what they thought about yours. You specifically want to know what they thought was the weakest part of your game. Get feedback on your weakest links and then work to resolve those weaknesses.</p>
<p>As you play more matches you’ll get better, gain match toughness and become difficult to beat. I really feel that being match tough is what gives me the decided advantage in so many of my most challenging contests.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Adapting To Conditions</h2>
<p>Being adaptable in tennis, like life, is mandatory for success. You must be willing to change your game in real time and without negativity. No amount of complaining or excuses will earn you victory. You may show up to your match and find it very windy, or ultra-sunny, or too hot, or too cold. Maybe the condition of the court is not to your liking – they haven’t been brushed that day or they’re too slippery. Maybe it’s too noisy because the court is right next to a main road. Or perhaps there are people playing next to you or the lighting isn’t good.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-291 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/Mental3.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/Mental3.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/Mental3-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/Mental3-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p>There could be a thousand things that distract you. You only need claim one of them to be the scapegoat for your poor performance that day. I say this, but admit I’ve used many excuses during my playing days. We all think we have valid excuses. I hear them all the time – my grip is too slippery, I just ate, the balls are not bouncing, etc. I want you to completely forget about excuses and take full responsibility for everything that happens on the court. If you lose, it’s your fault, period. That’s the only way you’ll evolve as a player and human being. That’s being mentally tough.</p>
<p>It’s not only the conditions, court and equipment you need to adapt to. You also need to be adaptable to your opponent. Like mentioned before, you may play someone completely new. Every player hits differently. Now you must adapt to a new kind of hitting that you are unfamiliar with. Remember, the greatest tennis players in the game are problem-solvers on the court. Yes, they falter like the rest of us. But they take full responsibility (ownership, as Agassi likes to say) and figure out a way to win.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>Here’s an example that happened to me on more than several occasions. You may be playing a baseline opponent who you feel very comfortable hitting against. Things are going your way in the match. Suddenly that player starts serving and volleying and chipping and charging. He or she has changed their style because the previous style of staying back wasn’t working. What now?</p>
<p>If you continue hitting the same way, you’ll likely lose. So now your opponent is forcing you to hit harder, lower to the net, and closer to the lines. If you can’t adapt, you’ll be taken out of the match and knocked out of the tournament. This is why it’s so important to be fluid in tennis. On a second’s notice, you have to be willing to go outside your comfort zone to win. When you play to win, you do what works and you do it without reservation. That’s the mark of a winner! That’s mental toughness.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Summary</h2>
<p>The mental game is extremely important in tennis. For players close in levels, the one who has the stronger mind will win almost 100% of the time. Having a formidable mental game in tennis can allow you to beat players you never thought possible.</p>
<p>I hope this article inspires you to think more about the mental game and use it in your matches. At the top levels of the game, the physical differences are so slight that the mental game is really what separates the all-time greats from the rest of the pack. The mental game can be a great overlooked weapon in tennis. I hope my tennis stories motivate you to make your own. So go to the court, be strong, be brave and win!</p>
<p>The post <a href="/how-to-truly-master-the-mental-game-of-tennis/">How To Truly Master The Mental Game Of Tennis</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/how-to-truly-master-the-mental-game-of-tennis/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
