<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Theory Archives - Serve and Volley Tennis</title>
	<atom:link href="/category/theory/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/category/theory/</link>
	<description>Your secret weapon on the court.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sun, 11 Jul 2021 16:20:12 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	

<image>
	<url>/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/cropped-ted_svt_favicon-32x32.png</url>
	<title>Theory Archives - Serve and Volley Tennis</title>
	<link>/category/theory/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>Can You Play Tennis In The Rain?</title>
		<link>/can-you-play-tennis-in-the-rain/</link>
					<comments>/can-you-play-tennis-in-the-rain/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chad Walner]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 28 Feb 2019 13:30:46 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Theory]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=2012</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>If you’re a fan of ATP or WTA tennis, you know that rain will usually delay or end a professional tennis match. This is usually decided by the tournament referee when he or she deems it too slippery or unsafe &#8230; <a class="kt-excerpt-readmore" href="/can-you-play-tennis-in-the-rain/" aria-label="Can You Play Tennis In The Rain?">Read More</a></p>
<p>The post <a href="/can-you-play-tennis-in-the-rain/">Can You Play Tennis In The Rain?</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>If you’re a fan of ATP or WTA tennis, you know that rain will usually delay or end a professional tennis match. This is usually decided by the tournament referee when he or she deems it too slippery or unsafe for the match to continue.</p>
<p>Sometimes the players will take it upon themselves to stop the match, but the referee has the final say. In club tennis, there is no referee and the players decide when to call it quits.</p>
<p>In theory, you could play tennis in a light rain, but definitely not in a strong rain. The determining factor is the intensity of the rain, the court surface, and how slippery or not the court is becoming.</p>
<p>Most club matches are played on either hard court or clay. There are two types of clay – green clay and red clay, but green is more popular.</p>
<p>Green clay is often referred to as “har-true” and red clay is a finer, softer type of clay that absorbs water slightly more. If enough rain comes down, it will affect any surface (hard court or clay) making it too slippery to risk playing.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Can You Play Tennis On A Wet Court?</h2>
<p>Yes, you can play tennis on a wet court, but it depends how wet. On hard courts, you’ll have more traction than on clay, but the lines can be very slippery.</p>
<p>If playing on wet hard courts, you need to be careful around the lines. You should also not run 100% speed or try to move too quickly. Additionally, if puddles begin forming, you should stop playing, as the balls will soon become water-logged and lose most of their bounce.</p>
<p>Clay courts are better able to absorb water than hard courts. But once they get saturated, your level of traction will be much worse than a hard court.</p>
<p>Once clay is saturated with water, it becomes like mud and it’s nearly impossible to have traction. In periods of light rain, you can certainly play on clay. The deciding point to stop is when the clay turns to mud.</p>
<p>If the clay turns to mud in a light rain, stop playing, as you’re only risking falling or injuring yourself. Hang out by the court for a bit and monitor the weather.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>How Long Does It Take For Tennis Courts To Dry After Rain?</h2>
<p>If a light rain stops, it will usually require 15-25 minutes for clay courts to dry enough to be played on. This is only in light rain.</p>
<p>When the rain comes down heavy and the clay court is mudded up, it will take at least an hour or more to dry. I would say in most cases, heavy rain on average takes 2-3 hours to dry for clay courts during the day. At night, it could be longer due to the lack of sun.</p>
<p>On hard courts, the time for drying can take longer. If a light rain occurs and the court looks wet and the lines are slippery, I recommend stopping play. And if puddles occur, you certainly want to stop.</p>
<p>After a light rain on a hard court, it could take up to an hour for the court to dry. This really depends on the material used to build the court and the time of day.</p>
<p>I’ve seen some hard courts dry in 30 minutes while others took over an hour. Some courts are just better irrigated, while others seem to collect water in spots and puddle up.</p>
<p>If a hard rain hits for 10 minutes or more, you could be looking at several hours before the court dries.</p>
<p>To summarize, you can still play tennis on a wet court, but it depends on how much traction you have, how hard it’s raining, and what kind of surface you’re playing on (hard court or clay).</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>How Does Water Affect Tennis Balls?</h2>
<p>All tennis balls absorb water on the furry or hairy part of them. This causes the ball to be water-logged and gain weight (usually a 1-3 ounces). Keep in mind the tennis ball itself is only 2 ounces.</p>
<p>When this happens, the ball definitely slows down, does not bounce as high and does not travel as fast or far. Furthermore, water will come off the ball every time it is hit – usually splashing you in the process.</p>
<p>It’s no fun playing tennis with water-logged balls. So even if you have good traction on a wet court, the tennis balls will absorb the moisture and they will severely affect your game.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>This is a big reason why playing tennis in the rain can be difficult. The only solution is to wait until the courts dry or put new, dry tennis balls in play.</p>
<p>If the courts have a lot of moisture on them, then the new balls will quickly collect that and become water-logged again. That’s why I recommend not playing when the courts are wet.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Does Rain Ruin Tennis Balls?</h2>
<p>No, rain will not ruin the tennis ball in that it can’t be used again. But it will make the tennis ball practically unplayable for the time it is wet.</p>
<p>If you open new balls and it rains soon after, the balls will likely get water-logged if you play for a bit. You’ll see the balls don’t bounce that well and they’ll feel heavier.</p>
<p>As we mentioned before, tennis balls absorb moisture, which is why they lose performance when wet. If this happens, just put the balls back in the can or your bag and dry them off when you get home.</p>
<p>When the tennis balls dry, they should be fine to use again for practice or a friendly match.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>What Is The Best Way To Dry Off A Wet Court?</h2>
<p><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-2017" src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/02/1024px-Citi_Open_Rain_Delay.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2019/02/1024px-Citi_Open_Rain_Delay.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/02/1024px-Citi_Open_Rain_Delay-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/02/1024px-Citi_Open_Rain_Delay-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>In regard to clay courts, the only thing you can do is wait. There is no tool or blower that will dry clay courts. The best course of action (to avoid them getting wet in the first place) is to place a tarp over them when it rains.</p>
<p>In this way, you can begin playing as soon as the rain stops, and the tarp is removed. Tarps are not commonly used in most tennis clubs.</p>
<p>But they can often be seen at such prestigious events as Wimbledon, where a crew of 20 balls boys can cover a court in less than a minute.</p>
<p>When it comes to hard courts, the best option to dry a wet court is with a squeegee. This is a tool that is specially designed to push water off the court. It also spreads it out so that the water can dry faster.</p>
<p>Most good hard courts have at least one squeegee nearby. The squeegee should be used when it stops raining. It will take some time to dry a wet court with a squeegee (depending on the level of wetness).</p>
<p>On hard courts with just a few small puddles, I’ve been able to dry the courts in 5-10 minutes with a squeegee. But on very wet courts, it can take 15-25 minutes to squeegee the entire court.</p>
<p>In addition, you may need to allow time for the court to dry, even though you moved most of the puddles off the court. For places that stubbornly won’t dry (or if you don’t have a squeegee), an old towel, shirt or rag works well.</p>
<p>While you won’t be able to dry an entire court with one towel, shirt or rag, you can hit a few bad spots and dry them faster than with a squeegee in most cases.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Can You Play Tennis On A Wet Court? What Is The Best Way To Play Tennis In The Rain?</h2>
<p>As I mentioned earlier, yes, it’s possible to play tennis on a wet court. Here are some helpful pieces of advice for playing tennis in the rain:</p>
<ul>
<li>Make sure your sneakers have good traction. If you’re playing on clay, you should be using clay court tennis sneakers that have extra material on the bottom for grip.</li>
<li>Wear a hat to protect your head or glasses from getting wet. If you wear glasses (like I do), it’s nearly impossible to play with water all over your lenses.</li>
<li>Bring extra towels. You may need them to dry off your racket and body.</li>
<li>Bring extra tennis balls. One can is not enough in wet weather. I recommend bringing at least two cans, if not three to play in the rain. When the first can becomes water-logged, let them dry off out of the rain. You can then put the second fresh can into play.</li>
<li>Bring extra rackets or over-grips. In the rain, the handle of the racket can easily get wet. If this happens, it’s difficult to grip the racket. For this reason, it’s beneficial to bring extra over-grips and rackets.</li>
<li>Bring extra shirts. Depending on the intensity of rain, your shirt may become water-logged too, making you feel heavy, wet and uncomfortable. I recommend bringing at least three shirts (if not more) for play in the rain.</li>
</ul>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<h2>Conclusion</h2>
<p>When playing in the rain, it’s ultimately your judgment or call as to whether you can go on our not. There have been times I really wanted to play, but the courts just became too wet.</p>
<p>In cases like that, better to air on the side of caution. I’ve played complete matches in a light rain on clay. But hard courts are different. Once it gets to a certain point, they are pretty much unplayable.</p>
<p>I hope the information in this post helps you. The next time it rains while you play, you’ll know what to expect and how to handle it.</p>
<p>If you have any questions about playing tennis in the rain, please post them below in the comments section. Thanks for reading!</p>
<p>The post <a href="/can-you-play-tennis-in-the-rain/">Can You Play Tennis In The Rain?</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/can-you-play-tennis-in-the-rain/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>20 Mistakes Tennis Players Need To Correct</title>
		<link>/20-mistakes-tennis-players-need-to-correct/</link>
					<comments>/20-mistakes-tennis-players-need-to-correct/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chad Walner]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 20 Feb 2019 14:04:53 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Theory]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1995</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>I’ve been playing tennis regularly for 25 years. I coach tennis, I live tennis and I breathe tennis. It goes without saying that I’ve made many tennis mistakes in that time. When I first started, I made mistake after mistake. &#8230; <a class="kt-excerpt-readmore" href="/20-mistakes-tennis-players-need-to-correct/" aria-label="20 Mistakes Tennis Players Need To Correct">Read More</a></p>
<p>The post <a href="/20-mistakes-tennis-players-need-to-correct/">20 Mistakes Tennis Players Need To Correct</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I’ve been playing tennis regularly for 25 years. I coach tennis, I live tennis and I breathe tennis. It goes without saying that I’ve made many tennis mistakes in that time.</p>
<p>When I first started, I made mistake after mistake. It took me years of playing and meditating on the game to realize those mistakes and correct them.</p>
<p>I truly wish I knew then what I know now. My motivation for writing this article is so that you can learn from my experience.</p>
<p><strong>Without any more delay, here are the top 20 mistakes tennis players need to correct. If you can learn from even one of these, then it was worth your time to read this post.</strong></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Never Assume The Ball Is Out</h2>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-2004" src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/02/outornot.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="449" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2019/02/outornot.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/02/outornot-300x168.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/02/outornot-768x431.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Many people I play often assume my ball is going long. They abruptly stop moving and then my ball falls in. They’ll often say something like, “I thought that ball was going five feet out!”</p>
<p>In tennis it’s wise to never assume the ball is going on unless it’s blatantly obvious. It’s better to play the ball and hit it, even if you think it may go out. If you take a swing, you can still call it out.</p>
<p>But if you don’t swing and the ball goes in, then you’ve lost the point for sure. One way to circumvent this mistake is to just run down everything. It’s a good drill and habit to get into anyway.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Always Carry The Proper Equipment</h2>
<p>I know a lot of players who show up to matches ill-prepared. They don’t have grips, carry one racket and some don’t even have a tennis bag.</p>
<p>It’s always a good idea to show up to a match with everything you’ll need to perform your best. It may be annoying to acquire all the stuff you need, but once you do, it’s in your bag and done.</p>
<p>Here are the essential items I carry to every match. If you’re new to tennis, these are great items to keep in your bag: at least three rackets, new grips, hats, extra shirts, water, wrist bands, a towel, vibration dampeners, tennis balls, an energy bar, sunblock, and a racket weight.</p>
<p>Showing up prepared means you’re serious about tennis and serious about winning. It doesn’t take much, so learn to come prepared to all your matches and you’ll play better for it.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Never Judge A Book By Its Cover</h2>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-2002" src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/02/a-fist-pounding.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2019/02/a-fist-pounding.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/02/a-fist-pounding-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/02/a-fist-pounding-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>I’ve probably played over several hundred people in the last couple of decades. Sometimes I’ll play someone I’ve never met or seen play before.</p>
<p>One thing I quickly learned is never to judge someone’s play on looks. I’ve seen the most unathletic, dumpy-looking players be able to hit the most extraordinary shots. Those players could do things I could only dream about.</p>
<p>Never assume you can beat someone on appearance alone. Always judge by the level of play. The same holds true for players that look good.</p>
<p>I’ve played against athletic-looking, young players with great stroke technique, and they were some of the easiest matches I’ve played. If you count yourself out before the match begins, you can play yourself right into an unnecessary loss.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Practice Like You Play</h2>
<p>A friend of mine, who was like a mentor to me early on, always reiterated, “you practice like you play.” This means you should practice as hard as you play.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, I don’t see many players heeding that advice. When I first began playing tennis, I would practice very nonchalantly.</p>
<p>But I realized that to maximize my practice sessions, I needed to practice as hard as I worked in matches. Once I did, my game evolved, and I saw noticeable improvements.</p>
<p>The next time you are on the practice court, be intense and focused. Practice is your time to improve, not goof off.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Use The Best Racket And Strings You Can Find</h2>
<p>I know great players may tell you differently, but for most of us club hacks, which racket you use has a huge impact on your game. Many club players I know use old rackets with bad string.</p>
<p>If you’re an avid tennis player, you need to upgrade your racket and string now. It may be a surprise to hear this, but you should be changing rackets every 3-4 years at max. New racket technology comes out every year and after 1-2 years, rackets begin to lose their “pop”.</p>
<p>Do you want to know the fastest way to improve in tennis? Purchase yourself a new racket and put good strings in it. By good strings, I mean 17-gauge strings with good feel. Try to avoid the cheap 16-gauge crap.</p>
<p>If you don’t know what racket to buy, try demoing several different rackets from your local pro shop or an online site like tenniswarehouse. If you call them, they’ll give you suggestions. Trust me, rackets make a big difference in play.  If you like the serve and volley game &#8212; which is probably why you are here in the first place &#8212; check out our specific recommendations <a href="/the-best-5-rackets-for-serve-and-volley-in-2018/">here</a>.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<h2>Focus On The Process, Not The Results</h2>
<p>As you may know from reading my blog and seeing my youtube videos, I’m a tennis coach. When I teach experienced players, they often have big expectations of improving right away.</p>
<p>Often during a lesson, I’ll tweak or change a player’s technique. Not surprisingly, they play worse for a while, as it takes time to adapt to new changes. I notice the player gets awful discouraged when the new changes don’t work right away.</p>
<p>At that point, I’ll tell them to focus on the process, not the results. Too often we get caught up thinking the results need to be ideal all the time, or else something is flawed. That’s how many of us are programmed to think.</p>
<p>Just remember, when you are improving or learning a new technique in tennis, focus on the actual process (the technique) and not on where the ball is going. You’ll improve a lot faster that way.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Know That No Player Is Unbeatable</h2>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-2006" src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/02/term.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2019/02/term.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/02/term-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/02/term-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Most of you play matches. Some of those players you beat every time. Other players beat you every time. And against some players, it’s a toss-up on who plays better that day.</p>
<p>For those players who always beat you, never assume going into the match the outcome is certain defeat. It would be wise to think positively, construct a viable game plan and try to execute it throughout the match.</p>
<p>I always try to give myself the best chance of winning. You never know when a better opponent may be off that day. Or, maybe you’ll play the best tennis of your life and end up winning.</p>
<p>Nobody is unbeatable in tennis. I’ve seen poor players beat good players more than a few times in my life. They did it simply by out-hustling them and wanting it more. Always believe in yourself and never give up on the court. Better to go down in flames fighting hard, then tank like a loser and be soft.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Say The Score</h2>
<p>This one is important when you play matches. It’s especially important when you play league and tournament matches!</p>
<p>On many occasions in my playing days, I’ve forgotten the score, especially after long points. If you don’t know the score, you can easily end up giving one or two points to your opponent and ultimately the game and match.</p>
<p>When serving, it’s always a good idea to say the score out loud, so your opponent can hear it. In this way, if they contest the score after a point, you can tell them you said the score before every point.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>It also helps you remember the score better too. When your opponent serves to you, it helps to say the score to yourself. In practice matches, I’ll also utter the score out loud before my opponent serves (if he doesn’t).</p>
<p>If the court you’re playing at has pegs or flip cards to keep track of the games, use them. In this way, there’s no disputing the score of the match.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Never Argue With Cheaters</h2>
<p>I’ve played quite a few cheaters in my years. These are players who make blatantly bad calls. It’s one thing to call a ball good that misses by an inch, but when it’s six inches out or more, it gets to be ridiculous.</p>
<p>I say never argue with cheaters because you really can’t win. Leopards don’t usually change their spots. So if a player is a cheater, most likely they’ll always be a cheater.</p>
<p>This doesn’t mean they cheat you on every call – just the close and important ones it seems. I usually approach cheaters in two ways. One is that I won’t play with them again. The second is much more passive, where I turn the other cheek.</p>
<p>I only turn the other cheek if I know I can beat that player – especially if we are friendly. For example, there are a couple of guys I like, but they often make bad calls in our matches.</p>
<p>Instead of arguing, I just except the call and play on, knowing I can beat them despite a few really bad calls in the match.</p>
<p>If you argue with cheaters, it usually ends bad and someone usually winds up walking off the court. I’ve even seen physical confrontations break out over bad line calls!</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Don’t Overhit</h2>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-2007" src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/02/Angelique-Kerber.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2019/02/Angelique-Kerber.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/02/Angelique-Kerber-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/02/Angelique-Kerber-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>This is one that really irks me. I see it with a lot of experienced but lower level players I teach. They’re overhitting the ball and making tons of errors.</p>
<p>I believe most players overhit because they see the way professional tennis players hit and think they should be hitting with the same pace. Well, news flash – it ain’t happening!</p>
<p>Yes, racket speed is important. But if you’re not generating enough topspin due to poor technique or whatever the case, your ball is going to fly out or into the net much more than land inside the court.</p>
<p>I tell these players to either generate more spin or slow their swing down a bit. But it often goes in one ear and out the other. Consistency is a lot more important than power when it comes to winning at the club level.</p>
<p>If you hit hard and most of your shots are landing out, you definitely need to heed this advice. Tone it down a bit and watch your level of play rise.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Avoid Playing Matches When Changing Your Technique</h2>
<p>When you make a change in technique, often your level will decline for a period. With practice, you’ll become accustomed to the new technique and you may even be a better player after the change.</p>
<p>One important thing I learned early on is to not play matches in the midst of making big changes to your game. You’ll end up resorting back to what’s comfortable during the match and sabotage the new technique.</p>
<p>Or, if you use the new technique during the match and it doesn’t work well (because it’s not yet ingrained in your muscle memory) you may end up believing it’s unusable and scrap it prematurely.</p>
<p>If you make a wholesale change to your forehand, backhand or serve, work out all the kinks in practice before setting up a match. Once you’re comfortable with the changes, then you’re ready to play.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Practice Your Second Serve More Than Any Other Shot</h2>
<p>It’s a tennis cliché that you’re only as good as your second serve. The second serve is the one shot that gives club players the most trouble.</p>
<p>If another player can tee off on your second serve, it means you probably can’t hold serve. And if you can’t hold serve, you can’t win in tennis.</p>
<p>A poor second serve also makes you reluctant to go for a big first serve and puts more pressure on you. So why not learn proper second serve technique and practice it religiously?</p>
<p>When I first started playing, I put the emphasis on my groundstrokes and first serve. But in time, I realized the smartest thing to do was practice my second serve as much as possible.</p>
<p>By doing so, I feel much more confident when serving. I know I can take the chance of missing a big first serve because I have a reliable second serve in my arsenal.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Work With The Best Coach Or Tennis Course You Can Find</h2>
<p>When it comes to learning the game of tennis, you only want to learn from the best. This is especially true for new players who are just picking up the rudiments of the game.</p>
<p>If you learn from a coach or tennis course with less-than-optimal technique, your entire game may be permanently flawed. You’ll end ingraining bad habits that will have to be undone months or years later. Trust me, you don’t want that.</p>
<p>Ask around and seek out the best coach in your area. If you can’t afford private lessons or don’t have a great coach in your area, online tennis lessons are your next best option.</p>
<p>Check out the awesome video course available from Coach Mencinger &#8211; <a href="/the-serve-unlocked-make-your-serve-your-natural-weapon/">The Serve Unlocked</a>.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Don’t Play The Same Players All The Time</h2>
<p>A lot of tennis players I know get stuck playing the same people over and over. This is mostly a matter of convenience and comfortability.</p>
<p>If you’re only looking for exercise or enjoy playing with a particular person, then great. But if your goal is to improve in tennis as quickly as possible, it’s best to seek out as many different players as you can find.</p>
<p>Tennis is a wonderful sport because no two players are the same. Each one brings a different style to the table that can’t be replicated by anyone else in the world.</p>
<p>Some players hit hard, others are more consistent. Some like to crash the net and some avoid it like the plague. Some players have big serves, some tricky ones, and others use great placement.</p>
<p>In order to fulfill your tennis potential, you need to face as many different styles as possible. I owe a lot of my success in tennis to facing hundreds of different players over the years.</p>
<p>When I’m in a tough match against a player, I can usually recall a player with a similar style and determine the best game plan. The experience you get from playing a wide range of players is invaluable.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>If You’re A Singles Player, Don’t Avoid Doubles</h2>
<p>In the early years of my tennis life, I hardly ever played doubles. I loved singles and one-on-one battles. As a result, my net game hardly ever got better.</p>
<p>When I moved to Florida back in 2007, many of the guys that played here enjoyed doubles, so I decided to partake in it. Besides, I was getting older and doubles seemed inevitable. Additionally, I really wanted to improve my net game.</p>
<p>After playing a couple of years of doubles, my doubles game and net skills evolved tremendously. This has helped me out greatly in my singles game as well.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>I highly recommend you play more doubles if you don’t already. Find players your level or above and enjoy the game. Trust me on this, when you play with good players, doubles is even more enjoyable than singles!</p>
<p>Within a few months of playing, even if you don’t consciously work on your volleys in practice, you should see an improvement in your net game. Doubles also helps your return game, as you need to be much more accurate with your returns.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Go Easy On Yourself</h2>
<p>This one took me a lot of time to develop. By this, I mean not berating yourself for mistakes and bad play. I see a lot of club players cursing themselves, throwing their rackets and exhibiting negative body language after poorly hit shots.</p>
<p>While it may feel good for the moment to do as a stress release, in the long term it hurts you and your game. The best way to react after a poorly hit shot is to remain neutral and just observe.</p>
<p>I no longer get upset when I hit a bad shot. Instead I think of the reason why I hit that shot badly and then offer a solution to myself. It could be to get to the ball quicker next time, follow through higher or change my grip.</p>
<p>In providing a solution, I create a positive feeling in me instead of a negative one. The next time I receive the same ball, I can better make the adjustment as well.</p>
<p>You see, I look at tennis like a science. If something doesn’t work, there’s no reason to be upset. A change needs to be made. If I can make it during the match, then great.</p>
<p>If not, then I’ll need to accept me errors during the match and work to improve my technique after the match, during my practice sessions. All tantrums and bad-talking is really nothing more than overinflated egos.</p>
<p>We’re all just club players and most of the time, no money or stakes are on the line. I think players need to relax a lot more and they’ll find they play a lot better.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Join A Tennis Club – Don’t Shy Away From Competition</h2>
<p>If you live in any major city or even if you don’t, there is often a tennis club somewhere in driving distance. Mine is fortunately located in my city, about 15 minutes by car.</p>
<p>If you love tennis and enjoy playing, you owe it to yourself to go down to the local tennis club and join. Many of them offer leagues where you can meet new people and players.</p>
<p>My club offers leagues for players from level 3.0 up to 5.0. This is where most club players fall in terms of level. If you’re someone who doesn’t like to lose, you have to overcome that bad trait.</p>
<p>Losing is par for the course in tennis. All tennis players lose, no matter who they are. We all have bad days. And we all face players who occasionally present bad matchups for us.</p>
<p>Believe me, it’s far better to play tennis against new and challenging players than not at all. If you lose, at least you’ll learn. There are so many levels in tennis, you could play all your life and never reach a point where you can beat everyone in your area.</p>
<p>The most important thing is to have fun, get exercise, enjoy the competition and make some new friends. In the end, none of us are competing for grand slam trophies, so wins and losses really don’t matter.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Don&#8217;t Underestimate Footwork</h2>
<p>I’ve said it time-and-time again, and I’ll say it one more time here: footwork is the most important aspect of tennis. If you can’t move to set up for the ball properly, your game will always be a struggle.</p>
<p>If you ask Roger Federer and Andre Agassi the same question (what is the most important aspect of tennis), they’ll both tell you footwork. Yet I see almost no club players working on it!</p>
<p>There are so many footwork drills you can practice. How about agility ladders, cones and mini hurdles? I never see players using them. Why? Because footwork is difficult to work on and hitting groundstrokes and serves is not.</p>
<p>I understand it takes a lot of work and sweat to move your feet. But tennis is a running sport and it requires excellent footwork to play at the higher levels.</p>
<p>If you underestimate the footwork required to reach the higher levels of tennis, you’ll never practice it and you’ll never improve. And that’s the bottom line on footwork. Enough said.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Avoid Setting Up Late</h2>
<p>This is one that affects almost all club players. I rarely see players striking a great power position and waiting on the ball.</p>
<p>Most of the club players I see move right through their power position (or worse yet, don’t have one) and hit last second. These players tend to hit off target and often feel rushed when playing.</p>
<p>I once saw my buddy, Mike (a 4.5 level player), hitting with a female coach who was ranked inside the top 200 in the world a few years earlier. She was setting up to hit the ball when it crossed the net.</p>
<p>Mike didn’t set up until the ball landed – which was usually beyond the service line. Who do you think hit better?</p>
<p>I learned years ago that early preparation is best in tennis. If you can prepare early, you can slow down the game and play more at your pace.</p>
<p>This is a lesson that a lot of club players struggle with. I’ve tried to teach this to 3.5-4.0 level players, but most prefer to hit last second because they’re so stuck in that habit. If you can learn to set up early, you’ll see the difference it makes in your game.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Be Wary Of Technical Advice From Random Players</h2>
<p>Most players like to give advice on how you should play. They’ll tell you that your grip is not correct, or you need to change your stroke in some fashion. In my experience, most players know squat about effective technique.</p>
<p>Even players that are high level and experienced have a difficult time spotting mistakes and explaining technique. For these reasons, it’s best to ignore all technical advice and focus on doing only what your coach says.</p>
<p>Personally, when someone gives me advice on my strokes, I listen and just brush it off. I know my game well enough at this point that I know what works and doesn’t.</p>
<p>But if you’re a newer player or a lower level player, just focus on doing the things your coach asks of you. If you get caught up in thinking that you need to try every piece of advice offered, it’ll drive you insane.</p>
<p>Everyone has an opinion on how you should play better. The best athletes and players in the world only listen to their coaches and themselves.</p>
<p>Sure, it can be helpful to get a tip sometimes, but if you’re an inexperienced player, how do you know what’s right and what’s not? So best to just work with a qualified coach and assess your game on your own.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>The post <a href="/20-mistakes-tennis-players-need-to-correct/">20 Mistakes Tennis Players Need To Correct</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/20-mistakes-tennis-players-need-to-correct/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>2</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>How To Overcome A Plateau In Tennis</title>
		<link>/how-to-overcome-a-plateau-in-tennis/</link>
					<comments>/how-to-overcome-a-plateau-in-tennis/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chad Walner]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 18 Feb 2019 18:31:54 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Theory]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1993</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>If you’re like me, you probably don’t remember the very first time you started playing tennis. You’ve always played tennis and all those early matches and practice sessions blended together. Or, maybe you started playing tennis a few years ago &#8230; <a class="kt-excerpt-readmore" href="/how-to-overcome-a-plateau-in-tennis/" aria-label="How To Overcome A Plateau In Tennis">Read More</a></p>
<p>The post <a href="/how-to-overcome-a-plateau-in-tennis/">How To Overcome A Plateau In Tennis</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>If you’re like me, you probably don’t remember the very first time you started playing tennis. You’ve always played tennis and all those early matches and practice sessions blended together.</p>
<p>Or, maybe you started playing tennis a few years ago and you remember precisely how you started and how awful you were in the beginning. But now, a few years later you’re a lot better.</p>
<p>No matter which of these two scenarios best fits you, at a certain point after learning tennis and playing for a while, you reached a plateau. You had thought your game would just go up and up and up, but for some reason, it never went beyond what it is now.</p>
<p><strong>Let me give you seven ways you can overcome a tennis plateau before talking more about why it plagues almost all tennis players.</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Work on one shot for a prolonged time (weeks or months)</strong></li>
<li><strong>Practice placement as often as possible</strong></li>
<li><strong>Take a lesson with a qualified tennis coach</strong></li>
<li><strong>Improve your physical conditioning</strong></li>
<li><strong>Work on your mental toughness</strong></li>
<li><strong>Practice your net game religiously</strong></li>
<li><strong>Play against better players as much as possible</strong></li>
</ul>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Despite playing often, watching dozens of tennis videos on youtube and wanting to improve badly, you just have not been able to get to the next level. And you wonder if you ever will.</p>
<p>It’s been months or maybe even years and your tennis level has remained the same. So what’s going on here? When you played an instrument, the more you practiced the better you got.</p>
<p>When you draw or learn a language, the same applies. The more often you draw or speak a language, the better you got at it.</p>
<p>But you may have noticed the same philosophy doesn’t always apply to tennis. Why is that? Why aren’t you hitting harder more accurate shots after each passing week and month you play?</p>
<p>Ah, there’s a very good reason for that. Do you want to know? I’m sure you do. Okay, here’s the secret no tennis coach really wants to tell you. Despite how much you practice tennis, you’re capped by your physical and mental abilities.</p>
<p>What does that mean? Well, let’s look at the physical first. Your body only has a certain limit to how fast it can move or how explosive it can be. Even with ideal technique, you’ll be limited by the physical capabilities of your body.</p>
<p>Some of you are in your 40s and beyond. Your movements are going to be slower and less explosive than players in their 20s. It’s just a fact of nature.</p>
<p>I think most people underestimate how much athleticism plays a part in tennis. It’s not only athleticism it’s also hand-eye coordination and focus.</p>
<p>When you look at the professional players on the ATP and WTA tours, they have fantastic physical gifts. They move fast and their muscles are super explosive. They combine those gifts with near-perfect technique to produce ungodly shots.</p>
<p>If you lack their speed and explosion, you’ll never serve 120 mph or run around the court with the speed of Novak Djokovic. But the good news is you don’t have to at the club level. You can use other ways to improve your game, like tactics, placement, and better mental toughness, which we’ll get into in more detail soon.</p>
<p>The mental side of tennis is a whole other ball of wax from the physical. To break a tennis plateau requires a certain degree of mental toughness and fortitude. In my opinion as a player and coach, I believe 90% of club players or more lack it.</p>
<p>I see the same players year-after-year playing at the same level. All of them have reached a plateau. As a matter of fact, in the 12 years I’ve been playing at the same club, not one of them has broken through to the highest flight, where I play.</p>
<p>Let’s get into the seven ways you can break a tennis plateau. I am sure they will help you if you’ve been struggling for some time.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Work On One Shot For A Prolonged Time</h2>
<p>Why only one shot? Why not work on two, three or four shots for a prolonged time? It’s because we can hyper-focus on that one particular shot we need to improve the most.</p>
<p>You know the old cliché, “you’re only as good as your weakest link.” Well in tennis it’s kind of the same. If you have great groundstrokes but an awful serve, you’ll lose tons of points on your serve and never progress very far.</p>
<p>Or maybe you have an all-around solid game except your backhand is horrible. If so, your opponents will notice that and key in on it to exploit it.</p>
<p>For that reason, it’s important to immediately go to work on developing our worst shot. For me that would be the second serve.</p>
<p>While I can hit hard second serves (85 mph +) with some spin, they are not as consistent as I want them to be. At the 4.5-5.0 level, they are rarely exploited. But I know at the higher levels they will be.</p>
<p>It would, therefore, serve me to work on practicing just the second serve for say a month. I would do this by practicing the second serve only for 45-60 minutes per practice session. Ideally, I would practice three times per week or every other day.</p>
<p>If you have the time and inclination, you can practice every day, and in extreme cases, twice a day. After practicing your weakest shot only for several weeks, you should see a huge improvement.</p>
<p>When playing matches, you should also experience that improvement. That will translate into greater confidence, better play and more match wins. Congratulations, you just made it to the next level up and broke through your long-standing plateau.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<h2>Practice Placement As Often As Possible</h2>
<p>Some of us are endowed with the ability to hit very hard groundstrokes. If that’s you, great. But most of us can’t hit laser forehands like Federer or rocketing backhands like Stan Wawrinka.</p>
<p>To be frank, we’ll probably never develop the technique or physical ability to hit balls that hard in tennis. Additionally, we’ll never serve harder than 100 mph. So how do we offset those weaknesses and get up to the next level?</p>
<p>The answer is placement. A wise coach only told me tennis is 80% placement. It’s not always how hard you hit the ball, but how well you place it. A well-placed groundstroke at 50 mph can often win a point better than a 75-mph ball hit to the opponent. It’s the same deal with the serve.</p>
<p>Instead of trying to hit harder or with more spin, we need to practice placing the ball better to get to the next level. To do this, set up targets on the court and work at trying to hit them.</p>
<p>Do this for your serve first. The three targets you should aim for are out wide, into the body and up the T. For groundstrokes, practice hitting near the corners. If you can hit groundstrokes at tight angles, you can get your opponent off the court and finish the points a lot easier.</p>
<p>You can also do the same with volleys and overheads, aiming for angling the ball off the court. Don’t focus on hitting with more power or spin. Simply practice placement.</p>
<p>After several weeks to months or placement practice, you should notice a huge difference in your matches. You’ll be winning more matches with less effort.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Take A Lesson With A Qualified Tennis Coach</h2>
<p>Others can see what you can’t see in yourself. But not just any person – a qualified or certified tennis coach. You need someone with a trained eye to spot the flaws in your game and correct them.</p>
<p>Yes, a private tennis lesson can be expensive (typically $40-$60). But if you love tennis, play often and have been struggling for a long time, one tennis lesson can make a tremendous difference.</p>
<p>Why? Because just one tip can make a ton of difference. I’ll give you an example. Recently another coach I work with named Luke offered to take a look at my serve.</p>
<p>He asked me to take a few first serves. I did and he observed from the side. He then took out his phone and squatted near the ground to video my feet. He then asked me to serve a few more times.</p>
<p>I did and he recorded only my feet. He then replayed the video to me and pointed out two big flaws I had. One was that I moved my lead foot around excessively. The second, and biggest flaw was that I was not jumping off the ground nearly enough.</p>
<p>Luke told me I needed to bend my knees more and explode up into the ball. I told him I was concerned about my racket drop and some other technical things. He told me not to worry about it and just focus on bending my knees and exploding up.</p>
<p>I tried and at first, it felt difficult. But after practicing several times, I got more used to bending my knees further and jumping higher. My timing improved the more I practiced.</p>
<p>Within just a week of that tip, I added 5-10 mph on my serve and at least several of the guys I routinely play with said my serve got a lot better. Serves that were hitting the middle of the box were now landing close to the line.</p>
<p>In a singles match I played yesterday, I hit three aces in one game and had over 15 aces in the match, which is nearly a record for me.</p>
<p>There’s not much more talk about for this tip. Ask around and find a very good coach. Have them give you a few tips for each of your shots and then remember them and work on it.</p>
<p>If you can afford several or more lessons, go for it. Small improvements in technique can translate to big differences in your matches.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<h2>Improve Your Physical Conditioning</h2>
<p>This one is really a no-brainer. I think every long-time tennis player knows that they should improve their physical conditioning. Better conditioning means you can get to more balls, wear out your opponent and maintain good technique in long matches.</p>
<p>What prevents most club tennis players from doing so is lack of time, injuries and age. It also comes down to a desire to improve physical conditioning.</p>
<p>When young, we can play tennis all day long and still go to the gym. But as we age into our late 30s, 40s and beyond, it’s not so easy. We also have more responsibilities and less time.</p>
<p>Therefore, the only real chance we have to improve our conditioning is when we play. If we play a couple of times per week, that’s generally not enough to make a big improvement.</p>
<p>So what’s the solution? How can we drastically improve our physical conditioning for tennis in a short period of time? If you’re able-bodied and your joints are in good health, the answer may be found in sprinting!</p>
<p>Why sprinting? Because sprinting takes a lot less time than jogging and it’s even more effective at improving physical conditioning. It also mimics the start and stop runs of tennis better than a slow, long jog.</p>
<p>The good thing is that you only need to sprint twice a week to see a noticeable improvement. But you need to be consistent with your sprinting. If you let a week or two go between sessions, you’ll lose conditioning.</p>
<p><strong>Each sprinting session only requires about 15-20 minutes to complete. You can sprint on a track (preferred), in the street or a sidewalk, or on a treadmill. Here is how I do it:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Warm up for five minutes with fast walking or light jogging.</strong></li>
<li><strong>Once warmed up, you’ll do 5-10 sprints of approximately 50-60 meters. You can start with 5 sprints and work up to 10 as your conditioning improves.</strong></li>
<li><strong>Get down into a sprinters stance and then explode from that position into a full sprint until you reach the 50-60 meter mark.</strong></li>
<li><strong>Once you complete the first sprint, don’t stop. Walk for 30-45 seconds and then get down into a sprinter’s stance again and repeat another sprint.</strong></li>
<li><strong>Keep repeating this process until 5-10 sprints are accomplished. You should walk or light jog the final 5 minutes to cool down.</strong></li>
</ul>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Each sprint will only last 6-10 seconds, depending on your speed. It’s very important you DO NOT sprint 100% speed in your first 1-2 or even three sessions. You can pull or strain a muscle doing so.</p>
<p>This is especially true if you don’t normally play other sports or ever run full speed. Instead, start your first sprint session at 60-70% of max speed. Assess how sore you are the next day. If very sore, repeat the sprint session at 60-70%.</p>
<p>Once you are no longer very sore, you can move up to 80% of max speed. Repeat the process, assessing your level of soreness until you get up to 100%. I usually require at least two sprint sessions before I allow myself to go 100% speed.</p>
<p>Try this program out for yourself. You’ll notice a huge difference in your conditioning on court after 3-4 weeks on the program. You should also experience a slight increase in your top speed, maybe as much as 1-2 mph.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Improve Mental Toughness</h2>
<p>This one is also a no-brainer for me. And it requires no physical effort whatsoever. If you simply improve your mental outlook, your tennis game will improve for sure.</p>
<p>How can I be sure? Because I’ve personally experienced both sides. I used to be very negative and berate myself after bad shots. Often I would chew myself out over easy misses and constantly frame my tennis in a negative light.</p>
<p>But after years of playing and reading Brad Gilbert’s awesome book “Winning Ugly”, I changed my approach. I started to be more understanding with myself when I made errors. I realized I was always trying to do my best, so my errors were caused mostly from poor technique and lack of skill more than anything.</p>
<p>Instead of saying things like, “you suck” or “what a lousy player I am”, I began to not say those things. In their place, I would think something like, “I need to improve my technique on that shot in order not to miss in the future. It’s a technique and practice problem – nothing more”.</p>
<p>I would then practice that shot and the next time I was faced with it in a match, I would often make the shot. I would then commend myself saying, “See, I was right. With practice, I turned that liability into a strength.”</p>
<p>I know that sounds idealistic, but I really do think like that. When I’m in a close match, I tell myself the match is mine and I visualize myself winning. These mental tactics really do work.</p>
<p>I can’t promise you they’ll work all the time because they don’t. But they sway the odds in your favor. At the least, you need to stop being hard on yourself when you miss.</p>
<p>You may be tempted to throw your racket, have a tantrum or give up on tennis. I know how it is. Instead, channel your anger and frustration into promising yourself you’ll work to improve.</p>
<p>Even if you practice all the time and still miss shots, you shouldn’t get on yourself. Look, tennis is a science. If you’re missing, there’s a valid scientific reason for it. You need to figure out that reason and correct it. There’s no use in berating yourself, which only makes things worse.</p>
<p>If you can follow these tips and improve your mental game, I promise you’ll not only see a difference in the number of matches you win, but you’ll feel better about yourself as well.</p>
<p>It’s just not healthy in any way to turn anger inwards over missing tennis shots. Leave that for John McEnroe. He’s the only one who can thrive off that kind of tactic.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Practice Your Net Game Religiously</h2>
<p>Most club players don’t like being at the net. It’s kind of like trying to throw a cat in water. They’ll do everything they can to prevent it.</p>
<p>The same holds true of most club players. Put them at the net and they’ll scurry back to the safety of the baseline as soon as they can – just like a cat would scurry out of the water.</p>
<p>Why you ask? The simple reason is that most club players spend little time practicing their net game. They, therefore, feel helpless at the net. The solution is to work religiously on your net game.</p>
<p>I really like this tactic for overcoming a tennis plateau. You don’t need to hit harder, improve your serve, work on your physical conditioning, or even play more matches.</p>
<p>All you need do is practice your volleys, which typically don’t require a lot of movement – so little energy is expended. You can literally practice your volleys for hours with no fatigue.</p>
<p>Of course, you would need to practice your overheads as well. You can practice your net game with a partner, a ball machine or even on a wall.</p>
<p>I promise you, the more you practice, the quicker you’ll improve. Once you get the hang of volleying, it even becomes fun.</p>
<p>Once your volleys and overheads are adept, you can come in more during matches and knock off easy shots near the net. And if you’re playing doubles, then all the easier.</p>
<p>Believe me, getting up to net is critical for improving your tennis play. Look at Rafael Nadal. He doesn’t come to net often, but when he does, he wins 90% of the points there.</p>
<p>You should need to be strategic about when you come up. Trust me on this, if you don’t do any of the other tips in this article, do this one.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<h2>Play Against Better Players As Much As Possible</h2>
<p>This is a great way to break through a tennis plateau. Here’s a perfect analogy to highlight this tip.</p>
<p>Let’s say you read at 300 words per minute. If you force yourself to read at 800 words per minute for a matter of days, you may comprehend less and feel uncomfortable doing so.</p>
<p>You may never be able to each full comprehension and comfortability reading 800 words per minute. But if you then dropped down to 400 words per minute, it would seem very slow in comparison. And there’s a good chance you would comprehend most of the words and feel comfortable there.</p>
<p>If that was true, you just made a 33% improvement in your reading speed with little or no loss of comprehension. Are you seeing where I’m going with this?</p>
<p>Let’s suppose you’re a 3.5 level player. Not a bad 3.5 or a good one, just an average 3.5 level player.</p>
<p>Now let’s pretend I set up matches for you for the next three weeks against players rated no less than 5.0 level. At first, you might lose 6-0, 6-0. But after playing against better players for a couple of weeks, something begins to happen.</p>
<p>You notice their technique and start copying it a bit. You begin to understand where and when they’ll hit the ball, maybe even reading their shots a bit better.</p>
<p>You may even develop your own little strategies for winning points here and there. After a few weeks of playing only 5.0 players, you’re still losing badly, but now you’re winning 1, 2 or 3 games each set.</p>
<p>So after three weeks, are you worse, the same, or better as a player. Clearly, you are now a better player.</p>
<p>Now imagine I match you up with a 4.0 level player who you could never beat in the past. Do you think you would have a better chance of victory now? Of course, you would. I would even put my money on you.</p>
<p>That 4.0 level player is going to be way easier to play than against the 5.0 players you were facing for three straight weeks. The balls the 4.0 level player hits now seem slow and telegraphed compared to before. You have more time to set up.</p>
<p>The little strategies you developed against the 5.0 level players are now working very well against the 4.0 level player. Additionally, the 4.0 level player is missing more, giving you more free points.</p>
<p>Do you see how this works? You can’t be afraid to face better players. Remember, tennis is a science. Except losing is a part of the game and get your butt beat as much as possible by far better players.</p>
<p>When you return to your level, the game will seem way easier. I’ve also experienced this personally in my tennis play. It’s improved my game and gotten me out of a rut several times.</p>
<p>Now, the main key to this strategy is finding better players who want to play you. Most good players don’t enjoy playing matches against players way below their level.</p>
<p>If this happens to you, you have a few options. One would be to play leagues or tournaments slightly above your level. If you’re a 4.0, try to get into tournaments for 4.5 players.</p>
<p>Another strategy is to pay better players to play you. Or at least bet them they can’t beat you. If you tell a much better player, “I bet you $20 you can’t beat me in a match,” they will be much more inclined to play you than if you offered them $20 to play you. $20 is just a suggested figure, but it could be as little as $5 or $10.</p>
<p>The last way would be if you take lessons. If so, ask the coach to play you a set in the final 15-20 minutes of the lesson.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Summary</h2>
<p>I’m sure one or more of these tennis tips will help you break through your tennis plateau. I’ve used all of them at one point or another in my tennis life.</p>
<p>The main thing is to stick with whichever option or options you choose. If you practice your net game for two weeks every day and then stop, after a few weeks your gains will diminish.</p>
<p>It’s the same thing with everything else. Consistency is key. Once you break through to the next level, you’ll be having so much fun, you’ll probably continue practicing so it won’t even be an issue.</p>
<p>If you have any questions about these tips, let me know. I don’t always have the time to clarify every little point, but I think you get the main ideas.</p>
<p>Thanks for reading and drop me a comment below and let me know which tip you’ll use first.</p>
<p>The post <a href="/how-to-overcome-a-plateau-in-tennis/">How To Overcome A Plateau In Tennis</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/how-to-overcome-a-plateau-in-tennis/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>What Are The Best Tennis Footwork Tips?</title>
		<link>/what-are-the-best-tennis-footwork-tips/</link>
					<comments>/what-are-the-best-tennis-footwork-tips/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chad Walner]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 15 Feb 2019 12:53:07 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Theory]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[footwork]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1989</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Roger Federer was once interviewed by Charlie Rose after winning the 2004 U.S. Open. In the video, he was asked why his game looked so graceful. Without hesitation, Roger cited his footwork as the single most important factor in his &#8230; <a class="kt-excerpt-readmore" href="/what-are-the-best-tennis-footwork-tips/" aria-label="What Are The Best Tennis Footwork Tips?">Read More</a></p>
<p>The post <a href="/what-are-the-best-tennis-footwork-tips/">What Are The Best Tennis Footwork Tips?</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Roger Federer was once interviewed by Charlie Rose after winning the 2004 U.S. Open. In the video, he was asked why his game looked so graceful. Without hesitation, Roger cited his footwork as the single most important factor in his game – for beauty and effect.</p>
<p>Specifically, Roger said, “The key to exploring my potential is improving my footwork…It’s always what I’ve been working on.”</p>
<p>During the interview, Roger kept coming back to footwork. In my opinion as a coach, tennis player and critic, footwork is the single most important factor in determining a player’s success in tennis.</p>
<p>I say this because it doesn’t matter how good a player’s strokes are, if his footwork is lacking, he won’t be able to place himself into position to hit effective shots. If we look at the best players on the ATP tour in today’s era (Djokovic, Federer, Nadal), they all have the best footwork in the game.</p>
<p>It’s no coincidence these men have consistently dominated the game for the last 15 years either. If you want to improve your tennis game, nothing will do so faster than bettering your tennis footwork.</p>
<p>But what does tennis footwork exactly mean? We hear so much about it but it’s quite a nebulous term which is rarely clearly defined. Let’s do that now.</p>
<p><strong>I can break up footwork into four distinct stages. Each stage is important and crucial to hitting great, powerful shots. </strong></p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Attaining the optimal position &#8211; Getting to the spot where the striking of the ball takes place.</strong></li>
<li><strong>Planting of the feet &#8211; placing the body into the proper firing position.</strong></li>
<li><strong>Harnessing momentum &#8211; pushing off the ground, thrusting the torso and generating the necessary momentum to propel the arm into the swing.</strong></li>
<li><strong>Recovering &#8211; returning or moving to the best location on the court.</strong></li>
</ol>
<p>I’ll go through all four stages in detail shortly. I can tell you for certain that the best players blend them seamlessly together. They do so all match long and repeat the process over and over during a point.</p>
<p>When a player can use his footwork so quickly and efficiently, often and oddly, it goes unnoticed by the casual observer. What remains is a virtuoso of perfection on the court with the final punctuating shot riveted as the last memory in the viewer’s mind – not the footwork.</p>
<p>This is the primary reason why footwork does not get talked about enough. Furthermore, not enough coaches work on it with their players.</p>
<p>By reading this entire article, you’ll know exactly what proper footwork entails and how to use it to dominate all your future matches. Your level of play or age is irrelevant. Everyone can improve their footwork if they determine to.</p>
<p>Without further ado, let’s get into the four stages of tennis footwork.</p>
<div class="kad-youtube-shortcode videofit"  ><iframe loading="lazy" width="600" height="400" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/v6wauVoK6N4?autoplay=0&controls=1&fs=1&modestbranding=1&theme=dark&rel=0&loop=0&showinfo=1" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="true"></iframe></div>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Stage 1: Attaining the Optimal Position</h2>
<p>This stage can be the most difficult of all four for beginner and intermediate players to achieve correctly. This is because most people use inefficient movement to reach the ball.</p>
<p>Furthermore, most people set up to close or far away from the ball. However, when done correctly, getting to the spot where you can strike the ball should set you up perfectly for stage 2.</p>
<p>There are only three ways to move to the ball in tennis. The first is by taking a cross-step and then shuffling (or side-stepping) to the ball. This is the most commonly used technique by players.</p>
<p>A first cross-step and shuffle is primarily done when moving laterally but can be accomplished when moving backwards and forwards as well. This is done for balls not too close or far away – but at a middle distance.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>The second is to simply shuffle to the ball. This movement is used when the ball is relatively close, like a few steps away. Shuffling is done laterally but can be executed forwards and backwards as well.</p>
<p>The third way to move to the ball is to simply run. We run when the ball is far away or we have little time to get there (like on a drop shot). Running is the quickest way to reach a ball but gives us the least amount of control when hitting.</p>
<p>If we run to the ball, it would benefit us to slow down before reaching the ball. Another important factor in helping us hit the ball (no matter which of the three methods we use) is to position the racket to the side of our body (close to the power position) before reaching the ball.</p>
<p>By doing so, we can save time and put ourselves into a better position as we reach stage 2. This is the reason why professional players rarely looked rushed when hitting shots and amateurs often do.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Stage 2: Planting of the Feet</h2>
<p>By virtue of stage 1, we should now be in the ideal position to hit the ball. In this stage (# 2), we stop our feet (if only for a second) and plant them to the ground.</p>
<p>Why would we do this? Because all power is generated from the ground up. It’s true for every sport and tennis is no exception. In order to use the ground, we need to have our feet firmly planted on it.</p>
<p>We then bend our knees and push off the ground to create energy for the swing. As we plant our feet we must also rotate our body what’s called the power position.</p>
<p>This is a position where our racket is back (or loaded) and our torso is turned to the side. This position creates torque and kinetic energy that can be released into the shot.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, many club players (especially those 4.0 and lower) fail to achieve enough torque to hit truly powerful shots. This stems from improper technique and the discomfort required in torquing the body.</p>
<p>I believe this stage is of huge importance when it comes to hitting very powerful shots. Both feet need to be planted firmly on the ground and the body torqued well past 90 degrees in the shoulders.</p>
<p>When you study pros in slow motion, you’ll see them set up in this way if they have even a second of time. When on the run, they don’t always have the time to achieve a perfect stage 2 position.</p>
<p>But they get around that by using the momentum of their run in stage 1 to generate pace. This is evident in the tremendous on-the-run passing shots of Nadal and Sampras off the forehand side. They can still manage to hit 80 mph+ passing shots on a dead run due to the momentum created in their movement to the ball.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Stage 3: Harnessing Momentum</h2>
<p>At the commencement of this stage, the body and racket will have completed the setup to strike the ball. Think of stage 2 as being a loaded gun or a crossbow pulled back into the final position before being released.</p>
<p>In stage 3 we execute the forward part of the stroke. This is done initially by pushing off the ground with both feet. However, it should be noted that most of your weight will be on the back foot.</p>
<p>This is so because we want to distribute our weight from the back leg to the front leg in order to transfer our body weight into the shot. You’ll see every great player do this on every basic shot in tennis (forehand, backhand, serve and volley).</p>
<p>As the legs push off the ground, the torso begins to rotate towards the net, releasing the stored kinetic energy it achieved in stage 2. The last part of the swing happens from the arm, which more-or-less goes along for the ride.</p>
<p>The major mistake most club players make here is thinking the arm is the primary source of power when it’s the legs and torso that really do the heavy lifting. The arm should be loose and flexible, snapping forward from the momentum of the body.</p>
<p>If a player never achieves an ideal power position and pushes off from the ground, then the arm is left to do the work. This results in a labored swing and slower velocity shot. Such players can never seem to generate power no matter how hard they swing.</p>
<p>This is because the legs and torso play a huge roll in how hard the ball is struck. If the legs and torso only play a small factor in the swing, the arm must work extra hard to compensate. This approach can tire a player out over a long match and result in weak swings.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Stage 4: Recovering</h2>
<p>After the ball is struck and the player completes his follow through, the next and final stage is to move again. This time it’s a movement to the best location on the court to set up for the next shot.</p>
<p>Experienced players rely on their anticipation to move to the ideal spot to hit the next ball. This can mean moving in any direction and any distance, just depending on the situation.</p>
<p>Often, you’ll see a player like Djokovic (who has the best footwork in the game) immediately move to a different spot on the court after completing his follow through. He seems to always know exactly where to go.</p>
<p>This comes from years of playing. Beginner players often stand in the same position after hitting a shot or move only a couple of steps. This usually puts them out of position for the next shot in the rally.</p>
<p>If you’re unsure of where to go, a good rule of thumb is to get back to the middle of the court. In general, it’s best to play slightly in back of the baseline or inside the service line (if you come into net).</p>
<p>The movement in stage 4 is similar to the movement in stage 1. You can shuffle back, cross-step and shuffle back, or just run. The quicker you can reach the ideal position to set up for the next shot, the easier the game gets. It’s also more difficult for your opponent to cause an unforced error on your part.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Summing It Up</h2>
<p>Ideal footwork requires technique, anticipation, and willingness to put in the work. Most players with great footwork are constantly in motion, taking as many steps as they need to place themselves into ideal hitting position.</p>
<p>The next time you watch a professional tennis match on TV or in person, take note of the footwork of the players. Instead of watching the ball or the strokes, notice how much the feet are moving.</p>
<p>Then compare that footwork to yours – if you’ve ever videoed your play. You’ll probably notice a big difference. One of the reasons I’m better than I look on camera is my footwork.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>While my strokes weren’t honed at a prestigious tennis academy in my formative years, I make up for a lot of deficiencies with my tennis footwork. My college coach instilled it in me early on and I’ve used it religiously throughout my playing life.</p>
<p>Due to being in great physical shape and having a light body weight (150 lbs), I can move nearly as well as most professional players, despite being in my mid-40s. I’m actually known for being a great mover (more than anything else) and dazzle people with the balls I can track down.</p>
<p>I do this by utilizing the four stages of footwork I outlined in this article. If you’ve never given much thought to tennis footwork, I hope this blog post sheds new light on it for you.</p>
<p>While this article is by no means a comprehensive guide to tennis footwork, I hope it gives you food for thought and motivates you to improve your foot movement on court.</p>
<p>Thanks for reading. If you wish to leave a comment or question, please do so below and I will respond.</p>
<p>Don’t forget I have a ton of great blog content on here to improve every aspect of your tennis game. Use the search feature to find what you’re interested in.</p>
<p>The post <a href="/what-are-the-best-tennis-footwork-tips/">What Are The Best Tennis Footwork Tips?</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/what-are-the-best-tennis-footwork-tips/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Why Is Roger Federer Most People’s Favorite Player?</title>
		<link>/why-is-roger-federer-most-peoples-favorite-player/</link>
					<comments>/why-is-roger-federer-most-peoples-favorite-player/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chad Walner]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 24 Jan 2019 12:42:31 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Theory]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1955</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Let me count the ways for this question. Roger Federer is without question the greatest role model and icon tennis has ever had. In fact, I’d go so far to say he’s the best role model in all of sports &#8230; <a class="kt-excerpt-readmore" href="/why-is-roger-federer-most-peoples-favorite-player/" aria-label="Why Is Roger Federer Most People’s Favorite Player?">Read More</a></p>
<p>The post <a href="/why-is-roger-federer-most-peoples-favorite-player/">Why Is Roger Federer Most People’s Favorite Player?</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Let me count the ways for this question. Roger Federer is without question the greatest role model and icon tennis has ever had. In fact, I’d go so far to say he’s the best role model in all of sports period – perhaps with LeBron James second.</p>
<p><strong>Roger is widely acclaimed as the greatest tennis player of all time. There are few who would against argue it. But seemingly there must be more to it than just great tennis for his immense popularity. Here’s why I believe Roger Federer is most people’s favorite player.</strong></p>
<div class="hrule clearfix" style="background:#81d742; height:1px"></div>
<ul>
<li><a href="#clean">Roger has a clean image (family man)</a></li>
<li><a href="#beautiful">Roger plays a beautiful tennis game (smooth and accurate)</a></li>
<li><a href="#regal">Federer is regal, debonair, and charming</a></li>
<li><a href="#gracious">Roger Federer is gracious in victory and defeat (on and off-court)</a></li>
<li><a href="#loves">The Fed truly loves the game of tennis</a></li>
<li><a href="#generous">The Swiss Maestro is generous with charitable causes</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="hrule clearfix" style="background:#81d742; height:1px"></div>
<p>At only 37, the “Fed” has already reached legendary status with his vast trove of tennis accomplishments. To date, that includes 20 grand slam trophies and so many records that it would fill this entire post up.</p>
<p>The only glitch is that Federer has come up short against Rafael Nadal on clay. Other than that, Federer’s star has shined brighter than any other male tennis player in history.</p>
<p>One coach I know says Federer’s style is like “flowing water”. Surely, Roger has one of the prettiest games of all time, and his one-handed backhand and volleys are absolute strokes of beauty. His game matches his on and off-court persona &#8211; class personified.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="clean"></a></p>
<h2>Roger Has A Squeaky Clean Image</h2>
</div>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-1973 alignright" src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/Fed9.jpg" alt="Federer" width="400" height="318" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/Fed9.jpg 400w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/01/Fed9-300x239.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" /></p>
<p>Federer is one of the most well-tempered athletes of all time. He is esteemed by his peers, the fans, analysts, and even his top rivals. The Swiss Maestro is an extremely likable person and hasn’t made one major publicity mistake in his career.</p>
<p>He always has a smile and is well-groomed and well-spoken. Federer can also speak five languages fluently, which is another reason he endears himself so well to fans around the world.</p>
<p>In an age when many sports stars are mired in controversy, Federer has managed to keep a squeaky-clean image. This has garnered him dozens of endorsement deals with the likes of companies like Rolex, Wilson, Mercedes, and Nike.</p>
<p>A rarity in sports, Federer has been able to maintain a stable family life with his loving wife, Mirka. The marriage has worked out perfectly. Mirka was a former professional tennis player too but quit early on to work as Roger’s manager.</p>
<p>You can see her seated courtside at his every match to support him. The couple now has four children and are as wholesome a family as you can find. Roger has been with Mirka since the beginning of his career.</p>
<p>It seems to me that most male tennis players are one-woman type guys. Federer is no different. He’s been loyal to Mirka since they met and I believe having the stability of her as his wife and manager has allowed him to thrive on court.</p>
<p>This is another reason why Roger Federer is so popular with tennis fans. He’s loyal, devoted to his family and always seems to do the right thing. But on top of that, he’s also the most talented tennis player to ever live.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="beautiful"></a></p>
<h2>He Has A Beautiful Tennis Game</h2>
</div>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1969" src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/Fed5.jpg" alt="Federer forehand" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/Fed5.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/01/Fed5-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/01/Fed5-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>When it comes to tennis style, perhaps no other player moves and hits the ball as gracefully as Federer. While most other players seem labored in their games, Federer makes tennis look effortless with his adept footwork.</p>
<p>I believe this is one of the reasons for Roger’s longevity. If you watch his footwork, you’ll notice its textbook. He makes the most efficient movements possible, which help to preserve his body.</p>
<p>His footwork, combined with keen anticipation, has allowed him to remain at the pinnacle of the tennis world for nearly the last two decades. Roger’s style is very pleasing to the eye and all his strokes are marvelous to watch.</p>
<p>Roger’s forehand is one of the prettiest strokes in the game. It’s also one of the most lethal. The Swiss Maestro’s serve is classic in style and his volley game is superb.</p>
<p>I love watching Roger come in and knock off volleys. Of course, his one-handed backhand is a shot of beauty too. Especially when he hits it down the line for an outright winner.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="regal"></a></p>
<h2>He Is Regal, Debonair, and Charming</h2>
</div>
<div style="width: 153px" class="wp-caption alignright"><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Roger-Federer-Life-Size-Cutout/dp/B010QWXJNG/ref=as_li_ss_il?ie=UTF8&amp;linkCode=li3&amp;tag=aim078-20&amp;linkId=5668cade65f52049b6e3437f003d7050&amp;language=en_US" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="//ws-na.amazon-adsystem.com/widgets/q?_encoding=UTF8&amp;ASIN=B010QWXJNG&amp;Format=_SL400_&amp;ID=AsinImage&amp;MarketPlace=US&amp;ServiceVersion=20070822&amp;WS=1&amp;tag=aim078-20&amp;language=en_US" alt="" width="143" height="400" border="0" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">Lifesize Federer Cutout available from Amazon</p></div>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" style="border: none !important; margin: 0px !important;" src="https://ir-na.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=aim078-20&amp;language=en_US&amp;l=li3&amp;o=1&amp;a=B010QWXJNG" alt="" width="1" height="1" border="0" /><br />
Federer is unlike any other player on the tour in the way he conducts himself. He’s had that charm and charisma most of his career, but it’s become more evident upon reaching his 30s.</p>
<p>Some say Roger carries himself like royalty, but without the pomp and arrogance. You can see that in the impeccable way he dresses and how he always appears calm, organized and collected.</p>
<p>Many professional tennis players disdain the press and answer questions simply because they must. But Roger truly loves people and is very gracious with his time to reporters.</p>
<p>I’ve never watched a press conference or post-match interview with Roger and came away feeling like he’s not the greatest guy in the world. He always praises his opponents, thanks to the fans and staff, and is generally very positive.</p>
<p>There’s just something about the way Roger conducts himself at all times that is regal. It’s hard to put your finger on it, but you know it when you see it.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="gracious"></a></p>
<h2>He&#8217;s Gracious in Victory and Defeat</h2>
</div>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1972" src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/Fed8.jpg" alt="Federer" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/Fed8.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/01/Fed8-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/01/Fed8-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Being gracious in defeat is something expected in professional tennis, but it doesn’t happen all the time. Players scoff at each other, berate officials or blame circumstances for their losses.</p>
<p>While John McEnroe and Jimmy Connors set the bar high for most outrageous behavior on the tennis court, Federer has gone the opposite direction.</p>
<p>Yes, early on in his career, Federer had some tantrums and broke some rackets. But he quickly learned to temper his anger and accept his mistakes and losses with grace. As a result, he’s won the Stefan Edberg Sportsmanship Award several times.</p>
<p>I personally like watching the tantrums of McEnroe but to each their own. I guess I favor players that wear their hearts on their sleeve – like Andre Agassi and even Nadal.</p>
<p>Even though Federer conducts himself with exemplary behavior on the court, he’s no stoic Pete Sampras. The Fed does pump his fist and show emotion when doing well. And that’s perfectly acceptable. I think it pumps the fans up too.</p>
<p>But no matter what happens on the court, Federer is always gracious in victory and defeat. You can see the losses really bother him, but he hides it well. His humbleness in defeat is part of the reason the fans love him, and he knows that.</p>
<p>Throughout his career, Roger has been in very few disputes with the chair umpires and lines people. He almost never shows anger accept to hit a ball hard after a point. I saw him do this in one match and the fans booed a bit.</p>
<p>Sometimes I feel Roger is held to an impossibly high standard by the tennis world, but he’s one of the few athletes (in any sport) who can live up to it. It’s doubtful we’ll ever see the likes of such an accomplished player on and off the court as Roger.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="loves"></a></p>
<h2>Federer Absolutely Loves The Game Of Tennis</h2>
</div>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-1968 alignleft" src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/Fed4.jpg" alt="" width="400" height="550" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/Fed4.jpg 400w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/01/Fed4-218x300.jpg 218w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>One of the most endearing parts of Roger (at least to me) is his love for the game. You can see he loves tennis more than any other player on the tour. And when you’re one of the best in the world, why would you want to stop?</p>
<p>Yes, he has a family, more commitments than ever before, and his body is aging, but that hasn’t stopped Roger from continuing to compete at the highest levels of the game.</p>
<p>Only a true love of the game has allowed Roger to go on at age 37.</p>
<p>At this point, Roger is the oldest player on tour in the top 100. I personally feel like he’ll play another several years if his body holds up and he can maintain a rank inside the top 10.</p>
<p>Roger is not a self-absorbed person, but he loves the spotlight when on court. He adores the adulation of the fans and loves to put on a great show for them. It’s what he does best in life and loves the most – along with his family.</p>
<p>Roger is also a student of the game and knows all the greats of tennis past. He is particularly fond of Rod Laver and the greats that came before him, like Sampras and McEnroe.</p>
<p>While Roger is acclaimed for his talent and awesome shot-making ability, his on-court intelligence is often understated. Roger knows exactly which strategy to carry out against each opponent he plays.</p>
<p>On many occasions, he’s dazzled us with some of the most brilliant shots the game has ever seen. In my opinion, Roger will always be connected to the game of tennis, even long after his career is over.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="generous"></a></p>
<h2>Roger Is Generous With Charitable Causes</h2>
</div>
<p>Roger is one of the more generous tennis players when it comes to charitable causes. His Roger Federer Foundation has been particularly helpful to children in Southern Africa and Switzerland.</p>
<p>His charity has raised millions of dollars over the last decade. These funds go directly into helping impoverished children in those environments receive an education.</p>
<p>Roger is also charitable with his time, even helping long-time rival Rafael Nadal when he opened his tennis academy in Mallorca, Spain. Federer has also helped a number of people financially that never gets mentioned in the media.</p>
<p>Amongst the many charitable causes that Federer has donated to are the Make-A-Wish-Foundation, Small Steps Project, Elton John AIDs Foundation, and Humpty Dumpty Foundation. There are others as well.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Bottom Line</h2>
<p>If Roger Federer is your favorite player in tennis, enjoy his game while he’s still on tour. I would personally love to see what he can do at age 40.</p>
<p>At the beginning of Roger’s career, I wasn’t a huge fan. But I’ve been won over and now see the brilliance of his game. His wonderful temperament has also swayed me into becoming a supporter.</p>
<p>I try to watch all Roger’s matches at the major tournaments. If I can’t watch them on TV, I watch highlights on youtube. We’re fortunate to have a player like Roger in tennis.</p>
<p>He’s truly an icon that kids can look up to as a role model. Roger’s the perfect player: grace under fire, elegant in appearance, a family man, generous, kind, and always smiling. What more could you ask for in an athlete and a person?</p>
<p>The post <a href="/why-is-roger-federer-most-peoples-favorite-player/">Why Is Roger Federer Most People’s Favorite Player?</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/why-is-roger-federer-most-peoples-favorite-player/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>3</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>How Can I Improve My Backhand?</title>
		<link>/how-can-i-improve-my-backhand/</link>
					<comments>/how-can-i-improve-my-backhand/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chad Walner]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 17 Jan 2019 20:49:39 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Theory]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[backhand]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1948</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The tennis backhand can be a difficult shot for beginners in tennis. Most players today are taught the two-handed backhand, which is the shot most professional players hit with on tour. As a tennis instructor, I only teach the two-handed &#8230; <a class="kt-excerpt-readmore" href="/how-can-i-improve-my-backhand/" aria-label="How Can I Improve My Backhand?">Read More</a></p>
<p>The post <a href="/how-can-i-improve-my-backhand/">How Can I Improve My Backhand?</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The tennis backhand can be a difficult shot for beginners in tennis. Most players today are taught the two-handed backhand, which is the shot most professional players hit with on tour.</p>
<p>As a tennis instructor, I only teach the two-handed backhand. But this doesn’t mean the one-handed backhand doesn’t have a place. I think this is evident by looking at the career of Roger Federer.</p>
<p>Federer uses a one-handed backhand, and as of the writing of this article, has racked up 20 grand slam titles. Not bad. If the one hander was a detriment, he would have never won a single major.</p>
<p>If you’re new to tennis and wondering which way to go on your backhand – one hands or two – I can tell you both are a great choice. But only one will work better for you. And only you know.</p>
<p>If you lack power or accuracy on your backhand, chances are your mechanics and timing are at fault. If you’re using the two-hander now, and you lack power, you may consider switching to the one.</p>
<p>I hit with both the two and the one, and I can tell you that there is no comparison for me. While the two-handed backhand offers stability, control, and allows me to hit late, it really lacks the drive and effortless power of the one-handed backhand.</p>
<p>I’ve always had a natural one-handed backhand and can crank the ball when it’s in my zone. I’m getting better at hitting the high shots (balls above the shoulder). This is the major challenge for all one-handed backhand players and the reason why Rafael Nadal always beats Federer on clay.</p>
<p>I discovered that you really need to brush strongly on the ball when it’s up high. By doing so, you can generate good topspin while still hitting with pace. However, it’s tricky and takes a while to learn.</p>
<p>Your best bet for improving your backhand (one or two) is on a ball machine. I like to have the balls bounce around head height so I can practice hitting the high shots. I feel like if you can deal with the high shots in tennis, you can deal with anything.</p>
<p>By now it may be clear that I favor the one-handed backhand. It’s one of the purest shots in tennis and if executed correctly, it’s virtually effortless. I know many people struggle with their one-hander, so I want to give you some tips that really helped me.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>How Do I Improve My Backhand For Tennis?</h2>
<p>I am only going to talk about the one hander here. I have other blog posts all about technique on the two-hander, if you’re interested.</p>
<p>First off for your one-hander, you’ll want to have an eastern backhand grip &#8211; or something very close to it. The modified eastern grip works well too. See below for more information on backhand grips.</p>
<p>When hitting the one hander, it’s very important that you establish a good power position. Take a look at the best one-handed backhand players in the game today.</p>
<p>You’ll see all of them getting into the power position before striking the ball – that is unless they have no time to set up. For that reason, I think it’s mandatory you establish a power position before hitting the ball.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>While this article is not meant to go into detail on technique, I must emphasize this part of the stroke. Look at the pictures here to see the power position for the one-handed backhand. It involves a very strong unit turn.</p>
<p>After establishing the power position, you’ll work your way into the slot position. On this part of the stroke, the racket will drop and your hand will be very close into your body. The tip of the racket should be behind you (meaning opposite side of the body) at this point.</p>
<p>I feel this is an area of the backhand where a lot of people go wrong. I see many club players failing to either drop the racket down or bring the hand in close enough to the body. A failure of either, especially the latter, will result in lost power.</p>
<p>I urge you to look at Federer’s backhand in super slow motion. You’ll first see him attain the power position. Next, he moves into the slot position. These are not difficult maneuvers to achieve. You just need to practice them.</p>
<p>Why is a good slot position so important? It’s because the racket needs maximum room to accelerate into the ball. It does that by moving away from the body and out into the ball.</p>
<p>Every groundstroke in tennis has an outside-inside-outside component. I talked about this in other blog posts. The one-handed backhand is no different.</p>
<p>This brings us to the third part of the one hand backhand, which is swing-to-contact. After reaching the slot position, you’ll swing to contact the ball.</p>
<p>Your nondominant hand will come off the racket and your dominant hand (the one with the racket) will remain perfectly straight throughout the rest of the stroke. This is crucial.</p>
<p>For some reason, people like to bend their elbow before they hit the ball or after. This will surely detract from power and accuracy. If the best one-handed players in the world don’t bend their arms throughout the whole stroke, why would you?</p>
<p>As you swing (with a fully straight arm) to hit the ball, contact should be made in front of the lead foot. Unlike the two-hander, where you can hit late, the one hander needs to be struck out in front of the body.</p>
<p>For this reason, good preparation and timing is essential for hitting the one hander. However, the benefit is more effortless power than the two-hander. Think of it like this: If you throw a frisbee, would you throw it further using one hands or two hands?</p>
<p>The answer is one, which is why frisbees are only thrown with one hand. Throwing a frisbee and hitting a one-handed backhand are similar motions. It makes sense then that the one hander can generate more power.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>The act of throwing a frisbee or hitting a one-hander is even a more natural motion than hitting a forehand. With the backhand motion, we are throwing away from our body. In the latter (the forehand) we’re throwing against or across our body.</p>
<p>I believe that the one hander provides the most powerful shot in the game of tennis, with the exception of the serve and overhead. This is because of the tremendous amount of torque created before the shot.</p>
<p>Okay, enough about biomechanics. Let’s get back to the swing-to-contact. As you make contact with the ball, your hitting hand should be almost in a punch position (see picture). Your first will be almost facing your opponent with hand, wrist, and arm all aligned straight.</p>
<p>This is another place where many club players get it wrong. I see them bending their wrist or hitting the ball too soon or too late. Look at the pictures here so you can see the correct arm position when making contact.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>After contact is made, you’ll continue the swing all the way to follow through. The best one handers on the pro tour (Dimitrov, Thiem, Wawrinka) make a complete follow through, so the bottom of their rackets end up facing their opponents at the end of the stroke.</p>
<p>This takes some flexibility. Most of you at the club level will be fine following through around 80-85% of the way (from the pros). Just make sure you finish high and your arm stays straight.</p>
<p>It’s critical to mention here that you should keep your nondominant hand back to stabilize your body. You’ll also want to keep closed (meaning stay to the side) as you hit the one hander.</p>
<p>Another common issue on the one-handed tennis backhand is opening up too soon. This means players face the court way too early when hitting the stroke. It’s important to stay to the side, as I just mentioned.</p>
<p>That’s it. Easy, right?</p>
<p>We just covered the four major points of the one-handed backhand. To recap they are:</p>
<ul>
<li>power position</li>
<li>slot position</li>
<li>swing-to-contact</li>
<li>follow through</li>
</ul>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>If you can put all these steps together into one nice, smooth-flowing stroke, you’ll have yourself a beautiful one-handed backhand. In time, you’ll be able to hit with power, topspin, and accuracy.</p>
<p>Remember to video yourself to make sure you’re hitting all the major positions correctly. Practice shadow swinging at home to ensure you lock them into your muscle memory. Then reinforce it on the ball machine or with a practice partner.</p>
<p>If you know somebody that can volley well, have them stand at the net and volley the ball to your backhand over-and-over. This one of the best ways to practice. You’ll hit more backhands than in rallies and learn to set up faster.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Who Has A One-Handed Backhand?</h2>
<p>While the one-handed backhand is waning in popularity, there are still some very successful pros in the men’s game that use it. As of 2019, here are the best one handers in the game of tennis.</p>
<ul>
<li>Roger Federer</li>
<li>Dominic Thiem</li>
<li>Gregor Dimitrov</li>
<li>Stanislaw Wawrinka</li>
<li>Richard Gasquet</li>
<li>Dennis Shapovalov</li>
<li>Stefanos Tsitsipas</li>
<li>Nicolas Almagro (if he returns to action from injury)</li>
</ul>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>On the women’s tour, very few players use the one hander. I can only think of two players that use the one-hander who are ranked inside the top 100. Everyone else uses the two-hander. Amazing.</p>
<ul>
<li>Carla Suarez Navarro</li>
<li>Tatjana Maria</li>
</ul>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>In the rest of this blog post, I’m going to answer some common questions people have about the one hander. I think you’ll find this segment interesting.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>What Grip Does Roger Federer Use For Backhand?</h2>
<p>Federer uses a modified eastern backhand grip. This is where the knuckles are not sitting directly over bevel one but positioned slightly more to the second bevel. This is the same grip I use on my one-handed tennis backhand. I feel it offers maximum power with sufficient spin.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>What Is Tennis Eastern Grip?</h2>
<p>The eastern grip, also called the eastern backhand grip, is when the knuckles of the hitting hand are positioned directly over bevel one. When hitting the backhand, bevel one is the top part of the handle.</p>
<p>This is a great grip for hitting the one handed backhand with good power and spin. It is used by many of the ATP pros who hit with one hand on their backhand.</p>
<h2></h2>
<h2>Why Do Some Tennis Players Play A Single Handed Backhand And Some A Two-Handed Backhand?</h2>
<p>It largely depends on how players were coached when young. Almost all coaches these days teach the two-hander over the one. But back in the 1990s, when most of today’s players were learning the game, old-time coaches still preferred the one hander.</p>
<p>For this reason, they taught it to their students. The great players on tour you see today who use the one probably had such coaches. In some instances, a coach will show a young player both strokes and see which one the player hits better.</p>
<p>Some players really take to the one hander. The one-hander was more popular when serve and volley was in vogue. This is because one-handed backhand players have an easier time serving and volleying.</p>
<p>Such was the case with Pete Sampras, who started off with a good two-handed backhand, but made the switch to the one when he was around 13-14 years of age. I personally use both the one and two, but favor the one, as I find it gives a lot more power.</p>
<p>As we already saw with the woman’s game, coaches are exclusively teaching the two-hander now. With serve and volley falling out of vogue, there’s really no reason for players to hit with the one anymore.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Why Are There So Few Tennis Players With One-Handed Backhands?</h2>
<p>The one-handed backhand was very popular in the 1960s and 70s. Popularity for the one started to wane in the 80s when better racket technology was invented. Balls were struck harder and there was less time to set up for shots.</p>
<p>The one-handed backhand requires more time to set up and more precise timing than the two-hander. For this reason, the learning curve on the two-hander is a lot shorter than the one.</p>
<p>Coaches recognized this as the game was becoming faster and more competitive. With increased racket technology, a two-hander could hit with comparable power to a one-hander. Two-handers can also take the ball later, hit the high balls easier, and have more control.</p>
<p>As a result, coaches favored the two-hander and an influx of great two-handed backhand players flooded the pro circuit in the 2000s, especially on the women’s tour. It’s now a novelty to see a female player use a one-handed backhand.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Is Wawrinka’s Backhand The Best One-Handed Backhand In Tennis History?</h2>
<p>I don’t think so. He certainly has a good one, but so do all the other players I mentioned in my list above. How can you not say Federer doesn’t have the best one hander in tennis? He’s only won 20 majors!</p>
<p>I think it all comes down to preference. All these guys can crush their one hander and can end the point in one swing. Personally speaking, I’ve always like the backhand of Nicolas Almagro. But Dominic Thiem’s backhand is amazing as well.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Why Is The Two-Handed Backhand Preferred In Men’s Professional Tennis Today? And Why In The Women’s Game Too?</h2>
<p>For the reasons I mentioned above. There’s a much shorter learning curve with the two-hander and it offers advantages over the one-hander, such as:</p>
<ul>
<li>Easier to return serve</li>
<li>Better able to cope with high balls</li>
<li>Ability to hit late compared to the one hander</li>
<li>More stability and control</li>
</ul>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>There are still men who use the one in the pro game, but the numbers decline each passing decade. On the women’s side, the one hander is virtually extinct. I wouldn’t be surprised to see the day when all top 100 women on the WTA tour use the two-hander.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Should Kids Learn The One-Handed Backhand?</h2>
<p>Absolutely. Why not? Here’s the thing about the one-handed backhand. I’ll put it in this light, or use this metaphor. Imagine teaching a child how to paint in watercolor and in oil. The watercolor can be learned in not too long a time, but it’s a bit limited in terms of its artistic ability on canvas.</p>
<p>Learning to paint in oil is a more refined craft that takes longer to master. However, you can create more diverse art with oil, as its textured. In the end, which is better? While both are beautiful, the oil painting is simply a richer art. But there’s a price to pay for learning to paint in oil (or hit a one-hander), namely the time and practice involved.</p>
<p>The one hander still has a place in the game of tennis. The most successful players of all time have and had one-handed backhands. Here are just a few: Federer, Sampras, the Bryan brothers, and Martina Navratilova. Combined, they have over 250 titles. Not too shabby.</p>
<p>I would suggest showing a child both and asking the child which one they like more. If a child likes to practice and can put in the time, the one handed backhand is an excellent choice.</p>
<p>Yes, there will be more of a struggle in the early stages, but it will pay off down the line. I’ve seen youtube videos of 10-12 year old children hitting incredible one handers.</p>
<p>Thanks for taking the time to read my blog. If you have any questions about the one handed backhand, drop me a comment below. Don’t forget to check out my youtube channel for awesome video tips on your backhand.</p>
<p>The post <a href="/how-can-i-improve-my-backhand/">How Can I Improve My Backhand?</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/how-can-i-improve-my-backhand/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>3</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Why Is Tennis A Hard Sport?</title>
		<link>/why-is-tennis-a-hard-sport/</link>
					<comments>/why-is-tennis-a-hard-sport/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chad Walner]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 16 Jan 2019 17:03:56 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Theory]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1929</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Tennis is one of the toughest sports of all the popular sports to play well. If you’re new to the game, just realize it can take months, or even years, to get to a level where you can hit and &#8230; <a class="kt-excerpt-readmore" href="/why-is-tennis-a-hard-sport/" aria-label="Why Is Tennis A Hard Sport?">Read More</a></p>
<p>The post <a href="/why-is-tennis-a-hard-sport/">Why Is Tennis A Hard Sport?</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Tennis is one of the toughest sports of all the popular sports to play well. If you’re new to the game, just realize it can take months, or even years, to get to a level where you can hit and play confidently.</p>
<p>If you have a good coach from the beginning, it will make your tennis journey a lot easier. I can tell you that for sure. Take it from someone who didn’t have coaching and didn’t know proper technique in my formative tennis years.</p>
<p><strong>I’ve heard it said that tennis and golf are the only two sports you can play life-long and never improve. And I believe it. How many of you know someone that plays either sport frequently and always stays at the same level?</strong></p>
<p><strong>Let me list the ways why tennis is a hard sport:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Tennis requires precise timing and years of practice.</strong></li>
<li><strong>Tennis utilizes technical skills often hidden without the aid of coaching.</strong></li>
<li><strong>Tennis demands a high level of athleticism and coordination.</strong></li>
<li><strong>Tennis calls for a strong mindset and positive attitude in the face of constant adversity.</strong></li>
</ul>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>I want to talk in more detail about these. I believe if you can understand why tennis is hard to pick up, you’ll gain a greater appreciation for the sport. You’ll also better understand how to learn the game.</p>
<p>While some of you may view me as a high-level player, I struggled with my game for years. I didn’t learn tennis at a prestigious academy. I learned through years of trial-by-fire and analysis of the game.</p>
<p>For this reason, I believe I’m perfectly qualified to help recreational players improve their tennis games. I do this in my lessons, my blog, and my videos. I’ve been through it all in tennis and know the little nuances of why people struggle and what they can do to improve.</p>
<p>But this blog post is not about giving technical advice. It’s a post more about the journey of learning the game and answering the question I’m so often asked: “Is tennis a difficult sport to learn?” I believe it is and I my thoughts are reaffirmed every time I give a lesson to a new player.</p>
<p>A couple of years ago, after Serena Williams won yet another major, I saw two women hitting on the court next to me. They clearly had never played tennis before or had minimum experience. They could barely hit the ball to each other but were inspired to play after watching Serena.</p>
<p>One of them commented, “This is harder than I thought. Serena makes it looks so easy on TV.” I thought in my mind, “If you only knew how many hours Serena put into the game to become that good, it would make you shutter.”</p>
<p>People that have never played tennis have little clue how difficult this game is. But with the right coaching and several hundred hours of practice time, a player can reach a beginner level and play entry-level competitive tennis.</p>
<p>Alright, so let’s go through each bullet point I listed above. In that way, I can clarify better.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Tennis Requires Precise Timing And Years Of Practice</h2>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1934" src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/time2.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/time2.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/01/time2-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/01/time2-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>When I first started playing tennis, I rarely hit the ball cleanly. It was only after a couple of years of constantly playing that I learned what it meant to hit the ball on the sweet spot of the racket consistently.</p>
<p>I believe one of the biggest reasons why people don’t succeed early on is a lack of precision in their game. If you can’t hit the ball on the sweet spot, chances are you’ll never excel in tennis.</p>
<p>This only comes through countless hours on the court, learning to time the ball. I find that kids and uncoordinated adults have the hardest time with this. They often hit the ball too early, too late, or near the frame.</p>
<p>It’s a real problem and one not easily solved. To time your swing to hit the ball at the perfect moment is not an easy feat. Sure, the pros make it look easy. But if you’re a beginner tennis player, you know it’s not.</p>
<p>Even after more than 20 years of playing, I still struggle with this on various shots. Most of them are shots taken right off the ground or ones with heavy topspin that raise up high.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>Another area where timing is crucial is the serve. If you want to play a match, you need to learn the tennis serve. I’ve written numerous articles on the serve and why it’s one of the toughest shots in tennis to master.</p>
<p>The serve requires absolutely perfect timing and years of practice to master. Unlike most other sports, the margin of error for this shot is extremely low. Yes, sports like golf and baseball are somewhat similar, but tennis requires precise timing in everything.</p>
<p>When I give lessons, the serve is really where the rubber meets the road. I can quickly tell how adept a player will be. Most struggle with the serve heavily, while others can pick it up at a decent pace. But a strong, advanced serve takes years of learning and good coordination.</p>
<p>The other areas of tennis that require precision timing are the volleys and overheads. These shots often perplex beginners, especially the overhead. But like all the other shots, with practice, they slowly begin to improve.</p>
<p>The volley is perhaps the easiest shot in tennis to hit. It’s a very short, compact motion that anyone can learn. Unfortunately, if the timing is not perfect on it, the volley usually fails.</p>
<p>When a ball is coming 80 mph directly at your body, even players with a great volley can miss. This is what makes tennis so difficult. You can never really predict where the ball is going to be due to factors such as wind and court surface. When playing on clay, it’s like a crapshoot.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Tennis Utilizes Technical Skills Often Hidden Without The Aid Of Coaching</h2>
<div id="attachment_1944" style="width: 810px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1944" class="size-full wp-image-1944" src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/coachandkid.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/coachandkid.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/01/coachandkid-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/01/coachandkid-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /><p id="caption-attachment-1944" class="wp-caption-text">Carine06 from UK [<a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.0">CC BY-SA 2.0</a>], <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Kyle_Edmund_%26_coach_trainer_(8338509649).jpg">via Wikimedia Commons</a></p></div>
<p>I played a lot of sports growing up and I was able to get good at most of them. But the one sport I couldn’t get good at was tennis. This is because it requires a special set of skills oblivious to the new or untrained player.</p>
<p>When I played baseball, the most difficult thing to do was to hit the ball. I did that okay but throwing and running came naturally. In football, all I had to do was catch and run. In basketball, I taught myself to shoot very well and dribble efficiently. It wasn’t very difficult if I practiced enough.</p>
<p>As I got into tennis in my late teens, I noticed my level improved only very gradually. It was almost imperceptible. I played for several hours every day for 4-5 years and saw almost no improvement. It was the one sport I couldn’t figure out.</p>
<p>And that’s because every stroke in tennis involves a unique set of technical skills. If you don’t do the stroke correctly, you end up with what I call a “homemade” stroke that will never compare to hitting the ball with proper technique.</p>
<p>Just watch a recreational player hit the ball and you’ll see a massive difference between them and a pro. Have you ever noticed that? Why is there so much of a difference?</p>
<p>The pro has been taught correct technique and honed it over years of play. The result is a vastly better shot. It’s also a vastly different-looking shot. It’s very evident when comparing a recreational player to a pro.</p>
<p>But when you look at most other sports, there doesn’t appear to be much of a difference between an amateur and a pro. Good examples of this include football, soccer, and basketball. You can go to a recreational game of these sports and the players don’t look that much different from pros if they have experience.</p>
<p>But tennis is different. It’s just a hard sport to learn if you don’t have proper coaching. But with proper coaching, it can be picked up in a year or two with continuous practice.</p>
<p>I’ve seen the difference in coached players and non-coached tennis players &#8211; the difference is stark. If you’re new to tennis and want to improve fast, the best bet is to hire a qualified coach.</p>
<p>If you can’t afford one, take an online tennis course or watch free tennis videos. Trust me, knowing proper technique makes all the difference. It always surprises me when experienced club players make the same glaring flaws in their technique year-after-year.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Tennis Demands A High Level Of Athleticism And Coordination</h2>
<div id="attachment_1938" style="width: 810px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1938" class="size-full wp-image-1938" src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/DjokovicAthleticism.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/DjokovicAthleticism.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/01/DjokovicAthleticism-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/01/DjokovicAthleticism-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /><p id="caption-attachment-1938" class="wp-caption-text"><a title="Novak Djokovic" href="https://flickr.com/photos/43555660@N00/8155421947">&#8220;Novak Djokovic&#8221;</a> by <a href="https://flickr.com/people/43555660@N00">Carine06</a> is licensed under <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.0/">CC BY-SA</a></p></div>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>While almost all sports require a high level of athleticism, it’s especially true in tennis. Being a great athlete is a must if you want to make it to the higher levels of tennis, such as being a Division I college player, advanced level tournament player, or professional tour level player.</p>
<p>If you look at the best players in the sport – Nadal, Federer, Serena – they all have one thing in common: being exceptional athletes. Tennis requires perfect footwork, quick starts and stops, and explosive movements. It also requires superb endurance, as matches could go on for hours.</p>
<p>One of the reasons recreational players fail to advance in tennis is a lack of athleticism. They just can’t move their bodies quick enough to hit a hard groundstroke or penetrating tennis serve.</p>
<p>I see this with my own students. Many of the older ones have trouble generating sufficient racket speed. They also lack the explosion necessary to move to a ball hit away from them and return to a good court position.</p>
<p>I’m afraid not much can be done to improve the athleticism of a 60-year-old woman or man looking to improve their game. For this reason, your level in tennis will largely be determined by your athletic prowess or lack thereof.</p>
<p>In cases like these, working on improved technique is paramount. Just by improving technique, a player can jump up a level without working on any athletic prowess. But movement is key in tennis, so it will be a small level up.</p>
<p>Tennis also requires a high degree of coordination. If you can’t coordinate all the pieces correctly, the kinetic chain breaks down. This will result in poorly hit shots and serves.</p>
<p>When I teach players – especially to new students – I can often spot 5-6 things they need to improve on for each stroke. For example, when teaching the forehand, the mistakes are evident and one seems to affect the other.</p>
<p>They could be lack of power position, not achieving a laid-back wrist, not extending out to hit the ball, lack of follow through and rotation in the body, and hitting late. These are just some examples.</p>
<p>I need to correct all these mistakes for my student to hit a great tennis forehand. But where to begin? Many adult students come to me with bad habits, which is why I like teaching children.</p>
<p>Children are like blank slates. You can show them the proper technique from the beginning and they don’t know anything different. That’s why all the professional players in the world learn tennis when young. Not one of them learned on their own or came to the game as an adult.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Tennis Calls For A Strong Mindset And Positive Attitude</h2>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1946" src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/palash-jain-1185010-unsplash.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/palash-jain-1185010-unsplash.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/01/palash-jain-1185010-unsplash-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/01/palash-jain-1185010-unsplash-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Unlike most other sports, tennis is a one-on-one battle that can drive you to insanity. That is unless you like to play doubles. I personally enjoy both singles and doubles.</p>
<p>In either play, tennis requires a stronger mindset to succeed than most other sports. Among the four major team sports in the U.S. (basketball, baseball, football, and hockey), there are at least four other teammates to rely on. And in football, there are 10!</p>
<p>In these sports, it’s perfectly fine to play a role and allow your teammates to do the rest. I’ll give you an example. In football, the kicker only plays in certain situations, such as when kicking field goals, punts, etc. But the entire rest of the game is dictated by all the other players.</p>
<p>In tennis, you’re responsible for everything that happens on the court. It, therefore, requires a strong mindset, as there are a lot of ups and downs that occur in a match. You’re on the court 100% of the time and all eyes are on you.</p>
<p>Just watch a professional tennis match to see evidence of it. There are so many ups and downs that are possible. During one point a player can be jubilant and the next one point he could be sulking.</p>
<p>I’ve seen so many matches where a player could have easily won, but their mind got the best of them. In one recent match, Sloan Stephens was playing a lower ranked Russian player named Ekaterina Alexandrova. In the first set, Stephens got starched, losing 6-0. That was a shock to everyone.</p>
<p>Alexandrova was up a break in the second set and serving for the match at 5-3. But out of the blue and for seemingly no reason, she began to fall apart. She exacerbated her problems with severe negative body language where it wasn’t necessary.</p>
<p>Instead of remaining poised and strong, every shot she missed would draw a noticeable sigh and shaking of her head. Sloan noticed her dismay and stayed the course. She eventually won the second set in a tie-breaker and took the match in a third set tie-breaker.</p>
<p>The only other sport that rivals tennis for mindset is combat fighting, like boxing or MMA. In those sports, mindset is very important. But even fighters with the best mindsets can be defeated in a single blow.</p>
<p>Tennis is a bit different in that a player always needs to win at least 12 games before the match is over. This can take anywhere from 45 minutes (if a very decisive victory) to several hours or more. A tennis player, therefore, needs to remain mentally strong and focused for hours at a time.</p>
<p>Any lapse in mental fortitude can result in losing the match. It took me a while to hone my mental attitude to where it is today. But beginners often become too despondent when they miss or lose.</p>
<p>For this reason, tennis is a hard sport to get good at. It definitely requires mental strength, as well as physical abilities.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Bottom Line</h2>
<p>As you can see, tennis is not an easy sport to learn. It requires a lot of time and practice to get good at. Unfortunately, it often involves a good deal of money to get good at as well.</p>
<p>I hope this post answers some questions you had about tennis. Please don’t let me discourage you from playing though. I know some of the things I said here make tennis seem difficult.</p>
<p>I admit tennis is a difficult sport to learn, but you’ll never know how good you can be until you try it out. So take to the court, learn proper technique, and have low expectations in the beginning. That’s your best route to success in tennis.</p>
<p>If you enjoyed this blog post, check out some of the other posts on my blog. I have a lot of great posts on improving your game as a beginner. Additionally, you might want to check out my youtube channel for awesome video tutorials. See you on court soon!</p>
<p>Featured image altered from Carine06 from UK [<a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.0">CC BY-SA 2.0</a>], <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Tecau_serve_(8155696716).jpg">via Wikimedia Commons</a></p>
<p>The post <a href="/why-is-tennis-a-hard-sport/">Why Is Tennis A Hard Sport?</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/why-is-tennis-a-hard-sport/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>How Much Does It Cost To Play Tennis?</title>
		<link>/how-much-does-it-cost-to-play-tennis/</link>
					<comments>/how-much-does-it-cost-to-play-tennis/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chad Walner]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 16 Jan 2019 16:09:26 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Theory]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[coaching]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1931</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>I’ve been playing tennis for 25 years and I can tell you it does cost money to play. But it may surprise you how little it can cost in the right locations. The cost to play tennis varies depending on &#8230; <a class="kt-excerpt-readmore" href="/how-much-does-it-cost-to-play-tennis/" aria-label="How Much Does It Cost To Play Tennis?">Read More</a></p>
<p>The post <a href="/how-much-does-it-cost-to-play-tennis/">How Much Does It Cost To Play Tennis?</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I’ve been playing tennis for 25 years and I can tell you it does cost money to play. But it may surprise you how little it can cost in the right locations.</p>
<p><strong>The cost to play tennis varies depending on your location and several other factors. If you’re curious to know if tennis only a rich man’s sport, this post will spell it all out for you.</strong></p>
<p><strong>Tennis is like anything else in life. The more money you spend, the better quality you get. If you’re stretched for money though, I’ll show you a few ways to play tennis on the cheap.</strong></p>
<p>I already said location is a factor in cost. Here are some other factors that will influence your tennis budget:</p>
<ul>
<li>Tennis gear</li>
<li>Court time</li>
<li>Coaching</li>
<li>Tournaments and leagues</li>
</ul>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Unlike basketball or soccer, where you can just show up and play for free, tennis usually requires money to play. This is because of the factors I just mentioned.</p>
<p>But tennis need not break your budget. In this article, I’ll explain how you can keep your tennis costs low. For those who have the money to spend, I’ll discuss how you can create an awesome tennis lifestyle and really take your game to the next level.</p>
<p>Without further ado, let’s get into it, starting with location.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Cost Depending On Location</h2>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1942" src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/piggybank.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/piggybank.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/01/piggybank-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/01/piggybank-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>In my opinion, location is one of the most important factors to influence the amount of money you spend on tennis. I’ll give you an example from my life.</p>
<p>I was born and raised in New York. In the summertime, outdoor public and private courts are available. Some public courts were free but most required small fees ($5-$8 per hour per person). I was glad to pay those fees to play in the warm months.</p>
<p>But when the cold months come, tennis outdoors is virtually out the window. Nobody likes to play in 30-degree weather with snow on the ground – although I did it a few times.</p>
<p>The only option at that point is to play indoors. We called indoor courts “tennis bubbles”. The cost for indoor courts is considerably more than outdoor courts. The costs for indoor courts usually range from $40-$100 per hour per person!</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>If you live in a cold-weather state or country, indoor courts are your only option. If you play three times per week for one hour each day, at an average cost of $50 per hour, you’re looking at $600 per month.</p>
<p>That’s not cheap. And that doesn’t include the tennis gear and possible coaching. When I was living in New York, some of the indoor tennis courts offered deals where you could buy a seasonal membership.</p>
<p>In one club where I bought a membership, it allowed me to play any time the courts weren’t booked. In another club, I could only book court time during certain hours.</p>
<p>If you like to play a lot of tennis and your schedule is flexible, ask your local indoor tennis club if they have seasonal memberships. This is by far the cheapest way to go. Try to avoid peak hours, where the rates are sky high.</p>
<p>So that was life in New York. On average, I’d spend around $20-$30 per week during the outdoor season on court time and approximately $100 per month for indoor court time in the cold season.</p>
<p>But that was over 20 years ago, in the mid-‘90s. It’s probably more now. I also got great deals on indoor courts due to playing on the local college tennis team.</p>
<p>If you live in a cold-weather state, plan to spend at least several hundred dollars per month if you want to play a couple of hours per week. There’s really no getting around the cost of indoor court time.</p>
<p>In January of 2007, I moved to sunny South Florida. A lot of my decision had to do with the tennis down here. First, there are no indoor courts; all courts are outside and there is an abundance of them. This dramatically lowered my cost of playing tennis alone.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>Tennis can be played outdoors here year-round, with average temperatures in the 70s during the winter months. Second, there are more players here and the tennis is better than New York.</p>
<p>Currently, I spend zero money on court time. This is because I have private tennis courts in my community. Now you may be lucky and have that in your community as well. If so, it really cuts down on the cost of tennis.</p>
<p>One of my clients, an esteemed gentleman who compensates me nicely to hit with him, pays for my membership to a private club. This club has 8 har-true tennis courts. Additionally, I have a ton of tennis buddies who have access to tennis courts all around the area, so playing here in Florida is very cheap.</p>
<p>If you’re serious about tennis, moving to a warm climate will decrease your tennis costs substantially. You’ll also find more players to hit with, be able to play more often, and enjoy life more. No, seriously. Warm climates are awesome!</p>
<p>Some of you may live in remote locations where tennis courts are far. In that case, you’ll need to drive quite a distance, which requires gas money and time.</p>
<p>The bottom line is that your location will largely dictate how much you spend on tennis. In the best of cases, like mine, tennis will be virtually free. In the worst case, and if you’re an avid player, you could spend as much as $1000 per month on indoor court time in cold-weather areas and months.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>How Much Does Tennis Gear Cost?</h2>
<p>Tennis gear isn’t cheap. But it need not break your budget. Below is a list of the necessary tennis gear you’ll need when you start playing. As you get better, you may add more items to the list, but these are the bare essentials.</p>
<ul>
<li>Tennis sneakers</li>
<li>Tennis shorts, shirt, and hat (optional)</li>
<li>Rackets</li>
<li>String</li>
<li>Balls</li>
<li>Tennis bag</li>
<li>Grips</li>
</ul>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>The most expensive cost will be your tennis rackets. Now, you could go out and buy a $10 racket off eBay, but I’m assuming you’ll want to buy a new racket of good quality. Any decent adult tennis racket is going to cost you at least $100.</p>
<p>You’ll need at minimum two rackets but having three is optimal. The reason is that strings break unexpectedly. If you have only two rackets and the strings go on one, now you have just one racket left. That’s why I always carry three rackets in my tennis bag.</p>
<p>The next most expensive item will be your tennis sneakers. These can range from $40 up to over $100. The type I buy (Addidas Barricade) costs around $65. While you can practically wear any sneaker on court, tennis sneakers are best because they give you the best traction and ankle support of any kind of sneaker for tennis.</p>
<p>Next up is tennis apparel, which I put as optional. You can wear any sports related garb you want on court, but if you want to look and feel the part, you’ll want to purchase tennis shorts, shirt, and hat.</p>
<p>Tennis apparel is not cheap. But if you have the budget and are fashion conscious, spend the money to get yourself some good-looking clothing. Most tennis apparel is light, colorful, and made for tennis. If you don’t buy tennis shorts, always use shorts or pants with pockets. You’ll need pockets to hold the balls.</p>
<p>String can be another big expense, but only if you buy it in bulk. I usually spend about $100 on buying bulk string every three months. But I play often. When you break the strings on your racket, you’ll need to either restring the racket yourself or bring it to a professional stringer.</p>
<p>Most professional tennis stringers charge a minimum of $20-$25 for their labor and string. This usually involves cheap string. If you want a higher quality string, you’ll need to spend upwards of $35, maybe even $40 or $45. This is for one racket.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>It’s actually cheaper to buy string in bulk and give it to the stringer every time you string a racket. That’s what I do. I buy the string from Amazon and then hand it to my stringer, who charges me $15 per racket. In total, I pay around $25 per racket (for labor and string) when all is said and done.</p>
<p>How often will you string your racket? That totally depends on how much you play and your level of play. I know people that restring only a couple of times per year. I also know people that restring every week.</p>
<p>The one cost you can’t skimp on is balls. Playing with dead balls is no fun. So you’ll want to open a new can of tennis balls each time you play a match. If you’re just practicing, used balls can work fine.</p>
<p>The cost for balls ranges in price from $2.50 per can up to about $4. When you play tennis with friends, it’s customary for you to alter opening a new can. For example, if I play tennis Monday with Gary, I’ll open a new can. When we play again on Thursday, it’s his turn to open a new can.</p>
<p>The cost for balls isn’t exorbitant. It’s just an expense you’ll need to continually pay, unlike when you buy a racket and you’re good for several years. Figure on spending $10 per month for balls on the low side, and up to $30-$40 per month on the high side.</p>
<p>The tennis bag is essential. I see some people show up with a backpack or some other contraption and it looks awful. If you don’t have a tennis bag, do yourself a favor and buy one if you play tennis consistently. It’s a one-time expense for the most part.</p>
<p>A tennis bag is made to carry rackets and all your equipment. Not just that, but it makes you look like a real player and it’s very practical. New tennis bags usually start around $40. If you’re on a budget, you can probably buy a cheap, used tennis bag on e-bay for $10 or so.</p>
<p>The last piece of tennis gear I&#8217;ll mention is grips. Grips are fairly cheap, at about $2 each. A grip will last you on average 5-10 hours of play. It really depends on how warm it is when you play, how much you sweat, and how aggressively you grip the racket.</p>
<p>I like to buy the 12-pack of Wilson Tennis Overgrips. I find them to be comfortable and really absorb sweat well. It’s always best to have more grips than less.</p>
<p>Most people underestimate the importance of grips, but they can vastly improve your strokes. Ever try playing with a ratty, frayed grip on a hot humid day? If you have, you know what I’m talking about.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>How Much Does Coaching Cost?</h2>
<p>If you’re new to tennis, I recommend getting coaching, at least in the beginning. Tennis is a lot more fun when you know proper technique. I’ll go over the cost of coaching here, plus a few other alternatives for those more budget-minded.</p>
<p>If you’re an experienced player, you can probably skip the coaching if you enjoy playing at your level. Still, it never hurts to take a lesson from a qualified tennis coach to up your game. Even Roger Federer has a coach!</p>
<p>The fastest way to learn tennis is through private coaching. Private coaching rates vary by location and coach. Figure on paying $30 on the low side, and $100 or more for the very best coaches. In my opinion, $60 per hour should get you an excellent coach.</p>
<p>If you take a lesson once a week from a $60 per hour coach, your costs per month will be $240. As a beginner, you will likely need coaching for several months to get up to speed.</p>
<p>A cheaper alternative is to do group lessons or join a clinic. You won’t get the one-on-one attention that a private coaching lesson affords, but it’s your next best option.</p>
<p>For example, you could ask a private coach to teach you and one or two other friends at the same time. This would cut the cost down considerably. It might also make the lesson more fun with your friends involved.</p>
<p>On the other hand, clinics can range from several people up to a dozen. The costs vary depending on group size and duration. Most clinics I know charge $15-$20 per person. Most clinics are more for practice than technique though, so it’s a good option if you already know proper technique.</p>
<p>The next alternative option is an on-line course. Courses can range in price from around $20 up to $100, depending on the instructor and what the course involves. These courses will show you step-by-step how to hit each tennis stroke.</p>
<p>These tennis courses are great in that you have the lesson right there in video any time you want. However, there’s one huge drawback when compared to private coaching: there’s nobody there to watch and correct your strokes.</p>
<p>For this reason, you’ll need to video your strokes and compare them to the video lesson. Or, you can send your video to a qualified coach to critique. It will cost you, but it’s a lot cheaper to go this route than regular private coaching lessons.</p>
<p>The last option is to watch free tennis videos on youtube. I have a lot of great tennis tutorial videos on my youtube channel if you need help with your game. I have videos on the backhand, forehand, serve, volleys, and footwork.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Costs Of Tournaments And Leagues</h2>
<p>If you’re a competitive player and know the fundamentals of tennis, you may consider joining a tennis tournament or tennis league. What’s the difference you may ask? And how much does each cost?</p>
<p>A tennis tournament is a one-time event that is usually played on the weekend. Many tournaments are a one-and-done event, meaning if you lose, you don’t play another matche.</p>
<p>The USTA is the best place to look for local tennis tournaments. As of 2019, it costs $44 per year for an adult membership. As a member, you’ll be able to enter local tournaments at your level.</p>
<p>The average USTA tournaments costs $50 to enter. The cost covers court time, balls, and lights (if necessary). It’s not a bad deal and it will give you good experience. The drawback is that it can become costly if you enter tournaments every weekend and need to drive far to get to them.</p>
<p>That’s why I prefer to join tennis leagues. These are usually offered by your local tennis club (if you have one). In my area, I have a club about 10 miles from my home. The club offers singles and doubles leagues every week.</p>
<p>The cost for joining the league is $46 and includes court time, balls, lights, and 7 guaranteed matches. It’s quite a deal, I know. But then again, this is South Florida.</p>
<p>The leagues are a lot of fun because you usually play with the same people year-after-year and make good friends. My league has five flights with 8 people per flight. The line-up in each flight changes slightly after each season ends (a season is 8 matches).</p>
<p>If you enjoy tennis and have a tennis club near you, call them and ask if they offer leagues. To me, they’re far better than tournaments and a lot cheaper.</p>
<p>Now, if you’re goal is to make it to the higher levels of tennis (past 5.0 level), than you’ll want to play tournaments. If I wanted to see how high I can go in tennis, I’d start playing open tournaments all throughout Florida.</p>
<p>But due to my coaching and work schedule, it’s not practical. But if you’re young, hungry for success, and have great talent, tournaments are the only way to go. By playing tournaments you can rank state-wide, nationally, and even gain a world ranking. Oh, if only I could have been ranked 758 in the world. My life would be so much better now (LOL).</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Summing It Up</h2>
<p>If you’ve read this far, you now have a good idea of the costs associated with tennis. Just know, it’s entirely possible to play tennis year-round for free. I know a guy near me who plays virtually for free.</p>
<p>His name is Drew and he’s a very talented club player (5.0 level). He’s so good, that other players don’t mind paying for his court time and the balls. Drew just shows up and plays whenever he’s asked. The only tennis expense Drew has are for strings, grips, and a change of sneakers a couple of times per year.</p>
<p>This is an extreme example. On the high side, if you want to play at prestigious tennis clubs, take lessons from the best pros, and have awesome new gear, you can easily spend $15,000-$25,000 per year on tennis.</p>
<p>I didn’t mention it earlier, but if you’re a parent who has a child who wants to excel in tennis, you’ll need to pay for private lessons (or group lessons at least). In that case, budget several thousand dollars per year for 1-2 hours of lessons per week.</p>
<p>If you’re one of those crazed parents who want their child to become a tennis pro, you’ll want to send your child to a tennis academy. The prestigious academies down here in Florida, like Bollettieri, Macci, and Evert will cost your child a hefty $40,000 per semester!</p>
<p>If you have any questions about the costs associated with tennis, drop me a comment below. Thanks for reading. Check out the rest of my blog for cool tennis tips and info.</p>
<p>The post <a href="/how-much-does-it-cost-to-play-tennis/">How Much Does It Cost To Play Tennis?</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/how-much-does-it-cost-to-play-tennis/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Is Tennis A Popular Sport?</title>
		<link>/is-tennis-a-popular-sport/</link>
					<comments>/is-tennis-a-popular-sport/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chad Walner]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 07 Jan 2019 09:53:15 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Theory]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1905</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>In the U.S., while basketball, football, and baseball take center stage, tennis is also huge with a reported 17.9 million players. Even more people than this are tennis fans and watch tennis matches regularly. Additionally, over 14 million Americans report &#8230; <a class="kt-excerpt-readmore" href="/is-tennis-a-popular-sport/" aria-label="Is Tennis A Popular Sport?">Read More</a></p>
<p>The post <a href="/is-tennis-a-popular-sport/">Is Tennis A Popular Sport?</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In the U.S., while basketball, football, and baseball take center stage, tennis is also <strong>huge</strong> with a reported <strong>17.9 million players.</strong> Even more people than this are tennis fans and watch tennis matches regularly.</p>
<p>Additionally, over 14 million Americans report they have an interest in playing tennis but are not playing yet. As the population of the U.S. steadily increases, so should the number of tennis players and fans.</p>
<p><strong>Many people are unaware that tennis is one of the most popular sports in the world. According to worldatlas.com, tennis currently sits at number 4 in popularity with one billion worldwide fans.</strong></p>
<p>The only three sports more popular than tennis are soccer (4 billion fans), cricket (2.5 billion fans), and field hockey (2 billion fans). For those in the United States, we know that cricket and field hockey are rarely played.</p>
<p>In the U.S., soccer falls behind the major four sports in popularity. But due to its popularity on a global scale, it has a large fan base in the U.S. as well.</p>
<p>With tennis having its own channel since 2003 (The Tennis Channel) and tournaments being featured almost every week on TV, the sport is growing. Currently, the Australian Open is coming up, which is one of the biggest tournaments of the year.</p>
<p>The total prize money for the tournament is $62.5 million, with an unprecedented $4.1 million going to the winner. In the last 18 years, the total prize money has increased a whopping 351%.</p>
<p>This goes to show that tennis is right on track to keep climbing in popularity, not just in the U.S. and Australia, but throughout the world. With megastars such as Roger Federer and Rafael Nadal owning the sport for the last two decades, tennis has enjoyed continued growth over that time.</p>
<p>The beauty of tennis is that new stars are always ready to emerge. A recent example is when 20-year-old Naomi Osaka shocked the world by easily beating Serena Williams in the 2018 U.S. Open.</p>
<p>There’s no shortage of amazing talent on the horizon. I watch the Tennis Channel often on my 75-inch big screen. Seems like every time I turn on the TV, there’s some new male or female player that “wows” me.</p>
<p>I’m sure tennis will be in good hands when Roger, Rafa, and the Williams sisters retire in a few years. Though with Roger, he looks so good now, he might stick around 10 more years just because he can.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Where Is Tennis Most Popular?</h2>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-1917 alignright" src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/worldBall.jpg" alt="" width="400" height="400" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/worldBall.jpg 400w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/01/worldBall-150x150.jpg 150w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/01/worldBall-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>While tennis is a popular worldwide sport, it’s played and watched in some nations more than others. One nation that comes up high on the list is Australia. It makes sense, with one of the four grand slam tournaments (Australian Open) being held there.</p>
<p>Participation in Australia for tennis is high, but cricket and football (or rugby) are ahead of tennis there. The same can be said for New Zealand, which is close to Australia.</p>
<p>The other countries that host the grand slams (the U.S., France, and England) are all high on the tennis popularity list. While we can never know for sure which country has the most fans and players, we can see its quite evenly spread out in the more developed nations.</p>
<p>Spain has had remarkable success in tennis over the last generation. Likewise, Switzerland has enjoyed great success as well. France has produced a ton of very good talent over the last 50 years.</p>
<p>Statistics on the Internet are often misleading. This makes it difficult to give a definitive answer to this question.</p>
<p>If you look at the top 100 men and women in the world, notice which countries the players represent. The countries most often represented probably have the largest popularity.</p>
<p>I’ve also read that China is a growing force in tennis, with many young men and women now being taught the game. Tennis courts are being built there as fast as they can make them.</p>
<p>It wouldn’t surprise me to see a bunch of new Chinese faces in both the men’s and women’s game in the top 100 a generation from now.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Who Made Tennis Popular?</h2>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1921" src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/1024px-Tennis_in_France_16th_century.jpg" alt="Tennis in France in the 16th century." width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/1024px-Tennis_in_France_16th_century.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/01/1024px-Tennis_in_France_16th_century-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/01/1024px-Tennis_in_France_16th_century-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Tennis was invented in the 1500s in France. While the game really didn’t resemble the beautiful game we see today, the rudiments were in place.</p>
<p>The game took a major leap forward in 1850 when vulcanized rubber was created. This type of ball, made of rubber, made it possible to play on grass lawns in the outdoors.</p>
<p>History has it that Major Walter Wingfield, a Londoner, thought up a game called “Playing Ball”. This game was developed in 1873 and it’s said that modern tennis evolved from Wingfield’s creation.</p>
<p>While it was originally played on an hourglass shape, it quickly changed to the rectangular court we know today.</p>
<p>In a few short years, croquet clubs in England began adopting the game. The first real tennis tournament on record was held in 1877 by the All England Croquet Club in Wimbledon.</p>
<p>The rules of this tournament were different from what we know today. First, women were not allowed to play. This changed in 1884 though, as a women’s championship for singles was created. Second, all serving was done underhand.</p>
<p>While a form of tennis was played in Europe and gaining popularity, it really wasn’t played in the U.S. That changed when an American lady named Mary Ewing Outerbridge took a vacation to Bermuda.</p>
<p>There she discovered the game of lawn tennis. It may seem odd that tennis was being played on the small island of Bermuda.</p>
<p>But British officials and their wives had brought the game to Bermuda and the colonies. It was primarily played by the wealthy.</p>
<p>Outerbridge loved the game and purchased tennis gear while in Bermuda. Upon her return home to Staten Island, New York, she introduced tennis to her family and friends.</p>
<p>Coincidentally, Outerbridge’s brother was the director of the Staten Island Cricket and Baseball Club. He took a liking to tennis and realized its potential as a popular sport. Without wasting any time, he added a lawn tennis court to the club.</p>
<p>It wasn’t long before the United States National Lawn Tennis Association formed (1884) and national singles and doubles championships were held. Of course, women were excluded at first. But a few years later, women were allowed to play both singles and doubles too.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1922" src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/Tennis-match-for-Davis-Cup-Rice-and-McLoughlin.jpg" alt="Davis Cup, 1913" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/Tennis-match-for-Davis-Cup-Rice-and-McLoughlin.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/01/Tennis-match-for-Davis-Cup-Rice-and-McLoughlin-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/01/Tennis-match-for-Davis-Cup-Rice-and-McLoughlin-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Unlike many other sports, men and women enjoyed fairly equal parity in tennis, which is why I believe it gained so much popularity so quickly. With women being allowed to play, earn prize money, and become stars, it attracted ever more women to the game.</p>
<p>As the game evolved, so did the equipment and skill level of the players. In the 1920s, the American Helen Wills burst onto the tennis scene and dominated the sport for a generation.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>In fact, she won a record 180 matches in a row – and all without dropping even a single set. Talk about domination.</p>
<p>Throughout the 1920s and 30s, Wills was the face of tennis. Crowds loved to see her play and she racked up 17 grand slams and two Olympic gold medals in that time. She retired in 1938 and was largely responsible for making tennis popular in America and Europe.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>What Countries Is Tennis Played In?</h2>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1923" src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/flags.jpg" alt="tennis flags" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/flags.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/01/flags-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/01/flags-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Tennis is played in most countries throughout the world. It’s difficult to even think of a single country that doesn’t have a tennis court or tennis players. Even the poorest countries in the world have them.</p>
<p>While nations like France, Germany, Croatia, Spain, the U.S., England, and Australia are firmly entrenched in the game, others like China and Korea are growing their tennis base.</p>
<p>Currently, professional tennis tournaments are played in every continent of the world with the exception of Antarctica. The most popular tennis countries are in Europe, North America, and Australia.</p>
<p>But tennis is gaining in popularity in Central and South America, as well as Asia, New Zealand, and Africa. You can now find tennis players ranked in the top 100 from all these places – and the list is growing.</p>
<p>Africa is the only continent still lagging behind. Currently, the only ATP and WTA tournaments in Africa are held in Morocco. But I expect that number will increase to two or more events in the coming decade, perhaps with South Africa hosting a tournament soon.</p>
<p>What may surprise some non-tennis fans, is that tennis is quite popular in the Middle East. Countries like Qatar (250 level) and the United Arab Emirates (500 level) host tournaments for both the ATP and WTA. No doubt the wealthy elite in those countries are big-time tennis fans and fund the tournaments.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Will Tennis Increase In Popularity?</h2>
<p>I believe the answer is yes, tennis will become more popular. As developing nations build tennis courts and have access to tennis coverage, tennis will see a surge in those nations.</p>
<p>The perfect example is China.</p>
<p>Tennis wasn’t a big sport there even as little as 20 years ago. But with the addition of thousands of new courts, better coaching, and millions of new potential players, tennis will be well-represented in the Asian countries.</p>
<p>Already a global sport, the chances of tennis remaining stagnant or waning in popularity are very slim. I believe tennis will continue to grow and could one day out-pace field hockey in popularity.</p>
<p>With new talent emerging from all over the globe, prize money at record levels, and tennis coverage greater than ever, tennis is poised to continue its upward growth. All signs point to a trend up.</p>
<p>When Roger and Rafa retire, it’ll be up to the new generation to find the next big superstars. Truly, in any sport, the superstars are why a lot of people tune in. It’s box office when LeBron James, Tom Brady, or Connor McGregor take to the stage.</p>
<p>It’s often the same in tennis. Yes, there will always be hardcore fans who tune in no matter what. I happen to be one. But there are certain players that come along once or twice in a generation that transcend the sport.</p>
<p>These larger-than-life personalities bring in new fans and make people interested in the sport. Examples are Muhammad Ali, Mike Tyson, Babe Ruth, Wayne Gretzky, Michael Jordan, Tiger Woods, Serena Williams, etc.</p>
<p>These people turned casual observers or people not even interested in the sport into raving fans. They even became icons for a whole new generation of young people.</p>
<p>But not all athletes need be icons to be entertaining. Even players not as successful can make us want to watch a sport. Look at John McEnroe.</p>
<p>No tennis expert recognizes John as the greatest of all time (though he was a top player of his generation) but he put fans in seats because of his over-the-top personality.</p>
<p>The same could be said for the former NBA player Dennis Rodman. With Dennis, a basketball game wasn’t just a sporting contest, it was a show. Which hair color would he have that night and which antics would he pull off next?</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>The closest we’ve had to Dennis in our sport is Ilie Nastase, who was a top player in the 1970s. His antics at matches, even during crucial points, always thrilled crowds. In the 90s and 2000s, Andre Agassi was by far the most colorful player and attracted tens of thousands of new fans to tennis.</p>
<p>I believe tennis needs a colorful personality like that to take a big jump up in popularity. Currently I don’t see any men or women like that in tennis.</p>
<p>But perhaps that’s because it’s a gentleman’s sport and that type of behavior goes against tennis protocol. With social media tracking everyone’s actions, players need to be more careful than ever with their words and antics.</p>
<p>Still, time will tell who emerges as the next tennis superstar. Even if they are not as flamboyant as John McEnroe – and chances are they won’t – tennis is in good hands. I believe it will certainly remain one of the most popular sports in the world for decades to come.</p>
<p>The post <a href="/is-tennis-a-popular-sport/">Is Tennis A Popular Sport?</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/is-tennis-a-popular-sport/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Why Is Tennis A Good Sport? 8 Questions Answered</title>
		<link>/why-is-tennis-a-good-sport-8-questions-answered/</link>
					<comments>/why-is-tennis-a-good-sport-8-questions-answered/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chad Walner]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 07 Jan 2019 07:08:43 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Theory]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1886</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>After years of playing all types of sports, I can genuinely tell you tennis is one of the greatest sports ever invented. I think that’s evident by its worldwide success. If you’re not a tennis fan, you may not realize &#8230; <a class="kt-excerpt-readmore" href="/why-is-tennis-a-good-sport-8-questions-answered/" aria-label="Why Is Tennis A Good Sport? 8 Questions Answered">Read More</a></p>
<p>The post <a href="/why-is-tennis-a-good-sport-8-questions-answered/">Why Is Tennis A Good Sport? 8 Questions Answered</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>After years of playing all types of sports, I can genuinely tell you tennis is one of the greatest sports ever invented. I think that’s evident by its worldwide success.</p>
<p>If you’re not a tennis fan, you may not realize how many people play the game. Almost every country in the world has tennis courts and players.</p>
<p>Looking at the players ranked in the top 100 for the ATP (men) and WTA (women) professional tour, you can see a tremendous number of countries represented.</p>
<p>Tennis is also played at the Olympics. There is a huge global interest in the game and the professionals play matches in filled stadiums around the world, including North America, South America, Europe, Asia, and Australia.</p>
<p>But there are other reasons why tennis is a great sport. After being involved in tennis for 25 years, I can list out many of the reasons quite easily.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="#seniors">Is Tennis A Good Sport For Seniors</a>?</li>
<li><a href="#kids">Is Tennis A Good Sport For Kids?</a></li>
<li><a href="#team">Is Tennis A Team Sport?</a></li>
<li><a href="#social">Is Tennis A Social Sport?</a></li>
<li><a href="#workout">Is Tennis A Good Workout?</a></li>
<li><a href="#challenging">Is Tennis A Challenging Sport?</a></li>
<li><a href="#fun">Is Tennis A Fun Sport?</a></li>
<li><a href="#competitive">Is Tennis A Competitive Sport?</a></li>
</ul>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>As you can see, there are many reasons to answer the question: Why is tennis a great sport? For me, I wouldn’t want to play any other sport.</p>
<p>I was an avid baseball and basketball player growing up. I dabbled in football and tried my hand at combat sports too. But the one sport I always looked forward to playing the most is tennis.</p>
<p>When I was younger, basketball was the only sport that came close to tennis for me. Unfortunately, father time forced me to step away from the game around age 40.</p>
<p>My knees couldn’t take the stress that constant jumping puts on them. Interestingly, no matter how much I play tennis on hard courts, my knees always feel fine.</p>
<p>Since its inception 400 years ago, tennis has been a popular game – no doubt because of how much fun it is to play. Most tennis participants find the game absolutely addictive, which non-tennis players will never understand.</p>
<p>If you play tennis, you know what I’m talking about. If you don’t play tennis, I urge to begin playing.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<h2>Is Tennis A Good Sport For Seniors?</h2>
</div>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-1899 size-full" src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/forseniors.jpg" alt="Tennis is a good sport for seniors." width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/forseniors.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/01/forseniors-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/01/forseniors-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Many of the most popular sports, like football, basketball, and soccer, are a young persons game. I don’t know anybody who plays tackle football at age 50. In these types of contact sports, participants can easily be hurt.</p>
<p>Tennis, on the other hand, is a non-contact sport and so the chances of injury are much less. Sure, tennis can be hard on the body, but it depends on your level.</p>
<p>In my experience, competitive tennis players can play well into their 60s and even 70s. At my local tennis club, we have a regular player named “Wolf” who is 71. The guy plays three hours a day and is as sharp as a tack.</p>
<p>Wolf is definitely an inspiration to me. At 71, he tracks down balls that you would expect from someone 30 years younger. Wolf doesn’t do other exercises except for play tennis, and his diet is not the best, but playing tennis every day has kept his body in good form and his mind clear.</p>
<p>In my opinion, as long as you don’t wreck your knees or shoulders at any point in life, you can probably play tennis life-long. Now, you may not be able to compete at the same level when you get to be 50 and beyond, but the drop-off is much less steep than other sports.</p>
<p>For example, John McEnroe is almost 60 and he can compete with pros who are 40-years-old and off the tour just a few years. The same just can’t be said for a sport like football or basketball.</p>
<p>I recognize Michael Jordan (now aged 55) as the greatest basketball player of all time. If you put him in a one-on-one game versus a player currently in the NBA who is 20 years younger, that NBA player would torch him.</p>
<p>It wouldn’t even be a contest, despite Jordan’s immense skill level. That’s because the physical drop-off makes a huge difference in other sports.</p>
<p>But in tennis, the drop-off is much less noticeable. Additionally, physical shortcomings can be made up with skill and smarts in tennis.</p>
<p>I play in singles and doubles leagues with guys in their 50s and 60s. I can tell you for certain, that these guys still have it.</p>
<p>They may not be able to run with me in singles (few can), but their hitting skills and volley touch are still there. I believe power and hand-eye coordination remain with you life-long, as long as you play consistently.</p>
<p>Watching the older guys play, it gives me hope I can still be a competitive player 30 years from now.</p>
<p>In a weird way, I kind of look forward to seeing what it will be like to play tennis in my 70s. Now, my 80s might be a different story. But you know what, I’ll still get out there and at least hit the ball!</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<h2>Is Tennis A Good Sport For Kids?</h2>
</div>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1900" src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/forkids.jpg" alt="Tennis is a good sport for kids." width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/forkids.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/01/forkids-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/01/forkids-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Tennis is one of the most awesome sports because anyone can play. You don’t have to be a super athlete, 7 feet tall, or be extremely gifted to hit a tennis ball.</p>
<p>You can be a boy, a girl, 5 years old or 70 years old, and still play and enjoy the game all the same. Tennis is also one of the few sports where skill and technique can really make up for physical differences.</p>
<p>Being this is the case, trained female players can easily beat male players with little or no training. I like the parity there.</p>
<p>In sports like football, basketball, fighting, and hockey, men can use their strength and size advantages to excel over women. No such luck in tennis.</p>
<p>While kids can compete in contact sports at a young age, it’s not always advisable, such as in football and combat fighting. Head trauma is a real thing. But tennis involves none of that. It’s completely safe for children.</p>
<p>Nowadays, we have balls, rackets, and courts specially created for kids. The younger ones really love the game and take to tennis very quickly. I don’t see the same love in other sports from kids, though that’s my subjective opinion.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<h2>Is Tennis A Team Sport?</h2>
</div>
<div id="attachment_1901" style="width: 810px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1901" class="size-full wp-image-1901" src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/teamsport2.jpg" alt="Tennis is a team sport." width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/teamsport2.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/01/teamsport2-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/01/teamsport2-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /><p id="caption-attachment-1901" class="wp-caption-text"><a title="High five" href="https://flickr.com/photos/93558439@N05/13917120702">&#8220;High five&#8221;</a> by <a href="https://flickr.com/people/93558439@N05">Thomson20192</a> is licensed under <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/">CC BY</a></p></div>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Tennis can be played as an individual sport or as a team (doubles).</p>
<p>When playing singles, it’s all you out there. You take all the reward for your victories and all the responsibility for your losses. There is no partner to blame and nobody to rely on to carry you.</p>
<p>Doubles, on the other hand, brings in the team aspect of the sport. I love the comradery of playing with a partner. It’s us against them. Not only that, but there are so many possible combinations to form teams and matchups.</p>
<p>For example, if you have 8 guys playing in a group, you can mix up the teams in many ways. This creates intriguing style matchups.</p>
<p>Most other sports aren’t versatile like tennis in this way. Nobody can play baseball or football alone. Basketball and soccer can be played one-on-one, but it’s not nearly as fun and interesting as playing team-vs-team.</p>
<p>Most players in tennis prefer one or the other – singles or doubles. Doubles is usually the preferred choice for older players who don’t want to cover the whole court.</p>
<p>In this sense, tennis offers a nice variety. Players who like to run favor singles. Those who don’t &#8211; usually older or out-of-shape people &#8211; usually opt for doubles. Many of the guys I play with enjoy singles and doubles equally – same as me.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<h2>Is Tennis Social?</h2>
</div>
<div id="attachment_1902" style="width: 810px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1902" class="size-full wp-image-1902" src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/tennissocial.jpg" alt="Tennis is a social sport." width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/tennissocial.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/01/tennissocial-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/01/tennissocial-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /><p id="caption-attachment-1902" class="wp-caption-text"><a title="Cathri @ Bowen Road Tennis Courts" href="https://flickr.com/photos/spirosk/5902667862">&#8220;Cathri @ Bowen Road Tennis Courts&#8221;</a> by <a href="https://flickr.com/people/spirosk">SpirosK photography</a> is licensed under <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/2.0/">CC BY-NC-ND</a></p></div>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>In terms of being a great social sport, perhaps no other sport compares to tennis – except maybe golf. Every sport has its own type of participants.</p>
<p>Most of the people that play tennis are educated, successful, and respectful people. That’s one of the reasons I really love playing tennis: the people.</p>
<p>You get to meet tons of new people and make awesome new friends. I met all my best friends in life through tennis.</p>
<p>It’s also a great way to network. If you are looking to branch out and find new people to make friends with, or even for business reasons, tennis is a great way to do that and have fun at the same time.</p>
<p>Simply through playing tennis, I’ve gained some great business opportunities. What’s also great is being able to have a network of people you can call on for help.</p>
<p>Most tennis players I find are very helpful and good people. When you get to know them, you can hire them (if need be) and trust they’ll do a good job and give you a fair price.</p>
<p>For example, one of the guys I play tennis with own an air conditioner repair company. When my air conditioner is not working, who do you think I call? It’s the guy I play tennis with every Monday.</p>
<p>Some people even find the love of their life through tennis. I never met a romantic partner through tennis, but I still have hope. How cool would it be to hit and play matches with your boyfriend or girlfriend?</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<h2>Is Tennis A Good Workout?</h2>
</div>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1908" src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/workout.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/workout.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/01/workout-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/01/workout-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>When it comes to cardio, most people dread being on a Stairmaster or treadmill. Even 20 minutes can feel like an eternity. However, with tennis you get your cardio in without even thinking about it.</p>
<p>Hitting a tennis ball is extremely pleasurable, even if you need to move to hit it. Without realizing it, you’re burning calories and improving your conditioning, all while having fun on the tennis court.</p>
<p>I researched google and see that a 150 lb. person can reasonably expect to burn 300 calories from doubles and 400 calories from singles in a one-hour period. The number of calories increase the more someone weighs.</p>
<p>If you’re looking to lose weight and stay in shape, there are few better ways than playing tennis 3-4 times a week. Tennis requires you to use every muscle in your body and if you don’t take many breaks, you’ll really work up a good sweat.</p>
<p>One of my tennis clients pays me only to hit with him and play sets. He’s about 50 lbs. overweight and loves tennis. He lives out of town and doesn’t play much when at home.</p>
<p>However, when he comes into town, we play almost every morning for an hour. Typically, he’ll lose 5 lbs. in the first week, even without changing his diet.</p>
<p>Three months ago, I met a new player to our group named Ignacio. He’s 34, around a 5.0 level player, and was out of the game a while.</p>
<p>Ignacio is also around 50 lbs. overweight. Within three months of playing 4-5 times per week, he dropped an incredible 33 lbs. (he just text me yesterday to tell me). I’m proud of him.</p>
<p>If you’re looking to lose weight or stay in shape, don’t overlook tennis. Most people much prefer tennis over the gym. As someone who plays tennis nearly every day, I never worry about cardio.</p>
<p>As a matter of fact, my heart and breathing rate is so low from playing all the time, that I was accused of trying to fake a polygraph (lie detector) test a few years ago. No, I wasn’t in trouble. I was applying for a job and they required me to do a polygraph test.</p>
<p>The giver of the test actually accused me of holding my breath to try to beat the test. I was then made aware of my breathing and could see that I was only inhaling and exhaling once every 12-15 seconds.</p>
<p>I explained I was an endurance athlete and just breathing normally. He told me I better breathe faster if I want to pass the test – so I did. In case you were wondering, I passed.</p>
<p>When you play tennis consistently – especially singles – you’ll be one of the fittest people you know. Just from playing tennis and going to the gym twice a week, I’ve been able to drop my body fat levels under 10%, despite eating a diet where around 40% of my calories come from fat.</p>
<p>Check out these photos I just took. (Ted, I’ll send you photos). You can see how lean I am. Now, I’m not saying everyone will experience these results, but I’ve known a lot of people to drop weight playing tennis.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<h2>Is Tennis a Challenge?</h2>
</div>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1909" src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/challenge.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/challenge.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/01/challenge-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/01/challenge-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>One aspect of tennis I really love is being able to improve despite your age. I’m 45 and I am still a work in progress. Just recently I improved my volley technique, kick serve, and two-handed backhand.</p>
<p>Tennis can be a mysterious game. Just when you think you know it all, you realize you don’t. Not even close!</p>
<p>Even an avid tennis player and long-time coach like myself is always learning new things about the game. And there’s no shortage of new techniques, drills, and ways of teaching I find.</p>
<p>Being in one location for a while, I’ve played with the same group of players for the last dozen years. Some have really improved their game, despite being in their 40s and 50s.</p>
<p>That can’t be easily said for other physical sports. Sure, anyone can improve their golf swing or bowling average, even after middle age, but they’re not physically demanding sports.</p>
<p>I ask you this. In what other physical sport can a 60-year-old man or woman dramatically improve?</p>
<p>Of the four major sports (basketball, football, baseball, and hockey – I’ll throw track and field and combat sports in there too), you never see a single athlete play better at 60 than they did at 20, 30 or even 40.</p>
<p>There’s a reason why most athletes retire in their 30s. Unfortunately, with age, our bodies decline in physical abilities every year. Over the long run (30-40 years), it really adds up.<br />
While the same rule set holds true in tennis, I believe recreational players can improve their technique and footwork any time in life (though after 80 it gets to be very difficult).</p>
<p>Sure, it’s hard to teach an old dog new tricks, but it can be done.</p>
<p>If you picked up tennis later in life, don’t fret. You can certainly improve if you have good coaching, practice diligently, and play often. But you have to really want it.</p>
<p>Remember, no matter what your age, improvement can be made. It’s all up to you. As Ray Lewis (the famous football player) likes to say, “Effort is between you and you.”</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="fun"></a></p>
<h2>Is Tennis Fun?</h2>
</div>
<p>Once you know the basics of tennis and can rally, it’s incredibly pleasurable to hit the ball. It’s even more fun to play matches. And it’s even more fun to win!</p>
<p>I play tennis with a group of guys around my level. While I don’t play tournaments anymore due to time restrictions, I play in a singles and doubles league every week. It’s a blast.</p>
<p>I can honestly tell you, there isn’t anything I want to do more than play tennis these days. After a long day of work, I can’t wait to hit the tennis court and hit some balls. If you play too, you know the feeling.</p>
<p>The fresh air, the feel of the clay under my feet, and the smell of new tennis balls are all sensations I love. Tennis is one of the only things I do that gives me the chance to fully express myself. And all while enjoying the outdoors, great exercise, and awesome people.</p>
<p>As I stated earlier, tennis is quite an addictive sport. There’s just something that happens chemically in the brain when you hit a tennis ball. You almost never get tired of hitting it.</p>
<p>I used to hit with a bunch of guys in Eisenhower Park, located in Long Island, New York. Without making any plans, about two dozen guys would meet at the park every weekend morning in the warm months. We’d just pick a partner and hit.</p>
<p>I vividly remember hitting on those crisp summer mornings with the guys. It was so much fun. I loved the feeling of hitting a hard, accurate shot. Even to this day, I love hitting every chance I get.</p>
<p>While hitting is great for perfecting technique, these days I prefer playing matches, and mostly doubles at that. There’s just something about playing with a partner I love. Don’t get me wrong, singles is great too.</p>
<p>One of the coolest things about tennis is that every player has their own unique style. No two players are identical. Each one offer a different perspective.</p>
<p>Simply by changing the partners you play against, the whole complexion of the match changes. There are power hitters, retrievers, net players, all-court players, etc.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>Each player poses different challenges. It’s always fun figuring out how to beat a player and then executing on that strategy. And if I lose (which is rare), I really look forward to a rematch.</p>
<p>For those not as competitive, it’s just fun to get together with the guys or girls and play. A lot of people who play doubles like to sit around and talk and enjoy a drink afterwards. It’s often a very relaxing atmosphere – especially at the nicer clubs.</p>
<p>I don’t care where I play. For me, the important thing is to play intensely. One of the best parts of tennis is going home and knowing I got in my exercise for the day.<br />
Most of the time, I go home drenched in sweat. I’m physically beat.</p>
<p>I enjoy returning home, taking off my wet clothes, and entering a warm shower. After I get clean, I not only sleep better, but I feel like I had a productive day and a lot of fun too. You should try it.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="competitive"></a></p>
<h2>Is Tennis Competitive?</h2>
</div>
<p>Tennis is one of the few sports you can compete in effectively from early childhood to your senior years. I teach 10-year-old who compete in tournament play.</p>
<p>They can serve, rally, and play out points. I can really see the enjoyment they have, even though they look serious when playing.</p>
<p>Likewise, players 70-years-old can play tournaments too, just like kids. In what other sport can you compete at 10 all the way to 70? You can’t do that in any of the four major sports.</p>
<p>If you’re competitive like me, tennis is one of the best sports to compete in. First, there’s an endless number of players to challenge.</p>
<p>If you live in any populated town or city, you’ll probably never scratch the surface of meeting all the players in your area. On a state and national level, you’ll have enough competition for a lifetime.</p>
<p>Second, the levels in tennis are wide and many. Unlike other sports, where it’s difficult to classify the skill level of recreational players, tennis has a ranking system.</p>
<p>This makes it easy to find players around your level. But even players ranked around your level can vary by wide margins. This is due to physical ability, age, mental toughness, etc., which always makes matches interesting.</p>
<p>Third, tennis is a great sport to let out your frustrations and calm your stress. You can step onto the court and whack the ball as hard as you want. At the end of the match, all your frustrations and stress are typically gone.</p>
<p>Lastly, for those looking to be the very best, tennis offers an unlimited opportunity to play tournaments and move higher up in the rankings. And it’s all based on the merit system.</p>
<p>The more you win in tennis, the higher up go. For those with a very competitive drive, there are USTA open tournaments, challenger level tournaments, and satellites.</p>
<p>There’s just no end to the number of competitive matches you can play all year round in tennis. At these higher levels, which is really professional tennis, you get to travel the</p>
<p>world, play against all different style players, and have great experiences.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>The Bottom Line</h2>
<p>As you may be able to deduce from this post, tennis is the greatest sport. Yes, I’m going to proclaim it now for all of time. Even the legendary Mike Tyson said that tennis is the ultimate sport.</p>
<p>If you play tennis, you now have a few more reasons to boost your game and ramp up the play. If you don’t play tennis, well what are you waiting for? Get out there and start learning.</p>
<p>Tennis has something for everyone. If you want exercise &#8211; tennis provides it. If you want to have a barrel of fun, tennis has it. If you love to compete, you guessed it – tennis is the sport for you.</p>
<p>I hope you enjoyed this post and found it entertaining. Thanks for reading. Check out my other blog posts for awesome tips to improve your game.</p>
<p>The post <a href="/why-is-tennis-a-good-sport-8-questions-answered/">Why Is Tennis A Good Sport? 8 Questions Answered</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/why-is-tennis-a-good-sport-8-questions-answered/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
