<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>forehand Archives - Serve and Volley Tennis</title>
	<atom:link href="/tag/forehand/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/tag/forehand/</link>
	<description>Your secret weapon on the court.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 15 Aug 2019 09:53:15 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	

<image>
	<url>/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/cropped-ted_svt_favicon-32x32.png</url>
	<title>forehand Archives - Serve and Volley Tennis</title>
	<link>/tag/forehand/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>What Are The 8 Basic Tennis Shots?</title>
		<link>/what-are-the-8-basic-tennis-shots/</link>
					<comments>/what-are-the-8-basic-tennis-shots/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chad Walner]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 04 Jan 2019 19:56:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Theory]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[backhand]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[dropshot]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[forehand]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[lob]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[overhead]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[serve]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[slice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[volley]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1862</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The game of tennis might seem complicated for those new to it, but it can essentially be broken down into 8 basic shots. All 8 shots need to be mastered to excel and proceed to the higher levels of tennis. &#8230; <a class="kt-excerpt-readmore" href="/what-are-the-8-basic-tennis-shots/" aria-label="What Are The 8 Basic Tennis Shots?">Read More</a></p>
<p>The post <a href="/what-are-the-8-basic-tennis-shots/">What Are The 8 Basic Tennis Shots?</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The game of tennis might seem complicated for those new to it, but it can essentially be broken down into 8 basic shots. All 8 shots need to be mastered to excel and proceed to the higher levels of tennis.</p>
<p>In this blog post, I discuss all 8 basic shots in the game of tennis. By the time you finish this article, you’ll know all of them inside and out. You’ll also have a much better understanding of the game of tennis.</p>
<p>Here are the 8 basic shots in the game of tennis:</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<ol>
<li><a href="#forehand">Forehand</a></li>
<li><a href="#backhand">Backhand</a></li>
<li><a href="#serve">Serve</a></li>
<li><a href="#volley">Volley</a></li>
<li><a href="#slice">Slice</a></li>
<li><a href="#overhead">Overhead</a></li>
<li><a href="#dropshot">Drop shot</a></li>
<li><a href="#lob">Lob</a></li>
</ol>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Most tennis newbies wonder, “What are the basic strokes in tennis?” Well now you know. And by knowing all the basic strokes, you can learn them and use them in your own game.</p>
<p>This will make you a more versatile and dangerous player to face. It’s ironic, but I see club players with decades of experience who never utilize all 8 shots in their game.</p>
<p>I believe there are a lot of players out there who never quite learned some of them, so they just don’t use them. If you’re new to tennis, I implore you to learn all 8 basic shots.</p>
<p>Certainly, the forehand, backhand, and serve are essential to playing tennis.</p>
<p>Other shots, like the slice and dropshot, are not part of the arsenal of some club players. I honestly don’t know how they cope in tennis without a slice. To me, the slice on both the forehand and backhand wings are a must-know stroke.</p>
<p>Without more talk, let’s get into the details of each stroke, so you know what each one entails.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="forehand"></a></p>
<h2>The Basic Forehand Shot</h2>
</div>
<p><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-1867 size-full" src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/forehand.jpg" alt="Pat Cash forehand" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/forehand.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/01/forehand-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/01/forehand-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>The forehand is the most basic and often-used shot in tennis. It’s also the easiest to learn and the shot beginners pick up the quickest.</p>
<p>Think of the forehand as akin to the queen in the game of chess. The forehand is your most versatile shot. Good players can hit with power, spin, and place the ball where they want.</p>
<p>Being the most basic stroke in tennis, it’s often the one everyone learns first. Professional players can dominate matches primarily with their forehand (a la Roger Federer).</p>
<p>The strength and placement of the forehand is often what separates great players at the highest levels. In my experience, the forehand is the most comfortable shot to hit and the most enjoyable too.</p>
<p>The forehand is hit on the dominant side of your body and is typically struck with one arm (your dominant arm). It’s possible to hit a two-handed forehand as well, but I would estimate less than 2% of recreational and professional players use it.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>On the men’s pro tour, there have only ever been two players to use the two-handed forehand. And this is out of thousands of players since 1940.</p>
<p>Those two players are the legendary Pancho Segura, and more lately, Fabrice Santoro. Segura was a lot more successful than Santora but played in the 40s and 50s when the game and racket technology was a lot different.</p>
<p>Santoro played in the 90s and 2000s. He reached a career high of 17 and his best result at a major was the quarterfinals of the 2006 Australian Open.</p>
<p>On the women’s side, the two-handed forehand had much more success, with players such as Monica Seles (10 career grand slam titles) and Marion Bartoli. Bartoli won Wimbledon in 2013 and then promptly and unexpectedly retired. She was my favorite woman to watch.</p>
<p>If you’re just starting out in tennis, hire a qualified pro to teach you the basics of the forehand. With just a couple of lessons, you’ll at least know the correct technique.</p>
<p>If you can’t afford lessons or don’t have a qualified pro near you, you can <a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCHaY0w7QtG205o4ByUHXkEg/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">check out my youtube channel</a> for free forehand lessons.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="backhand"></a></p>
<h2>The Basic Backhand Shot</h2>
</div>
<div id="attachment_1869" style="width: 810px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img decoding="async" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1869" class="size-full wp-image-1869" src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/backhand.jpg" alt="Pablo Cuevas" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/backhand.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/01/backhand-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/01/backhand-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /><p id="caption-attachment-1869" class="wp-caption-text">Carine06 from UK [<a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.0">CC BY-SA 2.0</a>], <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Pablo_Cuevas_backhand_(14536242152).jpg">via Wikimedia Commons</a></p></div>
<p>The backhand is hit on the non-dominant side of your body. For example, if you’re a righty and strike the ball on the left side of your body, it’s considered a backhand.</p>
<p>Most player’s backhands are not as strong as their forehand. This is because it’s more difficult to achieve the same level of racket speed on the backhand wing as the forehand side.</p>
<p>However, some players do have better backhands than forehands. If you’re one of those players, then you’re fortunate. Most club players dread hitting their backhands.</p>
<p>I find that most women have better two-handed backhands than forehands. This is likely due to them using more of their core and legs on the backhand. For men, I find most have much better forehands.</p>
<p>The backhand can either be hit with one hand or two. Examples of players with one-handed backhands are Roger Federer, Stan Wawrinka, Carla Suarez Navarro, and Justine Henin (now retired). Some would argue Henin had the best one-handed backhand in the women’s game.</p>
<p>The one-handed backhand offers some pros an advantage over the two-handed backhand. The pros using the one-handed backhand would have greater range of motion, slightly more drive and power, and more versatility with spin.</p>
<p>The cons of the one-handed backhand (compared to the two-) are less control, it’s more difficult to hit high shots, and there’s less ability to hit the ball late. Additionally, it’s more difficult to return serve with a one-hander.</p>
<p>These cons are enough to have persuaded most players and coaches to only teach and hit the two-handed backhand. For this reason, most of the players on the pro level (for both men and women) use a two-handed backhand.</p>
<p>If you wish to reach the upper levels of tennis, it’s essential you develop your backhand into a reliable shot. You’ll need to be able to hit it with depth, spin, placement, and a decent amount of pace.</p>
<p>While it’s not essential you smash winners from the baseline with your backhand, it is essential that it keeps you in the rally. Most professional players use their backhand to stay in a rally long enough to set up their forehand.</p>
<p>If you wish to learn the backhand, I suggest the two-hander. Get a qualified coach to teach you the basics of the shot and then just keep practicing it. I have videos on my youtube channel showing how to hit both the two-hander and the one-hander.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="serve"></a></p>
<h2>The Basic Serve</h2>
</div>
<p>Along with the forehand and backhand, the serve is one of the three primary shots in tennis you must know to begin playing. If you can effectively execute all three shots, you can play tennis.</p>
<p>The next shot in tennis you should learn is the volley. If you know these four shots (forehand, backhand, serve, volley) you can play matches, even in tournaments.</p>
<p>It sounds amazing, but you can literally choose to avoid the other four basic shots (drop shot, overhead, slice and lob) and still play competitive tennis. I wouldn’t suggest it though.</p>
<div id="attachment_1871" style="width: 410px" class="wp-caption alignleft"><img decoding="async" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1871" class="size-full wp-image-1871" src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/serve1.jpg" alt="Andre Agassi serve" width="400" height="610" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/serve1.jpg 400w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/01/serve1-197x300.jpg 197w" sizes="(max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" /><p id="caption-attachment-1871" class="wp-caption-text">Srinayan Puppala [<a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.0">CC BY-SA 2.0</a>], <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Agassi_serve_US_open_05.jpg">via Wikimedia Commons</a></p></div>All tennis players (whether in singles or doubles) get two serves on each point. The first serve is usually hit flat and hard.</p>
<p>The second serve is often hit with topspin or kick. These types of serves have more margin of error and are about 15-20% slower in speed than first serves.</p>
<p>Of the 8 basic shots in tennis, the serve is by far the most difficult to learn and the most complicated. This is for a few reasons.</p>
<p>First, the serve is the only shot in tennis where you start and finish the stroke. All other strokes rely on the ball coming to you.</p>
<p>Second, the serve requires you to toss the ball high in the air (usually twice your height) and strike it on the way down. This requires split-second timing.</p>
<p>The toss can also be problematic. This is because it’s done with the non-dominant hand, which can be very difficult for uncoordinated people and beginners.</p>
<p>Third, the serve is a complicated series of movements that must be performed in about two seconds. It also requires knee-bend, flexibility, and high racket speed.</p>
<p>Due to these factors, many club players never develop anything beyond a mediocre serve. This means their serves typically don’t break the 100-mph barrier or possess enough spin to hurt opponents.</p>
<p>If you are just starting out in tennis, realize the serve is a shot that will take you months or years to master. Everyone is limited on the serve by their physical ability, so be aware of that too.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>If you have dreams of serving 120-mph, unless you’re young and very talented, it’s not likely to happen. Instead, your goal should be a very consistent serve with excellent placement.</p>
<p>The serve is one of those shots you’ll need to continually practice. It requires perfect timing and tremendous hand-eye coordination when hit well.</p>
<p>Some of you may just want to play tennis for the exercise, or for the fun. If that’s your goal, you can use a very simple beginner’s serve to get the ball in the box and start the point.</p>
<p>If that sounds like you, I would advise you to check out my youtube video on the abbreviated serve motion. It’s a beginner’s serve, but slightly more advanced, offering more power and spin.</p>
<p>For those who aspire to hit their serve like Roger Federer, check out my video on Roger Federer’s serve motion. In this video, I explain how to hit your serve like Roger. Just don’t blame me if you can’t.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="volley"></a></p>
<h2>The Basic Volley</h2>
</div>
<div id="attachment_1873" style="width: 810px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1873" class="size-full wp-image-1873" src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/volley.jpg" alt="Jo-Wilfried Tsonga" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/volley.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/01/volley-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/01/volley-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /><p id="caption-attachment-1873" class="wp-caption-text">Kate from UK [<a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.0">CC BY-SA 2.0</a>], <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Jo-Wilfried_Tsonga_Wimbledon_2011_jump_volley.jpg">via Wikimedia Commons</a></p></div>
<p>The volley is unique all to itself. At its most basic element, it doesn’t require any swing of the racket or much body movement at all. Yet, it can be one of the most difficult shots in tennis to master.</p>
<p>What is a volley? A volley is when a player hits the ball directly out of the air, instead of letting the ball bounce first. When the ball bounces first, it’s called a “rally”. When taken in the air, it’s called a volley.</p>
<p>The volley is a very short compact “block” of the ball, most often close to the net. The volley can be hit on either the forehand side or the backhand side.</p>
<p>One of the reasons so few players master the volley is the very short amount of time provided to hit the ball. When you’re up at net, the ball is coming to you much sooner than at the baseline.</p>
<p>This makes it largely a reflexive shot, while baseline groundstrokes are much more deliberate.</p>
<p>Even the best players in the world today prefer not to come to net. The pace of groundstrokes at the pro level is just too much to handle, even for the best volley players.</p>
<p>With groundstroke speeds coming in excess of 80-90 mph, it’s very difficult to hit effective volleys, much less get a racket on the ball. For this reason, we have seen a trend away from net play over the last generation.</p>
<p>If you want to read more about this, I wrote an article entitled <a href="/why-did-serve-and-volley-die-out/">Why Did The Serve And Volley Die Out</a>?  It’s an interesting look at why the volley declined in both the women’s and men’s game over the last 20 years.</p>
<p>Despite the volley dying out, all players must learn to volley. This is because if you’re forced into net, you’ll have no choice but to eventually volley. The volley is also an essential part of doubles, which many people play.</p>
<p>If you’ve been struggling with your volleys, have no fear. I wrote a great blog post about the <a href="/seven-volley-types-you-must-know-to-master-your-net-game/">7 types of volleys</a> to use in your game. By knowing all 7 types and how to hit them, you’ll instantly improve your net game.</p>
<p>I also have a bunch of volley videos on my youtube channel. I recommend starting off with the block volley and then working your way through the other 6 volley types.</p>
<p>On the volley, always remember less is more. Most people over-complicate the volley and do too much swinging. The volley is more about great footwork and less about what you do with your racket.</p>
<p>If you want to play good doubles, or be an offensive player in singles, it’s imperative you learn to hit volleys with pace, spin, touch, and placement. It all comes in time.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="slice"></a></p>
<h2>The Basic Slice</h2>
</div>
<p>Traditional forehand and backhand strokes are hit with topspin (forward rotation of the ball). However, the slice employs backspin, which is a backward rotation of the ball.</p>
<p>Interestingly, it can also involve side spin.</p>
<p>The slice can be hit on either wing: the forehand or backhand. It can also be hit with either two hands or one. However, most players (probably more than 95%) hit their slice with one hand.</p>
<p>The slice generally refers to the downward motion of the racket when contacting the ball. The downward motion is what causes the backspin on the ball.</p>
<p>This is in contrast to traditional groundstrokes, which use a low-to-high swing path. In my opinion, it’s more difficult to learn the slice though.</p>
<p>I can teach a child or adult to make solid contact on a traditional forehand or backhand, but the slice is a different animal. For this reason, it can take a long time to develop a penetrating, effective slice shot on both wings.</p>
<p>One of the reasons for the difficulty level is the downward motion of the swing. Most beginners aren’t used to contacting the ball like that. The continental grip used on the slice also throws people off.</p>
<div id="attachment_1875" style="width: 410px" class="wp-caption alignright"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1875" class="size-full wp-image-1875" src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/slice.jpg" alt="Federer hitting a slice." width="400" height="404" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/slice.jpg 400w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/01/slice-297x300.jpg 297w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" /><p id="caption-attachment-1875" class="wp-caption-text">Steve Collis from Melbourne, Australia [<a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0">CC BY 2.0</a>], <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Federer_2009_Australian_Open_crop.jpg">via Wikimedia Commons</a></p></div>Most players open the racket face too much, or too early, and float the ball on their slice. For this reason, I teach my students to hit the ball completely flat but with a high-to-low trajectory of the racket.</p>
<p>If the slice is hit well, it can be a very damaging shot to the opponent. A good slice will skid on the ground and stay low. It can also be difficult to volley a tightly rotating slice.</p>
<p>Most players use the slice as a defensive shot, but it can certainly be used offensively as well. One example of an offensive slice shot is the approach shot. This is a hard, low slice away from the opponent.</p>
<p>On an approach shot, a player will quickly come to net in hopes of putting away an easy volley. The former greats like Pete Sampras, Patrick Rafter, and Stefan Edberg all used this tactic.</p>
<p>Many players also use the slice on the return of serve. I find the slice to be an excellent way to neutralize fast serves. It’s also much easier to control a slice return than a topspin return on fast or high serves.</p>
<p>The downside of returning a serve with a slice is that your opponent could volley it for a winner. But that’s only if they are a serve and volley type player. If you’re playing a strict baseliner, it’s a good tactic for the return.</p>
<p>The slice is an excellent way to handle high shots too (balls higher than your shoulder level). This is especially true on the backhand side, where there is less flexibility and strength to hit the ball high up.</p>
<p>For this reason, you’ll see many professional players turn to the slice on the high backhand. I personally use the slice to great effect on my forehand wing too – mostly on high shots.</p>
<p>The slice is also a great way to change up the spin on the ball. In this way, you offer different looks to your opponent, so they never know what to expect.</p>
<p>Lastly, the slice is often used as a last resort when the ball is far from the body. This typically happens when a ball is hit far from us and we are on the run to it.</p>
<p>Being it’s nearly impossible to hit a traditional groundstroke when so out of position, players will simply slice the ball back, as it’s the only option. When done on the forehand side, some call it a “squash shot”.</p>
<p>Roger Federer probably hits the best “squash shot” in the game. He also has one of the best slices the game has ever seen, period.</p>
<p>If you play tennis but haven’t developed a slice – or a good slice – work with a coach who can show you the shot. I have a great blog post here on <a href="/how-to-backhand-slice-in-tennis-the-right-way/">how to hit a backhand slice</a>.  I’ll be adding one for the forehand slice soon.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="overhead"></a></p>
<h2>The Basic Overhead Shot</h2>
</div>
<p>The overhead is a shot you hit above your head. It’s very similar to the serve motion, except the ball will be hit at you, instead of you initiating the stroke.</p>
<p>Overheads can be hit directly out of the air or after they hit the ground. If taken out of the air, exquisite timing is necessary to hit an effective overhead.</p>
<p>On occasion, it’s wise to let the ball hit the ground first and not take it out of the air. If the ball bounces high enough, you can strike the ball over your head.</p>
<p>Allowing the ball to hit the ground first is a lot easier than taking it out of the air. However, most of the time you’ll want to hit the ball out of the air.</p>
<div id="attachment_1877" style="width: 410px" class="wp-caption alignright"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1877" class="size-full wp-image-1877" src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/overhead.jpg" alt="Rafael Nadal hitting an overhead shot." width="400" height="599" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/overhead.jpg 400w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/01/overhead-200x300.jpg 200w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" /><p id="caption-attachment-1877" class="wp-caption-text">Carine06 from UK [<a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.0">CC BY-SA 2.0</a>], <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Flickr_-_Carine06_-_Rafa_overhead.jpg">via Wikimedia Commons</a></p></div>It’s really a judgment call which one you choose. The more you play, the easier it becomes to decide. You’re much more likely to hit the ball out of the air when you’re at net and lobbed.</p>
<p>It&#8217;s my belief that if you have a good serve motion, you’ll have a good overhead. The fundamentals of the serve and overhead are basically the same.</p>
<p>However, if your serve fundamentals are lacking, your overheads are going to be spotty at best. I believe a good racket drop is crucial to hitting great overheads. The racket drop is when your racket inverts before swinging up to contact.</p>
<p>If you have a beginner’s serve, also known as a waiter’s serve, you’ll likely never have world-class overheads. But you can still make do and place the ball well.</p>
<p>The overhead requires good footwork and great timing. Most people miss their overheads because their footwork does not put them in proper position to hit the ball well.</p>
<p>When you see a ball lobbed to you, your first instinct should be to turn to your forehand side and get your racket up. This is the side from which you hit your forehands and serves.</p>
<p>From here, you’ll want to use a cross-step as your first move. Once done, side-step back into position to hit the perfect overhead.</p>
<p>A major mistake I often see is people walking backwards to hit the overhead. They clearly missed the first step of turning to their side. This rarely works and can result in you falling over and hurting yourself.</p>
<p>With the right footwork and practice, you can make the overhead one of your best shots. If you can put your overheads away with pace and placement, it’ll put a ton of pressure on your opponents – especially when you come to net.</p>
<p>I should mention that the overhead can be hit on the backhand side as well. It’s rare, but most professional players can put away balls using a backhand overhead. A lot of it involves a flick of the wrist.</p>
<p>However, most club players find the backhand overhead shot to be very difficult. It’s still worth practicing, as you’ll experience hitting it from time-to-time in your matches. It involves using a combination of your arm and wrist.</p>
<p>The normal overhead is an important shot to learn in tennis and will serve you well in both singles and doubles. Most people don’t practice the overhead enough. I suggest working on it every practice session, if even for 5-10 minutes.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="dropshot"></a></p>
<h2>The Basic Drop Shot</h2>
</div>
<p>When done right, the drop shot is an extremely effective shot that can win you a point outright. It is often made from the baseline, whereby a player hits the ball very slowly with a lot of backspin.</p>
<p>Optimally, the ball will go barely over the net, not more than 5-6 feet into the court, and have very little forward movement. This will force the opposing player to sprint up to the ball and hit it.</p>
<p>This causes difficultly for the opposing player for several reasons. One is that the ball may be out of reach, whereby you win the point outright. Second, the opposing player must run fast and stop in time to avoid hitting the net.</p>
<p>If that player touches the net with their body or racket after hitting the ball, they automatically lose the point. Third, most good drop shots will cause the opposing player to lift the ball over the net, making it difficult to hit a good shot back on you.</p>
<div id="attachment_1865" style="width: 410px" class="wp-caption alignright"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1865" class="size-full wp-image-1865" src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/dropshot.jpg" alt="Boris Becker drop shot" width="400" height="267" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/dropshot.jpg 400w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/01/dropshot-300x200.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/01/dropshot-272x182.jpg 272w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" /><p id="caption-attachment-1865" class="wp-caption-text">James Phelps from USA [<a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0">CC BY 2.0</a>], <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Boris_Becker_in_action.jpg">via Wikimedia Commons</a></p></div>The drop shot can be hit off either side – forehand or backhand. It can be used at any time during the point, even off the serve. As a matter of fact, it can be very effective off the serve.</p>
<p>I like to throw in at least a few drop shots per set – usually in my baseline rallies. I do this for several reasons. One, it keeps the opposing player honest; he or she never knows what to expect from me.</p>
<p>Second, it makes the opposing player sprint to net, which expends their energy. This makes them just a bit more tired during the rest of the match.</p>
<p>I especially like to drop shot my opponent in the first set, as it will tire them out in the second set, and possibly the third (if we go there). If you want to compare it to boxing, drop shots are like body blows.</p>
<p>Even if the opponent gets to my drop shot and wins the point, it takes a small physical toll on them. In boxing, a fighter may land body shots early in the fight, but they typically don’t pay off until the later rounds. Same thing in tennis.</p>
<p>The drop shot can be used in these different scenarios: off the serve (as I just mentioned), during a baseline rally, and when you’re at net hitting a volley (called a drop volley). Another really good time to use the drop shot is off a drop shot.</p>
<p>That last scenario may sound confusing, so I’ll clarify. Let’s say your opponent drop shots you and you sprint up to the net to hit the ball. Usually your best option at that point is to drop your opponent right back.</p>
<p>Why? Because it’s often unexpected and your opponent will need to cover a large distance to get to the ball. It’s also easier to drop shot from the net rather than the baseline.</p>
<p>The drop shot requires a more delicate touch than any other shot in tennis. If you’re playing against a fast player who anticipates well, you’ll have a slim margin of success with the drop shot.</p>
<p>The danger of the drop shot occurs when it’s hit too deep or too high. If this happens, expect your opponent to easily get up to it and hit a clear winner on you.</p>
<p>As this can happen, it’s an excellent idea to disguise your drop shot. You do this by making it look like you’re going to hit your normal forehand or backhand.</p>
<p>At the last second you pull the rug out from under your opponent and slice the ball short. If you can learn to disguise your dropper, you’ll have a lot more success with it.</p>
<p>I think the number one reason players fail when using the drop shot is that they telegraph it. Most have no idea they’re showing their hand a mile away – as their opponents are usually mum to the fact.</p>
<p>One more point about the drop shot: It can be a great way to get a baseline player who hates the net out of his element.</p>
<p>By dropping such players, you force them to play the net, where their weakest. This is a great strategy to use against a perennial baseline player.</p>
<p>Practicing the drop shot is quite easy. Just rally at the baseline with your hitting partner. After one or two shots, hit a drop shot. You can also practice it on a ball machine.</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="lob"></a></p>
<h2>The Basic Lob</h2>
</div>
<div id="attachment_1880" style="width: 810px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1880" class="wp-image-1880 size-full" src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/lob2.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/lob2.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/01/lob2-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/01/lob2-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /><p id="caption-attachment-1880" class="wp-caption-text"><a title="Running down a lob" href="https://flickr.com/photos/mirsasha/5000452102">&#8220;Running down a lob&#8221;</a> by <a href="https://flickr.com/people/mirsasha">mirsasha</a> is licensed under <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/2.0/">CC BY-NC-ND</a></p></div>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>The lob is chiefly a defensive tennis shot. In tennis, a lob is a slow-moving shot hit at a high trajectory. Its purpose is to go over the head of a net player – or make the net player hit a difficult shot.</p>
<p>Some people even go so far as to use the lob in rallies. While that can work at the lower levels of tennis, it doesn’t work at the intermediate level &#8211; and certainly not at the advanced level.</p>
<p>I suggest only lobbing when the opposing player is at the net or when you’re far out of position and off the court. The latter works well to give yourself time to get back into the point.</p>
<p>Lobbing when you’re off the court is especially effective if the opposing player doesn’t like to move off the baseline. I use this tactic a lot when I’m strung wide against a perennial baseline player.</p>
<p>The lob can be hit off any side, forehand or backhand. It is most often hit with topspin but can be hit with slice as well. A topspin lob is much preferred and more effective for three distinct reasons.</p>
<p>One is that the topspin will help keep the ball in the court. Two, it’s more difficult for your opponent to hit a fast spinning ball that is dipping quickly; slice shots tend to float more and are much easier to hit.</p>
<p>Lastly, you can lob with more pace and margin of error with a topspin as opposed to slice. To hit the lob, simply brush on the bottom of the ball and finish your stroke up high. You’ll be taking almost all the pace off the ball and putting that energy into the “brush”.</p>
<p>Keep in mind it’s always more effective to lob your opponent on his or her backhand side. The backhand overhead is a much tougher shot to hit than the normal overhead.</p>
<p>You can make the lob more even more effective if you disguise it well. Do this by preparing the same way you would on any forehand or backhand. Instead of hitting with your normal stroke, put a lot of brush on the ball.</p>
<p>Lobbing is a good strategy but it’s not the cure-all to beat a player that likes to come to net on you. Instead, it’s best to mix in hard shots and heavy topspin shots with your lobs.</p>
<p>This throws your opponent off and will keep them guessing. If you’re playing outside and it’s very windy, take note of which way the wind is blowing.</p>
<p>My best advice on a windy day is not to lob into the wind. I find it to be very challenging to hit a lob when the wind is against me.</p>
<p>If I lob into the wind, the ball will not be very deep, and my opponent will crush it. On the contrary, lobbing with the wind is advisable.</p>
<p>You just need be careful not to put too much on the ball. When hitting a lob with the wind at your back, hit lightly and let the wind do the work.</p>
<p>You can practice your lobs as easily as your drop shots. Just have someone stand at the net and see how well you can lob them. Practice over-and-over on both forehand and backhand wings. Do this until you’re a master of the topspin lob off of both sides.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Conclusion</h2>
<p>This wraps up the 8 basic shots in tennis. I hope this post has given you a good insight into each stroke. My point was to give some information on each stroke to all level of players.</p>
<p>If you’re new to tennis, take your time learning each stroke. Tennis is a difficult game to learn and master. Give yourself several years to reach an intermediate level.</p>
<p>For those experienced players reading this, if you’re not using all 8 basic shots in your game, you’re selling yourself short. For example, if you’ve never sliced, or don’t believe you can do it well, take on the challenge of learning it.</p>
<p>It will add great depth to your game. Remember, always make sure you know the fundamentals and are executing them properly. If you can’t get a coach, at least video your strokes so you can see where corrections need to be made.</p>
<p>Hey, I have a lot of cool and interesting articles on this blog, so don’t be afraid to browse around and check them out. I’ve categorized most of them into “training” and “theory”.</p>
<p>Thanks for coming this far with me. If you have any questions on these basic strokes of tennis post them in the comment section below. And don’t forget to check out my youtube channel for great tips and tricks to accelerate your tennis game.</p>
<p>The post <a href="/what-are-the-8-basic-tennis-shots/">What Are The 8 Basic Tennis Shots?</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/what-are-the-8-basic-tennis-shots/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>What Is The Windshield Wiper Forehand – 10 Questions And Answers All About It</title>
		<link>/what-is-the-windshield-wiper-forehand-10-questions-and-answers-all-about-it/</link>
					<comments>/what-is-the-windshield-wiper-forehand-10-questions-and-answers-all-about-it/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chad Walner]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 25 Dec 2018 05:28:09 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Theory]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[forehand]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1714</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>If you’ve been around tennis circles for enough time, you’ve probably heard the term “windshield wiper forehand”. For the past many years I’ve seen a lot of tennis videos on youtube talking about it – including my own! You may &#8230; <a class="kt-excerpt-readmore" href="/what-is-the-windshield-wiper-forehand-10-questions-and-answers-all-about-it/" aria-label="What Is The Windshield Wiper Forehand – 10 Questions And Answers All About It">Read More</a></p>
<p>The post <a href="/what-is-the-windshield-wiper-forehand-10-questions-and-answers-all-about-it/">What Is The Windshield Wiper Forehand – 10 Questions And Answers All About It</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><strong>If you’ve been around tennis circles for enough time, you’ve probably heard the term “windshield wiper forehand”. For the past many years I’ve seen a lot of tennis videos on youtube talking about it – including my own!</strong></p>
<p><strong>You may have no idea what the windshield wiper forehand is. Or maybe you have an idea but you’re not entirely clear. If so, you’re in the right place.</strong></p>
<p><strong>Today I’m going to dispel the mystery of the windshield wiper forehand. I’ll be answering the 10 most common questions about it, as seen below. By the time you’re done with this post, you’ll know this shot inside and out.</strong></p>
<div class="hrule clearfix" style="background:#81d742; height:1px"></div>
<ol>
<li><a href="#how-to-hit">How do you hit the windshield wiper forehand?</a></li>
<li><a href="#what-is-different">What’s the difference between a windshield wiper forehand and a regular forehand?</a></li>
<li><a href="#when-to-use">When do you use the windshield wiper forehand?</a></li>
<li><a href="#pros">Do all professional players hit the windshield wiper forehand?</a></li>
<li><a href="#effective">Why is the windshield wiper forehand so effective?</a></li>
<li><a href="#beginner">Can a beginner hit the windshield wiper forehand?</a></li>
<li><a href="#topspin">Does the windshield wiper forehand provide more topspin than a traditional forehand?</a></li>
<li><a href="#power">Can I hit with power using the windshield wiper forehand?</a></li>
<li><a href="#how-long">Will it take me a long time to learn the windshield wiper forehand?</a></li>
<li><a href="#child">Can a child learn the windshield wiper forehand?</a></li>
</ol>
<div class="hrule clearfix" style="background:#81d742; height:1px"></div>
<p>Before I answer the first question, I just want to say that I believe every serious tennis player should learn the windshield wiper forehand. It’s an incredibly effective shot and something I teach all my long-time students.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="kad-youtube-shortcode videofit"  ><iframe loading="lazy" width="600" height="400" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/QZvD97VXHGU?autoplay=0&controls=1&fs=1&modestbranding=1&theme=dark&rel=0&loop=0&showinfo=1" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="true"></iframe></div>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>You can check out the accompanying video to see how I hit the windshield wiper forehand. By reading this post and seeing the video, you’ll be covering all bases. Alright let’s get to those questions.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="how-to-hit"></a></p>
<h2>How Do You Hit The Windshield Wiper Forehand?</h2>
</div>

<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/Start-The-Forehand-With-Your-Normal-Setup.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="450" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/Start-The-Forehand-With-Your-Normal-Setup.jpg" class="attachment-large size-large" alt="Start the forehand with your normal setup." srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/Start-The-Forehand-With-Your-Normal-Setup.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/12/Start-The-Forehand-With-Your-Normal-Setup-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/12/Start-The-Forehand-With-Your-Normal-Setup-768x432.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/12/Start-The-Forehand-With-Your-Normal-Setup-732x412.jpg 732w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/12/Start-The-Forehand-With-Your-Normal-Setup-366x206.jpg 366w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></a>
<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/Contact-the-ball-with-the-racket-head-below-the-hand.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="450" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/Contact-the-ball-with-the-racket-head-below-the-hand.jpg" class="attachment-large size-large" alt="Contact the ball with the racket head below the ball." srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/Contact-the-ball-with-the-racket-head-below-the-hand.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/12/Contact-the-ball-with-the-racket-head-below-the-hand-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/12/Contact-the-ball-with-the-racket-head-below-the-hand-768x432.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/12/Contact-the-ball-with-the-racket-head-below-the-hand-732x412.jpg 732w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/12/Contact-the-ball-with-the-racket-head-below-the-hand-366x206.jpg 366w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></a>
<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/The-tip-of-the-racket-head-will-move-straight-up.-The-strings-will-face-your-opponent-1.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="450" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/The-tip-of-the-racket-head-will-move-straight-up.-The-strings-will-face-your-opponent-1.jpg" class="attachment-large size-large" alt="The tip of the racket head will move straight up." srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/The-tip-of-the-racket-head-will-move-straight-up.-The-strings-will-face-your-opponent-1.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/12/The-tip-of-the-racket-head-will-move-straight-up.-The-strings-will-face-your-opponent-1-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/12/The-tip-of-the-racket-head-will-move-straight-up.-The-strings-will-face-your-opponent-1-768x432.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/12/The-tip-of-the-racket-head-will-move-straight-up.-The-strings-will-face-your-opponent-1-732x412.jpg 732w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/12/The-tip-of-the-racket-head-will-move-straight-up.-The-strings-will-face-your-opponent-1-366x206.jpg 366w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></a>
<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/Allow-the-racket-to-flip-to-the-other-side-of-your-body.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="450" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/Allow-the-racket-to-flip-to-the-other-side-of-your-body.jpg" class="attachment-large size-large" alt="Allow the racket to flip to the other side of the body." srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/Allow-the-racket-to-flip-to-the-other-side-of-your-body.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/12/Allow-the-racket-to-flip-to-the-other-side-of-your-body-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/12/Allow-the-racket-to-flip-to-the-other-side-of-your-body-768x432.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/12/Allow-the-racket-to-flip-to-the-other-side-of-your-body-732x412.jpg 732w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/12/Allow-the-racket-to-flip-to-the-other-side-of-your-body-366x206.jpg 366w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></a>
<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/The-racket-will-finish-close-to-the-waist-on-follow-through.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="450" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/The-racket-will-finish-close-to-the-waist-on-follow-through.jpg" class="attachment-large size-large" alt="The racket will finish close to the waist at follow through." srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/The-racket-will-finish-close-to-the-waist-on-follow-through.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/12/The-racket-will-finish-close-to-the-waist-on-follow-through-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/12/The-racket-will-finish-close-to-the-waist-on-follow-through-768x432.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/12/The-racket-will-finish-close-to-the-waist-on-follow-through-732x412.jpg 732w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/12/The-racket-will-finish-close-to-the-waist-on-follow-through-366x206.jpg 366w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></a>
<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/Complete-follow-through.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="450" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/Complete-follow-through.jpg" class="attachment-large size-large" alt="Complete follow through." srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/Complete-follow-through.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/12/Complete-follow-through-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/12/Complete-follow-through-768x432.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/12/Complete-follow-through-732x412.jpg 732w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/12/Complete-follow-through-366x206.jpg 366w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></a>

<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>To hit the windshield wiper forehand, use your normal setup on the forehand. Your pivot, unit turn, power position, and slot position will be the same as the forehand you always hit.</p>
<p>The difference in the windshield wiper forehand comes immediately after you contact the ball. Of course, you’ll need to make sure your racket head is below your hand on the swing to contact.</p>
<p>Your forearm to racket angle should be around 90 degrees. This is something that I talk about a lot in my videos and blog. I also made a dedicated video demonstrating this technique, check it out below.</p>
<p>Now that we have the setup right, we can talk about what happens right after contact is made. Okay, so immediately after contact you’re going to flip your wrist as if you are waving “bye-bye”. Another way to think of it is turning a lock or doorknob.</p>
<p>You don’t actually use wrist muscles or joints to flip the racket. It’s more pronation of the forearm than anything else.</p>
<p>The difference between this type of pronation and the serve is that on the windshield wiper forehand, your wrist is laid back, while on the serve it’s flat.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>Once you “flip” the wrist, your racket will make a 180-degree rotation. Assuming you’re right-handed, on contact the butt cap of the racket should be facing to the left.</p>
<p>But within fractions of a second, the racket will “flip” sides and the butt cap will end up facing the right side. This allows the player to generate an absurd amount of racket speed.</p>
<p>For the follow through, just allow your hitting shoulder and arm to move to the left (for righties). It will naturally want to go in that direction anyway. The follow through on the windshield wiper forehand is often under the shoulder and close to the navel or waist.</p>
<p><strong>The main key in hitting the windshield wiper forehand is not to flip the racket (or use the pronation) until the ball contacts the racket. It takes a bit of practice to learn the timing, but it’s not that difficult if you are an experienced player.</strong></p>
<p>When first learning this shot, you may find a lot of your shots going into the net. This is because of the increased topspin. If so, aim higher over the net until you learn a safe clearance height.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="what-is-different"></a></p>
<h2>What’s The Difference Between A Windshield Wiper Forehand And A Regular Forehand?</h2>
</div>
<p>&nbsp;</p>

<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/A-traditional-forehand-has-the-arm-extending-out-more-after-contact2.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="450" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/A-traditional-forehand-has-the-arm-extending-out-more-after-contact2.jpg" class="attachment-large size-large" alt="A traditional forehand has the arm extending out more after contact." srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/A-traditional-forehand-has-the-arm-extending-out-more-after-contact2.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/12/A-traditional-forehand-has-the-arm-extending-out-more-after-contact2-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/12/A-traditional-forehand-has-the-arm-extending-out-more-after-contact2-768x432.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/12/A-traditional-forehand-has-the-arm-extending-out-more-after-contact2-560x315.jpg 560w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></a>
<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/The-windshield-wiper-has-a-shorter-extention-on-the-forehand2.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="450" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/The-windshield-wiper-has-a-shorter-extention-on-the-forehand2.jpg" class="attachment-large size-large" alt="The windshield wiper has a shorter extension on the forehand." srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/The-windshield-wiper-has-a-shorter-extention-on-the-forehand2.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/12/The-windshield-wiper-has-a-shorter-extention-on-the-forehand2-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/12/The-windshield-wiper-has-a-shorter-extention-on-the-forehand2-768x432.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/12/The-windshield-wiper-has-a-shorter-extention-on-the-forehand2-560x315.jpg 560w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></a>

<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>The major difference is that the windshield wiper forehand is a shorter swing.</strong> Instead of the arm extending fully out in front, like on a regular forehand, the arm extends out only 50-60% as far and the racket makes an abrupt flip to the other side of the body.</p>
<p>With a regular forehand, the racket covers a much larger radius in terms of swing path. The windshield wiper forehand is more of an abbreviated swing, with the racket quickly moving from one side to the other (or from right to left for righthanded players).</p>
<p>The other difference is that a regular forehand will generally be a heavier shot with less topspin. If you want to hit a penetrating shot, use a traditional forehand with a long swing path (a la Roger Federer).<br />
The windshield wiper forehand will not be as “heavy” as a traditional forehand but often possesses more topspin.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="when-to-use"></a></p>
<h2>When Do You Use The Windshield Wiper Forehand?</h2>
</div>
<p>The windshield wiper forehand is not the normal forehand that most professionals hit. They mostly favor their regular forehand in rallies but use the windshield wiper forehand during certain moments.</p>
<p>Each pro is different, so I’ll tell you some of the occasions I like to use the windshield wiper forehand. One that I like a lot is <strong>to send the ball deep into the corner of my opponent’s backhand with topspin</strong>.</p>
<p>I find the windshield wiper forehand is easier to control in this instance than a regular forehand. Since there is less power and more spin, I find it a more manageable shot to place and control.</p>
<p>The second occasion is <strong>when an opponent hits a low-to-medium height shot inside the service line</strong>. In this case, hitting a traditional forehand can be difficult because of being much closer to the net.</p>
<p>The windshield wiper forehand is a better choice in this case, as we only need to spin the ball over the net with medium pace to win the shot – especially if the opponent is at net.</p>
<p>The other occasion it’s very effective is on the lob. For most lobs, we don’t need power but spin and control. As a result, the windshield wiper forehand is extremely useful to hit on lobs and can be disguised well too.</p>
<p>The final instance I use the windshield wiper forehand is <strong>when I just need to get the forehand in play</strong>. For example, I may be hitting my regular forehand long and I want to limit errors.</p>
<p>In that case, I’ll turn to the windshield wiper forehand just to keep the ball in play until I get my normal forehand back on track. But really, you can use the windshield wiper forehand any time you want.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="pros"></a></p>
<h2>Do All Professional Players Hit The Windshield Wiper Forehand?</h2>
</div>
<p><strong>I would think yes.</strong> For sure, I’ve seen the top male players in the world (Federer, Nadal, Djokovic, Murray, etc.) use it many times. Interestingly, I see female players use it less.</p>
<p>This could be because the windshield wiper forehand is easier to hit with a takeback (which men do) then a pendulum swing, which the women mostly use. If you want to know the difference between the WTA and ATP forehand swing, <a href="/atp-vs-wta-anatomy-of-great-groundstrokes/">check out this blog post</a> I wrote.</p>
<p>While I can’t be certain if every single professional player on tour hits the windshield wiper forehand, I can say that most do. Probably all of them know how to hit it, but some prefer to use it more than others.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="effective"></a></p>
<h2>Why Is The Windshield Wiper Forehand So Effective?</h2>
</div>
<p>I kind of answered that already. <strong>The windshield wiper forehand allows you to hit with more topspin, greater </strong>control,<strong> and is a bit easier to hit than a regular forehand on certain shots.</strong></p>
<p>I find that the windshield wiper forehand is extremely effective when hitting lobs and it can even be used to great effect on passing shots. That’s because the heavy topspin makes the ball dip quickly.</p>
<p>A quick dipping ball is very difficult to hit for a net player. For this reason, I’ll sometimes use the windshield wiper forehand to pass opponents at the net.</p>
<p>For those players that lack topspin, the windshield wiper forehand is a great hack to get more topspin. For these reasons, I feel it can be an effective shot for any player, any gender, at the intermediate and advanced levels.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="beginner"></a></p>
<h2>Can A Beginner Hit The Windshield Wiper Forehand?</h2>
</div>
<p><strong>Yes, absolutely.</strong> Like I said before, in some ways it’s easier to hit than a traditional forehand. The danger in teaching it to beginners is that they’ll overuse it.</p>
<p>Instead, it’s always best to teach a traditional (long swing path) first and once that is ingrained, then you can move on to the windshield wiper forehand.</p>
<p>To me, the windshield wiper forehand is an accessory to a tennis player’s tennis game. It’s not 100 percent necessary to use, but it’s a very good adjunct to a player’s game.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="topspin"></a></p>
<h2>Does The Windshield Wiper Forehand Provide More Topspin Than A Traditional Forehand?</h2>
</div>
<p>This is a tricky question to answer. Great players can hit with a ton of topspin on traditional forehands, but club players usually can’t.</p>
<p><strong>For this reason, the windshield wiper forehand is an excellent choice to increase topspin for club players.</strong> As I mentioned previously, I think it’s an excellent hack on upping topspin for players who struggle with it.</p>
<p>However, this doesn’t mean you should rely exclusively on the windshield wiper forehand for your topspin. I encourage players to use their traditional forehands to generate topspin.</p>
<p>If you want to know how to generate more in your game, check out this detailed blog post I wrote on the subject.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="power"></a></p>
<h2>Can I Hit With Power Using The Windshield Wiper Forehand?</h2>
</div>
<p>This is a good question. The short answer is yes. The longer answer is it depends on the player and your definition of power.</p>
<p>You usually don’t see professional tour level players using it for power. However, at the club level, a 60 mph forehand using the windshield wiper technique might be considered powerful, whereas in the pro ranks it wouldn’t.</p>
<p>You’ll always be able to generate more power on a traditional forehand because you’re extending out and putting all your weight behind it. Of course, most club players use too short of an extension on their strokes anyway, but that’s a different topic.</p>
<p>With the windshield wiper forehand, the faster you can whip the racket from one side to the other, the faster the ball is going to travel. Some people have very fast pronation and can generate good pace.</p>
<p>Others not.</p>
<p><strong>In my opinion, you can hit powerful enough shots with the windshield wiper forehand to make a difference in your game.</strong> But if you want to hit a scorching forehand winner or passing shot, best to stick to a traditional forehand with full extension.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="how-long"></a></p>
<h2>Will It Take Me A Long Time To Learn The Windshield Wiper Forehand?</h2>
</div>
<p>It always depends on the individual, talent level, and experience. I personally learned it quickly, probably within 3-5 hours of using it.</p>
<p><strong>Learning the concept of the technique is easy. But timing the windshield pronation part of the swing is what trip’s most people up.</strong> If you’re an experienced player, you should be able to learn it within a few hitting sessions.</p>
<p>As a caution, I don’t think it’s wise to teach this shot to total beginners and children just starting out. If you’re a newbie to tennis, learn the traditional forehand first.</p>
<p>But if you really want to hit the windshield wiper forehand, I think you could learn it with a fair amount of practice.</p>
<p>By learning it, I mean hitting it consistently well in a rally. New players may find the shot difficult to control at first, hitting balls into the net or too long. It just takes time to adjust.</p>
<p>Remember, additional topspin on the ball means you’ll need to hit with a higher trajectory. This will allow the ball to pass over the net with some clearance. Otherwise, you’re going to hit the ball into the net a lot.</p>
<p>This took me a few hours to get used to and I was an experienced player when I learned the windshield wiper forehand. If you want to teach it to your child, I’m sure your child can eventually learn it.</p>
<p>However, it’s much better for a young child to stick with a traditional forehand for several years before learning the windshield wiper. Young children often can’t distinguish between the two hitting forms anyway.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="child"></a></p>
<h2>Can A Child Learn The Windshield Wiper Forehand?</h2>
</div>
<p>I addressed this in the last question. The short answer is yes. But I think<strong> it depends on the age of the child, how long they’ve been playing, and their talent level.</strong></p>
<p>For example, I have a 10-year-old girl named Kayden who hits an incredibly powerful traditional forehand. If I show her the windshield wiper forehand, she may learn it, but I’m certain it will confuse her.</p>
<p>She’s in her formative tennis years now and it’s best for kids at this stage to perfect traditional strokes. When Kayden reaches the age of 13-14, and her traditional forehand has been cemented, it may be fine to teach the windshield wiper forehand to her. But not now.</p>
<p>The main issue I have with teaching the windshield wiper forehand to children is that they’ll overuse it and be unable to distinguish between that shot and a traditional forehand. For this reason, I don’t recommend teaching it to children younger than 13-years-old and with less than 3-4 years of playing experience.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Wrapping It All Up</h2>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1745" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/gift.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/gift.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/12/gift-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/12/gift-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>I trust this post answered all your questions about the windshield wiper forehand. It can be a tremendous asset to your tennis game, so consider learning it.</p>
<p>If you had any doubts about what the windshield wiper forehand is, hopefully, the information here cleared that up. If you have additional questions about the windshield wiper forehand, feel free to drop me a comment below.</p>
<p>Thanks for reading. Check out some of my other blog posts while you’re here. I post awesome content weekly designed to supercharge your tennis game.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>The post <a href="/what-is-the-windshield-wiper-forehand-10-questions-and-answers-all-about-it/">What Is The Windshield Wiper Forehand – 10 Questions And Answers All About It</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/what-is-the-windshield-wiper-forehand-10-questions-and-answers-all-about-it/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>How To Hit High Forehands in Tennis</title>
		<link>/how-to-hit-high-forehands-in-tennis/</link>
					<comments>/how-to-hit-high-forehands-in-tennis/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chad Walner]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 11 Dec 2018 16:41:53 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Theory]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[forehand]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1541</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The high shot in tennis is a ball hit above shoulder height. Most beginner and intermediate players struggle with hitting the high shot in tennis, even on the forehand side. If you can’t handle the high ball, then you’re always &#8230; <a class="kt-excerpt-readmore" href="/how-to-hit-high-forehands-in-tennis/" aria-label="How To Hit High Forehands in Tennis">Read More</a></p>
<p>The post <a href="/how-to-hit-high-forehands-in-tennis/">How To Hit High Forehands in Tennis</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>The high shot in tennis is a ball hit above shoulder height. Most beginner and intermediate players struggle with hitting the high shot in tennis, even on the forehand side.</p>



<p>If you can’t handle the high ball, then you’re always going to feel uncomfortable playing tennis. Furthermore, opponents that hit with topspin or loop the ball to you will always pose a threat.</p>



<p>In order to reach the next level in tennis, it’s critical to effectively deal with high shots, particularly on the forehand side, which is your strong side. The backhand side is a lot more difficult for several key reasons, but we’ll focus on it in a different post.</p>



<p>It took me several years to learn how to successfully deal with high forehands in my tennis game. Once I did, it made the game a lot easier and I was able to beat massive topspin players I couldn’t before.</p>



<p>In this post I’m going to talk exclusively about how you can effectively hit high shots off your forehand side. If hitting high shots is placing you on the defensive and causing unforced errors, this post is for you.</p>



<p><strong>When dealing with high forehands, it’s essential we know the following. These points are critical to success on high forehands.</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list"><li><strong>A slight grip change is important for generating topspin</strong></li><li><strong>The open stance works best for dealing with high balls</strong></li><li><strong>The high forehand swing path is different than for a low or medium height ball</strong></li><li><strong>It’s important to use your body to rotate on a high ball</strong></li></ul>



<p>I will go into detail on each one of these points. If you can put them all together, not only will you be able to hit high forehands comfortably, you may even be able to crush them back to your opponent.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Grip Change</h2>



<p>If you hit with an eastern forehand grip, you’ll want to change to a semi-western grip when hitting high forehands. The eastern forehand grip has your index finger knuckle on the third bevel of the racket.</p>


<script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script>
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins>
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script>


<p>For the semi-western grip, you’ll be moving your index knuckle to the fourth bevel. This will cause the racket head to turn down more, allowing your forehand shot to stay in the court.</p>



<p>If you remain in the eastern forehand grip on the high shots, you run the risk of hitting long. I know the grip change may seem awkward at first, but I promise you’ll get used to it.</p>



<p>When I hit a high forehand, I automatically hit with the semi-western grip. It’s not something I have to consciously think about it. If you play enough, you will automatically assume the correct grip on every shot.</p>



<p>When practicing the high shots, make sure your grip changes to the semi-western. A lot of players aren’t aware of their grips when hitting the ball so look to see where your hand is after striking the ball.</p>



<p>One last thing here. If you already hit out of the semi-western grip (or even the western grip), you don’t need to make a grip change.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Open Stance</h2>



<p>When hitting high forehands, you’ll want to set up in the semi-open or open stance. See this post for <a href="/how-to-effortlessly-generate-more-power-on-your-groundstrokes/">the different stances in tennis</a>.</p>



<p>If you try to hit a high forehand out of a neutral or closed stance, you’ll likely make an error. This is because the neutral and closed stances&nbsp;do not allow for sufficient body rotation into the ball.</p>



<p>If you’re a long-time player who prefers a traditional neutral or closed stance, it could be challenging to change to the open stance. The open stance allows more versatility and torque.</p>



<p>Even if you don’t generate massive racket head speed on your forehands, it will be easier to deal with the high ball from the open stance. If you’re young and athletic, it should come fairly easily to you.</p>



<p>When preparing for the high forehand, you’ll be in a more upright stance than on lower balls. By upright, I mean your body will be more vertical. On lower shots, you’ll have a bit more of a tilt to your body.</p>



<p>It’s also important to load a bit on your right leg by bending it and placing pressure on it. Lefties will do the same on their left leg. This helps generate power.</p>



<p>Here is how I set up for high shots on my forehand. When the ball is on its way and I identify it’s going to be high, I start setting up in the open stance and change my grip – usually at the same time.</p>



<p>Since high balls usually take longer to arrive, you’ll have the time to set up – especially if the ball is coming right to you. It’s important the grip and stance are correct for the rest of the shot to work.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Swing Path</h2>



<p>The swing path of the high forehand is different than for low or medium-height shots. On low or medium height shots, you can really dip your racket under the ball significantly.</p>



<p>However, on the high shots, it’s not necessary to dip the racket so low. You’ll want to get only slightly under the ball before hitting it.</p>



<p>Once you strike the ball, the swing path will be much more across than up, especially on the drive shots (those with pace). If you’re a beginner, you may have been told to swing low-to-high on all your shots.</p>



<p>However, this doesn’t apply to high forehands where you are looking to drive the ball. Let me just be clear here. There are really two types of shots you can hit on the high forehand:</p>



<ol class="wp-block-list"><li>A <strong>drive shot</strong> where you are hitting with pace and less topspin.</li><li>A<strong> topspin shot</strong> where you are hitting with less pace and more topspin</li></ol>



<p><strong>Let’s talk about the drive shot first.</strong> You’ll want the racket to start only slightly under the ball – perhaps 6-8 inches. Strike the ball and then allow the racket to move across your body.</p>



<p>To simplify things for my beginner students, I demonstrate the high swing path. It will basically go straight across (after hitting the ball), so it remains the same height from the ground.</p>



<p>While this is an over-simplification, it works because it helps my students better visualize and execute the swing path. You may be thinking this swing path won’t work because we need to lift the ball over the net by swinging low-to-high.</p>



<p>However, on high shots, we can swing across (with no up or down trajectory) and allow gravity (and a little topspin) to bring the ball down into the court.</p>



<p>The faster you swing, the more you’ll need to lower your follow through – perhaps to under the shoulder. Also, the closer you are to the net, the same applies. You’ll need to follow through lower.</p>



<p>The best way to practice the high shots is with a ball machine. Stand a couple of feet in back of the baseline and practice hitting forehands at shoulder-to-head height.</p>


<script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script>
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins>
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script>


<p>Adjust your swing path and swing speed until you are hitting consistently in. Notice what happens if you slow your swing speed or lower your follow through.</p>



<p><strong>Now, if you plan on returning a high forehand with topspin, you’ll need to get under the ball a bit more (12-18 inches).</strong> You’ll also have a more vertical follow through – basically hitting low to high.</p>



<p>Often, for these shots, the buggy whip follow-through works well. This follow- through was popularized by Rafael Nadal early in his career. It’s really his signature move.</p>



<p>In order to counteract a heavy topspin shot that is rising to your forehand, you’ll need to meet it with force. This means racket speed.</p>



<p>To achieve high racket speed, you’ll need to drive up from the legs out of the open stance. If the racket is coming from a bit lower than the ball (12-18 inches), you’ll have more time to build up racket speed as well.</p>



<p>When making contact on very high balls, the angle of your racket should be slightly vertical. This concept can be confusing.</p>



<p>It really helped to me visualize the head of the racket being higher than the hand. That’s what I mean by “vertical”.</p>



<p>On low and medium-height shots, you would never do this. But once the ball raises to around head-height, you want the racket head to be above your hand. This applies to both the forehand and backhand side.</p>



<p>A vertical racket head will allow the power to come more from the chest and core, rather than the front deltoid. If you lift the arm too high, you’ll be using much weaker muscles and lack power.</p>



<p>That’s what you’re likely doing on your current forehands, which is why the high shots feel awkward. It comes from raising the arm too far up and not having the right technique. However, it doesn’t have to feel like that or be that way.</p>



<p>Give my suggestions a try and watch the video here to understand the technique better.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Body Rotation</h2>



<p>A lot of beginner and lower-level intermediate players struggle with rotation. When I say “rotation”, I mean the pivoting and turning of the entire body – shoulders, hips and feet.</p>



<p>For righties, the chest will face to the right at the start of the stroke and finish facing to the left at the completion of the stroke.</p>



<p>I think good rotation is difficult for some people because it requires athleticism, coordination, and good timing to execute right.</p>



<p>If you set up properly and swing across your body, you’ll naturally have some degree of rotation. That’s just the natural mechanics of the body at work.</p>



<p>But I see many players struggling to rotate fully. Lower level club players may only rotate half way. And some not even that much.</p>



<p>When swinging out of the open or semi-open stance it’s crucial to rotate fully. Unlike the neutral or closed stance, where we can transfer our weight forward, it’s not possible from the open stance.</p>



<p>From the open stance, the way we generate power is from racket speed and body rotation. This will sometimes cause us to take flight, even if a couple of inches off the ground. That’s perfectly fine.</p>



<p>When initiating the swing on the high forehand, you’ll be pushing mostly off your right foot (if you are right-handed). When making contact, both feet might be in the air.</p>



<p>The left foot should land first after rotation has completed. If you are not a high-flyer or not as athletic, you can keep both feet on the ground. Just make sure you’re pivoting on the balls of your feet.</p>



<p>I think a lot of lower level players don’t rotate properly because their hitting with their heels on the ground. If you do so, it’s nearly impossible to rotate.</p>



<p>Additionally, the feet may be pointed in the wrong direction. If your toe is pointed to far to the right (so that your foot is almost parallel to the baseline) it will also be nearly impossible to rotate.</p>



<p>Check out the video for how to properly set up the feet.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Putting It All Together</h2>



<p>The high forehand is a shot that takes time to master. This is because there’s no one-size-fits-all solution, such as on the serve or the volley.</p>



<p>There are too many variables on the high forehand, which makes it a bit complex to teach. It really depends on how much topspin is on the ball, where you strike it on the court, the height you hit it, and how much pace or spin you wish to apply to the ball.</p>



<p>Again, practicing on a ball machine is your best bet. You could also practice with a hitting partner or hit against a wall. Video yourself to make sure you are doing everything properly.</p>


<script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script>
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins>
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script>


<p>In time, you’ll find hitting the high forehand more and more comfortable and won’t struggle as much. You’ll also cut down on the errors and may even be able to hit offensive shots back.</p>



<p>Keep these two points in mind on all high forehands. If you want to safely get the ball back in play, use the topspin swing path. If you want to hit hard, then use more of the drive swing path.</p>



<p>Once you get it, you won’t fear the high ball anymore. When I first started playing tennis, I could handle the low ball well, but high shots killed me. Topspin hitters were my worst matchup.</p>



<p>I struggled for several years to master the high shot, but I’m glad I did. If it seems difficult at first, don’t give up. I’m sure you’re going to get it with enough practice</p>



<p>It’s an incredibly rewarding feeling to be able to handle any shot in tennis – and even rip the cover off some of those high forehands once in a while!</p>



<p>If you have any questions for me about hitting the high tennis forehand, let me know below. Thanks for stopping by my blog.</p>
<p>The post <a href="/how-to-hit-high-forehands-in-tennis/">How To Hit High Forehands in Tennis</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/how-to-hit-high-forehands-in-tennis/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>TopSpin Pro Tennis Review</title>
		<link>/topspin-pro-tennis-review/</link>
					<comments>/topspin-pro-tennis-review/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chad Walner]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 11 Nov 2018 17:47:44 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Reviews]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[backhand]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[forehand]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[topspin]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1213</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>If you’ve struggled with hitting topspin, this post may be the answer to your topspin issues. In it, I give my honest review of the Topspin Pro. Don’t forget to check out the video I made to see it in &#8230; <a class="kt-excerpt-readmore" href="/topspin-pro-tennis-review/" aria-label="TopSpin Pro Tennis Review">Read More</a></p>
<p>The post <a href="/topspin-pro-tennis-review/">TopSpin Pro Tennis Review</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>If you’ve struggled with hitting topspin, this post may be the answer to your topspin issues. In it, I give my honest review of the Topspin Pro. Don’t forget to check out the video I made to see it in action!</p>
<p><div id="attachment_1276" style="width: 410px" class="wp-caption alignright"><a href="https://amzn.to/2zFCfWJ" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1276" class="wp-image-1276 size-full" title="Our affiliate link to Amazon.com" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/topspinpro-45.jpg" alt="" width="400" height="635" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/topspinpro-45.jpg 400w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/11/topspinpro-45-189x300.jpg 189w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-1276" class="wp-caption-text">Click the picture to check the current pricing on Amazon.com.</p></div></p>
<p><strong>What exactly is the Topspin Pro?</strong></p>
<p><strong>The Topspin Pro is a tennis training device specifically designed to aid players in developing topspin.</strong></p>
<p>To my knowledge, the Topspin Pro hit the market in 2015 and has been well-received by tennis coaches and enthusiasts around the world since. It’s a simple machine but very effective in teaching topspin.</p>
<p>The company claims it can be used by children 5 years old and up. That really means everyone who plays tennis &#8211; even adults. Hey, we all need to practice, don’t we?</p>
<p>But seriously, I even find the Topspin Pro to be useful for an advanced player like myself. It simply reinforces the correct swing path for topspin. <strong>And I like topspin.</strong></p>
<p>I also find it to be a great tool for beginners, but intermediate players will also improve with it. I use the Topspin Pro mainly with my younger students, who range in age from 10-15 years old.</p>
<p>Every time I bring it to the court, I’m always amazed how children react to it. At first glance, they crowd around the Topspin Pro in a curious fashion. They ask me, “What is that?” It only takes me two minutes to give them an answer and demonstrate how it works.</p>
<p>Within seconds they’re copying me and hitting with topspin. If they don’t at first, it’s easy to grab their rackets and move it in the correct swing path. This does the trick every time.</p>
<p>There has literally never been one child that couldn’t make the ball spin forward. In my experience, all children and adults are fully capable of hitting topspin. In theory, if they can produce forward ball rotation on the Topspin Pro, they can do it during actual hits in practice and matches.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>How The Topspin Pro Works</h2>
<p><div id="attachment_1278" style="width: 410px" class="wp-caption alignleft"><a href="https://amzn.to/2zFCfWJ" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1278" class="wp-image-1278 size-full" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/topspinpro-side.jpg" alt="" width="400" height="401" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/topspinpro-side.jpg 400w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/11/topspinpro-side-150x150.jpg 150w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/11/topspinpro-side-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-1278" class="wp-caption-text">Click the picture to check the current pricing on Amazon.com.</p></div></p>
<p>The Topspin Pro is designed to provide instant feedback to the user, which I love about it. It does this by suspending an actual tennis ball on a thin rod that allows it to rotate forward.</p>
<p>The machine is used by standing to the front side of it and striking the ball with a tennis racket. If the ball is struck correctly, it rotates forward, creating topspin. If not struck correctly, no rotation occurs on the ball.</p>
<p>That’s really all there is to it. The machine doesn’t have any options, besides allowing the ball to move about 8 inches forward or not after it has been hit. I prefer the ball to move forward rather than stay in place.</p>
<p>The Topspin Pro can be adjusted for any height person, from kid to full grown adult. The adjustment pin is very easy to use and requires just a few seconds to adjust up or down.</p>
<p>This innovative teaching tool can be used indoors or outdoors. To me, it’s one of the best indoor tennis training devices on the market.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<blockquote><p>You can learn to hit topspin in your living room if you want! Now that’s cool.</p></blockquote>
<p>I find the Topspin Pro to be durable and haven’t experienced any issues since purchasing it. I’ve whacked it pretty hard and it’s never fallen over. The three tripod legs it stands on are strong and stable.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>How Does The Topspin Pro Teach Topspin?</h2>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignleft size-full wp-image-1305" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/TopSpin-Pro-Chad4.jpg" alt="" width="400" height="400" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/TopSpin-Pro-Chad4.jpg 400w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/11/TopSpin-Pro-Chad4-150x150.jpg 150w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/11/TopSpin-Pro-Chad4-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" />It teaches topspin by forcing the user to move the tennis racket in a low to high swing path. This is accomplished using the shoulder, elbow, and wrist joints in conjunction with each other.</p>
<p>If the ball is struck on the lower side first, and brushed on, the ball will rotate forward. This is how all topspin shots are achieved in tennis, whether on the forehand, the backhand, or the serve.</p>
<p>Racket angle is also important for topspin. The face should be slightly closed on contact, which is easier said than done. The Topspin Pro is built using this in mind.</p>
<p>According to Topspin Pro’s website, the angle of the racket face at contact should be in the mid-to-high 70s. For example, Federer hits with a 79-degree racket face and Nadal 76.</p>
<p>The mesh screens are designed at this angle, forcing the player to hit along it to create topspin. But don’t take my words for it. Here are the company’s exact words on how it teaches topspin:</p>
<blockquote><p>The screen reflects the required racket face angle and forces exact bio-mechanics of modern topspin groundstrokes – as seen by today’s professional players.</p></blockquote>
<p>When I demonstrate the Topspin Pro to my students, I show them how I align my racket face to the mesh screen. Once it’s aligned, it’s now at the perfect angle to generate topspin.</p>
<p>From there, all I need to do is swing in a low-to-high manner, brushing from underneath the ball. Voila, instant topspin! I then have my students swing, doing a couple of minutes on each wing – forehand and backhand.</p>
<p>I definitely see a difference in my students’ strokes after using the Topspin Pro. After using the device for only a couple of minutes, they have more topspin on their shots during practice.</p>
<p>However, the new angle face and swing path they learn needs to be reinforced. After 10-15 minutes, they may go back to their old swing, which does not generate topspin.</p>
<p>When I see that happen, I put them back on the Topspin Pro. For that reason, it’s a good idea to have students practice with it for a few minutes before every practice session.</p>
<p>Even using the Topspin Pro two or three times in a one-hour practice is perfectly fine. It only requires a couple of minutes to reinforce the swing.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Why Is Topspin Important?</h2>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignright size-full wp-image-1303" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/TopSpin-Pro-Chad.jpg" alt="" width="400" height="400" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/TopSpin-Pro-Chad.jpg 400w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/11/TopSpin-Pro-Chad-150x150.jpg 150w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/11/TopSpin-Pro-Chad-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" />Topspin is important for several reasons in tennis.</p>
<ol>
<li>First, it helps keep the ball in play. The forward spin on the ball causes more pressure to build on top of the ball, forcing it downwards. This is critical when hitting fast-paced shots. The forward rotation of the ball forces it down into the court. Without topspin, hard flat shots have a slim margin of staying in the court. But with topspin, the margins are much higher.</li>
<li>Topspin also makes the ball more difficult to volley at the net. This is because of the dipping effect the ball has with topspin. Balls that dip are tough to volley. The reason is that they drop below the net and must be volleyed near the ground.</li>
<li>Furthermore, it’s more difficult to control a ball hit with heavy spin. A lot of spin often results in the ball “flying” off the opponent’s racket. This is another reason why serve and volley is so difficult in today’s modern era of polyester strings and space-age like rackets.</li>
<li>Another reason for hitting topspin is net clearance. Balls struck with heavy topspin can be hit higher, providing more net margin. When a player only hits flat, the ball must be struck with less velocity, closer to the net, or both. Topspin allows for so much more versatility in a player’s strokes.</li>
</ol>
<p>If you look at today’s modern game, players are hitting harder than ever. The margins for error are so slim that players can’t afford to hit without high amounts of spin on the ball.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2><strong>Why The Topspin Pro Works</strong></h2>
<p><div id="attachment_1277" style="width: 410px" class="wp-caption alignright"><a href="https://amzn.to/2zFCfWJ" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1277" class="wp-image-1277 size-full" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/topspinpro-45left.jpg" alt="" width="400" height="375" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/topspinpro-45left.jpg 400w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/11/topspinpro-45left-300x281.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-1277" class="wp-caption-text">Click the picture to check the current pricing on Amazon.com.</p></div></p>
<p>Every good junior player I’ve hit with has great topspin on the ball. While topspin is an easy concept to explain (swing low-to-high and brush on the lower side of the ball), it’s not easy to do. If it was, a device like the Topspin Pro wouldn’t have been created.</p>
<p>I find that most beginner and intermediate players struggle with using their wrist to produce topspin. They also don’t come from underneath the ball nearly as much as they should. Doing these components, in addition to racket speed, generates serious topspin.</p>
<p>The Topspin Pro teaches all this for me. If the player doesn’t use their wrist and strike the ball from underneath, the ball will fail to rotate. Instead of teaching all this manually, I only need set up the Topspin Pro and let the kids have at it.</p>
<p>I want to stress that adults will also benefit from it. I have a few beginner adult students who I use the Topspin Pro with. I find that it helps adults equally well. It’s amazing to me that such a simple concept took so long to hit the market. I’m glad it has though.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Some Drawbacks of The Topspin Pro</h2>
<p>You heard me say a lot of excellent things about the TopSpin Pro so far. While I do own one and use it with my students without any issues, I want to address a few negatives that you should be aware of. I’ll list them out below.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Transportability</strong> – The Topspin Pro can be a little cumbersome to transport. It can only retract so far. This is a small drawback for me only if I take it to the tennis courts. If I’m using it at home, then it’s no issue at all.</li>
<li><strong>Usability</strong> – The Topspin Pro is great at teaching topspin but after using it for a few minutes, it can become monotonous. There’s only so many times you can brush on the ball. For this reason, I advise using it for a couple of minutes on the forehand and a couple of minutes on the backhand per use. It’s much better to have short, consistent training sessions with the TopSpin Pro frequently rather than long training sessions once in a while.</li>
<li><strong>Wear and Tear</strong> – I personally haven’t experienced any issues with the device since purchasing it. But I’ve gone through the reviews on Amazon and a few people have said either the pin falls out easily or they had problems with the mesh fabric or the bungees that hold it in place. As of the writing of this post, these claims were stated in 3 of the 67 total reviews. My students and I have personally whacked the Topspin Pro around like it’s a pinata and it’s still as good as the first day I got it. You can see my pictures and my review. The Topspin Pro in them is the exact one that I have been using with my students. In my opinion, it holds up quite well to wear and tear, so I wouldn’t worry about it.</li>
</ul>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Final Conclusion</h2>
<p>If you’re a beginner or intermediate player struggling with tennis topspin, the Topspin Pro is an excellent training tool. I can’t think of a better training device to help you hit topspin.</p>
<p>If you’re buying the Topspin Pro for a child or junior player, I feel it’d be very beneficial to their game. For convenience, you can leave it in your garage or home. It’s completely unnecessary to take to the court. Your child can practice with it at home whenever they want.</p>
<p>If you have good topspin already, then I feel the Topspin Pro is not needed. It’s really not a tool for advanced players, though it can’t hurt to be used by one. I personally like to use it just to reinforce the perfect racket angle for topspin.</p>
<p>The cost of the device is not cheap. You can take a private tennis lesson for the same cost as the TopSpin Pro. I looked at the purchase of mine as an investment. I’ll have it for years to come plus it’s going to help all my students.</p>
<p>If you’re a parent buying it for your child, I think it’s a good investment in your child’s tennis career. If you’re a tennis coach, I highly recommend you buy it to use with your students, as I do.</p>
<p>If you’re a beginner or intermediate adult, consider what you’re willing to pay to improve your strokes. For some, it’s worth it, for others not.</p>
<p>I hope this honest review of the Topspin Pro helps. <strong>If you have any questions about it, feel free to leave it in the comment section below.</strong></p>
<p>The post <a href="/topspin-pro-tennis-review/">TopSpin Pro Tennis Review</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/topspin-pro-tennis-review/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>9 Proven Ways To Generate More Topspin In Your Tennis Game</title>
		<link>/9-proven-ways-to-generate-more-topspin-in-your-tennis-game/</link>
					<comments>/9-proven-ways-to-generate-more-topspin-in-your-tennis-game/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chad Walner]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 06 Nov 2018 10:52:32 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Theory]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[backhand]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[forehand]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[topspin]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1013</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Do you want to generate more topspin on your tennis shots? Well, I’m going to discuss all the ways you can do that in this post, so make sure to read all the way through. To me, personally, I feel &#8230; <a class="kt-excerpt-readmore" href="/9-proven-ways-to-generate-more-topspin-in-your-tennis-game/" aria-label="9 Proven Ways To Generate More Topspin In Your Tennis Game">Read More</a></p>
<p>The post <a href="/9-proven-ways-to-generate-more-topspin-in-your-tennis-game/">9 Proven Ways To Generate More Topspin In Your Tennis Game</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Do you want to generate more topspin on your tennis shots? Well, I’m going to discuss all the ways you can do that in this post, so make sure to read all the way through.</p>
<p>To me, personally, I feel like players fall into one of two categories. They’re either topspin hitters or flat hitters. If you’re reading this post, you’re most likely a flat hitter who wants some topspin in your game.</p>
<p>I consider myself to be a flat hitter, and there’s nothing wrong if you are one too. But it seems like nowadays everyone wants more topspin on their forehand and backhand. Perhaps we’re all mesmerized by Rafael Nadal. We hear about the awesome RPM (3000+) he generates on his shots and want some of that too.</p>
<p><strong>So why is topspin important? Topspin makes the ball stay in the court and gives the ball more margin for error over the net. It also makes shots more difficult to return, as the ball bounces higher and accelerates off the ground. </strong></p>
<p><strong>The only drawback to topspin is that the ball moves through the air slower than flat shots. This gives the opponent more time to get to the shot. Often, I can get to topspin balls hit out of reach. But flat shots that stay low are problematic. However, flat shots are not easy to hit, which is why all professional players hit with topspin. </strong></p>
<p>So remember: Hit with topspin in tennis to improve your game. All pros use topspin shots, even though flat shots can be more powerful. Here&#8217;s how.</p>
<p>I’ve studied topspin for a long time, watched many videos of the pros hitting, and used various <a href="/improve-tennis-skills-with-these-top-10-tennis-training-devices/#topspin-pro">tennis training devices for spin</a>. After all that analysis, I’m finally ready to talk about it. As of this post, I’ve narrowed down topspin to nine key attributes:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="#grip">Grip (Eastern vs. Semi-Western vs. Western)</a></li>
<li><a href="#racket-face-angle">Racket Face Angle In Slot Position</a></li>
<li><a href="#swing-path">Swing Path of Racket (The Low To High Concept)</a></li>
<li><a href="#hitting-in-front">Hitting Out In Front Of Body (Open Stance)</a></li>
<li><a href="#wrist-pronation">Wrist Pronation</a></li>
<li><a href="#racket-speed">Racket Speed</a></li>
<li><a href="#racket-head-down">Turn Down Of Racket Head On Contact</a></li>
<li><a href="#follow-through">Follow Through</a></li>
<li><a href="#strings">Strings</a></li>
</ul>
<p>You don’t need to master every attribute on my list to hit topspin. But all of them are key contributors in one way or another to generating spin. I have my own unique theories on each one, which I’ll share in a second.</p>
<p>By the end of this post, you’ll have a good idea of how to generate more topspin in your tennis game. There’s no time to waste. So let’s begin!</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="grip"></a></p>
<h2>Grip (Eastern vs. Semi-Western vs. Western)</h2>
</div>
<p>Can a change in grip on the forehand or backhand produce more spin? <strong>Yes, absolutely.</strong> That’s why the biggest topspin hitters on the pro tour use semi-western and western grips and not the eastern grip. Grip matters because a slightly closed face at contact (like western grips produce) will impart spin to the ball. (<a href="/beginners-serve-vs-advanced-tennis-serve-what-are-the-differences/">You can learn the different grips here</a>).</p>
<p>Does a western grip guarantee you’ll hit massive topspin? No, definitely not. Why not? Because there are other factors involved with hitting topspin. Grip is one attribute that helps. But by itself, it won’t produce massive topspin. It is a foundation which while essential, is not adequate on its own.</p>
<p>For me, the eastern grip is what I prefer. However, I notice that when I hit with the semi-western grip, I can dip the racket head more, which is a key attribute in generating more topspin as well.</p>
<p>I’ll get into this more in the next section. For now, I’ll say it’s easier to drop the racket head below the hand from the semi-western grip. This creates more of a brushing effect on the ball, producing more spin.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>If you use an eastern grip, don’t worry. You can generate topspin with that grip. The good thing about the eastern grip is it’s easy to flatten out your shots, which is important at times.</p>
<blockquote><p>My conclusion on grip is that you can generate spin from either eastern, semi-western or western. However, the western grips are easier to work with when trying to generate a lot of spin.</p></blockquote>
<p>Almost all good coaches and academies start their students with the semi-western grip. Older folks will most likely hit with eastern grips. But all can generate topspin if the other concepts are utilized. Let’s go onto the next one.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="racket-face-angle"></a></p>
<h2>Racket Face Angle In Slot Position</h2>
</div>
<p>Since the advent of youtube, I’ve been able to study all the forehands of the top professional players, such as Federer, Zverev, Murray, Nadal, Djokovic, etc.</p>
<p>From what I see, almost all of them have their racket face or strings pointing down in the slot position. I believe this is an important contributor to topspin.</p>
<p>The slot position is the final point the racket stops during the takeback on a groundstroke before making its forward movement. Most players take their racket back high and drop it into the slot position. From there, they move the racket forward to contact the ball.</p>
<p>I noticed from my own play, that when I keep the racket face pointing down in the slot position, it automatically puts the racket in a great position for topspin when I swing to contact. I think it’s because it creates a lag with the racket head and angles the face down more than if the head is not faced down in the slot position.</p>
<p>Almost all the men on the pro tour hit like this, so much so that this is known as the <strong>modern ATP forehand</strong>. However, 90% of the women on the WTA tour are not using this method to hit, as it requires a take-back rather than a loop. If you’re curious to know more details on this, check out the blog post I wrote on <a href="/atp-vs-wta-anatomy-of-great-groundstrokes/">ATP forehand vs WTA forehand</a>.</p>
<p>If you want to generate more topspin, try facing the racket head down in the slot position. I must warn you that it may feel strange if you’ve never done it before. This is because you may be used to aligning the strings to the ball like is done in a pendulum swing.</p>
<p>However, with practice, you can make it feel more comfortable and make it work. The other part of this is getting the racket head to drop below the hand. Even if you don’t face the racket head down, you need to drop the racket head below the hand or it’s almost impossible to generate massive topspin.</p>
<p>As I said earlier, the semi-western and western grips are fantastic for allowing a deeper drop of the racket head. I think it has to do with the position of the hand. On the eastern grip my hand is kind of blocking the racket handle from dropping. But in the western grips, there is less blockage and the handle can angle down.</p>
<blockquote><p>In summary, either keep the racket face down in the slot position or drop the racket head below the hand. The racket head must meet the ball slightly under the hand on contact for topspin to work.</p></blockquote>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="topspin-pro"></a></p>
<h2>The Topspin Pro – The Ideal Tennis Training Tool For Spin</h2>
</div>
<p><div style="width: 343px" class="wp-caption alignright"><a href="https://www.amazon.com/TopspinPro-Tennis-Training-Topspin-Minutes/dp/B01N1F8M6I/ref=as_li_ss_il?ie=UTF8&amp;linkCode=li3&amp;tag=aim078-20&amp;linkId=c277f747de74929846fbd334aba20992&amp;language=en_US" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="//ws-na.amazon-adsystem.com/widgets/q?_encoding=UTF8&amp;ASIN=B01N1F8M6I&amp;Format=_SL800_&amp;ID=AsinImage&amp;MarketPlace=US&amp;ServiceVersion=20070822&amp;WS=1&amp;tag=aim078-20&amp;language=en_US" alt="" width="333" height="500" border="0" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">Click the picture to check the current pricing on Amazon.com.</p></div></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" style="border: none !important; margin: 0px !important;" src="https://ir-na.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=aim078-20&amp;language=en_US&amp;l=li3&amp;o=1&amp;a=B01N1F8M6I" alt="" width="1" height="1" border="0" /><br />
A perfect training device for learning to drop the racket head is the Topspin Pro. This device is fantastic for teaching players to brush on the ball. I use it often with my students. I find it works best with beginners and children.</p>
<p>What I like about the Topspin Pro is that it gives instant feedback. If the student is not brushing correctly on the ball, it won’t spin forward. I’ll demonstrate how to do it and then let them try.</p>
<p>If they still don’t get it, I have them use their hand only. Then they can try again with a racket. If they just can’t do it, I’ll move their racket slowly with my hand so they can feel what it’s like to brush from underneath the ball.</p>
<p>Once they get the concept, it becomes a lot easier to hit groundstrokes with topspin. For this reason, I like using the Topspin Pro for a few minutes before each lesson, just to refresh the muscle memory of the student.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="swing-path"></a></p>
<h2>Swing Path Of The Racket</h2>
</div>
<p>If you learned tennis from a coach, you probably heard the phrase “swing low to high” more times than you care to think about. I think all tennis players have heard it at one time or another. This attribute mainly applies to traditional groundstroke shots.</p>
<p>The truth is that swinging low to high does work for generating topspin. But it may not work in the way you are doing it. In general, we want to start our swing lower than the ball and finish higher. But we also need to extend our arm forward and not just low to high.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>For the average waist-high shot, a good topspin hitter may drop the racket 12-18 inches below the ball at the lowest part of the swing. And he may finish two feet above the ball, after contact. In all, the racket may be moving as much as three or more feet from the lowest point to the highest point.</p>
<blockquote><p>I highly suggest videoing your forehand and backhands. You may be surprised how little space exists between your lowest and highest point of the swing. If you lack topspin, you’re most likely swinging on a very level plane.</p></blockquote>
<p><strong>Your mental image in tennis is often vastly different than reality.</strong> For that reason, you really need to video your strokes. If your swing is very level, you’ll need to consciously lower your swing and finish higher.</p>
<p>One good drill is to start your swing with the racket face on or near the ground. As the ball approaches, swing up to contact. After contact, continue moving the racket upward into the follow through. At the finish point, the elbow of your hitting arm should be head height and pointing toward the net.</p>
<p>This is a great drill to exaggerate the low-to-high swing path. It will help you to feel the correct swing path for generating more topspin. Again, this for traditional type strokes.</p>
<p>You should start to see a difference in your spin using this attribute alone. It’s absolutely proven to work for both forehands and backhands.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="hitting-in-front"></a></p>
<h2>Hitting Out In Front Of The Body</h2>
</div>
<p>You may have never considered hitting in front of the body for topspin, but it’s important. I’ll explain how in a minute. But first, stand to your side with your arm straight in back, like you were going to hit a forehand. Your hand should be a little lower than waist height.</p>
<p>Now move your arm as far forward as possible, keeping your arm straight. What happens? Your arm should automatically raise up towards your shoulder. This creates a low-to-high movement in the arm, ideal for topspin, as we just discussed in the last attribute.</p>
<p>Now consider this. If we make contact too soon, which is close to the body, our arm will not have the necessary time or acceleration to impart maximum pace and spin on the ball.</p>
<blockquote><p>Think of a plane taking off on a runway. If the plane tries to take off 60% down the runway, instead of 100%, it may fail to lift. The same principle applies on your groundstrokes.</p></blockquote>
<p>For that reason, we need to hit in front of the body, where the arm is moving at maximum speed. Of course, the wrist will play a part too. I discuss the wrist later.<br />
Now, all this may be a revolutionary concept for you. You may have never thought about hitting out in front of your body for topspin. You may also be having that “a-ha” moment like I did when I first thought about this.</p>
<p>That’s the reason we hear good coaches tell us to hit in front of the body. We need to build up the arm speed and hit the ball as the arm is raising up. Hitting in front of the body translates to more power and a steeper angle of incline at impact, resulting in more topspin.</p>
<p>This concept especially applies to the forehand and one-handed backhand. It&#8217;s true however, two-handed backhand players can make contact closer to the body because it’s a different stroke dynamic. I just want to point that out for the all the two-handers out there in case they are wondering.</p>
<p>I found that hitting in front of the body is a little easier in the open or semi-open stance. However, it can be done in the neutral stance as well. Stand in front of a full-length mirror and practice the swing path without a racket and take note.</p>
<p>Watch where your arm finishes extending. Optimally, you should contact the ball about 4-6 inches before full extension. This allows you to still have some forward movement on the racket after contact.</p>
<p>Where the racket goes after contact is dependent on what height you strike the ball and how much spin you want to impart. On lower shots, you only need to come from slightly under the ball. For these low shots, you’ll raise your arm and finish near your shoulder.</p>
<p>On higher shots (shoulder level) you can swing more level and finish on the same plane or even lower. You’ll still impart topspin by coming from a little under the ball. I know that sounds a bit confusing. Again, it depends on what height you&#8217;re striking the ball and from what location on the court. The main take away here is to hit in front of the body.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="wrist-pronation"></a></p>
<h2>Wrist Pronation</h2>
</div>
<p>There are a few major techniques for producing topspin. <strong>Pronation of the wrist is my favorite</strong>. When done correctly, the racket moves like a windshield wiper on a car window. Hence the name “windshield wiper forehand”.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-1022 size-full" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/windshieldwiperforehand1.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/windshieldwiperforehand1.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/11/windshieldwiperforehand1-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/11/windshieldwiperforehand1-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>I love using this type of stroke to put massive spin on the tennis ball. It can be done on the backhand too, but to a lesser degree because of biomechanics. We just have more versatility on the forehand side.</p>
<p>Of all the techniques I tried for topspin, the windshield wiper works the best for me. I can literally swing the racket as fast as I want and keep the ball in play. This is all done with the eastern forehand grip too.</p>
<p>When I broke it down to its core component, I noticed the windshield wiper is just pronation of the forehand with the wrist/racket combination coming along for the ride.</p>
<p>It’s important to stress that the wrist needs to be completely laid back (extension) before approaching the ball. This is essential for making this shot work. If no extension is present, the spin will be severely compromised.</p>
<p>Soon after contact with the ball, the wrist will probably move to a neutral position (between extension and flexion). Don’t confuse that with pronation though. Let me explain how to do the windshield wiper forehand.</p>
<p>Swing with extension and make contact in front of your body. Once contact is made, the forearm will pronate. The hand and racket will thus make a 180-degree flip (approximately) going from right to left (for righthanded forehands).</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>As you swing the racket, the strings will move past your face (your arm will be almost fully extended in the front of you). I call this the reverse mirror because the opposite side of the hitting strings are facing you after contact (but only for a fraction of a second). The hitting side of the racket will face your opponent (again, for a split second) as it moves to the follow through.</p>
<p>If all this sounds confusing, don’t worry. Look at the pictures and the video I made. You can check them out for clear visuals. Trust me, if you lack topspin, the windshield wiper is a great way to do it. And in my opinion, the easiest.</p>
<p>Upon first trying this stroke, it will take time knowing when to pronate the forearm. Pronate too soon or too late and it won’t work. But once you get the timing, it’s a very powerful technique for generating lots of topspin.</p>
<p>The one drawback is that the ball moves through the air slower (than a flat shot) because of all the spin. But if you have good racket head speed, you can still hit speeds in excess of 70-80 mph.</p>
<p>This is plenty fast at the club level. The very fastest hitters on tour (both men and women) average between 72-80 mph on their groundstrokes. Slower, looping shots with lots of topspin deep into the court can be very effective. Don’t forget that.</p>
<p>Some popular questions about the Windshield Wiper Forehand are <a href="/what-is-the-windshield-wiper-forehand-10-questions-and-answers-all-about-it/">answered here</a>.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="racket-speed"></a></p>
<h2>Racket Speed</h2>
</div>
<p>A major reason for lack of power and topspin is slow racket head speed. I think many beginner and club level players are afraid to hit out, so they swing slower than they’re capable of swinging.</p>
<p>They think by moving the racket slower, they can control the ball better. However, sometimes the opposite is true, as a slower swing means less spin. And less topspin can mean the ball is more likely to fly out.</p>
<p>I feel like there are two parts to this equation. First, is achieving maximum racket head speed. Some people just can’t swing the racket fast enough to generate the massive amount of topspin the pros do.</p>
<p>Second, even if a player can achieve high levels of racket speed, the fundamentals of the swing need to be in place for the ball to have hopes of consistently making it into the court.</p>
<p>So there’s really two parts to this equation. A good player needs to have proper stroke mechanics and swing fast to produce great spin. When you combine both you can hit topspin shots that jump off the court with tremendous speed. Ever see Nadal’s put away forehand?</p>
<p>Let’s suppose a player has good stroke mechanics but doesn’t swing fast enough to generate the level of topspin he or she desires. What now? Well, there are small hacks the player can use to increase racket speed, but it will only be a slight improvement.</p>
<p>I believe every player has their own racket speed limit. Some people just swing faster than others. The good news is that even if you swing on the slower side, by using proper mechanics, you can still generate topspin.</p>
<p>If you look at the pro tour, particularly women’s tennis, you’ll see a variety of hitters. You have those players like Caroline Wozniacki and Agnieszka Radwanska, who are known for their consistent strokes. They swing fast enough to hit good shots, but not as fast as players like Karolina Pliskova or Dominika Cibulkova, who are massive power hitters.</p>
<p>If you swing on the slower side, work with what you have. Be the consistent player who is smart and uses placement. Work on improving your swing speed day-by-day by using resistance weights, like <a href="https://amzn.to/2RBY4Nq">the racket weight</a> along with racket speed drills.</p>
<p>If every player on the ATP tour could hit topspin like Nadal, they would. But they can’t. Don’t worry if you can’t achieve massive topspin on your strokes. A little is all you need to be effective at the club level. I tell you this from experience.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="racket-head-down"></a></p>
<h2>Turning Down Of Racket Head On Contact</h2>
</div>
<p>A few years ago, I was curious to know how Roger Federer and the other professionals of men’s tennis generated topspin on their hard forehands. I watched slow motion videos of them hitting and was really surprised at what I saw.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><div class="kad-youtube-shortcode videofit"  ><iframe loading="lazy" width="600" height="400" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/rFLab8X2AtQ?autoplay=0&controls=1&fs=1&modestbranding=0&theme=dark&rel=0&loop=0&showinfo=1" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="true"></iframe></div></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>I thought for the longest time that only swinging low to high produced topspin. I was wrong. I saw the pros hitting the ball fairly level but closing down the racket head at contact. This produced topspin without having to hit low to high.</p>
<p>It was quite a revelation. I tried it the next time I played. True to form, it worked. If you hit with a slightly closed face and turn the racket head down after contact, you can still generate topspin on a hard shot.</p>
<p>Most people who are flat hitters subconsciously turn their racket face down but don’t generate much topspin. This is because the angle of the racket must be slightly closed at contact (about 10-15 degrees). Flat hitters at the club level often have a neutral racket face at contact, which is why they miss so often.</p>
<p>I teach tennis and study the game closely. I like to watch all the different variations people have in their strokes. But one common mistake I see is failing to close the racket face after contacting the ball.</p>
<p>If you want to produce topspin on a hard shot, I think it’s essential the racket face immediately start turning down after contact. To be crystal clear, I mean the hitting side of the racket will turn to face the ground soon after contact. Once it does, simply extend out as far as possible and bring the racket straight across the body until you hit the follow through.</p>
<p>This can be done on both the forehand and backhand. It works especially well on short balls taken above the shoulder. In fact, if you don’t close down the racket face, you’ll likely miss those high, short balls.</p>
<p>The next time you take to the court, try it out for yourself. Watch the video above. Video your own strokes and watch them in slow motion if possible. Pay close attention to the angle of your racket on contact and how it moves across your body after contact.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="follow-through"></a></p>
<h2>Follow Through</h2>
</div>
<p>The follow through is important for one main reason &#8211; it maintains racket speed. If you don’t follow through on your groundstrokes, the racket will lack the speed to impart spin and pace on the ball.</p>
<p>I know it may seem unreasonable to think that follow through has anything to do with the speed and spin of the ball. After all, once contact is made with the ball, who cares what the racket does? Unfortunately, that’s the actually not how it works.</p>
<p>Tennis is a magic game and what the racket does after contact absolutely affects the behavior of the ball. For that reason, we need to have a strong follow through on every topspin shot we hit.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>Whether we finish low (by the hip), in the middle (near the ribs), or up high (over the shoulder) makes no difference. What matters is finishing the swing on the opposite side of the body. That is unless your name is Rafael Nadal; only he can get away with breaking the rules.</p>
<p>One more thing about follow through. It’s very important there’s no slowing down of the racket or hitches during the stroke. Once you begin forward movement of the stroke, don’t stop or slow the speed of the racket.</p>
<p>Keep the racket accelerating fast. Move it right through contact to the final stopping point all at the same speed. This will aid in imparting maximum spin on the ball.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="strings"></a></p>
<h2>Strings</h2>
</div>
<p>All of the aforementioned attributes have to do with physical swing mechanics in one way or another. This one is different. It involves only your racket.</p>
<p>I mention it because you may have all the other attributes in place, but you lack the necessary spin to keep the ball in play. Maybe your ball is floating a little long or you just don’t feel the racket biting into the ball.</p>
<p>Whatever the case, it may be your strings to blame. This is the reason why professional players use several rackets or more during a single match. If even a few pounds of string tension is lost on a racket, it can result in less spin and more balls hit out.</p>
<p>Not only is it important to have the correct strings for spin, your strings also need to be tight enough to generate it. I personally use a 16L and 17-gauge polyester hybrid in my racket strung around 63-64 pounds of tension. The string has a hexagonal shape to it which grips the ball better than the common round shaped string.</p>
<p>If you want to read more about which tennis strings you should be using you can check out my detailed post <a href="/the-best-5-rackets-for-serve-and-volley-in-2018/">here</a>.</p>
<p>Here are my recommendations for maximizing spin with strings:</p>
<ul>
<li>Choose a 17-gauge string</li>
<li>Use hexagonal shaped string, rather than round string</li>
<li>Polyester strings will give you more spin and feel than synthetic gut</li>
<li>String your racket on the tighter side so you can swing faster</li>
</ul>
<p>If you heed my suggestions and go with a good polyester string, be aware it will cost a bit more and the strings won’t last as long. However, you may be able to put more spin on the ball than ever before.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>In Conclusion</h2>
<p>My final recommendation is to try these things out. Experiment with changing the grip, how you orient the racket in the slot position, the swing path, the windshield wiper forehand, etc.</p>
<p>Use what works and throw away the rest. For me, I like using the windshield wiper stroke on both the forehand and backhand. I find it easy to generate spin with it and it’s comfortable.</p>
<p>When I want to hit harder, I just close down the racket face. This makes tennis easy. I have two basic variations for my shots: the windshield wiper for maximum topspin and a closed shot for more pace.</p>
<p>I use both during matches. I even have a hybrid where I move my racket halfway between each technique (windshield wiper and closed shot). This gives me topspin and pace.</p>
<p>Let me know if you have any questions about this post. I’m happy to answer them for you. If not, I’ll see you in the next one.</p>
<p>The post <a href="/9-proven-ways-to-generate-more-topspin-in-your-tennis-game/">9 Proven Ways To Generate More Topspin In Your Tennis Game</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/9-proven-ways-to-generate-more-topspin-in-your-tennis-game/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>5</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>ATP vs WTA: Anatomy Of Great Groundstrokes</title>
		<link>/atp-vs-wta-anatomy-of-great-groundstrokes/</link>
					<comments>/atp-vs-wta-anatomy-of-great-groundstrokes/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chad Walner]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 15 Oct 2018 07:35:41 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Theory]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[backhand]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[forehand]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=809</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Many factors go into hitting great groundstrokes, like timing, racket speed and rotation of the body. Most people are aware of those and I’ve written about them before. However, I want to explore a few misunderstood concepts when it comes &#8230; <a class="kt-excerpt-readmore" href="/atp-vs-wta-anatomy-of-great-groundstrokes/" aria-label="ATP vs WTA: Anatomy Of Great Groundstrokes">Read More</a></p>
<p>The post <a href="/atp-vs-wta-anatomy-of-great-groundstrokes/">ATP vs WTA: Anatomy Of Great Groundstrokes</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Many factors go into hitting great groundstrokes, like timing, racket speed and rotation of the body. Most people are aware of those and <a href="/how-to-effortlessly-generate-more-power-on-your-groundstrokes/">I’ve written about them before</a>. However, I want to explore a few misunderstood concepts when it comes to the differences between the ATP and WTA swing paths in professional tennis and how you can learn from them. I believe there’s a certain swing path we must take to maximize power. In this post, I’ll elaborate on the differences in the swings and which one I think is best suited for the club player.</p>
<p>The nuances of swing paths of the ATP and WTA players are quite noticeable to most tennis coaches. However, these differences are quite subtle to the casual fan of tennis. My hope in this blog post is not only to enlighten you of this very interesting information but to give you a better idea of stroke anatomy so you can improve your own strokes.</p>
<p>All players, from beginner to advanced, can benefit from this information. If you’re lacking power in your groundstrokes, this article could be the solution. It took me years of studying stroke anatomy and watching the men and women on tour hit in slow motion to formulate my ideas. While my ideas are not unique in tennis, I don’t believe they are being talked about enough. Hence, I decided to write about them here. So let’s begin!</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>The Outside-Inside-Outside Concept</h2>
<blockquote><p>The swing path is the important aspect of all great tennis strokes.</p></blockquote>
<p>First, let me explain what I mean by <strong>outside-inside-outside</strong>. It basically means the player starts their swing (whether it be forehand or backhand) with the racket away from their body. The racket, or hitting hand, will then move close to the body. Finally, it will move back away to hit the ball. This is all done in one smooth, continuous motion and allows for maximum power. This is the basic concept of “outside-inside-outside”, but I’ll go into much greater detail about it right now so you really understand it.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><div id="attachment_872" style="width: 810px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-872" class="wp-image-872 size-full" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/wtavsatp.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/wtavsatp.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/wtavsatp-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/wtavsatp-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /><p id="caption-attachment-872" class="wp-caption-text">Men take back and women loop.</p></div></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Let’s assume a right-handed player is hitting a forehand groundstroke. When she sets up, her body will be facing to the right. All the space to the right of her body is what I call the “outside”. And all the space behind her and to the left is what I label the “inside”. The best swing path for maximizing power is to start with the racket about head height on the outside. This is traditionally where all great players start their swing. They do this by initiating a unit turn with the racket up high.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>As the player is naturally turning to her right for a forehand, the racket will be to her right side, which is the outside. This is extremely important. That’s why you see almost no deviations in professional tennis with this part of the forehand.</p>
<p>Every great player you watch, whether it be Serena Williams, Roger Federer or Pete Sampras, takes the racket up and to the right on almost every forehand. Of course, lefties do the opposite. It’s also vital the racket be some distance from the body. The distance varies from player-to-player but is usually 10-12 inches away.</p>
<p>
<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0126.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="450" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0126.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="ATP style forehand." srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0126.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0126-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0126-768x432.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0126-560x315.jpg 560w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></a>
<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0128.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="450" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0128.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="WTA style forehand." srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0128.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0128-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0128-768x432.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0128-560x315.jpg 560w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></a>
</p>
<p>Once the player achieves this position, the racket arm and hand will begin to drop and move to the “inside”. This means the racket hand will be much closer to the body when this part of the swing is completed. This is what I mean by “inside”. This is the second location of the swing path of the racket.</p>
<p>If you look at the forehand stroke of a WTA player head-on, you would notice their hitting hand moves directly behind them. Some players, like Madison Keyes, actually bring their hitting hand to the left side of the body, which is the far inside.</p>
<p>The further you bring the hitting hand to the inside, the more power you can generate. This is why Keyes is one of the hardest hitting players on the women’s tour. Incidentally, she’s also one of the hardest hitting players (men included) period! If you look at her average groundstroke speed on the WTA tour, she’s often # 1, averaging speeds in excess of 70 mph.</p>
<p>However, this type of aggressive inside action on the hand has a big drawback – and that’s <strong>timing</strong>. It’s more difficult to time a long, looping groundstroke than a shorter, more compact one. Perhaps this is the reason Keyes has underachieved in her career so far (as of October 2018).</p>
<p>Most women on the WTA tour bring the racket to the inside of their body. This is because they want to generate power using biomechanics rather than muscle. This type of swing path is called a “<strong>pendulum</strong>”, as it relies on momentum and gravity rather than muscle and might.</p>
<p>Interestingly, Juan Martin del Potro, one of the more successful players on the ATP, uses the pendulum motion to great effect on his forehand. He’s the only player I see in the top 20, or even top 50, using the pendulum forehand swing path. It must be working because it won him the 2009 U.S. Open and as of October 2018 he’s top 5 in the world. He’s also known for hitting one of the most powerful forehands on the tour.</p>
<p>Almost every other ATP tour player, however, has a slightly different swing path at this point of the stroke. As I said, almost all players (men and women) start with the stroke up and to the outside. But the ATP players do not bring the hitting hand to the inside. Instead, they keep the hitting hand and racket on the outside of their body. Still, it does move closer to the body.</p>
<p>This type of swing path results in less power but more control and a quicker racket swing. The men thus rely more on muscle and less on physics to hit the ball than the women. You may be wondering why the men do this? The reason the men do not bring the racket to the inside is because they don’t have the time. The ball is simply coming too fast to hit with a long swing path. That extra half a second it takes makes a big difference to time the ball.</p>
<p>When two strong guys are belting the ball at each other, especially on hard court or grass, a more compact swing is needed. Additionally, most men have more strength than women and can generate sufficient power with their bodies to compensate for their shorter swing paths. A former top 200 Russian player (now a coach) named Darya, once told me that, “men take back and women loop”. That’s a good way to think about it.</p>
<p>When I talk about these concepts with people, sometimes they’ll tell me the men do bring their hitting hand directly behind their body. I know it looks like that in slow motion, but that’s actually not the case. What’s happening is that the men are using wrist lag to generate extra power. The racket thus acts like a slingshot and the head of the racket moves to the inside of the player’s body (if only for a fraction of a second). However, the hitting hand remains on the outside.</p>
<blockquote><p>So what does all this mean for you? Well, I believe if you lack power at the club level, whether you’re male or female, you should experiment with bringing the racket a little further to the inside. At the club level, and especially on clay, you can get away with longer swing paths. I would advise you to start by bringing the hitting hand only slightly more to the inside at first. A big change in swing path may cause your timing to be way off.</p></blockquote>
<p>This is all great stuff. But we still have the third part of the stroke mechanic to discuss. This is when the hitting hand and racket move back to the outside. Again, on the WTA tour, this move back to the outside will be much more pronounced than the guys on the ATP.</p>
<p>When the women move from inside-to-outside, they are completing a circular movement that relies on momentum, which is why it’s called a pendulum swing. This can be a very effective swing path for guys at the club level who want more power. If you’re a guy reading this, don’t think of yourself as hitting like a woman. A lot of successful professional male clay court players have used this type of swing, such as Gustavo Kuerten, who won the French Open three times.</p>
<p>Since modern day ATP players keep their hitting hand outside their body (but not by much), they have a less pronounced movement of the hand. The wrist lag that causes the racket to flare behind them gives the illusion otherwise. But it’s just an illusion. The move of the hand back to the outside allows the racket to continue its swing path without slowing down.</p>
<p><div class="hrule clearfix" style="background:#81d742; height:1px"></div></p>
<p>Let’s summarize it all so it makes sense.</p>
<ol>
<li>The racket sets up on the far outside,</li>
<li>moves to the inside,</li>
<li>and then comes back outside to make impact with the ball.</li>
</ol>
<p>Women bring the racket inside their body and men keep it on the outside but close their body. I Hope that’s clear to everyone.</p>
<p><div class="hrule clearfix" style="background:#81d742; height:1px"></div></p>
<p>What does this mean for you? Again, once you recognize that all swing paths have this outside-inside-outside feature, you can begin to look at your own swing. This is valid for both forehands and backhands. Actually, in my opinion, it’s more important on the backhand side and a little more difficult to do.</p>
<p>Before we get to the backhand, I have a good piece of advice to help you with your forehand. Video your forehand swing from directly in front and behind. Look at how far your hitting hand moves to the inside (or not) and then experiment with changing it. If you use a pendulum swing this tip definitely applies to you.</p>
<p>If you have an ATP style forehand, you may want to bring your hand only very slightly closer to the body on the “inside” part of the swing. The wrist lag should give you all the power you need. However, moving the hand slightly closer to the body may give you that extra 5-10% of power you’re needing.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>When I teach new kids, I first access their natural level of tennis ability. I’ll then decide on which stroke to teach them – pendulum or ATP. Currently, I’m teaching the pendulum to most of them &#8212; all of the girls and most of the boys. I find that a good time to teach the pendulum swing to boys is when their aptitude is lower than average. This is especially true for boys that have slow racket speeds. The pendulum swing just makes more sense, as those type of players need more power.</p>
<p>Regardless of which stroke I teach to kids and adults, I explain the outside-inside-outside swing path to them. You can even tell them it’s like making a circle with your racket. A good way to illustrate this is to show a video or image from directly above the player. As it’s not so easy to find, we created this graphic to show the difference.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Backhand – One and Two-Handed Swing Path</h2>
<p>The two-handed backhand swing path is similar to the forehand in that it begins on the outside, moves to the inside and then returns to the outside to make contact with the ball. The WTA players have a more pronounced swing path – meaning they bring their rackets further to the inside on the two-handed backhand than the guys on the ATP. The ATP players generally stay on the outside, with perhaps a few players moving slightly inside.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><div id="attachment_873" style="width: 810px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-873" class="wp-image-873 size-full" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/wtavsatpbackhand.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/wtavsatpbackhand.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/wtavsatpbackhand-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/wtavsatpbackhand-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /><p id="caption-attachment-873" class="wp-caption-text">Again, men take back and women loop.</p></div></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>For beginners and club level players, I highly recommend bringing the racket to the inside, like the WTA women, as it supplies the most power. The racket actually moves so far inside for some WTA players that the dominant arm will actually be touching the torso of the body. If you view their backhands in slow motion on youtube, you’ll see this very clearly. This move further inside elongates the swing path and provides more power than a simple take back as the ATP men do.</p>
<p>I also want to make something clear about the one-handed backhand. ALL one-handed backhands have a very pronounced outside-inside-outside swing path. I don’t care if it’s Roger Federer, Stan Wawrinka or Dominic Thiem or Carla Suarez Navarro hitting. All of them bring the racket far inside their body. One-handed backhand players must do this because they are using one arm, which supplies less power than two arms.</p>
<p>All of the concepts I mentioned for the forehand hold true on the backhand side. For that reason, I won’t go into as much detail on it. But I still want to talk about the backhand, as it is a different stroke from the forehand and on the opposite side of the body.</p>
<p>
<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0139.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1191" height="668" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0139.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="Ready to meet the ball." srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0139.jpg 1191w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0139-300x168.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0139-768x431.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0139-1024x574.jpg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0139-732x410.jpg 732w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0139-366x205.jpg 366w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0139-538x302.jpg 538w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0139-269x151.jpg 269w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0139-1120x628.jpg 1120w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0139-560x314.jpg 560w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1191px) 100vw, 1191px" /></a>
<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0140.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="845" height="475" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0140.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="Begin your takeback early." srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0140.jpg 845w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0140-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0140-768x432.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0140-732x412.jpg 732w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0140-366x206.jpg 366w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0140-538x302.jpg 538w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0140-269x151.jpg 269w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0140-560x315.jpg 560w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 845px) 100vw, 845px" /></a>
<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0141.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="785" height="442" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0141.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="Generate power." srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0141.jpg 785w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0141-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0141-768x432.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0141-732x412.jpg 732w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0141-366x206.jpg 366w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0141-538x302.jpg 538w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0141-269x151.jpg 269w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0141-560x315.jpg 560w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 785px) 100vw, 785px" /></a>
<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0142.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="450" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0142.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="Contact the ball." srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0142.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0142-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0142-768x432.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0142-732x412.jpg 732w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0142-366x206.jpg 366w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0142-538x302.jpg 538w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0142-269x151.jpg 269w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0142-560x315.jpg 560w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></a>
</p>
<p>Let’s suppose a right-handed player is hitting a two-handed backhand. Both the WTA and ATP players will begin the stroke by making a unit turn and bringing the racket to the outside. For the backhand, the “outside” is the left side of the body and the “inside” is the right side of the body (the opposite of the forehand). Some players bring the racket up high (around head height) and others bring the racket back a bit lower. This is the first part of the swing.</p>
<p>In the next part of the swing, the WTA players will bring their hitting hand far to the inside. As I said before, they bring their hand and racket so far to the inside that their dominant arms (right) are touching their bodies. In contrast, the men on the ATP keep the racket on the outside of their bodies. Their arms therefore never contact their body on this part of the stroke. This is the major difference between the WTA and ATP two-handed backhands.</p>
<p>On the final part of the stroke to contact, the women move the racket from the far inside back to the outside. The men basically stay on the outside. Although like the forehand, there is a small movement closer to the body on the second part of the stroke. The racket then moves slightly back outside at this final stage to contact.</p>
<p>Like the forehand side, the women are using a longer, pendulum-like motion with gravity and momentum to generate power. The men are relying more on muscle. You may be wondering how the men can hit so hard with short backswings? Similar to the forehand, they lead with the butt cap by using a wrist drop that causes the racket head to drop and retract. It’s not as pronounced as the forehand, but it does offer additional power. Most of the women do something similar on their backhands, but it’s also not as pronounced. This allows both the men and women to hit up on the ball, allowing for topspin.</p>
<p>Now that you know the difference between the WTA and ATP two-handed backhands, what does it mean for you? To reiterate, if you’re a beginner or club player of any sex, I highly recommend the WTA style backhand. It offers more power and is easier to learn. The ATP two-handed backhand is tough because the timing and wrist drop need to be synchronized perfectly to generate substantial power.</p>
<p>I personally believe the women have the better backhands (overall) in professional tennis. Their technique looks better than most of the men. For many of the women, their backhands are their stronger wing, while for men, it’s just the opposite. The men prefer the shorter backswings of the ATP style backhand because it saves time. That’s really the only benefit. Some of my personal favorite two-handed backhands on the WTA tour are Monica Puig, Victoria Azarenka, and Caroline Wozniacki.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>The One-Handed Backhand</h2>
<p>
<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0131.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="450" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0131.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="Start from the ready position." srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0131.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0131-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0131-768x432.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0131-560x315.jpg 560w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0131-732x412.jpg 732w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0131-366x206.jpg 366w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></a>
<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0132.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="450" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0132.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="Begin the takeback with plenty of time." srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0132.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0132-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0132-768x432.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0132-560x315.jpg 560w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0132-732x412.jpg 732w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0132-366x206.jpg 366w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></a>
<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0133.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="450" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0133.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="Generate power." srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0133.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0133-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0133-768x432.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0133-560x315.jpg 560w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0133-732x412.jpg 732w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0133-366x206.jpg 366w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></a>
<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0134.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="450" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0134.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="Swing low to high." srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0134.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0134-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0134-768x432.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0134-560x315.jpg 560w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0134-732x412.jpg 732w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0134-366x206.jpg 366w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></a>
<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0135.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="450" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0135.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="Contact the ball." srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0135.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0135-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0135-768x432.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0135-560x315.jpg 560w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0135-732x412.jpg 732w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0135-366x206.jpg 366w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></a>
<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0136.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="450" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0136.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="Follow through." srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0136.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0136-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0136-768x432.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0136-560x315.jpg 560w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0136-732x412.jpg 732w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0136-366x206.jpg 366w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></a>
</p>
<p>Unlike the two-handed backhand, the one-hander is universal throughout both sexes. The player using the one-handed backhand will bring the racket so far inside, the dominant arm will almost be touching the torso. The only time this deviates is on returns and very high paced shots. The one-hander will forsake the strong inside move to contact with the ball in time. In this case, due to the velocity of the incoming ball, the inside part of the stroke (which supplies the power) is not needed. A short, compact stroke is all that’s necessary on fast shots.</p>
<p>The one-handed backhand is becoming a stroke not so much taught or seen in modern-day tennis. This is because it’s more difficult to learn, more difficult to hit high shots, and does not provide as much stability as the two-hander. For these reasons, we are seeing the two-handed backhand outnumber the one-hander on the order of 10-1 on the tour these days for both men and women. I never teach kids the one-hander, instead showing them the two right from the start. Still, if someone favors the one-hander, it’s still a valid shot and can be quite effective. Some of the best backhands on the WTA and ATP are one-handers.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Summary</h2>
<p>Now that you know the details of the forehand and backhand anatomy, use it to improve your own strokes. If you’re a coach or want to teach tennis to your child, you now have a great understanding of what provides power on groundstrokes. The other components, just to refresh your memory, are body rotation and racket head speed. The combination of these three aspects together into one fluid stroke, make for powerful forehands and backhands.</p>
<p>If you’ve read this far, congratulations. I hope you found this information interesting and helpful for your game. Remember, video your strokes, analyze your swing path and determine one that is suitable for your body type and strength. There is no one-size fits all in tennis. Some women use the ATP strokes and some men swing more like the WTA women. Use whatever works. I wish you all the best. If you have any questions for me, please drop a comment below.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>The post <a href="/atp-vs-wta-anatomy-of-great-groundstrokes/">ATP vs WTA: Anatomy Of Great Groundstrokes</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/atp-vs-wta-anatomy-of-great-groundstrokes/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>How To Effortlessly Generate More Power On Your Groundstrokes</title>
		<link>/how-to-effortlessly-generate-more-power-on-your-groundstrokes/</link>
					<comments>/how-to-effortlessly-generate-more-power-on-your-groundstrokes/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chad Walner]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 11 Oct 2018 16:02:33 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Training]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[backhand]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[forehand]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=683</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Let’s be real. Every serious tennis player aspires to hit huge forehands and powerful backhands. We see the pros doing it on TV and we want it for ourselves. Many club players I know have tried all kinds of tricks &#8230; <a class="kt-excerpt-readmore" href="/how-to-effortlessly-generate-more-power-on-your-groundstrokes/" aria-label="How To Effortlessly Generate More Power On Your Groundstrokes">Read More</a></p>
<p>The post <a href="/how-to-effortlessly-generate-more-power-on-your-groundstrokes/">How To Effortlessly Generate More Power On Your Groundstrokes</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Let’s be real.</p>
<p>Every serious tennis player aspires to hit huge forehands and powerful backhands. We see the pros doing it on TV and we want it for ourselves.</p>
<p>Many club players I know have tried all kinds of tricks and gimmicks to improve power, but with little or no results.</p>
<p>Well, I’ve got a permanent solution you can take to the bank.</p>
<p><strong>If you haven’t given much thought to rotation of the body while hitting, then this article is going to be a serious wake-up call.</strong></p>
<p><strong>Body rotation on both the forehand and backhand sides are what really generate effortless power in tennis. In this post, I am going to talk about three specific rotations you can use on each side to measurably increase your groundstroke speed. </strong></p>
<p>In my opinion, there are two major contributing factors to groundstroke velocity: racket head speed and body rotation. Achieving high levels of racket head speed like Rafael Nadal or Jack Sock is a skill most club players will never approach. It requires great technique, fast-twitch muscles and athleticism. If you don’t have those traits, your basically out of luck. Now that sounds a bit discouraging for your average club tennis player. But don’t despair. I have a solution that will work for everyone!</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-702 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/rotation.jpg" alt="rotation" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/rotation.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/rotation-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/rotation-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<h2>The Solution For Power Is Rotation</h2>
<p>What’s the solution? It’s <strong>body rotation</strong> and anyone can do it no matter age, athletic ability or skill level. If you can learn to rotate your body and sequence it with hitting the ball at the correct time, you can boost your pace by as much as 20-30%! That’s the difference between hitting a full out winner or just another shot your opponent gets back.</p>
<p>For a long time, I thought that keeping both feet on the floor was very important for hitting consistent groundstrokes. After all, we derive most of our power from the ground. This fact cannot be disputed; we need the ground to push off from to achieve power. As a result, I thought both feet on the ground would provide more power when hitting.</p>
<p>But when I carefully studied the professional players hitting their groundstrokes, I saw different.</p>
<blockquote><p>I discovered it’s actually more advantageous to hit on one leg in most situations.</p></blockquote>
<p>Hitting on one leg allows for better body rotation. The foot that remains on the floor acts as a pivot, swiveling around so the body can rotate. If that’s the case, the body acts like a top being spun. I noticed a big difference in my power when using one-foot rotations. I started teaching them to my students and the difference in power was night and day.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>The best players in the world all use various rotations to maximize their power. When Novak Djokovic hits his two-handed backhand (perhaps the best in the world), he swivels on his front leg, allowing his full body weight to be distributed into the ball. You would rarely see a club player hit like that.</p>
<p>I think a lot of people who watch professional tennis only focus on the ball. They should focus on the players’ footwork and rotations instead. This is where the true power comes from. The racket head speed is just the cherry on the cake. If you swing with medium-paced racket speed but use a heavy racket and rotate your body effectively, you can still hit heavy groundstrokes.</p>
<p>We’re going to get into the details of rotation now on both the forehand and backhand wings. While there are many different rotations that can be used, I want to talk about<strong> two on the forehand side and one on the backhand side.</strong> I believe anyone can do this (from kid to senior) and it can be learned quite quickly. If you’ve been lacking power in your groundstrokes, the rest of this post is a must-read for you. <strong>Your tennis game will never be the same after using this information! </strong></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Forehand Stances For Proper Rotation</h2>
<p>
<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0158.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="450" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0158.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="Open Stance." srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0158.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0158-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0158-768x432.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0158-560x315.jpg 560w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></a>
<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0159.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="450" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0159.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="Semi-Open Stance." srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0159.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0159-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0159-768x432.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0159-560x315.jpg 560w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></a>
<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0160.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="450" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0160.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="Neutral Stance." srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0160.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0160-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0160-768x432.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0160-560x315.jpg 560w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></a>
<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0161.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="450" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0161.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0161.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0161-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0161-768x432.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0161-560x315.jpg 560w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></a>
</p>
<p>A lack of rotation on the forehand side is common among club players. Even when I do see rotation, it’s often not done the correct way. This is usually because of one of three mistakes:</p>
<ol>
<li>The player does not set up in the correct stance to allow proper rotation.</li>
<li>The timing of the rotation is too early or too late to allow for maximum power.</li>
<li>The player does not raise the non-pivoted foot off the floor enough to allow the body to fully rotate.</li>
</ol>
<p>While these errors are quite common at the club level, we’re going to correct them by learning the ideal technique. You can correct error number one by becoming familiar with the chart below, showing the four basic stances:</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="wp-image-707 size-full aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/four-stances2.jpg" alt="The four common stances." width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/four-stances2.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/four-stances2-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/four-stances2-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Semi-Open Stance Forehands</h2>
<p>Let’s talk about the first type of rotation, which is the basic forehand that you have time to set up for.</p>
<p><strong>In this type of forehand, we’re going to use a semi-open forehand stance.</strong> To achieve the semi-open forehand stance, face the net and place both feet slightly wider than shoulder width. For right-handed players (lefties do the opposite of all instructions in this blog post), move your left foot forward so it’s several inches in front of your right foot.</p>
<p>This is the basic position of the feet. Next, we’re going to make sure our toes are pointed in the right direction. The right foot should be at a 45-degree angle to the baseline. The left foot will be pointed slightly more to the net at around a 60-degree or more angle off the baseline.</p>
<p>Once we achieve the semi-open forehand stance, <strong>we should be in our full power positio</strong>n. The power position is the last position we take with our body and racket before the forward movement into the ball.</p>
<p>This blog post is all about the footwork and rotation of the groundstrokes, so I won’t get into the details of forehand mechanics. If you want to know how to hit a proper forehand, please see my <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OzLIBLQHg4U" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">youtube video series on how to hit an ATP style forehand</a>.</p>
<p>At this point, you’ll be in the semi-open stance and your power position. As you poise to strike the ball, the majority of your weight should be on your right foot (again, lefties do the opposite of all instructions in this post). We’re going to transfer our weight to the front (left) foot soon. Now here’s the part that takes coordination and timing.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="wp-image-705 size-full aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/semi-open-forehand.jpg" alt="Semi-open stance with rotation for a forehand shot." width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/semi-open-forehand.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/semi-open-forehand-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/semi-open-forehand-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p><strong>Right before you strike the ball, you’ll raise your right foot off the ground.</strong> This will take your weight off the right foot and distribute it into the ball. This is where the true power comes from – your entire body. The moment you make impact, and for perhaps a short time after (a quarter to half a second), you may even be off your left foot too. This is perfectly fine. If you watch Djokovic rotate out of the semi-open stance in slow motion, you’ll notice he does the same.</p>
<p>If you’re left foot remains on the ground during the shot, don’t worry. That’s perfectly acceptable. You just want the majority of your weight going from the right foot to left foot. The key takeaway is that your right foot needs to leave the ground with your left foot acting as the pivot.</p>
<p>If your left foot leaves the ground (like Djokovic), when it touches down it will be facing about 90 degrees around. For example, say it was facing 60 degrees to the right when setting up to hit the ball. After the stroke is completed, it will be facing about 150 degrees to the left. The same can be said for the right foot. At the completion of the stroke, almost all your weight will be on the left foot. Most players find their right foot returns to the ground only on the front toe (with the foot almost perpendicular to the ground).</p>
<p>How about the shoulders? When in the power position, the shoulders will be more corked than the feet. A great shoulder rotation is 145 degrees away from the net. Slightly less is acceptable, but not less than 100 degrees. At the completion of the stroke, the shoulders should be approximately 80 degrees to the net in the opposite direction!</p>
<p>If we can rotate our shoulders that far, they would move an incredible 225 degrees during the stroke. That’s a lot of rotation into the ball. Club players will likely achieve less rotation, but if you can manage near 200 degrees, that would still be very effective. If you suffer from power issues on your groundstrokes, your shoulders are probably rotating a lot less than that amount.</p>
<p>I know this is a lot of information to take in. Two things though. One is that <strong>rotation into the ball is quite natural if you play tennis</strong>. We just need to do it correctly. Second is <strong>seeing pictures and video of the correct way to rotate</strong> in the semi-open forehand stance will give you a much clearer understanding of what needs to be done.</p>
<p>I urge you to practice this over and over, as it requires a lot of time to get right. While this can be thought of as a pivot shot off the left foot, it can also be seen as a transfer of weight, jumping from the right foot onto the left foot. Remember, the key objective is to transfer your weight into the ball to hit with more power. Whether you jump or pivot does not matter so much. The rotation is what’s important.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Forehand Rotation Out Wide</h2>
<p>This is one of my favorite rotations to do. It happens when your opponent hits a wide forehand that you hit on a slow-to-medium speed run. Here’s how it usually happens. You’re around the mid-line when someone hits a shot near the sideline or a little inside it. It’s on your forehand side, so you run to your right (lefties do the opposite) and hit the forehand with almost no power. Why?</p>
<p>The most probable answer is that you didn’t prepare early and didn’t transfer your weight into the ball. I see this happen at the club level all the time. I would say most club players don’t know much about footwork and body position. This is why their technique is often so poor.</p>
<p>The information I’m going to share here will enable you to hit a forehand on the run with a lot of power. You’ll know exactly what steps to take after reading this post. Best of all, you’ll actually be able to turn defense into offense with this one rotation. So don’t overlook it.</p>
<p>Alright, first thing’s first. Say you’re at the mid-line, by the baseline. As soon as you see the ball hit wide to your forehand, you should pivot onto your outside foot (for righties, it’s the right foot). As the pivot is being made, lift your racket up and to the right side of your body, slightly away from your body. This helps prepare you to hit the forehand when you get to the ball.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>Now take a crossover step and run to the ball. As you set up for the ball, keep in mind your right foot will be the pivot foot. Wherever you plant your right foot, that’s where you’ll hit from. As you plant your right foot, place most or all your weight on it. As you set up to hit the forehand, almost all your weight will now be on the right foot.</p>
<p>While taking your swing, you’ll be entirely on one foot (the right foot). Allow that right foot to act as a pivot by placing most of your weight on the ball of the foot. If you plant your foot with too much weight on the heel, it won’t pivot and turn.</p>
<p>As you make contact with the ball, really allow your body to turn with the right foot, which is serving as the pivot. The right foot should be turning with your body so that the toe will be facing to the left when the shot is complete – as should your body. Once you complete the stroke, quickly get to the ready position and then cross-step back to the middle.</p>
<p>I know many teaching pros don’t teach this particular rotation, but it’s very effective. For this rotation, unlike the first one we learned out of the semi-open stance, your right foot will remain on the floor the whole time. You should not be jumping on this rotation for several reasons. One is that you’ll likely be off balance, affecting your timing on the shot. The second is that you’ll probably be taken too far off court to effectively recover. The third is that it takes too much energy to jump.</p>
<p>This rotation relies heavily on the right foot to act as a pivot. You can even use it on forehands where you need to back straight up or diagonally (out wide and back). Practice this rotation by making slow shadow movements over and over until you feel the footwork is grooved into memory. Then have someone feed you slow-to-medium paced shots out wide so you can practice it.</p>
<p>I personally use this rotation quite often in my play. I find it makes hitting passing shots a lot easier. It also takes my opponents by surprise often, as they are not expecting how much power I can generate off the run. I taught this rotation to a few of my best child students (both 10-years-old) and they experienced great results with it too. Try it out and see for yourself.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>The Djokovic Two-Handed Backhand Rotation</h2>
<p>Most tennis coaches and analysts would agree that Novak Djokovic has the best two-handed backhand in tennis. Yes, his form and racket speed are superb. But the true key to his mastery of the backhand is how beautifully he rotates his body into the ball with precision timing. I truly believe if we want to play like the pros, we must try and hit like them.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="wp-image-737 size-full alignright" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/djokavic2.jpg" alt="Two-handed backhand stroke." width="400" height="542" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/djokavic2.jpg 400w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/djokavic2-221x300.jpg 221w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" /></p>
<p>The backhand rotation I’m going to talk about here is valid for two-handers only. A one-hander does not have to rotate nearly as much. This rotation is good for any backhand that you require more power on. It could be on a shot near you or a bit further away. In a way, it’s similar to the forehand rotation out wide. This backhand rotation will require you to hit out of a closed or neutral stance &#8211; slightly closed is preferred.</p>
<p>Here’s how it works. When the ball is hit to your backhand, move to it. As you begin to set up, make a unit turn with most of the weight on your back foot (your left foot). Your right foot will be off the ground and stepping forward. As your right foot (front foot) lands on the court, your left foot will come off. At this point, your front foot (right) will act as the pivot, so make sure you’re mostly on the ball of the foot. It’s very important you get these steps correct, because it initiates the weight transfer forward.</p>
<p>All of this is easier said than done. It may take some time to get right, but it’s well worth the effort with the amount of power you can generate. For most players taught from an early age, this footwork is completely natural. If you are learning it as an adult after playing for many years, it will be a challenge. Keep at it though!</p>
<p>Now back to the stroke. As you swing forward, you’ll be on your front foot. Allow it to swivel along with your body. Your body should finish with your chest facing the right net post. As you finish the stroke, your left (rear) leg will come around to your left side and you may finish close to feet parallel (like in the ready position).</p>
<p>Every stroke in tennis is slightly different, so there’s no one hard rule on where your body and foot position should finish all the time. Again, the key point for this rotation is to allow the body to provide the power and not the racket or arms. You really need to allow the foot to act as a pivot for this to happen, so hit on the ball of the foot only.</p>
<p>One other important point. I see some players hitting their two-handed backhands by coordinating their rackets and bodies to move at the same speed. That’s incorrect. You always want to move the racket faster. The body comes through last as a result of the momentum created in hitting the stroke. I just wanted to mention this, as it’s a common problem with two-handed backhand players at the club level.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Wrapping It Up</h2>
<p>While there are many rotations you can use in tennis, I find these three to be the most common and most useful. Read this post again, look at the pictures and watch the videos for best learning. Practice the footwork alone first and then do it in a controlled environment with someone feeding you. A ball machine like the Lobster Elite Liberty works great too.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>The next step would be to try out the rotations in practice and then finally in a match. Imagine how great the feeling will be when you use one of these rotations to hit a clean winner with almost effortless power? You’ll certainly think it was well worth the work and effort at that point. As a club player who learned tennis on my own, I can tell you these rotations absolutely took my game to the next level. Try them. Practice them. And use them to defeat your foes!</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>The post <a href="/how-to-effortlessly-generate-more-power-on-your-groundstrokes/">How To Effortlessly Generate More Power On Your Groundstrokes</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/how-to-effortlessly-generate-more-power-on-your-groundstrokes/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>3</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
