<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>footwork Archives - Serve and Volley Tennis</title>
	<atom:link href="/tag/footwork/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/tag/footwork/</link>
	<description>Your secret weapon on the court.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 15 Aug 2019 09:16:28 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	

<image>
	<url>/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/cropped-ted_svt_favicon-32x32.png</url>
	<title>footwork Archives - Serve and Volley Tennis</title>
	<link>/tag/footwork/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>What Are The Best Tennis Footwork Tips?</title>
		<link>/what-are-the-best-tennis-footwork-tips/</link>
					<comments>/what-are-the-best-tennis-footwork-tips/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chad Walner]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 15 Feb 2019 12:53:07 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Theory]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[footwork]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1989</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Roger Federer was once interviewed by Charlie Rose after winning the 2004 U.S. Open. In the video, he was asked why his game looked so graceful. Without hesitation, Roger cited his footwork as the single most important factor in his &#8230; <a class="kt-excerpt-readmore" href="/what-are-the-best-tennis-footwork-tips/" aria-label="What Are The Best Tennis Footwork Tips?">Read More</a></p>
<p>The post <a href="/what-are-the-best-tennis-footwork-tips/">What Are The Best Tennis Footwork Tips?</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Roger Federer was once interviewed by Charlie Rose after winning the 2004 U.S. Open. In the video, he was asked why his game looked so graceful. Without hesitation, Roger cited his footwork as the single most important factor in his game – for beauty and effect.</p>
<p>Specifically, Roger said, “The key to exploring my potential is improving my footwork…It’s always what I’ve been working on.”</p>
<p>During the interview, Roger kept coming back to footwork. In my opinion as a coach, tennis player and critic, footwork is the single most important factor in determining a player’s success in tennis.</p>
<p>I say this because it doesn’t matter how good a player’s strokes are, if his footwork is lacking, he won’t be able to place himself into position to hit effective shots. If we look at the best players on the ATP tour in today’s era (Djokovic, Federer, Nadal), they all have the best footwork in the game.</p>
<p>It’s no coincidence these men have consistently dominated the game for the last 15 years either. If you want to improve your tennis game, nothing will do so faster than bettering your tennis footwork.</p>
<p>But what does tennis footwork exactly mean? We hear so much about it but it’s quite a nebulous term which is rarely clearly defined. Let’s do that now.</p>
<p><strong>I can break up footwork into four distinct stages. Each stage is important and crucial to hitting great, powerful shots. </strong></p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Attaining the optimal position &#8211; Getting to the spot where the striking of the ball takes place.</strong></li>
<li><strong>Planting of the feet &#8211; placing the body into the proper firing position.</strong></li>
<li><strong>Harnessing momentum &#8211; pushing off the ground, thrusting the torso and generating the necessary momentum to propel the arm into the swing.</strong></li>
<li><strong>Recovering &#8211; returning or moving to the best location on the court.</strong></li>
</ol>
<p>I’ll go through all four stages in detail shortly. I can tell you for certain that the best players blend them seamlessly together. They do so all match long and repeat the process over and over during a point.</p>
<p>When a player can use his footwork so quickly and efficiently, often and oddly, it goes unnoticed by the casual observer. What remains is a virtuoso of perfection on the court with the final punctuating shot riveted as the last memory in the viewer’s mind – not the footwork.</p>
<p>This is the primary reason why footwork does not get talked about enough. Furthermore, not enough coaches work on it with their players.</p>
<p>By reading this entire article, you’ll know exactly what proper footwork entails and how to use it to dominate all your future matches. Your level of play or age is irrelevant. Everyone can improve their footwork if they determine to.</p>
<p>Without further ado, let’s get into the four stages of tennis footwork.</p>
<div class="kad-youtube-shortcode videofit"  ><iframe width="600" height="400" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/v6wauVoK6N4?autoplay=0&controls=1&fs=1&modestbranding=1&theme=dark&rel=0&loop=0&showinfo=1" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="true"></iframe></div>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Stage 1: Attaining the Optimal Position</h2>
<p>This stage can be the most difficult of all four for beginner and intermediate players to achieve correctly. This is because most people use inefficient movement to reach the ball.</p>
<p>Furthermore, most people set up to close or far away from the ball. However, when done correctly, getting to the spot where you can strike the ball should set you up perfectly for stage 2.</p>
<p>There are only three ways to move to the ball in tennis. The first is by taking a cross-step and then shuffling (or side-stepping) to the ball. This is the most commonly used technique by players.</p>
<p>A first cross-step and shuffle is primarily done when moving laterally but can be accomplished when moving backwards and forwards as well. This is done for balls not too close or far away – but at a middle distance.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>The second is to simply shuffle to the ball. This movement is used when the ball is relatively close, like a few steps away. Shuffling is done laterally but can be executed forwards and backwards as well.</p>
<p>The third way to move to the ball is to simply run. We run when the ball is far away or we have little time to get there (like on a drop shot). Running is the quickest way to reach a ball but gives us the least amount of control when hitting.</p>
<p>If we run to the ball, it would benefit us to slow down before reaching the ball. Another important factor in helping us hit the ball (no matter which of the three methods we use) is to position the racket to the side of our body (close to the power position) before reaching the ball.</p>
<p>By doing so, we can save time and put ourselves into a better position as we reach stage 2. This is the reason why professional players rarely looked rushed when hitting shots and amateurs often do.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Stage 2: Planting of the Feet</h2>
<p>By virtue of stage 1, we should now be in the ideal position to hit the ball. In this stage (# 2), we stop our feet (if only for a second) and plant them to the ground.</p>
<p>Why would we do this? Because all power is generated from the ground up. It’s true for every sport and tennis is no exception. In order to use the ground, we need to have our feet firmly planted on it.</p>
<p>We then bend our knees and push off the ground to create energy for the swing. As we plant our feet we must also rotate our body what’s called the power position.</p>
<p>This is a position where our racket is back (or loaded) and our torso is turned to the side. This position creates torque and kinetic energy that can be released into the shot.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, many club players (especially those 4.0 and lower) fail to achieve enough torque to hit truly powerful shots. This stems from improper technique and the discomfort required in torquing the body.</p>
<p>I believe this stage is of huge importance when it comes to hitting very powerful shots. Both feet need to be planted firmly on the ground and the body torqued well past 90 degrees in the shoulders.</p>
<p>When you study pros in slow motion, you’ll see them set up in this way if they have even a second of time. When on the run, they don’t always have the time to achieve a perfect stage 2 position.</p>
<p>But they get around that by using the momentum of their run in stage 1 to generate pace. This is evident in the tremendous on-the-run passing shots of Nadal and Sampras off the forehand side. They can still manage to hit 80 mph+ passing shots on a dead run due to the momentum created in their movement to the ball.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Stage 3: Harnessing Momentum</h2>
<p>At the commencement of this stage, the body and racket will have completed the setup to strike the ball. Think of stage 2 as being a loaded gun or a crossbow pulled back into the final position before being released.</p>
<p>In stage 3 we execute the forward part of the stroke. This is done initially by pushing off the ground with both feet. However, it should be noted that most of your weight will be on the back foot.</p>
<p>This is so because we want to distribute our weight from the back leg to the front leg in order to transfer our body weight into the shot. You’ll see every great player do this on every basic shot in tennis (forehand, backhand, serve and volley).</p>
<p>As the legs push off the ground, the torso begins to rotate towards the net, releasing the stored kinetic energy it achieved in stage 2. The last part of the swing happens from the arm, which more-or-less goes along for the ride.</p>
<p>The major mistake most club players make here is thinking the arm is the primary source of power when it’s the legs and torso that really do the heavy lifting. The arm should be loose and flexible, snapping forward from the momentum of the body.</p>
<p>If a player never achieves an ideal power position and pushes off from the ground, then the arm is left to do the work. This results in a labored swing and slower velocity shot. Such players can never seem to generate power no matter how hard they swing.</p>
<p>This is because the legs and torso play a huge roll in how hard the ball is struck. If the legs and torso only play a small factor in the swing, the arm must work extra hard to compensate. This approach can tire a player out over a long match and result in weak swings.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Stage 4: Recovering</h2>
<p>After the ball is struck and the player completes his follow through, the next and final stage is to move again. This time it’s a movement to the best location on the court to set up for the next shot.</p>
<p>Experienced players rely on their anticipation to move to the ideal spot to hit the next ball. This can mean moving in any direction and any distance, just depending on the situation.</p>
<p>Often, you’ll see a player like Djokovic (who has the best footwork in the game) immediately move to a different spot on the court after completing his follow through. He seems to always know exactly where to go.</p>
<p>This comes from years of playing. Beginner players often stand in the same position after hitting a shot or move only a couple of steps. This usually puts them out of position for the next shot in the rally.</p>
<p>If you’re unsure of where to go, a good rule of thumb is to get back to the middle of the court. In general, it’s best to play slightly in back of the baseline or inside the service line (if you come into net).</p>
<p>The movement in stage 4 is similar to the movement in stage 1. You can shuffle back, cross-step and shuffle back, or just run. The quicker you can reach the ideal position to set up for the next shot, the easier the game gets. It’s also more difficult for your opponent to cause an unforced error on your part.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Summing It Up</h2>
<p>Ideal footwork requires technique, anticipation, and willingness to put in the work. Most players with great footwork are constantly in motion, taking as many steps as they need to place themselves into ideal hitting position.</p>
<p>The next time you watch a professional tennis match on TV or in person, take note of the footwork of the players. Instead of watching the ball or the strokes, notice how much the feet are moving.</p>
<p>Then compare that footwork to yours – if you’ve ever videoed your play. You’ll probably notice a big difference. One of the reasons I’m better than I look on camera is my footwork.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>While my strokes weren’t honed at a prestigious tennis academy in my formative years, I make up for a lot of deficiencies with my tennis footwork. My college coach instilled it in me early on and I’ve used it religiously throughout my playing life.</p>
<p>Due to being in great physical shape and having a light body weight (150 lbs), I can move nearly as well as most professional players, despite being in my mid-40s. I’m actually known for being a great mover (more than anything else) and dazzle people with the balls I can track down.</p>
<p>I do this by utilizing the four stages of footwork I outlined in this article. If you’ve never given much thought to tennis footwork, I hope this blog post sheds new light on it for you.</p>
<p>While this article is by no means a comprehensive guide to tennis footwork, I hope it gives you food for thought and motivates you to improve your foot movement on court.</p>
<p>Thanks for reading. If you wish to leave a comment or question, please do so below and I will respond.</p>
<p>Don’t forget I have a ton of great blog content on here to improve every aspect of your tennis game. Use the search feature to find what you’re interested in.</p>
<p>The post <a href="/what-are-the-best-tennis-footwork-tips/">What Are The Best Tennis Footwork Tips?</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/what-are-the-best-tennis-footwork-tips/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>How To Play Tennis If You&#8217;re A Beginner</title>
		<link>/am-i-doing-it-right-tennis-fundamental-checklist/</link>
					<comments>/am-i-doing-it-right-tennis-fundamental-checklist/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chad Walner]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 29 Oct 2018 13:37:17 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Theory]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[footwork]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=880</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>If you’ve never played tennis, learning the game can be daunting. Tennis is a challenging sport to learn for most people. Players need years of practice to get really good. You may only be looking to play for fun. If &#8230; <a class="kt-excerpt-readmore" href="/am-i-doing-it-right-tennis-fundamental-checklist/" aria-label="How To Play Tennis If You&#8217;re A Beginner">Read More</a></p>
<p>The post <a href="/am-i-doing-it-right-tennis-fundamental-checklist/">How To Play Tennis If You&#8217;re A Beginner</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>If you’ve never played tennis, learning the game can be daunting. Tennis is a challenging sport to learn for most people. Players need years of practice to get really good.</p>
<p>You may only be looking to play for fun. If so, you probably have no intention of being a tournament player. Or maybe you’re a newbie who wants to get up to speed quickly. If so, have no concerns – you’re in good hands.</p>
<p><strong>This post will bring you up to speed quickly, giving you the basics on how to play tennis. In this post, I’ll teach you the easiest way to hit the forehand, backhand, serve and volley. We’ll talk a little about footwork too.</strong></p>
<p><strong>The point of this post is not to turn you into Roger Federer or Serena Williams. It’s to get you playing quickly as a tennis beginner so you can enjoy the game.</strong></p>
<p>After reading this post you will be able to rally, hit basic serves, and know the fundamentals of tennis footwork. Without further ado, let’s jump right into the first lesson, which is the basic ready position.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Ready Position</h2>
<p><strong>In tennis, you are either hitting the ball or waiting for it to come back.</strong> When waiting for it to come back, you’ll need to assume the basic ready position.</p>
<p>There is no movement involved with this position. It’s just setting up in a position from which we can move to or hit the tennis ball.</p>
<p>The ready position is absolutely essential if you want to play well and not look like a total newbie. Here’s how you do it.</p>
<ul>
<li>Stand with feet slightly wider than shoulder width, facing the net. Toes should be forward and knees slightly bent. Your weight should be more on the balls of your toes than your heels.</li>
<li>Hold the racket out in front of you. Your elbows should be about 4-6 inches away from your body. The top of the racket should be around chest level.</li>
<li>When holding the racket have the dominant hand at the bottom of the handle. The other hand will be on the throat of the racket.</li>
</ul>
<p>This is the basic ready position and you can use it anywhere on the court – baseline or net. After you hit serves, groundstrokes, and volleys, return to the ready position as quickly as possible.</p>
<p>The only times you will not get back to the ready position after a stroke is when you are out of position. If you are out of position, quickly get back into position and then assume the ready position.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-92" style="margin-bottom: 0px; padding-bottom: 0px;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/practice-tips220x40.png" alt="" width="220" height="40" /></p>
<blockquote><p>If you’re coming into net, use the ready position when your opponent begins to hit the ball. If you can take a small jump off one or two feet into the ready position, this is called the “split step”.</p></blockquote>
<p>The split step should be used to prepare for all returns (at least in theory). It allows you to move in any direction quickly or set up for a groundstroke, volley or overhead.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>The Forehand</h2>
<p>The forehand is like the queen in chess. If the queen is the most powerful and versatile piece on the chess board, the same can be said for the forehand in tennis.</p>
<p>Most of your groundstrokes will be hit with the forehand. Even the best players in the world run around their backhands (to hit their forehands) when they can. A good forehand can dictate the point and end it with power.</p>
<p>However, at the beginner level consistency is much more important than power or placement. <strong>All you need do as a beginner is keep the forehand in play. This will win you the majority of points.</strong></p>
<p>Proper technique for the forehand is vital to its success. Let’s go over it now. I’ll be giving instructions for a right-handed player throughout this post. Lefties do the opposite.</p>
<h4></h4>
<h4>How To Hit The Forehand</h4>
<ol>
<li>From the ready position, change your grip to the <strong>eastern forehand</strong> and slide your left hand to the throat of the racket.</li>
<li>You should still be facing the court at this point. From here I want you to make a unit turn. You do this by keeping your feet in the same place but turn your torso so that it faces to the right side. It’s fine if your knees bend and feet pivot slightly.</li>
<li>At this time, you can take your left hand off the racket and point it to the right side of the court.</li>
<li>Your right arm (the one with the racket) will extend back. Make sure the tip of the racket head is facing behind you. The strings on the racket side that will hit the ball should be facing the right side as well.</li>
<li>As the ball comes to you, step towards the ball with your left foot. Your left foot should be in front of your right foot, about shoulder-width apart.</li>
<li>At this point, you can begin the forward swing. Swing to waist level contact point if possible.</li>
<li>Follow through with the swing until the racket is over your left shoulder. The right elbow should be head height and facing the net.</li>
<li>Once the swing is completely finished, you can return to the ready position.</li>
</ol>
<h4></h4>
<h4>Forehand Keys</h4>
<ul>
<li>When you bring the racket in back of you (step 4), try to lay the wrist back (called extension). This will cause the handle of the racket to be at about a 90-degree angle to your forearm.</li>
<li>Contact the ball with your racket in front of your body. Around the toes of your front, left foot is acceptable.</li>
<li>Keep your eyes on the ball the entire time.</li>
<li>Don’t grip the racket too hard. A medium squeeze is fine.</li>
<li>Allow the back foot to rise onto the toes during and after the ball is struck. This ensures proper weight transfer.</li>
</ul>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>The Backhand</h2>
<p>If the ball is hit to the opposite side of your body (the left side), you’ll need to hit a backhand. Yup, that’s right. The dreaded backhand that plagues all beginners.</p>
<p>Fortunately, the backhand is a more natural motion for most people to execute than the forehand. Think of tossing a frisbee or disk. Most right-handers toss a frisbee from their left side.</p>
<p>The backhand is an essential shot in tennis. If you can’t hit a backhand, you’re dead in the water. Most beginners can sort of figure out the forehand. But the backhand is a different story.</p>
<p>If you never had a backhand tennis lesson, it’s an extremely difficult shot to hit or learn on your own. The good news is that you have me! I’m going to teach you the easiest way to hit the backhand (keep reading).</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>You may not be aware of this, but the backhand can be hit with one hand or two hands. I highly suggest learning the <strong>two-handed backhand</strong> and staying with it. It’s much easier to learn, execute, and control. So here we go.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h4>How To Hit The Backhand (Two-Handed)</h4>
<ol>
<li>From the ready position, you’ll want to have a <strong>continental grip</strong> for the right hand. The left hand will hold the racket with an <strong>eastern forehand grip</strong>. The right hand is always on the bottom of the racket. The left hand goes above the right hand. There should be no space or very little space between the hands.</li>
<li>Just like you did on the forehand, make a unit turn, but to the left. The feet should remain in the same position. Only the torso will turn. It’s okay if your knees bend and your feet pivot slightly.</li>
<li>As the ball is coming to you, step forward with the right foot. It should be on a slight diagonal to the left foot &#8211; slightly to the left of it and shoulder-width apart in front. This allows a weight transfer forward.</li>
<li>After you put the right foot down (waiting maybe a split second) begin to move the racket into the ball, hitting it at waist height (if possible).</li>
<li>Contact the ball near the right, front foot. If you contact the ball too far in front or back, the shot will not work.</li>
<li>Continue swinging the racket until it finishes over your right shoulder. Your left elbow should be head height and pointing towards the net. Your back foot (left foot) should be off the ground or on the toes.</li>
<li>Once the swing is completely finished, you can return to the ready position.</li>
</ol>
<h4></h4>
<h4>Backhand Keys</h4>
<ul>
<li>When you bring the racket back, the tip of the racket should be facing the back fence.</li>
<li>You can make the backhand much better if you use flexion in your right wrist. This will drop the head of the backhand below the hands allowing for topspin.</li>
<li>Don’t grip the racket too hard. A medium squeeze is fine.</li>
<li>Once you begin the swing, keep the racket moving through the ball all the way until the finish point.</li>
<li>If you want to ensure you are finishing correctly, remain in the follow-through position for 2-3 seconds after completing it. Check your form and make sure your left elbow is nice and high. Only do this during practice, not in a match.</li>
</ul>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>The Serve</h2>
<p>In tennis, the serve is the most complicated stroke. <strong>It’s the only shot that you have full control over</strong>. You start the serve and you end it. It’s also an essential shot, as every point in tennis begins with the serve.</p>
<p>The serve involves a series of complicated movements. These movements need to be performed correctly inside a small window of time (several seconds). As a consequence, it can take years to master the tennis serve – or at least be really good at it.</p>
<p>Let’s be realists though. You want to play now. Spending years learning the tennis serve is as appealing as waiting in line at the DMV. This begs the question, “What is the quickest and easiest way to learn the tennis serve?”</p>
<p>I actually have an entire blog post and video on <a href="/learn-how-to-serve-in-10-minutes-with-the-servemaster/">how to serve in 10 minutes</a>. It involves using the <strong>ServeMaster</strong>, which is a tennis teaching device. But I’ll assume you don’t have one conveniently on hand. So I’ll modify my instructions.</p>
<p>Before I begin, I need to warn you that if you can’t toss the ball, the serve ain’t happening. You’ll need to toss the ball accurately to serve – meaning around the same spot.</p>
<p>I’m telling you now, you can’t toss the ball a foot or two outside your target zone and still hit the ball. If it’s a matter of a few inches, we can work with that. But if any more, we, or rather you, are going to struggle with the serve.</p>
<p>Alright, enough talk. Let’s get into it.</p>
<h4></h4>
<h4>How To Hit The Serve</h4>
<ol>
<li>Stand with your body at a 45-degree angle to the net post. If serving from the deuce side (right side of the court), your chest should be facing the right net post.</li>
<li>The left foot should be near the baseline (but not touching it) at a 45-degree angle – facing in the direction of the right net post. The back foot (right foot) should be about 6-10 inches from the left foot. The toes of the right foot should be close to the heel of the left foot.</li>
<li>The grip on the racket will be the <strong>eastern forehand grip</strong>. The <strong>continental grip</strong> is for advanced serves, and we don’t have time for that here.</li>
<li>Raise your right arm into an L-shape. It should look like you’re about to throw something. If this was a judicial court, it would look like the “I swear to tell the whole truth and nothing but the truth” pose.</li>
<li>At this point, you should be in the correct stance and grip with your right arm in a throwing motion. The tennis ball will be in your left hand. Next, your left hand is going to toss the ball, starting from your left leg, palm facing to the right.</li>
<li>Raise your left arm, keeping it straight, without twisting your hand.</li>
<li>When raising your arm, do so at a medium speed and let go of the ball around head height.</li>
<li>Do not toss the ball very high – it shouldn’t go more than 2-3 feet higher than your head. The toss should put the ball 6-8 inches to the right of your head.</li>
<li>When the ball is near its zenith, move the right arm forward in a throwing motion and contact the ball, reaching up to hit it. The tossing arm should drop when you move the right arm forward.</li>
<li>After making contact with the ball, allow the hitting arm to continue its motion until finishing on the lower left side of your body.</li>
</ol>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Alright, I know, easier said than done. But that, in a nutshell, is the easiest way to serve in tennis (unless you serve underhand). We want to keep all the moving parts very simple.</p>
<p><strong>A low toss, short arm motion, and keeping the feet on the floor will simplify the motion. Remember, we are not trying to serve 100 mph. The main objective here is to get the ball in the service box to start the point.</strong></p>
<p>You can set up the same way on the ad side of the court, which is the left side. It’s definitely going to take practice to get acquainted with the serve. Don’t get frustrated if it&#8217;s not going into the box right away. It will, with practice.</p>
<p>One more thing about the serve. Don’t try to hit the serve too hard when starting out. Strive for consistency and swing about 50% speed, building up from there. Later on, you can go for power. Here are some keys on the serve.</p>
<h4></h4>
<h4>Serve Keys</h4>
<ul>
<li>Keep your eyes on the ball throughout the serve. It’s important to look up to see the ball when hitting it.</li>
<li>Hold the racket with a medium-to-light grip.</li>
<li>If possible, allow your weight to fall forward when you serve so that you get a little bit of your body into it.</li>
<li>If you want, you can step forward with your right foot after striking the ball – but only after the ball has made contact with the racket.</li>
<li>Make sure your feet are not touching the baseline or going over it (in the air is okay) while in the serving motion. This is called a foot fault and is illegal. Once the ball is hit, you can step or go over the baseline.</li>
<li>Don’t tense your arm when swinging. Allow it to be loose and finish easily on the left side of your body.</li>
<li>If you make a bad toss, it’s okay to not hit it and try again. As long as you don’t swing at the ball, you can take as many tries as you like. However, your opponent may not like you anymore.</li>
</ul>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Volleys</h2>
<p>A volley is a shot taken out of the air before it bounces on your side of the court. A rally shot is a forehand or backhand hit after the ball bounces on the court. Most beginners are confused by the terms “rally” and “volley”. Now you know the difference. And knowing is half the battle, isn’t it?</p>
<p>In tennis, you need to know how to volley. It’s especially true in doubles. I briefly want to go over some tips for the volley so you’re not left in a lurch here. Since the volley is a very simple stroke, we’ll skip the execution part.</p>
<p>There are <a href="/seven-volley-types-you-must-know-to-master-your-net-game/">a ton of volleys that you can learn</a>, but for now, a block volley will do. To volley, start in the ready position and simply block the ball with your racket. A good way to think about this is to imagine what it would be like to catch the tennis ball your racket. Don’t overly complicate the volley. Just let the ball come to your racket.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>That’s all you really need to do for now. Let me give you a few other tips that could make the volley easier for you.</p>
<ul>
<li>Use a <strong>continental grip</strong>. Any other grip used on the volley will get you into hot water.</li>
<li>Keep the head of the racket above the hands on a 45-degree angle if possible.</li>
<li>Always start the volley from the ready position if possible. After hitting a volley, either get back to the ready position or move closer to the net and then get into the ready position.</li>
<li>When hitting the backhand volley, you’ll need to turn your shoulders so that your torso is facing the left net post. This is essential. On the forehand volley, no turn is needed although a slight turn of the shoulders is best.</li>
<li>Keep a medium-squeeze grip on the racket. On very fast-paced shots, a light grip is required.</li>
<li>Let the ball come to your racket. Don’t try to move the racket to the ball or make any extraneous movements with the hand or wrist.</li>
<li>If possible, keep your arm relatively straight when you volley and contact the ball in front of you.</li>
</ul>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Footwork</h2>
<p>When most people think of learning or playing tennis, they think forehand, backhand, and serve. Footwork is not a word that comes to mind. However, it’s one of the most important aspects of tennis.</p>
<p>Without proper movement, you’ll be like a fish out of water. It’s not a good look. The famous coach Rick Macci said that tennis is a movement game. If you’re not willing to move, you shouldn’t be playing.</p>
<p>While that sounds harsh, there is some truth in it. I want to go over basic tennis footwork, so you can move around the court efficiently. At the least, you’ll have a good idea of what you need to do.</p>
<p>Now, on the court, you’ll either be moving forward and back or side-to-side (laterally). Let’s cover the various directions now.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h4>Moving Side-To-Side</h4>
<p>It doesn’t matter if you move to the right or to the left, the footwork will still be the same. There are two basic ways to move laterally.</p>
<p>The first is to shuffle or side-step. This is where you move your feet together and then apart, repeating as much as necessary, all while moving in one direction.</p>
<p>The second way to move laterally is simply to run. If you need to cover a large distance or get to a ball quickly, you’ll need to run. Running is the quickest way to move in tennis (in any direction).</p>
<p>For covering short-to-medium length distances laterally, you can shuffle. The shuffle is a lot slower than a run, however, it takes less energy and is used more often. If necessary, we can actually increase the speed of a shuffle. And you thought it couldn’t be done!</p>
<p>The solution is to make the first move a cross step. The outside foot will cross over and in front of the inside foot and then the inside foot will slide in back and to the side of it. This allows you to cover a larger distance on the first step.</p>
<p>The crossover step is only used on the first step. After that, you can simply shuffle back to position. In tennis, you’ll be shuffling from side-to-side on almost every rally. So get used to the footwork.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h4>Moving Forward</h4>
<p>To move forward we can run or turn to the side and shuffle forward. Most of the time it will be a slow run. When moving forward to the ball, slow down and stop once you get near it. You should only ever move full speed to a ball if you absolutely must.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h4>Moving Backward</h4>
<p>To move backward, turn to your side (right for the forehand and left for the backhand) and then shuffle backwards. To move faster, make the first step a cross step and then shuffle. If you need to move very quickly, which usually happen when you’re at net and get lobbed, turn completely around and run!</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h4>Keys To Footwork</h4>
<ul>
<li>When shuffling to the side (right or left), hold your racket to the side you are moving to. For example, if moving to your right to hit a forehand, place the racket to the right side of your body and away from it. This allows for early preparation and makes setting up quicker and easier.</li>
<li>Try to slow down when approaching the ball and stop to hit it if possible.</li>
<li>If moving forward, hold the racket out in front of you. This helps to ensure early preparation.</li>
<li>When backing up with a shuffle, hold the racket to the side you will be hitting the ball. If a forehand, it will be to the right side. If a backhand, the left side.</li>
<li>Try to stay in the middle of the court after returning the ball to your opponent. If you find yourself away from the middle of the court after hitting a shot, run or shuffle back to the middle and then assume the ready position.</li>
<li>When shuffling, try to keep a low center of gravity. If you bend your knees and stay low, you can move quicker.</li>
<li>If you find yourself near the service line, either move back to the baseline or closer to the net. Don’t hang out by the service line, which is referred to as “no man’s land”.</li>
</ul>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>In Conclusion</h2>
<p>I know there’s a lot of information in this post. Tennis is not a game you can easily explain how to play in a post. Use this information in conjunction with the videos. The videos show you the “how to” and the blog post fills in the details.</p>
<p>Don’t worry if you can’t get the hang of hitting the ball right away. It may take a few times – or a lot of times – before you figure out timing and such. But you’ll make progress each time you play.</p>
<p><strong>The most important thing on your groundstrokes is to turn to the side and get the racket behind you. If all else fails, do that.</strong></p>
<p>As for the serve, <a href="/duds-to-aces-8-must-know-tips-to-increase-tennis-serve-power/">there’s a bunch of different drills</a> you can do to improve. One drill I really like is to hold two tennis balls – one in your tossing hand and the other in your serving hand (instead of your racket). Toss the ball with your tossing hand and then throw the other ball with your racket hand. This simulates a real serve very well.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>Practice taking shadow swings before you play. Do at least 10 on each side (forehand and backhand). For footwork, practice shuffling side-to-side and try out the cross step. For the serve, another good drill is to simply practice your toss without swinging at the ball.</p>
<p>If you follow my advice, you’ll have the basics covered. My hope is that after a few times practicing, you’ll be able to play games and hit basic groundstrokes and serves – hopefully in the court.</p>
<p>Tennis is a barrel of fun and quite addictive once you get the hang of it. Believe me, if you implement the information in this article (and my videos) you’ll be miles ahead of your beginner friends.</p>
<p>If you have any questions for me, drop them in the comment section below. Have fun playing!</p>
<p>The post <a href="/am-i-doing-it-right-tennis-fundamental-checklist/">How To Play Tennis If You&#8217;re A Beginner</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/am-i-doing-it-right-tennis-fundamental-checklist/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>2</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
