<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Reviews Archives - Serve and Volley Tennis</title>
	<atom:link href="/category/reviews/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/category/reviews/</link>
	<description>Your secret weapon on the court.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 15 Aug 2019 09:51:21 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	

<image>
	<url>/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/cropped-ted_svt_favicon-32x32.png</url>
	<title>Reviews Archives - Serve and Volley Tennis</title>
	<link>/category/reviews/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>TopSpin Pro Tennis Review</title>
		<link>/topspin-pro-tennis-review/</link>
					<comments>/topspin-pro-tennis-review/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chad Walner]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 11 Nov 2018 17:47:44 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Reviews]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[backhand]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[forehand]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[topspin]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1213</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>If you’ve struggled with hitting topspin, this post may be the answer to your topspin issues. In it, I give my honest review of the Topspin Pro. Don’t forget to check out the video I made to see it in &#8230; <a class="kt-excerpt-readmore" href="/topspin-pro-tennis-review/" aria-label="TopSpin Pro Tennis Review">Read More</a></p>
<p>The post <a href="/topspin-pro-tennis-review/">TopSpin Pro Tennis Review</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>If you’ve struggled with hitting topspin, this post may be the answer to your topspin issues. In it, I give my honest review of the Topspin Pro. Don’t forget to check out the video I made to see it in action!</p>
<div id="attachment_1276" style="width: 410px" class="wp-caption alignright"><a href="https://amzn.to/2zFCfWJ" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1276" class="wp-image-1276 size-full" title="Our affiliate link to Amazon.com" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/topspinpro-45.jpg" alt="" width="400" height="635" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/topspinpro-45.jpg 400w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/11/topspinpro-45-189x300.jpg 189w" sizes="(max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-1276" class="wp-caption-text">Click the picture to check the current pricing on Amazon.com.</p></div>
<p><strong>What exactly is the Topspin Pro?</strong></p>
<p><strong>The Topspin Pro is a tennis training device specifically designed to aid players in developing topspin.</strong></p>
<p>To my knowledge, the Topspin Pro hit the market in 2015 and has been well-received by tennis coaches and enthusiasts around the world since. It’s a simple machine but very effective in teaching topspin.</p>
<p>The company claims it can be used by children 5 years old and up. That really means everyone who plays tennis &#8211; even adults. Hey, we all need to practice, don’t we?</p>
<p>But seriously, I even find the Topspin Pro to be useful for an advanced player like myself. It simply reinforces the correct swing path for topspin. <strong>And I like topspin.</strong></p>
<p>I also find it to be a great tool for beginners, but intermediate players will also improve with it. I use the Topspin Pro mainly with my younger students, who range in age from 10-15 years old.</p>
<p>Every time I bring it to the court, I’m always amazed how children react to it. At first glance, they crowd around the Topspin Pro in a curious fashion. They ask me, “What is that?” It only takes me two minutes to give them an answer and demonstrate how it works.</p>
<p>Within seconds they’re copying me and hitting with topspin. If they don’t at first, it’s easy to grab their rackets and move it in the correct swing path. This does the trick every time.</p>
<p>There has literally never been one child that couldn’t make the ball spin forward. In my experience, all children and adults are fully capable of hitting topspin. In theory, if they can produce forward ball rotation on the Topspin Pro, they can do it during actual hits in practice and matches.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>How The Topspin Pro Works</h2>
<div id="attachment_1278" style="width: 410px" class="wp-caption alignleft"><a href="https://amzn.to/2zFCfWJ" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><img decoding="async" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1278" class="wp-image-1278 size-full" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/topspinpro-side.jpg" alt="" width="400" height="401" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/topspinpro-side.jpg 400w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/11/topspinpro-side-150x150.jpg 150w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/11/topspinpro-side-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-1278" class="wp-caption-text">Click the picture to check the current pricing on Amazon.com.</p></div>
<p>The Topspin Pro is designed to provide instant feedback to the user, which I love about it. It does this by suspending an actual tennis ball on a thin rod that allows it to rotate forward.</p>
<p>The machine is used by standing to the front side of it and striking the ball with a tennis racket. If the ball is struck correctly, it rotates forward, creating topspin. If not struck correctly, no rotation occurs on the ball.</p>
<p>That’s really all there is to it. The machine doesn’t have any options, besides allowing the ball to move about 8 inches forward or not after it has been hit. I prefer the ball to move forward rather than stay in place.</p>
<p>The Topspin Pro can be adjusted for any height person, from kid to full grown adult. The adjustment pin is very easy to use and requires just a few seconds to adjust up or down.</p>
<p>This innovative teaching tool can be used indoors or outdoors. To me, it’s one of the best indoor tennis training devices on the market.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<blockquote><p>You can learn to hit topspin in your living room if you want! Now that’s cool.</p></blockquote>
<p>I find the Topspin Pro to be durable and haven’t experienced any issues since purchasing it. I’ve whacked it pretty hard and it’s never fallen over. The three tripod legs it stands on are strong and stable.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>How Does The Topspin Pro Teach Topspin?</h2>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignleft size-full wp-image-1305" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/TopSpin-Pro-Chad4.jpg" alt="" width="400" height="400" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/TopSpin-Pro-Chad4.jpg 400w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/11/TopSpin-Pro-Chad4-150x150.jpg 150w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/11/TopSpin-Pro-Chad4-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" />It teaches topspin by forcing the user to move the tennis racket in a low to high swing path. This is accomplished using the shoulder, elbow, and wrist joints in conjunction with each other.</p>
<p>If the ball is struck on the lower side first, and brushed on, the ball will rotate forward. This is how all topspin shots are achieved in tennis, whether on the forehand, the backhand, or the serve.</p>
<p>Racket angle is also important for topspin. The face should be slightly closed on contact, which is easier said than done. The Topspin Pro is built using this in mind.</p>
<p>According to Topspin Pro’s website, the angle of the racket face at contact should be in the mid-to-high 70s. For example, Federer hits with a 79-degree racket face and Nadal 76.</p>
<p>The mesh screens are designed at this angle, forcing the player to hit along it to create topspin. But don’t take my words for it. Here are the company’s exact words on how it teaches topspin:</p>
<blockquote><p>The screen reflects the required racket face angle and forces exact bio-mechanics of modern topspin groundstrokes – as seen by today’s professional players.</p></blockquote>
<p>When I demonstrate the Topspin Pro to my students, I show them how I align my racket face to the mesh screen. Once it’s aligned, it’s now at the perfect angle to generate topspin.</p>
<p>From there, all I need to do is swing in a low-to-high manner, brushing from underneath the ball. Voila, instant topspin! I then have my students swing, doing a couple of minutes on each wing – forehand and backhand.</p>
<p>I definitely see a difference in my students’ strokes after using the Topspin Pro. After using the device for only a couple of minutes, they have more topspin on their shots during practice.</p>
<p>However, the new angle face and swing path they learn needs to be reinforced. After 10-15 minutes, they may go back to their old swing, which does not generate topspin.</p>
<p>When I see that happen, I put them back on the Topspin Pro. For that reason, it’s a good idea to have students practice with it for a few minutes before every practice session.</p>
<p>Even using the Topspin Pro two or three times in a one-hour practice is perfectly fine. It only requires a couple of minutes to reinforce the swing.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Why Is Topspin Important?</h2>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignright size-full wp-image-1303" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/TopSpin-Pro-Chad.jpg" alt="" width="400" height="400" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/TopSpin-Pro-Chad.jpg 400w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/11/TopSpin-Pro-Chad-150x150.jpg 150w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/11/TopSpin-Pro-Chad-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" />Topspin is important for several reasons in tennis.</p>
<ol>
<li>First, it helps keep the ball in play. The forward spin on the ball causes more pressure to build on top of the ball, forcing it downwards. This is critical when hitting fast-paced shots. The forward rotation of the ball forces it down into the court. Without topspin, hard flat shots have a slim margin of staying in the court. But with topspin, the margins are much higher.</li>
<li>Topspin also makes the ball more difficult to volley at the net. This is because of the dipping effect the ball has with topspin. Balls that dip are tough to volley. The reason is that they drop below the net and must be volleyed near the ground.</li>
<li>Furthermore, it’s more difficult to control a ball hit with heavy spin. A lot of spin often results in the ball “flying” off the opponent’s racket. This is another reason why serve and volley is so difficult in today’s modern era of polyester strings and space-age like rackets.</li>
<li>Another reason for hitting topspin is net clearance. Balls struck with heavy topspin can be hit higher, providing more net margin. When a player only hits flat, the ball must be struck with less velocity, closer to the net, or both. Topspin allows for so much more versatility in a player’s strokes.</li>
</ol>
<p>If you look at today’s modern game, players are hitting harder than ever. The margins for error are so slim that players can’t afford to hit without high amounts of spin on the ball.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2><strong>Why The Topspin Pro Works</strong></h2>
<div id="attachment_1277" style="width: 410px" class="wp-caption alignright"><a href="https://amzn.to/2zFCfWJ" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1277" class="wp-image-1277 size-full" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/topspinpro-45left.jpg" alt="" width="400" height="375" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/topspinpro-45left.jpg 400w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/11/topspinpro-45left-300x281.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-1277" class="wp-caption-text">Click the picture to check the current pricing on Amazon.com.</p></div>
<p>Every good junior player I’ve hit with has great topspin on the ball. While topspin is an easy concept to explain (swing low-to-high and brush on the lower side of the ball), it’s not easy to do. If it was, a device like the Topspin Pro wouldn’t have been created.</p>
<p>I find that most beginner and intermediate players struggle with using their wrist to produce topspin. They also don’t come from underneath the ball nearly as much as they should. Doing these components, in addition to racket speed, generates serious topspin.</p>
<p>The Topspin Pro teaches all this for me. If the player doesn’t use their wrist and strike the ball from underneath, the ball will fail to rotate. Instead of teaching all this manually, I only need set up the Topspin Pro and let the kids have at it.</p>
<p>I want to stress that adults will also benefit from it. I have a few beginner adult students who I use the Topspin Pro with. I find that it helps adults equally well. It’s amazing to me that such a simple concept took so long to hit the market. I’m glad it has though.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Some Drawbacks of The Topspin Pro</h2>
<p>You heard me say a lot of excellent things about the TopSpin Pro so far. While I do own one and use it with my students without any issues, I want to address a few negatives that you should be aware of. I’ll list them out below.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Transportability</strong> – The Topspin Pro can be a little cumbersome to transport. It can only retract so far. This is a small drawback for me only if I take it to the tennis courts. If I’m using it at home, then it’s no issue at all.</li>
<li><strong>Usability</strong> – The Topspin Pro is great at teaching topspin but after using it for a few minutes, it can become monotonous. There’s only so many times you can brush on the ball. For this reason, I advise using it for a couple of minutes on the forehand and a couple of minutes on the backhand per use. It’s much better to have short, consistent training sessions with the TopSpin Pro frequently rather than long training sessions once in a while.</li>
<li><strong>Wear and Tear</strong> – I personally haven’t experienced any issues with the device since purchasing it. But I’ve gone through the reviews on Amazon and a few people have said either the pin falls out easily or they had problems with the mesh fabric or the bungees that hold it in place. As of the writing of this post, these claims were stated in 3 of the 67 total reviews. My students and I have personally whacked the Topspin Pro around like it’s a pinata and it’s still as good as the first day I got it. You can see my pictures and my review. The Topspin Pro in them is the exact one that I have been using with my students. In my opinion, it holds up quite well to wear and tear, so I wouldn’t worry about it.</li>
</ul>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Final Conclusion</h2>
<p>If you’re a beginner or intermediate player struggling with tennis topspin, the Topspin Pro is an excellent training tool. I can’t think of a better training device to help you hit topspin.</p>
<p>If you’re buying the Topspin Pro for a child or junior player, I feel it’d be very beneficial to their game. For convenience, you can leave it in your garage or home. It’s completely unnecessary to take to the court. Your child can practice with it at home whenever they want.</p>
<p>If you have good topspin already, then I feel the Topspin Pro is not needed. It’s really not a tool for advanced players, though it can’t hurt to be used by one. I personally like to use it just to reinforce the perfect racket angle for topspin.</p>
<p>The cost of the device is not cheap. You can take a private tennis lesson for the same cost as the TopSpin Pro. I looked at the purchase of mine as an investment. I’ll have it for years to come plus it’s going to help all my students.</p>
<p>If you’re a parent buying it for your child, I think it’s a good investment in your child’s tennis career. If you’re a tennis coach, I highly recommend you buy it to use with your students, as I do.</p>
<p>If you’re a beginner or intermediate adult, consider what you’re willing to pay to improve your strokes. For some, it’s worth it, for others not.</p>
<p>I hope this honest review of the Topspin Pro helps. <strong>If you have any questions about it, feel free to leave it in the comment section below.</strong></p>
<p>The post <a href="/topspin-pro-tennis-review/">TopSpin Pro Tennis Review</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/topspin-pro-tennis-review/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Improve Tennis Skills With These Top 10 Tennis Training Devices</title>
		<link>/improve-tennis-skills-with-these-top-10-tennis-training-devices/</link>
					<comments>/improve-tennis-skills-with-these-top-10-tennis-training-devices/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chad Walner]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 01 Nov 2018 10:55:27 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Reviews]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=959</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Learning the game of tennis isn’t easy. Fortunately, there is some great tennis training equipment on the market to make it easier. We&#8217;ve looked at a huge number of tennis training devices over the years and have come up with &#8230; <a class="kt-excerpt-readmore" href="/improve-tennis-skills-with-these-top-10-tennis-training-devices/" aria-label="Improve Tennis Skills With These Top 10 Tennis Training Devices">Read More</a></p>
<p>The post <a href="/improve-tennis-skills-with-these-top-10-tennis-training-devices/">Improve Tennis Skills With These Top 10 Tennis Training Devices</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Learning the game of tennis isn’t easy. Fortunately, there is some great tennis training equipment on the market to make it easier. We&#8217;ve looked at a huge number of tennis training devices over the years and have come up with a list of ten that can be really useful in upping your game.</p>
<p>In no order of importance, here are the top 10 training devices for tennis that we use in our own practice:</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<ol>
<li><a href="#topspin-pro">Topspin Pro</a></li>
<li><a href="#donut-rings">Tennis Donut Rings Set of 6</a></li>
<li><a href="#serve-doctor">Tennis Serve Doctor</a></li>
<li><a href="#swing-wrist">Tennis Swing Wrist Training Aid</a></li>
<li><a href="#tennis-power">Tennis Power Trainer Duo Pack (Racket Training Weight)</a></li>
<li><a href="#tennis-grip">Tennis Grip Trainer Swing Tool</a></li>
<li><a href="#agility">Pro Footwork Agility Ladder With Carry Bag</a></li>
<li><a href="#servemaster">Tennis ServeMaster</a></li>
<li><a href="#lobster">Lobster Elite Liberty Tennis Ball Machine</a></li>
<li><a href="#kbands">Kbands / Speed And Strength Leg Resistance Bands</a></li>
</ol>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>I want to go through each device in detail. I selected these tennis training devices because they help a wide range of issues on the court. These include serves, volleys, groundstrokes, grips, and footwork.</p>
<p>While you may not need all of them, some may prove invaluable to improving your game. If you have a child who’s learning, these tools are indispensable. And if you’re a coach like me, you can really fast-track your students’ success.</p>
<p>In my reviews, I’m going to inform you of the following:</p>
<ul>
<li>What each device does</li>
<li>How it can help you</li>
<li>Why it’s important to your training</li>
<li>My honest opinion of the product</li>
</ul>
<p>The main product images all link to Amazon.com where you can see the current pricing (affiliate links to Amazon for the exact model I’m reviewing here).</p>
<p>Now, I use all 10 training devices in my practice, so I endorse them all. However, every training tool has a drawback or two, and I’ll discuss those as well.</p>
<p>I want to be perfectly candid with you so you know all the facts before purchasing. Alright, let’s get into it!</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="topspin-pro"></a></p>
<h2>Topspin Pro</h2>
</div>
<div style="width: 343px" class="wp-caption alignright"><a href="https://www.amazon.com/TopspinPro-Tennis-Training-Topspin-Minutes/dp/B01N1F8M6I/ref=as_li_ss_il?ie=UTF8&amp;linkCode=li3&amp;tag=aim078-20&amp;linkId=c277f747de74929846fbd334aba20992&amp;language=en_US" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="//ws-na.amazon-adsystem.com/widgets/q?_encoding=UTF8&amp;ASIN=B01N1F8M6I&amp;Format=_SL800_&amp;ID=AsinImage&amp;MarketPlace=US&amp;ServiceVersion=20070822&amp;WS=1&amp;tag=aim078-20&amp;language=en_US" alt="" width="333" height="500" border="0" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">Click the picture to check the current pricing on Amazon.com.</p></div>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" style="border: none !important; margin: 0px !important;" src="https://ir-na.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=aim078-20&amp;language=en_US&amp;l=li3&amp;o=1&amp;a=B01N1F8M6I" alt="" width="1" height="1" border="0" /><br />
<strong>What It Does –</strong> Helps you learn topspin easily. It teaches you the correct racket angle to approach the ball.</p>
<p><strong>Who It’s For –</strong> Beginner and Intermediate players.</p>
<p><strong>How It Can Help You –</strong> Will improve your tennis strokes by adding topspin, which keeps the ball in the court. This is essential for getting to the higher levels of tennis.</p>
<p><strong>Why It’s Important –</strong> All great players hit with topspin. Most beginner and club players lack topspin or enough of it. This training device will teach you to consistently hit with topspin without learning complicated techniques.</p>
<p><strong>My Review –</strong> The Topspin Pro is fantastic training device for beginner players. I find intermediate players can benefit, but it works really well with kids and players with little or no experience.</p>
<p>Teaching or learning the concept of topspin can be challenging. Players are taught to brush on the ball but don’t notice if it spins or not. I like the Topspin Pro because the player gets instant feedback. He or she can see if the ball is spinning forward or not.</p>
<p>Most people think of this device for groundstrokes only. But it can be used for the slice serve, topspin serve, and slice backhand. The device is adjustable and I found it can be used for any height person.</p>
<p>This device is quite durable and you can hit the heck out of it with no problems. The main drawback to the Topspin Pro is its size. It does retract down, but when I go to the court, it’s just another bulky thing to bring along.</p>
<p>If you have a court where you can leave the Topspin Pro up, that would be ideal. Or, you could leave it set up at home and just practice in your house.</p>
<p>I find that you get better results using the Topspin Pro for 5-10 minutes a day over many days, rather than using it for a long period of time once in a while. If you’re a coach, you can have your students use it for 5-10 minutes before practice – doing 5 minutes of backhands and 5 minutes of forehands.</p>
<p>The only other drawback of this device is that after hitting on it for 10 minutes, it gets a little monotonous. That’s why I recommend using it 5-10 minutes a day every time you practice. Overall, this is a great training aid for learning and teaching topspin.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="donut-rings"></a></p>
<h2>Tennis Donut Rings &#8211; Set of 6</h2>
</div>
<div style="width: 410px" class="wp-caption alignright"><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Oncourt-Offcourt-Tennis-Dount-Rings/dp/B00E9O3I0C/ref=as_li_ss_il?ie=UTF8&amp;linkCode=li3&amp;tag=aim078-20&amp;linkId=36455cbc833a4c39f8a526f10f036096&amp;language=en_US" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="//ws-na.amazon-adsystem.com/widgets/q?_encoding=UTF8&amp;ASIN=B00E9O3I0C&amp;Format=_SL400_&amp;ID=AsinImage&amp;MarketPlace=US&amp;ServiceVersion=20070822&amp;WS=1&amp;tag=aim078-20&amp;language=en_US" alt="" width="400" height="400" border="0" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">Click the picture to check the current pricing on Amazon.com.</p></div>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" style="border: none !important; margin: 0px !important;" src="https://ir-na.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=aim078-20&amp;language=en_US&amp;l=li3&amp;o=1&amp;a=B00E9O3I0C" alt="" width="1" height="1" border="0" /><strong>What It Does –</strong> Improves agility on the court and good for learning various footwork patterns in tennis.</p>
<p><strong>Who It’s For –</strong> Any skill level or age. But probably best for kids and junior players.</p>
<p><strong>How It Can Help You –</strong> The rings will ingrain proper footwork position into memory. However, you need to know what you’re doing. If you do know, this will translate into more powerful and efficient groundstrokes.</p>
<p><strong>Why It’s Important –</strong> Footwork is everything at the higher levels of tennis. I can’t think of a better training aid to help learn correct footwork. The rings are very simple, but very effective.</p>
<p><strong>My Review –</strong> I first saw these rings used in a tennis training video for footwork on youtube. When I saw how effective they were, I had to order them.</p>
<p>I got them from Amazon and they’ve been indispensable to teaching my junior players advanced level footwork since. Keep in mind, the rings are only tools. You need to know footwork patterns to benefit from them.</p>
<p>I also use them myself and find they work perfectly. Six rings come in a set. Each set comes with three different colors: green, yellow, and red. I find one set can easily be used with 2-3 children.</p>
<p>The sets are available in either a 15” diameter or a 21” diameter. I use the 15” diameter, since most of my students are aged 6-12. They work fine for me as well.</p>
<p>The rings are nonslip, so they stay on the ground, even when hit a bit. This is seriously a great training tool for footwork, as it teaches players the proper spot to place their feet.</p>
<p>I can’t really see any drawback to the rings, except that you’ll need to know footwork patterns to use them.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="serve-doctor"></a></p>
<h2>Tennis Serve Doctor</h2>
</div>
<div style="width: 410px" class="wp-caption alignright"><a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/B0009PH2KC/ref=as_li_ss_il?ie=UTF8&amp;linkCode=li3&amp;tag=aim078-20&amp;linkId=07cbe7cb18719a818ea8ec7c708437a4&amp;language=en_US" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="//ws-na.amazon-adsystem.com/widgets/q?_encoding=UTF8&amp;ASIN=B0009PH2KC&amp;Format=_SL400_&amp;ID=AsinImage&amp;MarketPlace=US&amp;ServiceVersion=20070822&amp;WS=1&amp;tag=aim078-20&amp;language=en_US" alt="" width="400" height="400" border="0" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">Click the picture to check the current pricing on Amazon.com.</p></div>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" style="border: none !important; margin: 0px !important;" src="https://ir-na.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=aim078-20&amp;language=en_US&amp;l=li3&amp;o=1&amp;a=B0009PH2KC" alt="" width="1" height="1" border="0" /><strong>What It Does –</strong> Teaches you exactly where to toss and hit the serve.</p>
<p><strong>Who It’s For –</strong> Beginners and children. Also beneficial for intermediate players having trouble with their serve and overheads.</p>
<p><strong>How It Can Help You –</strong> Will provide a strong visual cue so you know the exact place you should be tossing and striking the ball on the serve. This is very important for tennis beginners of all ages.</p>
<p><strong>Why It’s Important –</strong> The serve is an essential stroke in tennis. If a you can’t toss in the ideal location to hit the ball, the serve will not work. This tool corrects that issue. The Tennis Serve Doctor is also helpful for learning overheads.</p>
<p><strong>My Review –</strong> Overall, I like this product and feel it brings a lot of value to children and complete newbies. I teach a lot of children and many of them have poor tosses, not allowing them to hit the ball on the serve.</p>
<p>I find this tennis device to be a great training aid for the serve. I have the children set up in the correct serving stance, go through their serve motion, and strike the ball.</p>
<p>The pole is adjustable to any height, so I can hold the pole in the perfect hitting zone for each student. This allows the kids to practice their serve motion, actually strike the ball in the perfect spot, and finish inside the baseline.</p>
<p>I use the Tennis Serve Doctor with the kids for a few minutes, having them hit about 15-20 serves. I then hand them a ball and have them toss and serve on their own.</p>
<p>After hitting with the Tennis Serve Doctor, they have a much better perception of the ideal place they need to hit the ball and usually end up tossing better.</p>
<div class="gmail_default">While this is a very simple device, it&#8217;s still quite effective. The main drawback of this tennis tool is you need someone to hold the pole for you. And it can be quite tiring holding it for long periods of time. But it’s a great training tool, especially if you&#8217;re teaching a child. Besides the serve, you can also use the Serve Doctor for improving groundstrokes.</div>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="swing-wrist"></a></p>
<h2>Tennis Swing Wrist Training Aid</h2>
</div>
<div style="width: 410px" class="wp-caption alignright"><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Swing-Training-Forehands-Backhands-Volleys/dp/B011M7GW92/ref=as_li_ss_il?ie=UTF8&amp;linkCode=li3&amp;tag=aim078-20&amp;linkId=593f88686600791803fd8caebce830e8&amp;language=en_US" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="//ws-na.amazon-adsystem.com/widgets/q?_encoding=UTF8&amp;ASIN=B011M7GW92&amp;Format=_SL400_&amp;ID=AsinImage&amp;MarketPlace=US&amp;ServiceVersion=20070822&amp;WS=1&amp;tag=aim078-20&amp;language=en_US" alt="" width="400" height="344" border="0" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">Click the picture to check the current pricing on Amazon.com.</p></div>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" style="border: none !important; margin: 0px !important;" src="https://ir-na.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=aim078-20&amp;language=en_US&amp;l=li3&amp;o=1&amp;a=B011M7GW92" alt="" width="1" height="1" border="0" /><strong>What It Does –</strong> Places your wrist in the correct 90-degree position to hit powerful and “effortless” groundstrokes and volleys.</p>
<p><strong>Who It’s For –</strong> Beginner and intermediate players of any age.</p>
<p><strong>How It Can Help You –</strong> The device allows you to feel the proper way to swing – like the pros. Trains the muscles in your wrist to remain in the 90-degree position, which will dramatically improve your shots.</p>
<p><strong>Why It’s Important –</strong> All professional players hit with or close to a 90-degree position in the wrist at contact. If you do not achieve this position, you’ll never maximize your potential on groundstrokes and volleys.</p>
<p><strong>My Review –</strong> For the price, this device is worth its weight in gold if it works for you. I’ve suggested it to some of my students (I teach tennis) and it helped them feel the correct way to swing.</p>
<p>It’s a tennis training device that works well in practices. You really couldn’t use it to play a match, because you can’t serve or hit slices with it. But for practicing your forehand, backhand, and volleys it’s great.</p>
<p>I read a few reviews on Amazon and some people complained that the Tennis Swing Wrist Training Aid either slipped off while hitting or did not fit. I didn’t find this to be the case with my students.</p>
<p>Overall, I would recommend trying this training aid out if you or you’re child/students are having difficulty maintaining the 90-degree laid-back wrist position.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="tennis-power"></a></p>
<h2>Tennis Power Trainer Duo Pack (Racket Training Weight)</h2>
</div>
<div style="width: 410px" class="wp-caption alignright"><a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/B01N31UHFF/ref=as_li_ss_il?ie=UTF8&amp;linkCode=li3&amp;tag=aim078-20&amp;linkId=5319752db1bc62152e09abefc27341cb&amp;language=en_US" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="//ws-na.amazon-adsystem.com/widgets/q?_encoding=UTF8&amp;ASIN=B01N31UHFF&amp;Format=_SL400_&amp;ID=AsinImage&amp;MarketPlace=US&amp;ServiceVersion=20070822&amp;WS=1&amp;tag=aim078-20&amp;language=en_US" alt="" width="400" height="400" border="0" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">Click the picture to check the current pricing on Amazon.com.</p></div>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" style="border: none !important; margin: 0px !important;" src="https://ir-na.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=aim078-20&amp;language=en_US&amp;l=li3&amp;o=1&amp;a=B01N31UHFF" alt="" width="1" height="1" border="0" /><strong>What It Does –</strong> Provides weighted resistance on the racket.</p>
<p><strong>Who It’s For –</strong> Any age and any level.</p>
<p><strong>How It Can Help You –</strong> Develops strength, racket speed, and endurance.</p>
<p><strong>Why It’s Important –</strong> This training aid will increase your racket speed by making it feel lighter when you remove the weighted resistance. Faster racket speed equates to more spin and power on all your shots.</p>
<p><strong>My Review –</strong> I carry this resistance tool in my tennis bag to every practice session and match. I find it’s a great way to warm up my swings and increase my racket speed. I practice forehands, backhands, and serves with the weights on my racket.</p>
<p>In the past, I used a small dumbbell tied to a racket I didn’t use. I always feared the dumbbell would fly off. So when I was that Tennis Power Trainer made this product, it was a no-brainer to order it.</p>
<p>This item comes with a racket weighted “vest” that slips over the head of the racket. You can take practice swings with it. It also comes with a weight that you can put in the throat of the racket.</p>
<p>The weight in the throat of the racket will supposedly allow you to hit with the extra weight. I find it to be too heavy and cumbersome to effectively hit with. So I just use both as a weighted resistance on practice swings.</p>
<p>Both myself and my students feel the racket is noticeably lighter after removing the racket training weight. Of course, the feeling doesn’t last long – maybe 10 minutes.</p>
<p>I typically keep the racket weight on one racket and swing it between games or during breaks. The resistance stays on the racket with no problem, so you can feel safe swinging as fast you want. It also goes on and comes off easily as well.</p>
<p>If you’re looking to increase your racket speed, at least temporarily, there is no product better to do it. I highly recommend this one for serious tennis enthusiasts.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="tennis-grip"></a></p>
<h2>Tennis Grip Trainer Swing Tool</h2>
</div>
<div style="width: 410px" class="wp-caption alignright"><a href="https://www.amazon.com/OnCourt-OffCourt-Tennis-Grip-Trainer/dp/B00UZC7KWY/ref=as_li_ss_il?ie=UTF8&amp;linkCode=li2&amp;tag=aim078-20&amp;linkId=5c090be05053d92d05782a43b610a6cd&amp;language=en_US" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="//ws-na.amazon-adsystem.com/widgets/q?_encoding=UTF8&amp;ASIN=B00UZC7KWY&amp;Format=_SL400_&amp;ID=AsinImage&amp;MarketPlace=US&amp;ServiceVersion=20070822&amp;WS=1&amp;tag=aim078-20&amp;language=en_US" alt="" width="400" height="400" border="0" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">Click the picture to check the current pricing on Amazon.com.</p></div>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" style="border: none !important; margin: 0px !important;" src="https://ir-na.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=aim078-20&amp;language=en_US&amp;l=li2&amp;o=1&amp;a=B00UZC7KWY" alt="" width="1" height="1" border="0" /><strong>What It Does –</strong> Teaches proper grip and hand placement on the racket.</p>
<p><strong>Who It’s For –</strong> Beginners of any age.</p>
<p><strong>How It Can Help You –</strong> Maintains the hand position in the proper grip for any stroke. Beginners tend to move their hands on the grip. This ensures the hand will stay in the chosen grip.</p>
<p><strong>Why It’s Important –</strong> Using the correct grip to hit certain shots, like the serve, forehand, backhand, and volley is essential in tennis. This device trains the beginner to keep their hands in the correct position. Also teaches what it feels like to use a particular grip.</p>
<p><strong>My Review –</strong> I like this product for beginners. It’s only made for teaching grip, which some beginners have difficulty with. Back when I was learning to serve with the continental grip, I use to shift back into the eastern forehand grip unconsciously.</p>
<p>My coach noticed I did it, but I was completely unaware. This device would have saved me from changing my grip. Most beginners change their grip because they don’t trust that the strings will align to hit the ball.</p>
<p>You can use this tennis grip tool to train such grips as the eastern backhand, eastern forehand, continental, semi-western forehand, and on and on. The training aid goes on any racket grip and is easy to put on and off.</p>
<p>If you’re a beginner who is having trouble hitting with the proper grip, this is a great tool to have for a fairly low price. I find it very helpful for beginner kids as well.</p>
<p>Perhaps the only drawback is that some people find it uncomfortable when hitting. But this training tool is only meant to be an aid. Once the grip is learned, it can be removed.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="agility"></a></p>
<h2>Pro Footwork Agility Ladder With Carry Bag</h2>
</div>
<div style="width: 410px" class="wp-caption alignright"><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Pro-Footwork-Training-Adjustable-Agility-Ladder/dp/B076ZTJ1P1/ref=as_li_ss_il?ie=UTF8&amp;linkCode=li3&amp;tag=aim078-20&amp;linkId=77207551c7506d84e378175152856f02&amp;language=en_US" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="//ws-na.amazon-adsystem.com/widgets/q?_encoding=UTF8&amp;ASIN=B076ZTJ1P1&amp;Format=_SL400_&amp;ID=AsinImage&amp;MarketPlace=US&amp;ServiceVersion=20070822&amp;WS=1&amp;tag=aim078-20&amp;language=en_US" alt="" width="400" height="146" border="0" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">Click the picture to check the current pricing on Amazon.com.</p></div>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" style="border: none !important; margin: 0px !important;" src="https://ir-na.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=aim078-20&amp;language=en_US&amp;l=li3&amp;o=1&amp;a=B076ZTJ1P1" alt="" width="1" height="1" border="0" /><strong>What It Does –</strong> Improves speed, agility, coordination, and explosiveness.</p>
<p><strong>Who It’s For –</strong> Ages 8 to adult can benefit. Older players may not have the energy or joint fitness to jump around.</p>
<p><strong>How It Can Help You –</strong> This set contains all that you need to improve your balance, stamina, and footwork. This will translate into a higher level of play on the court.</p>
<p><strong>Why It’s Important –</strong> Footwork and explosive, quick moves are everything in tennis. This speed and agility training set is all you need to improve those attributes.</p>
<p><strong>My Review –</strong> I’ve purchased several agility ladders on Amazon and wasn’t happy with any of them until buying from this company.They make quality, durable products, which is why the price is a little higher than comparable, cheaper sets. In this one, you get several distinct training items: agility ladder, hurdles, a jump rope and space markers.</p>
<p>I found from experience, I’d much rather spend $10-$20 extra and own a set that I enjoy using and lasts for the long term. Now that’s clear, we can talk about this training set and why it’s important.</p>
<p>If you’re an aspiring junior player or young adult who is an avid tennis player, you should absolutely be using a set like this – at least twice a week, if not three.</p>
<p>I selected this set because it contains the agility ladder (super important for footwork), the hurdles (excellent for teaching the split step and other footwork cues), and the space markers (great for marking out placements on the court).</p>
<p>You, or your child/student, can use the agility ladder to practice an infinite number of footwork drills. Just look on youtube or check out the article I wrote on the agility ladder here.</p>
<p>Athletes in almost every sport use the agility ladder, and tennis players are no different. Fast feet are essential at the higher levels. The hurdles are great too, with six all together in the set. They can be adjusted from 6-12 inches in height as well.</p>
<p>If you’re serious about tennis, or a coach, I recommend the use of just three products for your footwork training: this speed and agility training set, the Tennis Donut Rings Set of 6, and a good jump rope. That’s really all you need for conditioning, speed, and explosiveness.</p>
<p>Remember, footwork is everything in tennis. You should be trying to improve footwork just as much as your tennis strokes. This set will help you do it.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="servemaster"></a></p>
<h2>Tennis ServeMaster</h2>
</div>
<div style="width: 410px" class="wp-caption alignright"><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Total-Serve-ServeMaster-LTE-Ball/dp/B01MRH5RL4/ref=as_li_ss_il?ie=UTF8&amp;linkCode=li3&amp;tag=aim078-20&amp;linkId=52615f8c9abb43f33b4cf46a9572be70&amp;language=en_US" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="//ws-na.amazon-adsystem.com/widgets/q?_encoding=UTF8&amp;ASIN=B01MRH5RL4&amp;Format=_SL400_&amp;ID=AsinImage&amp;MarketPlace=US&amp;ServiceVersion=20070822&amp;WS=1&amp;tag=aim078-20&amp;language=en_US" alt="" width="400" height="400" border="0" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">Click the picture to check the current pricing on Amazon.com.</p></div>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" style="border: none !important; margin: 0px !important;" src="https://ir-na.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=aim078-20&amp;language=en_US&amp;l=li3&amp;o=1&amp;a=B01MRH5RL4" alt="" width="1" height="1" border="0" /><strong>What It Does –</strong> Helps improve the tennis serve, groundstrokes, and overheads.</p>
<p><strong>Who It’s For –</strong> Any age (6+) and skill level. Beginners and intermediate players will get the most benefit.</p>
<p><strong>How It Can Help You –</strong> Teaches you the correct tennis swing path using natural biomechanics. Teaches the continental grip along with pronation. Will improve your serve, overheads, and groundstrokes.</p>
<p><strong>Why It’s Important –</strong> No other training device I know is more effective at teaching the serve than the ServeMaster. It can bring players up to speed on the serve faster than any other tool or technique I’ve seen or experienced.</p>
<p><strong>My Review –</strong> I started using this tennis serving tool a couple of years ago after seeing it on youtube. I had to try it for myself and for my students. At first, I was put off by the $50 price point (varies depending on which ServeMaster you purchase) for a long piece of rubber. But after using it with my students, I quickly became a believer.</p>
<p>I can take kids who’ve never served before, and with the help of the ServeMaster, have them hit serves with fundamentally correct technique in less than 10-15 minutes. I love this product so much, I wrote <a href="/learn-how-to-serve-in-10-minutes-with-the-servemaster/">an entire blog post on it</a> and made a youtube video as well.</p>
<p>In fact, many of my young students’ serves look better than some club level adults who’ve been playing for several decades! And this is all in one lesson. However, for the serve motion to be ingrained, a lot of practice is required.</p>
<p>I’ll typically have my student use the ServeMaster before practicing their real serves. It always makes their motions better. Amazingly, it teaches the kids the racket drop, pronation, and the continental grip all at once. Simply amazing.</p>
<p>I’d say the only drawback of this tool is that it does nothing to improve the toss. You can teach a child to have an awesome serve motion using the ServeMaster, but if they can’t toss the ball in the right location, they’re not going to hit the ball.  Check out the Serve Doctor above which will take care of you in the toss department.  You can also take a look at  the Tennis Serve Toss Trainer. However, you need someone to hold it for you. You can see it on Amazon here: <a href="https://amzn.to/2Jwic0q" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://amzn.to/2Jwic0q</a></p>
<p>For an accurate and effective swing you can’t go wrong with this serving device. You can purchase it with either one, two, or three balls attached to the end. The two-ball ServeMaster is what I use and recommend. The one-ball is good for smaller children and the three-ball for strong adults.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="lobster"></a></p>
<h2>Lobster Elite Liberty Tennis Ball Machine</h2>
</div>
<div style="width: 410px" class="wp-caption alignright"><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Lobster-Sports-Lightweight-Full-Featured-Oscillation/dp/B00DBT4PPI/ref=as_li_ss_il?ie=UTF8&amp;linkCode=li3&amp;tag=aim078-20&amp;linkId=f8ab41b1bc701911f79a26f196d266ef&amp;language=en_US" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="//ws-na.amazon-adsystem.com/widgets/q?_encoding=UTF8&amp;ASIN=B00DBT4PPI&amp;Format=_SL400_&amp;ID=AsinImage&amp;MarketPlace=US&amp;ServiceVersion=20070822&amp;WS=1&amp;tag=aim078-20&amp;language=en_US" alt="" width="400" height="400" border="0" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">Click the picture to check the current pricing on Amazon.com.</p></div>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" style="border: none !important; margin: 0px !important;" src="https://ir-na.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=aim078-20&amp;language=en_US&amp;l=li3&amp;o=1&amp;a=B00DBT4PPI" alt="" width="1" height="1" border="0" /><strong>What It Does –</strong> Launches balls at you to practice all of your tennis strokes, with the exception of the serve.</p>
<p><strong>Who It’s For –</strong> Any age and any skill level will benefit.</p>
<p><strong>How It Can Help You –</strong> Provides you endless hours of practice. You can use the machine to learn and fine-tune any tennis stroke except the serve. This is one of the best training tools for helping improve your game, period. It also doesn’t require anyone else for you to practice. The machine does it all.</p>
<p><strong>Why It’s Important –</strong> The Lobster Elite Liberty feeds you balls in the exact location, with the exact spin, and the exact velocity you want. This allows you to fully concentrate on your strokes with no outside distractions. It’s really invaluable for improving your technique and will definitely increase your conditioning as well.</p>
<p><strong>My Review –</strong> I love this ball machine so much, I bought one for myself despite the hefty price tag. However, the price is a bargain compared to other similar ball machines on the market.</p>
<p>I’ve had the Lobster Elite Liberty for two years now and never once had an issue with it. Like the ServeMaster, I wrote <a href="/lobster-elite-liberty-ball-machine-review/">a long blog post reviewing it</a> and also have a youtube video on it. I won’t go into extreme detail here, since I already covered it in other posts and videos.</p>
<p>If you’re really interested in a ball machine, you should check out my blog post and video on it. Believe me, if I’m going to spend a grand on a ball machine, it’s going to be the best one on the market for the price.</p>
<p>The Elite Liberty will do everything you need. The more expensive models are unnecessary. If you have the money and are looking for a ball machine, do yourself a favor and buy this one. You’ll love it.</p>
<p>I use the Elite Liberty to practice all my strokes. You’re only limited by your imagination with how much you can do with it. It also oscillates from side-to-side, so you can practice your footwork too.</p>
<p>The only drawback to this machine is the price. Not that it’s expensive for what it’s worth, but if you don’t have the cash to spend, then there aren’t a lot of better options.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="kbands"></a></p>
<h2>Kbands / Speed And Strength Leg Resistance Bands</h2>
</div>
<div style="width: 410px" class="wp-caption alignright"><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Kbands-Strength-Resistance-Training-Programs/dp/B00AEST19Y/ref=as_li_ss_il?ie=UTF8&amp;linkCode=li3&amp;tag=aim078-20&amp;linkId=dbed2e3cae34b8f2336f42401fbf1d2c&amp;language=en_US" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="//ws-na.amazon-adsystem.com/widgets/q?_encoding=UTF8&amp;ASIN=B00AEST19Y&amp;Format=_SL400_&amp;ID=AsinImage&amp;MarketPlace=US&amp;ServiceVersion=20070822&amp;WS=1&amp;tag=aim078-20&amp;language=en_US" alt="" width="400" height="400" border="0" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">Click the picture to check the current pricing on Amazon.com.</p></div>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" style="border: none !important; margin: 0px !important;" src="https://ir-na.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=aim078-20&amp;language=en_US&amp;l=li3&amp;o=1&amp;a=B00AEST19Y" alt="" width="1" height="1" border="0" /><strong>What It Does –</strong> Increases speed and agility by building hit strength and explosiveness. Perhaps just as important it trains the athlete to keep a lower center of gravity.</p>
<p><strong>Who It’s For –</strong> Any age and skill level will benefit. But juniors and young adults are probably best suited for the rigorous training of this tool.</p>
<p><strong>How It Can Help You –</strong> Teaches you to bend your knees and creates resistance in the legs so they build strength and speed. Will definitely improve lateral footwork on the court.</p>
<p><strong>Why It’s Important –</strong> As I’ve said previously, footwork and explosive movements are everything in tennis. This training tool is perfect for working on those attributes.</p>
<p><strong>My Review –</strong> I really like this product for improving lateral movement. It will also improve sprint speed, which is important for quick bursts on the court.</p>
<p>While the agility ladder, hurdles, and rings I mentioned earlier are great for footwork, they don’t build speed exactly like the Kbands will. These resistance bands are being worn by all types of athletes now.</p>
<p>Movement for tennis players is just as important as any other sport. And lateral movement is key. I use these bands myself and find they are comfortable enough and really do work. I can feel my legs burning after wearing them for a while.</p>
<p>I have some of my advanced students wear them. It’s difficult to tell if they work on other people, but for my own body, I definitely notice a slight difference in quickness. One thing they’re supposed to do is help you get lower going from side-to-side, which is ultra-important in tennis.</p>
<p>I like to wear the Kbands leg resistance bands when hitting. When I take them off, I feel faster. I notice that if you wear them a lot, they really do build up your leg strength and conditioning, allowing you to move faster on the court.</p>
<p>For that reason, I have this product listed at number 10 on my list. Kbands the company, makes a lot of cool training gear. However, I chose these exact bands because they’re all you need to improve your explosiveness.</p>
<p>The other sets and tools are overkill in my opinion. For the price, this is an excellent tool for improving footwork and speed.</p>
<p>The post <a href="/improve-tennis-skills-with-these-top-10-tennis-training-devices/">Improve Tennis Skills With These Top 10 Tennis Training Devices</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/improve-tennis-skills-with-these-top-10-tennis-training-devices/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>3</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Best 5 Tennis Rackets For Serve And Volley In 2018</title>
		<link>/the-best-5-rackets-for-serve-and-volley-in-2018/</link>
					<comments>/the-best-5-rackets-for-serve-and-volley-in-2018/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chad Walner]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 30 Oct 2018 08:42:53 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Reviews]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[serve]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[volley]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=904</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>If you really wanted the best vehicle for cornering, would you waste time researching the best Jeep?  Of course not!  You need the tennis racket that will fit your level and your game more than the &#8220;best&#8221; all-purpose racket. So &#8230; <a class="kt-excerpt-readmore" href="/the-best-5-rackets-for-serve-and-volley-in-2018/" aria-label="The Best 5 Tennis Rackets For Serve And Volley In 2018">Read More</a></p>
<p>The post <a href="/the-best-5-rackets-for-serve-and-volley-in-2018/">The Best 5 Tennis Rackets For Serve And Volley In 2018</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>If you really wanted the best vehicle for cornering, would you waste time researching the best Jeep?  Of course not!  You need the tennis racket that will <strong>fit your level and your game</strong> more than the &#8220;best&#8221; all-purpose racket.</p>
<p>So in tennis, there are basically two types of broad styles. You’re either a baseliner or a net crasher (serve and volleyer). Each style has very different needs.</p>
<p>Baseline players have more margin for error. A racket with power that can produce topspin is their main need.</p>
<p><strong>For the serve and volley player, rackets with more control and maneuverability are more important. The top rackets for serve and volley players are definitely different from those for baseline players, and we&#8217;ve gathered all the data together here with this very specific player in mind.</strong></p>
<p><strong>In this post, you’ll find our selection of the top 5 rackets of 2018 for serve and volley players. We broke each racket down in detail and listed their strong points and weaknesses.</strong></p>
<p>This is what we chose to be the best of the best for S&amp;V:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="#babolat">Babolat Pure Strike – 16 x 19</a></li>
<li><a href="#wilson-pro">Wilson Pro Staff RF97 Autograph</a></li>
<li><a href="#prince">Prince Phantom Pro 100</a></li>
<li><a href="#wilson61">Wilson Six One 95 &#8211; 18 x 20</a></li>
<li><a href="#yonex">Yonex EZONE DR 98 Blue</a></li>
</ul>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>How We Determined The Best Rackets For Serve And Volley</h2>
<p>We determined the best serve and volley rackets in three different ways:</p>
<ol>
<li>Through personal experience, trying out each racket.</li>
<li>Studying the specs of each racket to make sure they are ideal for serve and volley.</li>
<li>Reviewing a very detailed study that <a href="https://tenniscompanion.org/best-tennis-racquets/">tenniscompanion.org</a> did on the 22 best rackets and then we used the study to narrow down the 5 best rackets for serve and volley.</li>
</ol>
<p>The tenniscompanion.org study was compiled using six key attributes. Each attribute was scored on a 1-10 scale for every racket they reviewed. These attributes are power, control, maneuverability, comfort, touch/feel, and stability.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-921 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/racketPriorities.png" alt="" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/racketPriorities.png 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/racketPriorities-300x169.png 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/racketPriorities-768x432.png 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p>Let’s quickly look at each attribute in order of importance and determine its significance to a serve and volley racket.</p>
<p><strong>Control</strong> – Control is very important to the serve and volley player, especially when placing shots. Typically, smaller head sizes and thinner beams offer more control but less power. Control was an attribute we deemed important for our selected rackets to score well in.</p>
<p><strong>Maneuverability</strong> – This is a measure of how easily the racket can be maneuvered to hit a shot, particularly a volley. Most good maneuvering rackets have more weight in the handle than the head. This makes them feel lighter and allows them to be moved quicker. We feel this is important for volley players, so we looked for rackets that scored high in this attribute.</p>
<p><strong>Touch/Feel</strong> – Interestingly, rackets that offer touch are very similar to rackets built for comfort – heavy and flexible. The main exception is touch rackets have smaller head sizes. Since touch is very important to the volley player, this is an attribute our rackets had to score well in.</p>
<p><strong>Stability</strong> – A stable racket is one that is responsive and delivers a consistent, accurate strike of the ball. These rackets tend to be heavy with wider beams and less flexible frames. This attribute is semi-important to the serve and volley player but it wasn’t one of the key attributes for our rackets.</p>
<p><strong>Comfort</strong> – This is a measure of how comfortable your arm and body feel when hitting the ball. If there is less vibration and stiffness in the frame, that is deemed a comfortable racket. Comfort is an attribute we feel is not very important to the serve and volley player. However, one of the rackets on our list has comfort as an added bonus.</p>
<p><strong>Power</strong> – Except on the serve, power is not the most important attribute for a serve and volley player; and it may even be the last. Serve and volley players are more concerned with touch and maneuverability. For that reason, most of the rackets on this list are not the most powerful.</p>
<p>Overall, the most important attributes for selecting a great racket for serve and volley are control, maneuverability and touch/feel. Keep in mind that all the rackets we selected have power as well, but not as much as the rackets made for baseliners.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>The 5 Best Serve And Volley Rackets Of 2018</h2>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="babolat"></a></p>
<h3><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-911 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/r_bab1.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/r_bab1.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/r_bab1-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/r_bab1-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></h3>
<h3>Babolat Pure Strike – 16 x 19</h3>
</div>
<p>This racket ranked first on the tenniscompanion.org list of all the rackets they reviewed. It’s an all-court racket but at 11.3 oz and 98 sq inches, excellent for serve and volley. Its light weight allows for great maneuverability at net and quick reaction times.</p>
<p>The frame of this racket is slightly more flexible than the other members of the Babolat racket family. This affords more control and touch, perfect for the serve and volley player.</p>
<p>The only drawback I saw of this racket is slightly less power than most of the other Babolats I’ve used. But there are always trade-offs. With the Babolat Pure Strike you sacrifice a bit of power for more control. However, it’s also a fantastic racket for groundstrokes and returns.</p>
<p>Overall, this racket scored high marks across the board. Though unchanged since 2017, we still endorse it as one of the best serve and volley rackets for 2018. If you’re an all-court player who serves and volleys part of the time, few choices are better for a racket.</p>
<p><a href="https://amzn.to/2DYriCy" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Check the current price of this racket on Amazon.com</a> (affiliate link to Amazon for the exact model I’m reviewing here).</p>
<p>I personally played with the Babolat Pure Drive for years and had great success with Babolats. In the last couple of years, I switched to the Head Prestige MP, but I’d easily buy another Babolat for my next racket.</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="wilson-pro"></a></p>
<h3><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-913 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/r_rf.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/r_rf.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/r_rf-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/r_rf-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></h3>
<h3>Wilson Pro Staff RF97 Autograph</h3>
</div>
<p>The original Wilson Pro Staff from the 1980s and 90s was made popular by Pete Sampras. The new model for 2018 was popularized by Roger Federer, hence his initials in the title.</p>
<p>This racket is quite unique to other rackets in its design. It makes use of braided graphite construction with thin beams and a light head.</p>
<p>At 97 square inches, it has a great head size for serve and volley. Surprisingly, the racket weighs 12.6 ounces, which is one of the heaviest strung rackets on the market. The heavy weight gives the racket great control, but maneuverability is compromised.</p>
<p>Still, the Wilson Pro Staff makes up for the heavy weight in every other way. It feels stable, solid, and affords excellent control. Whether at the baseline, net, or serving, the Wilson Pro Staff handled solidly.</p>
<p>We picked this racket because it scored very well on volleys, slices, and net play according to tenniscompanion.org, which stated:<br />
“One of our favorite places to hit with Roger’s Pro Staff was up at the net. It felt solid in our hands and allowed us to hit crisp and controlled volleys with little effort. Combined with a heightened sense of touch and it gave us the feeling that we were in control when we approached the net.”</p>
<p><a href="https://amzn.to/2Q7AlZc" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Check the current price of this racket on Amazon.com</a> (affiliate link to Amazon for the exact model I’m reviewing here).</p>
<p>We endorse this racket for serve and volley, especially if you’re an advanced player who can handle a heavier stick. Hey, if it works for Roger Federer, it can work for you, right?</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="prince"></a></p>
<h3><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-914 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/r_prince.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/r_prince.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/r_prince-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/r_prince-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></h3>
<h3>Prince Phantom Pro 100</h3>
</div>
<p>Prince has long been known as of the best racket manufacturers. They really nailed it with this racket. With a 100 square inch head, 11.3 oz strung weight and a frame stiffness of only 54, you couldn’t ask for a racket with more control.</p>
<p>Arm friendly and responsive, you can be confident coming to net with the Prince Phantom Pro 100. This is a racket ideal for intermediate and advanced players who like to attack the net and desire control.</p>
<p>Most of the 11.3 ounces of weight is in the handle of the racket. This translates to a low head weight, giving it exceptional maneuverability at the net. On groundstrokes, the racket proved capable but doesn’t give as much spin and power as some of the other rackets on this list.</p>
<p>The main drawback of this racket is lack of power. But power is the main sacrifice when designing a racket for control. Overall, I thought this racket performed well when I hit with it. Players who swing fast won’t have power issues.</p>
<p><a href="https://amzn.to/2QdeEaf" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Check the current price of this racket on Amazon.com</a> (affiliate link to Amazon for the exact model I’m reviewing here).</p>
<p>As a hack, you could string a bit looser than normal, which should make up for some of the lost power. I believe giving up some power for all the control the Prince Phantom Pro 100 offers, is worth the trade-off. Especially if you attack the net consistently.</p>
<p>For that reason, I highly endorse this racket as one of the best serve and volley sticks of 2018.</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="wilson61"></a></p>
<h3><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-915 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/r_61.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/r_61.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/r_61-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/r_61-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></h3>
<h3>Wilson Six One 95 18 x 20</h3>
</div>
<p>For the pure serve and volley players out there that love control, this is your racket. The head size is only 95 square inches yet it weighs 12.3 ounces strung, making it almost as heavy as the Wilson Pro Staff RF 97 Autograph.</p>
<p>The heavy frame allows for comfortable contact and moves through the ball with ease. A light head balance, thin 22 mm beams all the way around it, and added it weight at the 3 and 9 o’clock positions, give this racket superior control.</p>
<p>This racket also boasts Wilson’s parallel drilling technology, which creates a more forgiving string bed and increased sweet spot. The racket performed great from the baseline and at the net in tests.</p>
<p><a href="https://amzn.to/2Pf7PPX" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Check the current price of this racket on Amazon.com</a> (affiliate link to Amazon for the exact model I’m reviewing here).</p>
<p>The main drawbacks of the Wilson Six One is the heavy weight and reduced power. This is a common theme among some serve and volley rackets. Maneuverability and power are not this racket’s forte.</p>
<p>But if you can get past that part, you have a stick that will provide you a ton of control and stability on your shots. We’re sure you’ll love coming to net with this racket.</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="yonex"></a></p>
<h3><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-916 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/r_yonex.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/r_yonex.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/r_yonex-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/r_yonex-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></h3>
<h3>Yonex EZONE DR 98 Blue</h3>
</div>
<p>This racket is a great choice for all-court players. It will still be a valuable addition to the serve and volley player with it’s excellent control and touch.</p>
<p>Yonex made this racket with Nanometric DR carbon graphite composition. This allows the frame to flex while snapping back into place on contact. The EZONE also features Yonex’s signature square head shape.</p>
<p>The square head increases the sweet spot of the racket compared to other rackets of its size (98 square inches). This racket also has technology that dampens vibrations from the ball, offering increased comfortability.</p>
<p>Like most of the other rackets on this list, the Yonex offers superior control and good maneuverability. While the racket lacks a bit of power, we feel it more than made up for it with its other attributes.</p>
<p>You should be able to hit good serves with this racket and have plenty of feel on the volleys. From the baseline you’ll hit good, consistent groundstrokes, especially with the larger sweet spot on the racket.</p>
<p><a href="https://amzn.to/2Q9ohXm" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Check the current price of this racket on Amazon.com</a> (affiliate link to Amazon for the exact model I’m reviewing here).</p>
<p>If you’ve never played with a Yonex before, you’ll find them to be very comfortable. My first racket was actually a Yonex, but that was back in the day. If you’re an intermediate to advanced player who swings relatively fast, this racket is a great choice.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Other Factors That Affect The Racket For S&amp;V</h2>
<p>Other factors will affect the way the racket plays. These are grip size, choice of string, string gauge, and string tension. Here are some quick guidelines on ways to determine these choices.</p>
<p><strong>Grip Size:</strong> The size of the grip is largely dependent on the person. Rafael Nadal uses one of the smallest grips on the men’s professional tour, while Juan Martin Del Potro favors a larger one. It comes down to a personal choice.</p>
<p>Most grips start at 4 inches (on the small side) and up to 4 5/8 inches on the large size. We recommend trying out different size grips before selecting one. Going too small or too large is usually a detriment. Try to choose a grip that is comfortable for your hand size.</p>
<p>As a helpful tip, if you’re already playing with a grip that’s too small, you can add an over grip to make it larger. Grips that are too large cannot be made smaller unless you change the entire grip.</p>
<p><strong>Choice Of String:</strong> Nowadays, players generally have two different choices for string material – synthetic gut or polyester. Synthetic gut is easier on the elbow and usually costs less. The feel of the string will also last longer.</p>
<p>Consequently, synthetic gut is a good choice if comfort and durability is your main concern. You’ll also spend less in restringing costs.</p>
<p>On the flip side, polyester will give more feel and bite on the ball. This results in more spin and power, which is helpful to both baseline and serve and volley players.</p>
<p>The drawbacks are that polyester loses feel after playing with it much quicker and stringing costs will be higher. Polyester is also harder on the arm, especially when strung with a high tension.</p>
<p>I personally need to restring with polyester every 3-4 weeks in comparison to 7-8 weeks with synthetic gut. Almost all professional players use polyester and there are a ton of options to choose from.</p>
<p>For serve and volley players, either string, synthetic gut or polyester, will do the job. But polyester gives more bite on the ball.</p>
<p><strong>String Gauge:</strong> This is another important factor in playability. Tennis string gauge refers to the thickness of it. The gauges vary in size from 15 to 18, with 15 being the thickest and 18 being the thinnest. Most players use a 16 or 17-gauge string.</p>
<p>The lower the gauge, the longer the string will last, but the less playability it will have. The opposite is true. The higher the gauge, the shorter the string will last but the more playability it will have.</p>
<p>I use a 16L and 17-gauge string and love it. In the past, I used regular 16-gauge string and played fairly well with it. However, the increased feel of the 17-gauge string is worth the extra time and money for me.</p>
<p>For serve and volley players, either string will work, but polyester provides more feel and spin. If you can afford the extra money, go with polyester.</p>
<p>You can try my string recommendation if you like. If you’re an avid player, the difference is a few hundred dollars a year more for using good polyester strings. Remember, all the pros use polyester.</p>
<p><strong>String Tension:</strong> This refers to how tight or loose the strings are tensioned when put into the racket. Most rackets have a recommended string tension listed on it. It may say something like “Recommended Tension: 55-65”.</p>
<p>I personally favor higher string tensions because they give more control. They’ll also last a little longer, as even when the tension drops from playing, they’ll still remain fairly tight.</p>
<p>Keep in mind that tighter tensions are not very friendly on the elbow. So if comfort is important, string lower. Most rackets give you a 10-point spread in the recommended tension. You can’t go wrong with a tension in the middle. For example, if between 55-65, string at 60.</p>
<p>After you string your racket and play with it for a few weeks, you’ll know if you need to adjust up or down. Keep in mind that small bits of tension are lost every time you play.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>I find that the first few times of play don’t necessarily give a good indication of the strings. If you string tight, you need to hit with the racket a few times before the strings “break in” and you can honestly assess them.</p>
<p>If you use polyester and play often with the same strings, you may notice they ultimately become unresponsive and have a “dead” feel. That’s when you need to restring. If you continue playing with such strings, you’re likely to hurt your elbow and be an unhappy camper.</p>
<p>I personally favor polyester and go with a hybrid 16L and 17-gauge string with a high tension (around 63-65).</p>
<p><strong>Main Strings:</strong> Signum Pro Plasma HEXtreme Pure 16L String &#8211; <a href="https://amzn.to/2PjmI3I" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Check the current price on Amazon.com</a> (affiliate link to Amazon for the exact model I’m recommending here).</p>
<p><strong>Cross Strings:</strong> Diadem Evolution 17 (1.25) String (Azure Blue) &#8211; <a href="https://amzn.to/2PePqTq" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Check the current price on Amazon.com</a> (affiliate link to Amazon for the exact model I’m recommending here).</p>
<p>The post <a href="/the-best-5-rackets-for-serve-and-volley-in-2018/">The Best 5 Tennis Rackets For Serve And Volley In 2018</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/the-best-5-rackets-for-serve-and-volley-in-2018/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Learn How To Serve In 10 Minutes With The ServeMaster</title>
		<link>/learn-how-to-serve-in-10-minutes-with-the-servemaster/</link>
					<comments>/learn-how-to-serve-in-10-minutes-with-the-servemaster/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chad Walner]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 23 Oct 2018 18:46:28 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Reviews]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[serve]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=831</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The serve is the most complicated stroke in tennis. It’s also one of the most difficult to teach. Until now. If you’re not familiar with the ServeMaster by Total Serve, this article could potentially be your gateway to the serve &#8230; <a class="kt-excerpt-readmore" href="/learn-how-to-serve-in-10-minutes-with-the-servemaster/" aria-label="Learn How To Serve In 10 Minutes With The ServeMaster">Read More</a></p>
<p>The post <a href="/learn-how-to-serve-in-10-minutes-with-the-servemaster/">Learn How To Serve In 10 Minutes With The ServeMaster</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The serve is the most complicated stroke in tennis. It’s also one of the most difficult to teach. Until now. If you’re not familiar with the <strong>ServeMaster by Total Serve</strong>, this article could potentially be your gateway to the serve you’ve always wanted. Whether you are a beginner learning how to serve in tennis, or if you have been playing for years but never properly learning the effective serve mechanics, this post is for you.</p>
<p><strong>This post could even save years of time and a lot of cash on expensive lessons. Keep reading if you want to learn how to serve or how to improve your serve in just 10 minutes! The results I’ve seen with the Total Serve never cease to impress me. In this article, I’m going to show you how to use it and a few great drills you can use it for on improving your serves and even your overheads. </strong></p>
<p>In my years of coaching and playing, I’ve seen many kids and club players struggle with their serve for all kinds of reasons. Often, the problem is a bad toss coupled with poor serve mechanics. I can often narrow it down to a much more specific hitch like not hitting up on the ball or a lack of knee bend.</p>
<p>There are so many things that could go wrong with a serve and they are typically difficult pinpoint and then to correct. If you address one issue, it creates another one. I honestly don’t even know how players learned to serve quickly before the ServeMaster was invented. It’s such a useful tool for both adults and kids. Anyone, no matter what their level, can use it.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>What Is The ServeMaster?</h2>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1456" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/smWhat-Is-The-ServeMaster.jpg" alt="What is the servemaster?" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/smWhat-Is-The-ServeMaster.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/smWhat-Is-The-ServeMaster-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/smWhat-Is-The-ServeMaster-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p>The ServeMaster is a teaching tool for the serve and overhead strokes in tennis. It was created by a former professional tennis player named Lisa Dodson. It’s made entirely of rubber. It includes a rubber handle attached to a rubber rope with options for one, two, or three rubber balls at the end. The grip was created for both righties and lefties and teaches the continental grip, which is used on all advanced tennis serves. There are three options to choose from when purchasing the ServeMaster. I’ll go over all three here.</p>
<ul>
<li>The device with one ball is excellent for young children up to ages 10-12.</li>
<li>The device created with two balls will work for kids 12 and up. Adults can easily use this device as well. I personally use the two-ball ServeMaster to warm up before a match.</li>
<li>The third device is made with three balls and is ideal for stronger or bigger adults. The three-ball device, at about 16 oz (or one pound), is great for using as a warm up before serving. Use it for a minute and your racket (typically 10-13 oz) will feel super light when you serve. This is the heaviest of the three ServeMasters.</li>
</ul>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="kad-youtube-shortcode videofit"  ><iframe loading="lazy" width="600" height="400" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/PA5rfvjj7L4?autoplay=0&controls=1&fs=1&modestbranding=1&theme=dark&rel=0&loop=0&showinfo=1" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="true"></iframe></div>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>If you’re an adult new to tennis, I would recommend you purchase the two-ball ServeMaster, as it’s easier to work with than the three-ball model.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.thetotalserve.com/?aff=17" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Check the current price of the ServeMaster here.</a></p>
<p>The ServeMaster is simple, durable, and fun to use. Many tennis coaches, as well as myself, use it with their students. When I teach the tennis serve to a child or beginner, it’s the first thing I use with my students. We’ll get into why next.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Why Is The ServeMaster Effective?</h2>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1457" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/smWhy-Is-The-ServeMaster-Effective.jpg" alt="Why is the ServeMater effective?" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/smWhy-Is-The-ServeMaster-Effective.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/smWhy-Is-The-ServeMaster-Effective-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/smWhy-Is-The-ServeMaster-Effective-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p>In my opinion, The ServeMaster is the most effective training tool for the serve on the market, period. First and foremost, it teaches the student to feel and use the continental grip, which is extremely important for advanced serves. It does this with check marks on the grip.</p>
<p>The advanced tennis serve requires the continental grip. If not used, an advanced serve is just not possible. I also like that both righties and lefties can use the ServeMaster. I’ve personally seen both righties and lefties benefit from the tool equally well.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>The ServeMaster is designed to simulate the feel of the racket with most of the weight being on the end. This gives the user the feeling or experience of how to move the arm and coordinate the body so that it’s in motion the entire time – just like a racket would be while in play. If the practitioner stops or slows their arm, the balls at the end of the device will hit their back. This lets the practitioner know that the swing is not the one fluid motion which it should be.</p>
<p>This amazing device will simulate every part of the serve, including the all-important racket drop. The racket drop is an essential technique which so many adult club players struggle with in their serve. It is when the racket drops into what many players know as the “scratch your back” position. <strong>The ServeMaster can cure this flaw quickly and forever!</strong></p>
<p>Cleverly, the ServeMaster also teaches pronation! How the heck can it do this? I didn’t think that was possible to do with such a simple device. But yet it does. <strong>Pronation is one of the most confusing and misunderstood concepts in tennis.</strong> If you want to know exactly what it is, I wrote about <a href="/beginners-serve-vs-advanced-tennis-serve-what-are-the-differences/">pronation in a recent article</a>.</p>
<p>It can be difficult to apply the concept of pronation in your serve. The cool thing about the ServeMaster is that you don’t even need to know what pronation is, but by using the ServeMaster, it automatically forces you to pronate. For this reason alone, it’s worth the buy.</p>
<p>The weight and length of the ServeMaster makes it a bit cumbersome to use at first. But once the practitioner learns the proper swing path, it’s very easy to use. We’ll go over how to use it a little later on. Once the proper swing path is learned, the practitioner can then incorporate the other components of the serve. These are the toss, the knee bend, the drive up, and the follow through.</p>
<p>I know this next part may sound like hyperbole. But I’ve taught kids as young as eight to have a beautiful serve motion within half an hour. To swing the ServeMaster, proper serving mechanics are essential. Once the kids master the swing, all you need do is put a racket in their hand and they’ll mimic the perfect swing mechanics with the racket. While it’s true, that doesn’t guarantee kids or adults will have an awesome serve in one day. This is because of the other components of the serve.</p>
<p>The player who wants to master their serve must work hard on the other basics, like the toss. And the timing of racket hitting the ball is very crucial as well. That’s where a lot of practice is necessary. But at least the most difficult part of teaching the serve is done, which is the basic motion.</p>
<p>Before learning of the ServeMaster, I tried to manually teach kids and adults how to serve. I did this in a variety of ways. One of my favorite tricks was to have them toss a tennis ball in one hand and throw it with the other (simulating the toss and racket motion). However, none of my training tactics were nearly as effective as the ServeMaster.</p>
<p>I can literally teach a kid how to use the ServeMaster in 5-10 minutes, then take it away and place a racket in their hand. I then ask the child to toss an imaginary ball and swing with the racket. Voila! The perfect serve motion in 10 minutes! It never ceases to amaze me when I see it. From there, we can work on the toss and their timing.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>How A Beginner Can Use The ServeMaster</h2>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1458" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/smHow-A-Beginner-Can-Use-The-ServeMaster.jpg" alt="How can a beginner use the ServeMaster?" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/smHow-A-Beginner-Can-Use-The-ServeMaster.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/smHow-A-Beginner-Can-Use-The-ServeMaster-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/smHow-A-Beginner-Can-Use-The-ServeMaster-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p>To use the ServeMaster all you need is a tennis court. No ball, racket or special equipment is needed. If you don’t have access to a tennis court, you can use your backyard or an outdoor area that allows a radius of 25 feet from the user. Here is how Lisa Dodson, the creator of the ServeMaster, advises beginners to use it. Later in this post, I talk about the advanced version.</p>
<ol>
<li>Start by gripping the ServeMaster. The ServeMaster is labeled “R” on one side of the grip. This is for righties. The other side is labeled “L” for lefties. Each side has two “V” shapes on it that indicate where the hand is to be placed. See the picture on the side for a visual. Basically, the crease between your thumb and index finger will be on the V. The key here is to have the base or bottom of your hand hanging off the grip. Keep a light grip on the ServeMaster – avoid tensing up and gripping hard.</li>
<li>Once you properly grip the ServeMaster, swing it gently at your side. You’ll feel how the weight of the balls shift your hand with the momentum they create. Do this for 30-60 seconds just to feel it.</li>
<li>Next, set up in the proper serve stance with feet in a platform position. The lead foot should be at a 45-degree angle to the baseline and the back foot parallel to the baseline. For righties, the toe of the back foot should be slightly to the left of the lead (left) foot. Lefties can do the opposite.</li>
<li>The hand that is holding the ServeMaster will be raised up so that the part of your arm containing your biceps and triceps is about parallel to the ground. Your arm will look like it’s in a throwing motion with your hand around the middle of your head and close to it. At this point the balls should be dangling behind your back.</li>
<li>If you’re a right-handed player, put your left tossing arm straight up in the air. Keep it there for now. Lefties, do the opposite of all the instructions I give here. Gracias.</li>
<li>Swing your right arm up by fully extending it upwards. At this point your left arm will begin to drop by your left side. Allow the swinging right arm to finish at the left side of your body. Don’t swing ultra-fast. A nice, controlled swing is what’s important here. If you do it right, you should be able to catch the balls with your left hand. That’s it!</li>
</ol>
<p>These six steps are how all beginners and children should start learning with the ServeMaster. This motion mimics the tossing arm staying high up in the air, which most club players and bad servers don’t do. It also trains the body to use the basic swing path of all advanced serves. It’s important the swing contains no hitches. If you stop the motion at any point, the balls will likely hit your body. You’ll then know you are not swinging correctly. Bam – instant feedback! Don’t worry it doesn’t hurt.</p>
<p>A couple of key points that Lisa mentions in her videos is the use of the left hand and right leg in the serve (for righties). The left arm’s purpose is not only for tossing but for creating momentum for the body to raise up. It does this by coming down and to the left side. At the same time, the right leg is pushing off the ground, propelling the hitting arm and body upwards.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>Not to burden you with a thousand things, but there are more key points Lisa mentions. Here are two: keeping your head up and hitting out in front. You’ll want to keep your head, or chin, up during the swing up to contact. If the head drops, the body will likely drop too, not allowing for contact at maximum height. It’s always best to hit the serve at maximum contact point within your abilities; some people jump higher than others.</p>
<p>Lisa also stresses hitting the serve out in front. During your swing, the highest point of the balls will be the contact point on the ball. In this exercise we’re not using a ball, so I just wanted to point that out. It’s vital to not just swing up, but out (meaning in the court) as well.</p>
<p>The last thing I’ll mention in this part of the instructions is pronation. I told you earlier that the ServeMaster teaches proper pronation naturally. For righties, when you begin the swing make sure your palm is facing to the left. As you swing up, your palm will turn to face the court directly at impact (the zenith of the swing). Right after you reach the zenith, your palm will start moving to the right. After it does, just continue your motion in that position, with the right arm finishing its follow through to the left side of the body.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Advanced Use Of The ServeMaster</h2>
<p>Once you master the basic swing path just explained, you can begin to practice the complete serve motion. This will incorporate an actual toss, take back, and knee bend. Follow these instructions for the advanced use of the ServeMaster. Remember, they are written for the right-handed player. Lefties just use the opposite hand or arm.</p>
<ol>
<li>Start with “rope” part of the ServeMaster in your left hand while holding the ServeMaster about waist height in front of you with your dominant hand on the grip.</li>
<li>Let go of the ServeMaster with your left hand and begin a tossing motion, with your left hand going straight up in the air.</li>
<li>At the same time, move the right arm back and into the same “L-Shape” position you started from in the last series of steps (for beginners).</li>
<li>Keep the right arm constantly moving after you begin the swing. Once the balls drop behind your back, you can then lower your left hand (the tossing hand).</li>
<li>As the tossing hand lowers to your left side, the right hand will extend upwards and outwards, like you’re tossing a football. From this point on, the swing path is the same as the beginner method. The main difference is that you’ll have more momentum here and should leave the ground slightly and move into the court.</li>
<li>Do this by jumping (a few inches off the ground is fine) onto your left foot. For those who can’t jump, you can just step forward with your right foot, using your left foot as a pivot.</li>
</ol>
<p>All the top professional players that serve with their right hand land on their left foot. So if you have no physical limitations, you should always land with your weight on the left foot.</p>
<p>When you first start this more advanced method, it’s acceptable to not do part 6 of the above instructions. Just practice steps 1-5 without the jump to get the feel of the swing. Once you have it, you can then incorporate step 6.</p>
<p>A few important key are to be noted here. One, bend your knees when you reach the L-Shape position with your arm. You should remain with bent knees (90 degrees is the ideal) while the dominant hand begins to drop out of the L-Shape. Once the arm begins the forward part of the swing, you should be uncoiling and slightly jumping forward and up. Your legs will obviously be extended at this point.</p>
<p>It’s also important to make sure your left shoulder is higher than your right shoulder while the tossing hand is at its zenith. At impact (if you were hitting a real ball) the right shoulder will be high and the left lower. After you complete the swing, the left shoulder will then be higher once again. This is a cartwheel motion and creates a lot of power on the serve.</p>
<p>One other important point is to keep looking up when you toss and don’t allow your body to sink down. Many club players drop their chins, not keeping their head up at impact, which causes them to hit lower than the maximum impact point. I know I said that earlier in the post, but I have to reiterate to make sure you do not lower your head.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Summary</h2>
<p>The beginning phase of the ServeMaster can be mastered relatively quickly. If you have coordination, 5-10 minutes should be good enough. The advanced method will take a little longer, maybe 10-15 minutes of practice a few times. Once you achieve the whole swing, there isn’t much room to deviate. No ball or racket is involved with the using the ServeMaster, so it really cuts down on the complexity.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.thetotalserve.com/?aff=17" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Check the current price of the ServeMaster here.</a></p>
<p>When you feel that you can complete the correct swing over-and-over and it doesn’t feel like a challenge anymore, you can begin to try with a racket and ball. You may want to try with the racket at first and no ball. Do this for a few minutes. Next, you can pick up a tennis ball and toss it during the motion. However, I have a little trick that will help you here.</p>
<p>Instead of tossing to hit the ball, clearly toss the ball far to your right and out of your reach. Complete the rest of your swing as if the ball was perfectly tossed. The reason for this is to allow your body the feel of tossing while still completing the perfect swing. With your mind not focused on hitting the ball, you can focus on the swing.</p>
<p>The final step is to actually toss into good position to hit the ball – just like a real serve. At first don’t worry where the ball goes. The most important thing here to continue the proper swing. Slowly you’ll make better contact and time your toss appropriately. The toss will really dictate how good your serve will be. You need to time your toss so that by the time your racket reaches the impact point, the ball will be at that spot. That’s really the tricky part of this whole deal.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>Keep practicing. If you find that your swing is falling off tossing a real tennis ball, go back to the advanced method, practice that, and then come back to the real serve. Even if you start to hit great serves, I still recommend using the ServeMaster to practice your form. If you had a terrible serve to begin with, you will now see a marked difference in your serve. And all this can happen in just a few sessions of using the ServeMaster. You should now have a good racket drop, pronate and reach up to the hit the ball. Don’t underestimate using video. Video your swing when you go out and compare as you progress.</p>
<p>Let me know how it goes. If you have any questions, drop them in comment box below. Thanks for reading!</p>
<p>The post <a href="/learn-how-to-serve-in-10-minutes-with-the-servemaster/">Learn How To Serve In 10 Minutes With The ServeMaster</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/learn-how-to-serve-in-10-minutes-with-the-servemaster/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Lobster Elite Liberty Ball Machine Review</title>
		<link>/lobster-elite-liberty-ball-machine-review/</link>
					<comments>/lobster-elite-liberty-ball-machine-review/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chad Walner]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 14 Oct 2018 11:18:21 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Reviews]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=740</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>This is my honest review of the Lobster Elite Liberty Ball Machine. To me, this is the best tennis ball machine on the market for the price, which is why I bought it. I had been looking around for a &#8230; <a class="kt-excerpt-readmore" href="/lobster-elite-liberty-ball-machine-review/" aria-label="Lobster Elite Liberty Ball Machine Review">Read More</a></p>
<p>The post <a href="/lobster-elite-liberty-ball-machine-review/">Lobster Elite Liberty Ball Machine Review</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This is my honest review of the Lobster Elite Liberty Ball Machine. To me, this is the best tennis ball machine on the market for the price, which is why I bought it. I had been looking around for a tennis ball machine but didn’t want to spend the money until making the best possible choice.</p>
<p><strong>I’ve had the machine now for a year and a half and I absolutely love it! I’ve had no issues with it thus far and it’s met my expectations – and made me a better player. In this review I talk in detail about the ball machine and all its pluses and minuses (of which there are not many). In general, the Lobster Elite Liberty is a well-made machine, study and durable.</strong></p>
<p>If you want to know the important specs on the machine before going into the review, here they are:</p>
<ul>
<li>Weight – 35 lbs.</li>
<li>Dimensions – 24” long x 14” wide x 21” tall</li>
<li>Battery Life – 2-3 hours or more depending on the features you use while training</li>
<li>Ball Capacity – 150 balls</li>
<li>Ball Speed – 10-70 mph</li>
<li>Ball Spin – Top, Back and Flat</li>
<li>Elevation – 0-50 degrees (manual)</li>
<li>Oscillation – Random horizontal</li>
<li>Price</li>
</ul>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Why Consider Buying A Ball Machine?</h2>
<p>If you’re looking to improve your game, there are no better ways to do so. When I hit with the ball machine, it’s like being a scientist in a laboratory. I can experiment with all different grips, strokes, stances and follow-throughs. And I never have to worry about calling someone to practice with me. The Lobster is the perfect practice partner.</p>
<p>The cost of a ball machine makes some people pause, but if you are an avid player it can really make sense. Consider:</p>
<ul>
<li>Rapid Improvement &#8211; Most new techniques require a lot of practice before you start seeing the benefit. Having a ball machine deliver consistent balls to you allows you to experiment and dramatically broaden your repertoire of hits.</li>
<li>Take Control &#8211; Practice at any time without having to coordinate with a partner.</li>
<li>Reduced Coaching Costs &#8211; If you have a ball machine, any advice you get from your tennis coach can be practiced repeatedly in a controlled environment, over and over again, while the coach is off the clock, giving you tremendous value for your coaching dollar.</li>
</ul>
<p>I like to practice in the early evening, when the sun is setting. I’ll often take my phone and a couple of portable speakers to the court with my ball machine. I put on my music, turn on the Lobster and have a private tennis party. It’s a lot of fun, I get to improve and have a great work out.</p>
<p><a href="https://amzn.to/2UcYzzq" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Check the current price of the Lobster Elite Liberty ball machine on Amazon.com</a> (affiliate link to Amazon for the exact model I’m reviewing here).</p>
<p>If you’re a tennis coach, a ball machine is a very useful tool for learning tennis. I’ve used the Lobster countless times in lessons. Some of my students only want to hit on the ball machine and pay me my regular lesson rate for it. I bring the machine to my courts or theirs. In an hour’s time, they can usually hit 600 balls, which is four runs on the Lobster.</p>
<p>Sometimes I video them and they watch the replay while I pick up the balls and put them back in the machine. I’ve already paid for the machine two times over with the number of times I’ve used it in lessons – with both kids and adults.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="kad-youtube-shortcode videofit"  ><iframe loading="lazy" width="600" height="400" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/LkWJbhJrRiA?autoplay=0&controls=1&fs=1&modestbranding=1&theme=dark&rel=0&loop=0&showinfo=1" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="true"></iframe></div>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Usability Of The Machine</h2>
<p>I’ve been using this machine consistently for a year and a half now with zero issues. I’ve jostled the machine around, got caught in the rain several times with it, and left it in my car for days in the Florida summer with no problems. Before I use the machine, I charge it for several hours and then hit the courts.</p>
<p>When I’m on the court, I dial up the settings to my preference and then turn the machine on. The Lobster Elite Liberty waits 15 seconds after you turn the machine on to fire out the first ball. This is so you can walk to the other side of the court. I think this is a great feature, as no balls need to be wasted, and 15 seconds is enough time to walk to the other side of the court.</p>
<p>One of the best things of this machine is the seamless way it fires out balls. It’s just one after another with no delays or hitches until the final few balls are left. This delay at the very end is due to the final few balls making their way around the rotation before being dropped in the hatch. However, this is completely understandable when only two or three balls remain.</p>
<p>The distance and speed of the balls are consistent all through 150 balls except for possibly the first 4-5. The first 4-5 balls come just a little stronger and then the machine settles into a very consistent feed. The only time that changes is when the battery gets very low. At that point, I know the machine is almost done with its charge and I turn it off. But I’ll hit over 1000 balls before that point is reached.</p>
<p>One last point about the consistency of the balls. Keep in mind that if you’re using different types of balls (various brands, clay court, hard court, practice balls) the pressure of each one will be slightly different. This will result in some bouncing stronger to you than others. However, as long as the balls are not dead, they’ll bounce to you fairly consistent. The machine can handle any type of adult tennis ball: clay, hard court, practice, etc.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Ball Capacity</h2>
<p>The machine holds 150 balls, which is quite a lot once you start practicing. When I transport the machine, I keep the gray lid flipped down. Once I get the machine to the court, I flip the gray lid, it pops in with no tools required, and now its ready for the balls. I pour about 150 balls into the lid and I’m ready to go.</p>
<p>Lobster makes four higher model ball machines (which are all significantly more money) but all still have a ball capacity of 150 balls. I checked other similar priced ball machines on the market, but no other machine has a higher ball capacity for the price than the Lobster Elite Liberty.</p>
<p>If you set the machine to spit out a ball every 3.5 seconds, it’ll take you almost nine minutes to go through all 150 balls. Believe me, that’s quite a work out. If you go nine minutes straight, you’ll look forward to taking a break. If you’re older or not in shape, you can set the machine to spit out balls at longer intervals. Personally, I find 3-4 second intervals to be the best.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Portability And Storage</h2>
<p>The Lobster Elite Liberty Ball Machine is compact enough to be taken around in almost any vehicle. I have a Toyota Matrix hatchback and it safely goes in the back and is easy to place inside and take out. The gray plastic bin on the ball machine can be flipped down – as well as the handle &#8211; to make it more compact.</p>
<p>I also have a two-door Honda Accord. In my two-door car, it can fit in the front seat. The weight of the machine is 35 lbs., so it requires just a bit of muscle to maneuver, but nothing an able-bodied man or woman couldn’t do.</p>
<p>The machine is only two feet long and 21 inches tall, so storing it in my 1300 square foot condo is no problem. If space is an issue for you, and you don’t want the machine out in the open, it can easily fit into a standard size closet. Most people who can afford a ball machine will likely store it in their garage though.</p>
<p>As far as transporting, the machine offers great portability with its big wheels and long handle. The handle is retractable and can be set up or down. When transporting, you can place the handle up and simply roll the machine, which requires very little effort. The Lobster Elite Liberty Ball Machine is really made to roll over a smooth surface, so one drawback is that it’s difficult to roll on mulch or grass. However, the same can be said for almost any ball machine.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Charging</h2>
<p>The Lobster Elite Liberty requires about 3-6 hours to completely charge – at least mine does. It has a small spot by the controls where you plug in the charger and then plug the power part of it into any standard two-pronged outlet. The specs say that the basic charger that comes with the machine takes 18-24 hours to recharge.</p>
<p>Mine recharges in several hours, so I may have purchased the optional premium charger. I recommend the premium charger if you buy the machine, as it’s a lot quicker. One charge will allow 2-4 hours of play on the court. If you still have battery life left after play, I believe the charge will dissipate slightly over time if you don’t keep it charged.</p>
<p>For this reason, it’s good to keep the Lobster fully charged after you play. Once the machine is fully charged, a green light will appear. You can then unplug the machine and leave it unplugged. If a red light appears when you turn the machine on, it means it needs to be charged.</p>
<p>It’s also important to charge it at least once or twice a month. If you forget to charge the machine for several months, the battery could die and you would need to purchase a new one from Lobster. So far I’ve not had to do that.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>The Settings</h2>
<p>The Lobster Elite Liberty basically has five different setting options. I’ll go through each one here. I just want to say that I don’t believe it’s necessary to have any additional setting options on the machine. The five on the machine are really all you need to have great practice sessions.</p>
<h4><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-751 alignright" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/lobster-elite-liberty-gauges.jpg" alt="" width="400" height="320" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/lobster-elite-liberty-gauges.jpg 400w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/lobster-elite-liberty-gauges-300x240.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" />Spin</h4>
<p>The machine can fire out balls completely flat (no spin) or with underspin or topspin. This to me is one of the greatest features of the Lobster. I usually leave it on topspin at a setting near +2, as I believe this simulates the shots I play against the most. If you’re a beginner, you could try flat or +1. It’s a little easier to hit flat shots or those with a small amount of spin than heavier topspin.</p>
<p>I find that anything more than +3 is too much topspin unless you’re training for Rafael Nadal. I rarely use the underspin feature, though that is the ideal setting for practice against slices. Overall, the spin feature is one of the best settings on the machine and makes it very versatile.</p>
<h4>Speed</h4>
<p>This is the setting that controls the velocity of the ball. The Lobster Elite Liberty can shoot out balls between 10-70 mph, although the guage on the control panel it can go up to 80 mph! I usually put it at between 60-70 for baseline groundstrokes, which is plenty fast. I set the ball machine on the opposing baseline when hitting and it simulates another person very well.</p>
<p>I also use the machine for practicing my volleys – which I do quite frequently. For volleys, there’s really nothing better than a ball machine. It will put the ball right around the same place every time. This is ideal when you really want to groove a stroke like the volley. It’s helped my backhand volley immensely. When I’m at net, I’ll place the ball machine on the opposing baseline and set the speed to around 50-55 mph.</p>
<p>If you’re a total beginner, you could put the speed down to 30-40 mph to give yourself plenty of time to set up. I’ve used the machine with kids and adults who are beginners and they all love it. It gives them consistent speeds to hit, which are important when first learning.</p>
<h4>Feed</h4>
<p>This is the amount of time between ball feeds. I usually set it at “10-12” on the machine, which is about a 3-4 second interval. I find at this rate, I can hit a ball and have a couple of seconds before the next one comes. If you really want a workout, you can set the interval even lower and have balls shoot out one-after-another.<br />
I often use the machine with my clients, and I find the Lobster gives more than enough time between hits if on the slowest feed rate. Even 70-year-old out of shape guys don’t have to wait more than 5 seconds between hits. It sounds low but when you’re standing there waiting for the ball, it’s not. I find the feed rate to be a very useful setting on the machine.</p>
<h4>Horizontal</h4>
<p>The Lobster Elite Liberty tennis ball machine has a setting called “Horizontal”. This allows the machine to oscillate from side-to-side and will hit balls to both your forehand and backhand wings. I really like this feature because it simulates a real match, where you will be moving from side-to-side.</p>
<p>To use this feature, simply set the machine to horizontal and it will begin moving side-to-side spitting out balls at random. If you specifically want one ball to the forehand, then one ball to backhand repeated to the same spots, then you&#8217;ll need to coordinate this with the feed rate to achieve the ball delivery you want. But that’s easy enough. The first time you use the horizontal feature, you may have to adjust the feed. But once you do, you’re good to go.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>I use the horizontal feature often. I find that it adds variety to my practice sessions with the randomness of it. I also use this feature for volley practice at the net, which is great because I can never quite tell where exactly the ball will be.</p>
<h4>Elevation</h4>
<p>The Lobster Elite Liberty has a 0 to 50-degree elevation setting. You can change the degree of elevation with a small black knob on the right side of the machine. If you turn the knob clockwise, the elevation goes up. Turn it counter-clockwise and it will go down. The machine has the degrees listed on the front and uses a gray plastic stick to gauge them. Personally, I removed the gray plastic stick (which can be easily taken off) and judge the elevation by view. But if you know, for example, that 25 degrees is the perfect elevation for you, then just leave the stick on, as it will give you an exact measurement.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<blockquote><p>I find that having the perfect practice session with the Lobster is easy. Simple adjustments in the speed, spin, and height of the ball are all that’s necessary. When I’m at the baseline, I typically have an elevation of around 15-20 degrees. When I’m at the net, I’ll go 5-10 degrees lower, depending where I want to hit the volley.</p></blockquote>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>For lobs, I find that 50 degrees (the highest possible) is generally not enough to simulate a typical lob I’ll face in a match. I’ve found an easy solution to change that though. All you need to do is place something under the machine like a tennis ball can, and it will elevate it an additional 10-20 degrees. This is enough to simulate high lobs. I’ve used this tactic many times and it works flawlessly.</p>
<p>The more expensive Lobster machines all have 60-degree elevations with electronic controls. However, I find the additional hundreds of dollars you need to spend is not worth the extra 10 degrees or the electronic controls. It’s very easy to turn the elevation knob and you really won’t end up doing it that often anyway.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Maintenance And Safety</h2>
<p>There’s really no maintenance required on the machine. Other than charging it at least once or twice a month, you can simply let it be. The battery in the machine should be good for at least two years if you use and charge the machine regularly.</p>
<p>The one optional maintenance you could perform is vacuum or clean out the tennis ball fuzz that accumulates in the machine. Since I’ve had the machine, I’ve used in on average a couple of times per week and have never cleaned it. It still operates the same way as the first day I used it and I’ve never done anything but charge it.</p>
<p>I should mention that it’s not wise to leave the ball machine in a hot car for days on end. Lobster says this can short-circuit the machine. However, I’ve left the machine in my car for a couple of days at a time in 90+ degree Florida heat with no issues. I certainly wouldn’t leave it any longer than a couple of days though.</p>
<p>As far as safety is concerned, the only caution would be not to walk in front of the machine when it’s on. You also might want to make sure the ball speed is not too fast by watching a shot or two come out before trying to hit. This is particularly true when kids use the Lobster or when you’re volleying at the net.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Why I Believe More Expensive Models Are Unnecessary</h2>
<p>I’ve already mentioned a few times why I thought the four more expensive models are unnecessary. The next most expensive model is the Lobster Elite One. For a couple of hundred dollars more you get longer battery life (double the time), 10 degrees more of elevation with an electronic setting, and 10 mph more of speed.  Overall, I don’t think these extras are worth the additional money unless you plan to be on the court for hours and hours on end. The drawback to the Lobster Elite One, besides the extra cost, is that it weighs 42 lbs., which is 7 lbs. more than the Elite Liberty.</p>
<p><a href="https://amzn.to/2UcYzzq" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Check the current price of the Lobster Elite Liberty ball machine on Amazon.com</a> (affiliate link to Amazon for the exact model I’m reviewing here).</p>
<p>The three other models, Elite Two, Elite Three, and Elite Grand Four, all go up in price and offer additional features, such as random vertical oscillation and two-line function. The Elite Grand Four (which costs $1000 more than the Elite Liberty) offers the most options, the best of which is 6-preloaded drills. While the additional features are helpful in the superior models, they may not be worth the cost if you are simply looking for a basic machine at an affordable price.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Bottom Line</h2>
<p>For my money, the Lobster Elite Liberty does everything I need it to. I can work on any shot (forehand, backhand, slice, volleys, overheads, drop shots, short ball put-aways, etc.) with the options the Elite Liberty offers. I like that it’s reliable, compact, and quiet on the court. It does the job and takes a licking and keeps on ticking.</p>
<p>What more can I say? I highly recommend this tennis ball machine for anyone looking to purchase one. You’ll love it.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>The Optional Remote</h2>
<p>I just want to add that an optional remote control is available for the machine. I bought it but have not installed it yet. I believe the price I paid was around $65. It only does two things – turn the machine on and off and pause the machine. I bought the remote because I believe the pause function is excellent to have when teaching. I will update this post once the remote is installed.<br />
If you have any questions or concerns about the machine, please leave me a comment below. I’ll be glad to answer them.</p>
<p>The post <a href="/lobster-elite-liberty-ball-machine-review/">Lobster Elite Liberty Ball Machine Review</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/lobster-elite-liberty-ball-machine-review/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>2</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
