<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: How To Hit A Tennis Lob	</title>
	<atom:link href="/how-to-hit-a-tennis-lob/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/how-to-hit-a-tennis-lob/</link>
	<description>Your secret weapon on the court.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 28 Jul 2020 13:21:50 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	
	<item>
		<title>
		By: Rob Millsop		</title>
		<link>/how-to-hit-a-tennis-lob/#comment-359</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Rob Millsop]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 28 Jul 2020 13:21:50 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1553#comment-359</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[This was pretty half-assed in terms of the critical technical aspects of lobbing effectively.  Be reminded that your audience most likely is the club level (3.0--4.5) player.  You completely fail to explain the necessary grip(s) required to effectively hit the topspin and the slice/block lob. And--you should have emphasized that for all but the most elite players--the ball they would best attempt to lob would be coming towards them w/o a great deal of pace and by necessity would bounce up for them to hit at between upper thigh and shoulder height--otherwise their rate of success on a lower, faster paced ball would be virtually nil.  Staying with the forehand--you should have emphasized how important it is in doubles for the deuce-side returner, especially, to be competent in using the slice lob on the return of serve.  Since about 90% of your opponents will be right-handed..and likely his net man is right handed--the lob down the line is essential to keep the net player honest in his approach to poaching..and better yet, it causes the server to now have to change his aggressiveness in coming forward after the serve..plus the server will likely have to cross over to hit a backhand either out of the air..or off the bounce.  It&#039;s ludicrous for you not to explain that a topspin lob off of a serve is nearly impossible to successfully execute.
   And your nonsense about hitting a one-handed  topspin lob...granted an accomplished two-hander can hit a topspin lob effectively on a ball down by their knees--their top hand along with being able to rotate around their spine on the swing, makes the shot possible...to even attempt a one-handed backhand lob except in the rarest of circumstances (slow ball at chest height..on clay or an equally slow surface where the ball sits up)--is a complete fool&#039;s errand.  
   I could continue..but suffice it to say--this &quot;column&quot; was incredibly ill-informed and filled with either poor advice, incomplete instruction, or just a lack of understanding of how and when the LOB can and should be utilized.  Feel free to show this critique to any knowledgeable instructor, and I&#039;m confident they will be in complete agreement with me.  I appreciate good instruction...This was not that!]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This was pretty half-assed in terms of the critical technical aspects of lobbing effectively.  Be reminded that your audience most likely is the club level (3.0&#8211;4.5) player.  You completely fail to explain the necessary grip(s) required to effectively hit the topspin and the slice/block lob. And&#8211;you should have emphasized that for all but the most elite players&#8211;the ball they would best attempt to lob would be coming towards them w/o a great deal of pace and by necessity would bounce up for them to hit at between upper thigh and shoulder height&#8211;otherwise their rate of success on a lower, faster paced ball would be virtually nil.  Staying with the forehand&#8211;you should have emphasized how important it is in doubles for the deuce-side returner, especially, to be competent in using the slice lob on the return of serve.  Since about 90% of your opponents will be right-handed..and likely his net man is right handed&#8211;the lob down the line is essential to keep the net player honest in his approach to poaching..and better yet, it causes the server to now have to change his aggressiveness in coming forward after the serve..plus the server will likely have to cross over to hit a backhand either out of the air..or off the bounce.  It&#8217;s ludicrous for you not to explain that a topspin lob off of a serve is nearly impossible to successfully execute.<br />
   And your nonsense about hitting a one-handed  topspin lob&#8230;granted an accomplished two-hander can hit a topspin lob effectively on a ball down by their knees&#8211;their top hand along with being able to rotate around their spine on the swing, makes the shot possible&#8230;to even attempt a one-handed backhand lob except in the rarest of circumstances (slow ball at chest height..on clay or an equally slow surface where the ball sits up)&#8211;is a complete fool&#8217;s errand.<br />
   I could continue..but suffice it to say&#8211;this &#8220;column&#8221; was incredibly ill-informed and filled with either poor advice, incomplete instruction, or just a lack of understanding of how and when the LOB can and should be utilized.  Feel free to show this critique to any knowledgeable instructor, and I&#8217;m confident they will be in complete agreement with me.  I appreciate good instruction&#8230;This was not that!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
