<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>volley Archives - Serve and Volley Tennis</title>
	<atom:link href="/tag/volley/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/tag/volley/</link>
	<description>Your secret weapon on the court.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 15 Aug 2019 10:05:36 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	

<image>
	<url>/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/cropped-ted_svt_favicon-32x32.png</url>
	<title>volley Archives - Serve and Volley Tennis</title>
	<link>/tag/volley/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>What Are The 8 Basic Tennis Shots?</title>
		<link>/what-are-the-8-basic-tennis-shots/</link>
					<comments>/what-are-the-8-basic-tennis-shots/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chad Walner]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 04 Jan 2019 19:56:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Theory]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[backhand]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[dropshot]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[forehand]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[lob]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[overhead]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[serve]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[slice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[volley]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1862</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The game of tennis might seem complicated for those new to it, but it can essentially be broken down into 8 basic shots. All 8 shots need to be mastered to excel and proceed to the higher levels of tennis. &#8230; <a class="kt-excerpt-readmore" href="/what-are-the-8-basic-tennis-shots/" aria-label="What Are The 8 Basic Tennis Shots?">Read More</a></p>
<p>The post <a href="/what-are-the-8-basic-tennis-shots/">What Are The 8 Basic Tennis Shots?</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The game of tennis might seem complicated for those new to it, but it can essentially be broken down into 8 basic shots. All 8 shots need to be mastered to excel and proceed to the higher levels of tennis.</p>
<p>In this blog post, I discuss all 8 basic shots in the game of tennis. By the time you finish this article, you’ll know all of them inside and out. You’ll also have a much better understanding of the game of tennis.</p>
<p>Here are the 8 basic shots in the game of tennis:</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<ol>
<li><a href="#forehand">Forehand</a></li>
<li><a href="#backhand">Backhand</a></li>
<li><a href="#serve">Serve</a></li>
<li><a href="#volley">Volley</a></li>
<li><a href="#slice">Slice</a></li>
<li><a href="#overhead">Overhead</a></li>
<li><a href="#dropshot">Drop shot</a></li>
<li><a href="#lob">Lob</a></li>
</ol>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Most tennis newbies wonder, “What are the basic strokes in tennis?” Well now you know. And by knowing all the basic strokes, you can learn them and use them in your own game.</p>
<p>This will make you a more versatile and dangerous player to face. It’s ironic, but I see club players with decades of experience who never utilize all 8 shots in their game.</p>
<p>I believe there are a lot of players out there who never quite learned some of them, so they just don’t use them. If you’re new to tennis, I implore you to learn all 8 basic shots.</p>
<p>Certainly, the forehand, backhand, and serve are essential to playing tennis.</p>
<p>Other shots, like the slice and dropshot, are not part of the arsenal of some club players. I honestly don’t know how they cope in tennis without a slice. To me, the slice on both the forehand and backhand wings are a must-know stroke.</p>
<p>Without more talk, let’s get into the details of each stroke, so you know what each one entails.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="forehand"></a></p>
<h2>The Basic Forehand Shot</h2>
</div>
<p><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-1867 size-full" src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/forehand.jpg" alt="Pat Cash forehand" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/forehand.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/01/forehand-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/01/forehand-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>The forehand is the most basic and often-used shot in tennis. It’s also the easiest to learn and the shot beginners pick up the quickest.</p>
<p>Think of the forehand as akin to the queen in the game of chess. The forehand is your most versatile shot. Good players can hit with power, spin, and place the ball where they want.</p>
<p>Being the most basic stroke in tennis, it’s often the one everyone learns first. Professional players can dominate matches primarily with their forehand (a la Roger Federer).</p>
<p>The strength and placement of the forehand is often what separates great players at the highest levels. In my experience, the forehand is the most comfortable shot to hit and the most enjoyable too.</p>
<p>The forehand is hit on the dominant side of your body and is typically struck with one arm (your dominant arm). It’s possible to hit a two-handed forehand as well, but I would estimate less than 2% of recreational and professional players use it.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>On the men’s pro tour, there have only ever been two players to use the two-handed forehand. And this is out of thousands of players since 1940.</p>
<p>Those two players are the legendary Pancho Segura, and more lately, Fabrice Santoro. Segura was a lot more successful than Santora but played in the 40s and 50s when the game and racket technology was a lot different.</p>
<p>Santoro played in the 90s and 2000s. He reached a career high of 17 and his best result at a major was the quarterfinals of the 2006 Australian Open.</p>
<p>On the women’s side, the two-handed forehand had much more success, with players such as Monica Seles (10 career grand slam titles) and Marion Bartoli. Bartoli won Wimbledon in 2013 and then promptly and unexpectedly retired. She was my favorite woman to watch.</p>
<p>If you’re just starting out in tennis, hire a qualified pro to teach you the basics of the forehand. With just a couple of lessons, you’ll at least know the correct technique.</p>
<p>If you can’t afford lessons or don’t have a qualified pro near you, you can <a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCHaY0w7QtG205o4ByUHXkEg/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">check out my youtube channel</a> for free forehand lessons.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="backhand"></a></p>
<h2>The Basic Backhand Shot</h2>
</div>
<div id="attachment_1869" style="width: 810px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img decoding="async" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1869" class="size-full wp-image-1869" src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/backhand.jpg" alt="Pablo Cuevas" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/backhand.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/01/backhand-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/01/backhand-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /><p id="caption-attachment-1869" class="wp-caption-text">Carine06 from UK [<a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.0">CC BY-SA 2.0</a>], <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Pablo_Cuevas_backhand_(14536242152).jpg">via Wikimedia Commons</a></p></div>
<p>The backhand is hit on the non-dominant side of your body. For example, if you’re a righty and strike the ball on the left side of your body, it’s considered a backhand.</p>
<p>Most player’s backhands are not as strong as their forehand. This is because it’s more difficult to achieve the same level of racket speed on the backhand wing as the forehand side.</p>
<p>However, some players do have better backhands than forehands. If you’re one of those players, then you’re fortunate. Most club players dread hitting their backhands.</p>
<p>I find that most women have better two-handed backhands than forehands. This is likely due to them using more of their core and legs on the backhand. For men, I find most have much better forehands.</p>
<p>The backhand can either be hit with one hand or two. Examples of players with one-handed backhands are Roger Federer, Stan Wawrinka, Carla Suarez Navarro, and Justine Henin (now retired). Some would argue Henin had the best one-handed backhand in the women’s game.</p>
<p>The one-handed backhand offers some pros an advantage over the two-handed backhand. The pros using the one-handed backhand would have greater range of motion, slightly more drive and power, and more versatility with spin.</p>
<p>The cons of the one-handed backhand (compared to the two-) are less control, it’s more difficult to hit high shots, and there’s less ability to hit the ball late. Additionally, it’s more difficult to return serve with a one-hander.</p>
<p>These cons are enough to have persuaded most players and coaches to only teach and hit the two-handed backhand. For this reason, most of the players on the pro level (for both men and women) use a two-handed backhand.</p>
<p>If you wish to reach the upper levels of tennis, it’s essential you develop your backhand into a reliable shot. You’ll need to be able to hit it with depth, spin, placement, and a decent amount of pace.</p>
<p>While it’s not essential you smash winners from the baseline with your backhand, it is essential that it keeps you in the rally. Most professional players use their backhand to stay in a rally long enough to set up their forehand.</p>
<p>If you wish to learn the backhand, I suggest the two-hander. Get a qualified coach to teach you the basics of the shot and then just keep practicing it. I have videos on my youtube channel showing how to hit both the two-hander and the one-hander.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="serve"></a></p>
<h2>The Basic Serve</h2>
</div>
<p>Along with the forehand and backhand, the serve is one of the three primary shots in tennis you must know to begin playing. If you can effectively execute all three shots, you can play tennis.</p>
<p>The next shot in tennis you should learn is the volley. If you know these four shots (forehand, backhand, serve, volley) you can play matches, even in tournaments.</p>
<p>It sounds amazing, but you can literally choose to avoid the other four basic shots (drop shot, overhead, slice and lob) and still play competitive tennis. I wouldn’t suggest it though.</p>
<div id="attachment_1871" style="width: 410px" class="wp-caption alignleft"><img decoding="async" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1871" class="size-full wp-image-1871" src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/serve1.jpg" alt="Andre Agassi serve" width="400" height="610" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/serve1.jpg 400w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/01/serve1-197x300.jpg 197w" sizes="(max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" /><p id="caption-attachment-1871" class="wp-caption-text">Srinayan Puppala [<a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.0">CC BY-SA 2.0</a>], <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Agassi_serve_US_open_05.jpg">via Wikimedia Commons</a></p></div>All tennis players (whether in singles or doubles) get two serves on each point. The first serve is usually hit flat and hard.</p>
<p>The second serve is often hit with topspin or kick. These types of serves have more margin of error and are about 15-20% slower in speed than first serves.</p>
<p>Of the 8 basic shots in tennis, the serve is by far the most difficult to learn and the most complicated. This is for a few reasons.</p>
<p>First, the serve is the only shot in tennis where you start and finish the stroke. All other strokes rely on the ball coming to you.</p>
<p>Second, the serve requires you to toss the ball high in the air (usually twice your height) and strike it on the way down. This requires split-second timing.</p>
<p>The toss can also be problematic. This is because it’s done with the non-dominant hand, which can be very difficult for uncoordinated people and beginners.</p>
<p>Third, the serve is a complicated series of movements that must be performed in about two seconds. It also requires knee-bend, flexibility, and high racket speed.</p>
<p>Due to these factors, many club players never develop anything beyond a mediocre serve. This means their serves typically don’t break the 100-mph barrier or possess enough spin to hurt opponents.</p>
<p>If you are just starting out in tennis, realize the serve is a shot that will take you months or years to master. Everyone is limited on the serve by their physical ability, so be aware of that too.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>If you have dreams of serving 120-mph, unless you’re young and very talented, it’s not likely to happen. Instead, your goal should be a very consistent serve with excellent placement.</p>
<p>The serve is one of those shots you’ll need to continually practice. It requires perfect timing and tremendous hand-eye coordination when hit well.</p>
<p>Some of you may just want to play tennis for the exercise, or for the fun. If that’s your goal, you can use a very simple beginner’s serve to get the ball in the box and start the point.</p>
<p>If that sounds like you, I would advise you to check out my youtube video on the abbreviated serve motion. It’s a beginner’s serve, but slightly more advanced, offering more power and spin.</p>
<p>For those who aspire to hit their serve like Roger Federer, check out my video on Roger Federer’s serve motion. In this video, I explain how to hit your serve like Roger. Just don’t blame me if you can’t.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="volley"></a></p>
<h2>The Basic Volley</h2>
</div>
<div id="attachment_1873" style="width: 810px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1873" class="size-full wp-image-1873" src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/volley.jpg" alt="Jo-Wilfried Tsonga" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/volley.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/01/volley-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/01/volley-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /><p id="caption-attachment-1873" class="wp-caption-text">Kate from UK [<a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.0">CC BY-SA 2.0</a>], <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Jo-Wilfried_Tsonga_Wimbledon_2011_jump_volley.jpg">via Wikimedia Commons</a></p></div>
<p>The volley is unique all to itself. At its most basic element, it doesn’t require any swing of the racket or much body movement at all. Yet, it can be one of the most difficult shots in tennis to master.</p>
<p>What is a volley? A volley is when a player hits the ball directly out of the air, instead of letting the ball bounce first. When the ball bounces first, it’s called a “rally”. When taken in the air, it’s called a volley.</p>
<p>The volley is a very short compact “block” of the ball, most often close to the net. The volley can be hit on either the forehand side or the backhand side.</p>
<p>One of the reasons so few players master the volley is the very short amount of time provided to hit the ball. When you’re up at net, the ball is coming to you much sooner than at the baseline.</p>
<p>This makes it largely a reflexive shot, while baseline groundstrokes are much more deliberate.</p>
<p>Even the best players in the world today prefer not to come to net. The pace of groundstrokes at the pro level is just too much to handle, even for the best volley players.</p>
<p>With groundstroke speeds coming in excess of 80-90 mph, it’s very difficult to hit effective volleys, much less get a racket on the ball. For this reason, we have seen a trend away from net play over the last generation.</p>
<p>If you want to read more about this, I wrote an article entitled <a href="/why-did-serve-and-volley-die-out/">Why Did The Serve And Volley Die Out</a>?  It’s an interesting look at why the volley declined in both the women’s and men’s game over the last 20 years.</p>
<p>Despite the volley dying out, all players must learn to volley. This is because if you’re forced into net, you’ll have no choice but to eventually volley. The volley is also an essential part of doubles, which many people play.</p>
<p>If you’ve been struggling with your volleys, have no fear. I wrote a great blog post about the <a href="/seven-volley-types-you-must-know-to-master-your-net-game/">7 types of volleys</a> to use in your game. By knowing all 7 types and how to hit them, you’ll instantly improve your net game.</p>
<p>I also have a bunch of volley videos on my youtube channel. I recommend starting off with the block volley and then working your way through the other 6 volley types.</p>
<p>On the volley, always remember less is more. Most people over-complicate the volley and do too much swinging. The volley is more about great footwork and less about what you do with your racket.</p>
<p>If you want to play good doubles, or be an offensive player in singles, it’s imperative you learn to hit volleys with pace, spin, touch, and placement. It all comes in time.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="slice"></a></p>
<h2>The Basic Slice</h2>
</div>
<p>Traditional forehand and backhand strokes are hit with topspin (forward rotation of the ball). However, the slice employs backspin, which is a backward rotation of the ball.</p>
<p>Interestingly, it can also involve side spin.</p>
<p>The slice can be hit on either wing: the forehand or backhand. It can also be hit with either two hands or one. However, most players (probably more than 95%) hit their slice with one hand.</p>
<p>The slice generally refers to the downward motion of the racket when contacting the ball. The downward motion is what causes the backspin on the ball.</p>
<p>This is in contrast to traditional groundstrokes, which use a low-to-high swing path. In my opinion, it’s more difficult to learn the slice though.</p>
<p>I can teach a child or adult to make solid contact on a traditional forehand or backhand, but the slice is a different animal. For this reason, it can take a long time to develop a penetrating, effective slice shot on both wings.</p>
<p>One of the reasons for the difficulty level is the downward motion of the swing. Most beginners aren’t used to contacting the ball like that. The continental grip used on the slice also throws people off.</p>
<div id="attachment_1875" style="width: 410px" class="wp-caption alignright"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1875" class="size-full wp-image-1875" src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/slice.jpg" alt="Federer hitting a slice." width="400" height="404" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/slice.jpg 400w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/01/slice-297x300.jpg 297w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" /><p id="caption-attachment-1875" class="wp-caption-text">Steve Collis from Melbourne, Australia [<a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0">CC BY 2.0</a>], <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Federer_2009_Australian_Open_crop.jpg">via Wikimedia Commons</a></p></div>Most players open the racket face too much, or too early, and float the ball on their slice. For this reason, I teach my students to hit the ball completely flat but with a high-to-low trajectory of the racket.</p>
<p>If the slice is hit well, it can be a very damaging shot to the opponent. A good slice will skid on the ground and stay low. It can also be difficult to volley a tightly rotating slice.</p>
<p>Most players use the slice as a defensive shot, but it can certainly be used offensively as well. One example of an offensive slice shot is the approach shot. This is a hard, low slice away from the opponent.</p>
<p>On an approach shot, a player will quickly come to net in hopes of putting away an easy volley. The former greats like Pete Sampras, Patrick Rafter, and Stefan Edberg all used this tactic.</p>
<p>Many players also use the slice on the return of serve. I find the slice to be an excellent way to neutralize fast serves. It’s also much easier to control a slice return than a topspin return on fast or high serves.</p>
<p>The downside of returning a serve with a slice is that your opponent could volley it for a winner. But that’s only if they are a serve and volley type player. If you’re playing a strict baseliner, it’s a good tactic for the return.</p>
<p>The slice is an excellent way to handle high shots too (balls higher than your shoulder level). This is especially true on the backhand side, where there is less flexibility and strength to hit the ball high up.</p>
<p>For this reason, you’ll see many professional players turn to the slice on the high backhand. I personally use the slice to great effect on my forehand wing too – mostly on high shots.</p>
<p>The slice is also a great way to change up the spin on the ball. In this way, you offer different looks to your opponent, so they never know what to expect.</p>
<p>Lastly, the slice is often used as a last resort when the ball is far from the body. This typically happens when a ball is hit far from us and we are on the run to it.</p>
<p>Being it’s nearly impossible to hit a traditional groundstroke when so out of position, players will simply slice the ball back, as it’s the only option. When done on the forehand side, some call it a “squash shot”.</p>
<p>Roger Federer probably hits the best “squash shot” in the game. He also has one of the best slices the game has ever seen, period.</p>
<p>If you play tennis but haven’t developed a slice – or a good slice – work with a coach who can show you the shot. I have a great blog post here on <a href="/how-to-backhand-slice-in-tennis-the-right-way/">how to hit a backhand slice</a>.  I’ll be adding one for the forehand slice soon.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="overhead"></a></p>
<h2>The Basic Overhead Shot</h2>
</div>
<p>The overhead is a shot you hit above your head. It’s very similar to the serve motion, except the ball will be hit at you, instead of you initiating the stroke.</p>
<p>Overheads can be hit directly out of the air or after they hit the ground. If taken out of the air, exquisite timing is necessary to hit an effective overhead.</p>
<p>On occasion, it’s wise to let the ball hit the ground first and not take it out of the air. If the ball bounces high enough, you can strike the ball over your head.</p>
<p>Allowing the ball to hit the ground first is a lot easier than taking it out of the air. However, most of the time you’ll want to hit the ball out of the air.</p>
<div id="attachment_1877" style="width: 410px" class="wp-caption alignright"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1877" class="size-full wp-image-1877" src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/overhead.jpg" alt="Rafael Nadal hitting an overhead shot." width="400" height="599" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/overhead.jpg 400w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/01/overhead-200x300.jpg 200w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" /><p id="caption-attachment-1877" class="wp-caption-text">Carine06 from UK [<a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.0">CC BY-SA 2.0</a>], <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Flickr_-_Carine06_-_Rafa_overhead.jpg">via Wikimedia Commons</a></p></div>It’s really a judgment call which one you choose. The more you play, the easier it becomes to decide. You’re much more likely to hit the ball out of the air when you’re at net and lobbed.</p>
<p>It&#8217;s my belief that if you have a good serve motion, you’ll have a good overhead. The fundamentals of the serve and overhead are basically the same.</p>
<p>However, if your serve fundamentals are lacking, your overheads are going to be spotty at best. I believe a good racket drop is crucial to hitting great overheads. The racket drop is when your racket inverts before swinging up to contact.</p>
<p>If you have a beginner’s serve, also known as a waiter’s serve, you’ll likely never have world-class overheads. But you can still make do and place the ball well.</p>
<p>The overhead requires good footwork and great timing. Most people miss their overheads because their footwork does not put them in proper position to hit the ball well.</p>
<p>When you see a ball lobbed to you, your first instinct should be to turn to your forehand side and get your racket up. This is the side from which you hit your forehands and serves.</p>
<p>From here, you’ll want to use a cross-step as your first move. Once done, side-step back into position to hit the perfect overhead.</p>
<p>A major mistake I often see is people walking backwards to hit the overhead. They clearly missed the first step of turning to their side. This rarely works and can result in you falling over and hurting yourself.</p>
<p>With the right footwork and practice, you can make the overhead one of your best shots. If you can put your overheads away with pace and placement, it’ll put a ton of pressure on your opponents – especially when you come to net.</p>
<p>I should mention that the overhead can be hit on the backhand side as well. It’s rare, but most professional players can put away balls using a backhand overhead. A lot of it involves a flick of the wrist.</p>
<p>However, most club players find the backhand overhead shot to be very difficult. It’s still worth practicing, as you’ll experience hitting it from time-to-time in your matches. It involves using a combination of your arm and wrist.</p>
<p>The normal overhead is an important shot to learn in tennis and will serve you well in both singles and doubles. Most people don’t practice the overhead enough. I suggest working on it every practice session, if even for 5-10 minutes.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="dropshot"></a></p>
<h2>The Basic Drop Shot</h2>
</div>
<p>When done right, the drop shot is an extremely effective shot that can win you a point outright. It is often made from the baseline, whereby a player hits the ball very slowly with a lot of backspin.</p>
<p>Optimally, the ball will go barely over the net, not more than 5-6 feet into the court, and have very little forward movement. This will force the opposing player to sprint up to the ball and hit it.</p>
<p>This causes difficultly for the opposing player for several reasons. One is that the ball may be out of reach, whereby you win the point outright. Second, the opposing player must run fast and stop in time to avoid hitting the net.</p>
<p>If that player touches the net with their body or racket after hitting the ball, they automatically lose the point. Third, most good drop shots will cause the opposing player to lift the ball over the net, making it difficult to hit a good shot back on you.</p>
<div id="attachment_1865" style="width: 410px" class="wp-caption alignright"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1865" class="size-full wp-image-1865" src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/dropshot.jpg" alt="Boris Becker drop shot" width="400" height="267" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/dropshot.jpg 400w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/01/dropshot-300x200.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/01/dropshot-272x182.jpg 272w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" /><p id="caption-attachment-1865" class="wp-caption-text">James Phelps from USA [<a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0">CC BY 2.0</a>], <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Boris_Becker_in_action.jpg">via Wikimedia Commons</a></p></div>The drop shot can be hit off either side – forehand or backhand. It can be used at any time during the point, even off the serve. As a matter of fact, it can be very effective off the serve.</p>
<p>I like to throw in at least a few drop shots per set – usually in my baseline rallies. I do this for several reasons. One, it keeps the opposing player honest; he or she never knows what to expect from me.</p>
<p>Second, it makes the opposing player sprint to net, which expends their energy. This makes them just a bit more tired during the rest of the match.</p>
<p>I especially like to drop shot my opponent in the first set, as it will tire them out in the second set, and possibly the third (if we go there). If you want to compare it to boxing, drop shots are like body blows.</p>
<p>Even if the opponent gets to my drop shot and wins the point, it takes a small physical toll on them. In boxing, a fighter may land body shots early in the fight, but they typically don’t pay off until the later rounds. Same thing in tennis.</p>
<p>The drop shot can be used in these different scenarios: off the serve (as I just mentioned), during a baseline rally, and when you’re at net hitting a volley (called a drop volley). Another really good time to use the drop shot is off a drop shot.</p>
<p>That last scenario may sound confusing, so I’ll clarify. Let’s say your opponent drop shots you and you sprint up to the net to hit the ball. Usually your best option at that point is to drop your opponent right back.</p>
<p>Why? Because it’s often unexpected and your opponent will need to cover a large distance to get to the ball. It’s also easier to drop shot from the net rather than the baseline.</p>
<p>The drop shot requires a more delicate touch than any other shot in tennis. If you’re playing against a fast player who anticipates well, you’ll have a slim margin of success with the drop shot.</p>
<p>The danger of the drop shot occurs when it’s hit too deep or too high. If this happens, expect your opponent to easily get up to it and hit a clear winner on you.</p>
<p>As this can happen, it’s an excellent idea to disguise your drop shot. You do this by making it look like you’re going to hit your normal forehand or backhand.</p>
<p>At the last second you pull the rug out from under your opponent and slice the ball short. If you can learn to disguise your dropper, you’ll have a lot more success with it.</p>
<p>I think the number one reason players fail when using the drop shot is that they telegraph it. Most have no idea they’re showing their hand a mile away – as their opponents are usually mum to the fact.</p>
<p>One more point about the drop shot: It can be a great way to get a baseline player who hates the net out of his element.</p>
<p>By dropping such players, you force them to play the net, where their weakest. This is a great strategy to use against a perennial baseline player.</p>
<p>Practicing the drop shot is quite easy. Just rally at the baseline with your hitting partner. After one or two shots, hit a drop shot. You can also practice it on a ball machine.</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="lob"></a></p>
<h2>The Basic Lob</h2>
</div>
<div id="attachment_1880" style="width: 810px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1880" class="wp-image-1880 size-full" src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/lob2.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/lob2.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/01/lob2-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/01/lob2-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /><p id="caption-attachment-1880" class="wp-caption-text"><a title="Running down a lob" href="https://flickr.com/photos/mirsasha/5000452102">&#8220;Running down a lob&#8221;</a> by <a href="https://flickr.com/people/mirsasha">mirsasha</a> is licensed under <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/2.0/">CC BY-NC-ND</a></p></div>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>The lob is chiefly a defensive tennis shot. In tennis, a lob is a slow-moving shot hit at a high trajectory. Its purpose is to go over the head of a net player – or make the net player hit a difficult shot.</p>
<p>Some people even go so far as to use the lob in rallies. While that can work at the lower levels of tennis, it doesn’t work at the intermediate level &#8211; and certainly not at the advanced level.</p>
<p>I suggest only lobbing when the opposing player is at the net or when you’re far out of position and off the court. The latter works well to give yourself time to get back into the point.</p>
<p>Lobbing when you’re off the court is especially effective if the opposing player doesn’t like to move off the baseline. I use this tactic a lot when I’m strung wide against a perennial baseline player.</p>
<p>The lob can be hit off any side, forehand or backhand. It is most often hit with topspin but can be hit with slice as well. A topspin lob is much preferred and more effective for three distinct reasons.</p>
<p>One is that the topspin will help keep the ball in the court. Two, it’s more difficult for your opponent to hit a fast spinning ball that is dipping quickly; slice shots tend to float more and are much easier to hit.</p>
<p>Lastly, you can lob with more pace and margin of error with a topspin as opposed to slice. To hit the lob, simply brush on the bottom of the ball and finish your stroke up high. You’ll be taking almost all the pace off the ball and putting that energy into the “brush”.</p>
<p>Keep in mind it’s always more effective to lob your opponent on his or her backhand side. The backhand overhead is a much tougher shot to hit than the normal overhead.</p>
<p>You can make the lob more even more effective if you disguise it well. Do this by preparing the same way you would on any forehand or backhand. Instead of hitting with your normal stroke, put a lot of brush on the ball.</p>
<p>Lobbing is a good strategy but it’s not the cure-all to beat a player that likes to come to net on you. Instead, it’s best to mix in hard shots and heavy topspin shots with your lobs.</p>
<p>This throws your opponent off and will keep them guessing. If you’re playing outside and it’s very windy, take note of which way the wind is blowing.</p>
<p>My best advice on a windy day is not to lob into the wind. I find it to be very challenging to hit a lob when the wind is against me.</p>
<p>If I lob into the wind, the ball will not be very deep, and my opponent will crush it. On the contrary, lobbing with the wind is advisable.</p>
<p>You just need be careful not to put too much on the ball. When hitting a lob with the wind at your back, hit lightly and let the wind do the work.</p>
<p>You can practice your lobs as easily as your drop shots. Just have someone stand at the net and see how well you can lob them. Practice over-and-over on both forehand and backhand wings. Do this until you’re a master of the topspin lob off of both sides.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Conclusion</h2>
<p>This wraps up the 8 basic shots in tennis. I hope this post has given you a good insight into each stroke. My point was to give some information on each stroke to all level of players.</p>
<p>If you’re new to tennis, take your time learning each stroke. Tennis is a difficult game to learn and master. Give yourself several years to reach an intermediate level.</p>
<p>For those experienced players reading this, if you’re not using all 8 basic shots in your game, you’re selling yourself short. For example, if you’ve never sliced, or don’t believe you can do it well, take on the challenge of learning it.</p>
<p>It will add great depth to your game. Remember, always make sure you know the fundamentals and are executing them properly. If you can’t get a coach, at least video your strokes so you can see where corrections need to be made.</p>
<p>Hey, I have a lot of cool and interesting articles on this blog, so don’t be afraid to browse around and check them out. I’ve categorized most of them into “training” and “theory”.</p>
<p>Thanks for coming this far with me. If you have any questions on these basic strokes of tennis post them in the comment section below. And don’t forget to check out my youtube channel for great tips and tricks to accelerate your tennis game.</p>
<p>The post <a href="/what-are-the-8-basic-tennis-shots/">What Are The 8 Basic Tennis Shots?</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/what-are-the-8-basic-tennis-shots/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Best 5 Tennis Rackets For Serve And Volley In 2018</title>
		<link>/the-best-5-rackets-for-serve-and-volley-in-2018/</link>
					<comments>/the-best-5-rackets-for-serve-and-volley-in-2018/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chad Walner]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 30 Oct 2018 08:42:53 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Reviews]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[serve]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[volley]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=904</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>If you really wanted the best vehicle for cornering, would you waste time researching the best Jeep?  Of course not!  You need the tennis racket that will fit your level and your game more than the &#8220;best&#8221; all-purpose racket. So &#8230; <a class="kt-excerpt-readmore" href="/the-best-5-rackets-for-serve-and-volley-in-2018/" aria-label="The Best 5 Tennis Rackets For Serve And Volley In 2018">Read More</a></p>
<p>The post <a href="/the-best-5-rackets-for-serve-and-volley-in-2018/">The Best 5 Tennis Rackets For Serve And Volley In 2018</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>If you really wanted the best vehicle for cornering, would you waste time researching the best Jeep?  Of course not!  You need the tennis racket that will <strong>fit your level and your game</strong> more than the &#8220;best&#8221; all-purpose racket.</p>
<p>So in tennis, there are basically two types of broad styles. You’re either a baseliner or a net crasher (serve and volleyer). Each style has very different needs.</p>
<p>Baseline players have more margin for error. A racket with power that can produce topspin is their main need.</p>
<p><strong>For the serve and volley player, rackets with more control and maneuverability are more important. The top rackets for serve and volley players are definitely different from those for baseline players, and we&#8217;ve gathered all the data together here with this very specific player in mind.</strong></p>
<p><strong>In this post, you’ll find our selection of the top 5 rackets of 2018 for serve and volley players. We broke each racket down in detail and listed their strong points and weaknesses.</strong></p>
<p>This is what we chose to be the best of the best for S&amp;V:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="#babolat">Babolat Pure Strike – 16 x 19</a></li>
<li><a href="#wilson-pro">Wilson Pro Staff RF97 Autograph</a></li>
<li><a href="#prince">Prince Phantom Pro 100</a></li>
<li><a href="#wilson61">Wilson Six One 95 &#8211; 18 x 20</a></li>
<li><a href="#yonex">Yonex EZONE DR 98 Blue</a></li>
</ul>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>How We Determined The Best Rackets For Serve And Volley</h2>
<p>We determined the best serve and volley rackets in three different ways:</p>
<ol>
<li>Through personal experience, trying out each racket.</li>
<li>Studying the specs of each racket to make sure they are ideal for serve and volley.</li>
<li>Reviewing a very detailed study that <a href="https://tenniscompanion.org/best-tennis-racquets/">tenniscompanion.org</a> did on the 22 best rackets and then we used the study to narrow down the 5 best rackets for serve and volley.</li>
</ol>
<p>The tenniscompanion.org study was compiled using six key attributes. Each attribute was scored on a 1-10 scale for every racket they reviewed. These attributes are power, control, maneuverability, comfort, touch/feel, and stability.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-921 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/racketPriorities.png" alt="" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/racketPriorities.png 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/racketPriorities-300x169.png 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/racketPriorities-768x432.png 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p>Let’s quickly look at each attribute in order of importance and determine its significance to a serve and volley racket.</p>
<p><strong>Control</strong> – Control is very important to the serve and volley player, especially when placing shots. Typically, smaller head sizes and thinner beams offer more control but less power. Control was an attribute we deemed important for our selected rackets to score well in.</p>
<p><strong>Maneuverability</strong> – This is a measure of how easily the racket can be maneuvered to hit a shot, particularly a volley. Most good maneuvering rackets have more weight in the handle than the head. This makes them feel lighter and allows them to be moved quicker. We feel this is important for volley players, so we looked for rackets that scored high in this attribute.</p>
<p><strong>Touch/Feel</strong> – Interestingly, rackets that offer touch are very similar to rackets built for comfort – heavy and flexible. The main exception is touch rackets have smaller head sizes. Since touch is very important to the volley player, this is an attribute our rackets had to score well in.</p>
<p><strong>Stability</strong> – A stable racket is one that is responsive and delivers a consistent, accurate strike of the ball. These rackets tend to be heavy with wider beams and less flexible frames. This attribute is semi-important to the serve and volley player but it wasn’t one of the key attributes for our rackets.</p>
<p><strong>Comfort</strong> – This is a measure of how comfortable your arm and body feel when hitting the ball. If there is less vibration and stiffness in the frame, that is deemed a comfortable racket. Comfort is an attribute we feel is not very important to the serve and volley player. However, one of the rackets on our list has comfort as an added bonus.</p>
<p><strong>Power</strong> – Except on the serve, power is not the most important attribute for a serve and volley player; and it may even be the last. Serve and volley players are more concerned with touch and maneuverability. For that reason, most of the rackets on this list are not the most powerful.</p>
<p>Overall, the most important attributes for selecting a great racket for serve and volley are control, maneuverability and touch/feel. Keep in mind that all the rackets we selected have power as well, but not as much as the rackets made for baseliners.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>The 5 Best Serve And Volley Rackets Of 2018</h2>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="babolat"></a></p>
<h3><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-911 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/r_bab1.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/r_bab1.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/r_bab1-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/r_bab1-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></h3>
<h3>Babolat Pure Strike – 16 x 19</h3>
</div>
<p>This racket ranked first on the tenniscompanion.org list of all the rackets they reviewed. It’s an all-court racket but at 11.3 oz and 98 sq inches, excellent for serve and volley. Its light weight allows for great maneuverability at net and quick reaction times.</p>
<p>The frame of this racket is slightly more flexible than the other members of the Babolat racket family. This affords more control and touch, perfect for the serve and volley player.</p>
<p>The only drawback I saw of this racket is slightly less power than most of the other Babolats I’ve used. But there are always trade-offs. With the Babolat Pure Strike you sacrifice a bit of power for more control. However, it’s also a fantastic racket for groundstrokes and returns.</p>
<p>Overall, this racket scored high marks across the board. Though unchanged since 2017, we still endorse it as one of the best serve and volley rackets for 2018. If you’re an all-court player who serves and volleys part of the time, few choices are better for a racket.</p>
<p><a href="https://amzn.to/2DYriCy" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Check the current price of this racket on Amazon.com</a> (affiliate link to Amazon for the exact model I’m reviewing here).</p>
<p>I personally played with the Babolat Pure Drive for years and had great success with Babolats. In the last couple of years, I switched to the Head Prestige MP, but I’d easily buy another Babolat for my next racket.</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="wilson-pro"></a></p>
<h3><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-913 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/r_rf.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/r_rf.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/r_rf-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/r_rf-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></h3>
<h3>Wilson Pro Staff RF97 Autograph</h3>
</div>
<p>The original Wilson Pro Staff from the 1980s and 90s was made popular by Pete Sampras. The new model for 2018 was popularized by Roger Federer, hence his initials in the title.</p>
<p>This racket is quite unique to other rackets in its design. It makes use of braided graphite construction with thin beams and a light head.</p>
<p>At 97 square inches, it has a great head size for serve and volley. Surprisingly, the racket weighs 12.6 ounces, which is one of the heaviest strung rackets on the market. The heavy weight gives the racket great control, but maneuverability is compromised.</p>
<p>Still, the Wilson Pro Staff makes up for the heavy weight in every other way. It feels stable, solid, and affords excellent control. Whether at the baseline, net, or serving, the Wilson Pro Staff handled solidly.</p>
<p>We picked this racket because it scored very well on volleys, slices, and net play according to tenniscompanion.org, which stated:<br />
“One of our favorite places to hit with Roger’s Pro Staff was up at the net. It felt solid in our hands and allowed us to hit crisp and controlled volleys with little effort. Combined with a heightened sense of touch and it gave us the feeling that we were in control when we approached the net.”</p>
<p><a href="https://amzn.to/2Q7AlZc" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Check the current price of this racket on Amazon.com</a> (affiliate link to Amazon for the exact model I’m reviewing here).</p>
<p>We endorse this racket for serve and volley, especially if you’re an advanced player who can handle a heavier stick. Hey, if it works for Roger Federer, it can work for you, right?</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="prince"></a></p>
<h3><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-914 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/r_prince.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/r_prince.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/r_prince-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/r_prince-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></h3>
<h3>Prince Phantom Pro 100</h3>
</div>
<p>Prince has long been known as of the best racket manufacturers. They really nailed it with this racket. With a 100 square inch head, 11.3 oz strung weight and a frame stiffness of only 54, you couldn’t ask for a racket with more control.</p>
<p>Arm friendly and responsive, you can be confident coming to net with the Prince Phantom Pro 100. This is a racket ideal for intermediate and advanced players who like to attack the net and desire control.</p>
<p>Most of the 11.3 ounces of weight is in the handle of the racket. This translates to a low head weight, giving it exceptional maneuverability at the net. On groundstrokes, the racket proved capable but doesn’t give as much spin and power as some of the other rackets on this list.</p>
<p>The main drawback of this racket is lack of power. But power is the main sacrifice when designing a racket for control. Overall, I thought this racket performed well when I hit with it. Players who swing fast won’t have power issues.</p>
<p><a href="https://amzn.to/2QdeEaf" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Check the current price of this racket on Amazon.com</a> (affiliate link to Amazon for the exact model I’m reviewing here).</p>
<p>As a hack, you could string a bit looser than normal, which should make up for some of the lost power. I believe giving up some power for all the control the Prince Phantom Pro 100 offers, is worth the trade-off. Especially if you attack the net consistently.</p>
<p>For that reason, I highly endorse this racket as one of the best serve and volley sticks of 2018.</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="wilson61"></a></p>
<h3><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-915 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/r_61.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/r_61.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/r_61-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/r_61-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></h3>
<h3>Wilson Six One 95 18 x 20</h3>
</div>
<p>For the pure serve and volley players out there that love control, this is your racket. The head size is only 95 square inches yet it weighs 12.3 ounces strung, making it almost as heavy as the Wilson Pro Staff RF 97 Autograph.</p>
<p>The heavy frame allows for comfortable contact and moves through the ball with ease. A light head balance, thin 22 mm beams all the way around it, and added it weight at the 3 and 9 o’clock positions, give this racket superior control.</p>
<p>This racket also boasts Wilson’s parallel drilling technology, which creates a more forgiving string bed and increased sweet spot. The racket performed great from the baseline and at the net in tests.</p>
<p><a href="https://amzn.to/2Pf7PPX" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Check the current price of this racket on Amazon.com</a> (affiliate link to Amazon for the exact model I’m reviewing here).</p>
<p>The main drawbacks of the Wilson Six One is the heavy weight and reduced power. This is a common theme among some serve and volley rackets. Maneuverability and power are not this racket’s forte.</p>
<p>But if you can get past that part, you have a stick that will provide you a ton of control and stability on your shots. We’re sure you’ll love coming to net with this racket.</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="yonex"></a></p>
<h3><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-916 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/r_yonex.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/r_yonex.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/r_yonex-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/r_yonex-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></h3>
<h3>Yonex EZONE DR 98 Blue</h3>
</div>
<p>This racket is a great choice for all-court players. It will still be a valuable addition to the serve and volley player with it’s excellent control and touch.</p>
<p>Yonex made this racket with Nanometric DR carbon graphite composition. This allows the frame to flex while snapping back into place on contact. The EZONE also features Yonex’s signature square head shape.</p>
<p>The square head increases the sweet spot of the racket compared to other rackets of its size (98 square inches). This racket also has technology that dampens vibrations from the ball, offering increased comfortability.</p>
<p>Like most of the other rackets on this list, the Yonex offers superior control and good maneuverability. While the racket lacks a bit of power, we feel it more than made up for it with its other attributes.</p>
<p>You should be able to hit good serves with this racket and have plenty of feel on the volleys. From the baseline you’ll hit good, consistent groundstrokes, especially with the larger sweet spot on the racket.</p>
<p><a href="https://amzn.to/2Q9ohXm" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Check the current price of this racket on Amazon.com</a> (affiliate link to Amazon for the exact model I’m reviewing here).</p>
<p>If you’ve never played with a Yonex before, you’ll find them to be very comfortable. My first racket was actually a Yonex, but that was back in the day. If you’re an intermediate to advanced player who swings relatively fast, this racket is a great choice.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Other Factors That Affect The Racket For S&amp;V</h2>
<p>Other factors will affect the way the racket plays. These are grip size, choice of string, string gauge, and string tension. Here are some quick guidelines on ways to determine these choices.</p>
<p><strong>Grip Size:</strong> The size of the grip is largely dependent on the person. Rafael Nadal uses one of the smallest grips on the men’s professional tour, while Juan Martin Del Potro favors a larger one. It comes down to a personal choice.</p>
<p>Most grips start at 4 inches (on the small side) and up to 4 5/8 inches on the large size. We recommend trying out different size grips before selecting one. Going too small or too large is usually a detriment. Try to choose a grip that is comfortable for your hand size.</p>
<p>As a helpful tip, if you’re already playing with a grip that’s too small, you can add an over grip to make it larger. Grips that are too large cannot be made smaller unless you change the entire grip.</p>
<p><strong>Choice Of String:</strong> Nowadays, players generally have two different choices for string material – synthetic gut or polyester. Synthetic gut is easier on the elbow and usually costs less. The feel of the string will also last longer.</p>
<p>Consequently, synthetic gut is a good choice if comfort and durability is your main concern. You’ll also spend less in restringing costs.</p>
<p>On the flip side, polyester will give more feel and bite on the ball. This results in more spin and power, which is helpful to both baseline and serve and volley players.</p>
<p>The drawbacks are that polyester loses feel after playing with it much quicker and stringing costs will be higher. Polyester is also harder on the arm, especially when strung with a high tension.</p>
<p>I personally need to restring with polyester every 3-4 weeks in comparison to 7-8 weeks with synthetic gut. Almost all professional players use polyester and there are a ton of options to choose from.</p>
<p>For serve and volley players, either string, synthetic gut or polyester, will do the job. But polyester gives more bite on the ball.</p>
<p><strong>String Gauge:</strong> This is another important factor in playability. Tennis string gauge refers to the thickness of it. The gauges vary in size from 15 to 18, with 15 being the thickest and 18 being the thinnest. Most players use a 16 or 17-gauge string.</p>
<p>The lower the gauge, the longer the string will last, but the less playability it will have. The opposite is true. The higher the gauge, the shorter the string will last but the more playability it will have.</p>
<p>I use a 16L and 17-gauge string and love it. In the past, I used regular 16-gauge string and played fairly well with it. However, the increased feel of the 17-gauge string is worth the extra time and money for me.</p>
<p>For serve and volley players, either string will work, but polyester provides more feel and spin. If you can afford the extra money, go with polyester.</p>
<p>You can try my string recommendation if you like. If you’re an avid player, the difference is a few hundred dollars a year more for using good polyester strings. Remember, all the pros use polyester.</p>
<p><strong>String Tension:</strong> This refers to how tight or loose the strings are tensioned when put into the racket. Most rackets have a recommended string tension listed on it. It may say something like “Recommended Tension: 55-65”.</p>
<p>I personally favor higher string tensions because they give more control. They’ll also last a little longer, as even when the tension drops from playing, they’ll still remain fairly tight.</p>
<p>Keep in mind that tighter tensions are not very friendly on the elbow. So if comfort is important, string lower. Most rackets give you a 10-point spread in the recommended tension. You can’t go wrong with a tension in the middle. For example, if between 55-65, string at 60.</p>
<p>After you string your racket and play with it for a few weeks, you’ll know if you need to adjust up or down. Keep in mind that small bits of tension are lost every time you play.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>I find that the first few times of play don’t necessarily give a good indication of the strings. If you string tight, you need to hit with the racket a few times before the strings “break in” and you can honestly assess them.</p>
<p>If you use polyester and play often with the same strings, you may notice they ultimately become unresponsive and have a “dead” feel. That’s when you need to restring. If you continue playing with such strings, you’re likely to hurt your elbow and be an unhappy camper.</p>
<p>I personally favor polyester and go with a hybrid 16L and 17-gauge string with a high tension (around 63-65).</p>
<p><strong>Main Strings:</strong> Signum Pro Plasma HEXtreme Pure 16L String &#8211; <a href="https://amzn.to/2PjmI3I" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Check the current price on Amazon.com</a> (affiliate link to Amazon for the exact model I’m recommending here).</p>
<p><strong>Cross Strings:</strong> Diadem Evolution 17 (1.25) String (Azure Blue) &#8211; <a href="https://amzn.to/2PePqTq" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Check the current price on Amazon.com</a> (affiliate link to Amazon for the exact model I’m recommending here).</p>
<p>The post <a href="/the-best-5-rackets-for-serve-and-volley-in-2018/">The Best 5 Tennis Rackets For Serve And Volley In 2018</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/the-best-5-rackets-for-serve-and-volley-in-2018/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>How To Serve And Volley Effectively In Tennis &#8211; Complete Guide</title>
		<link>/how-to-serve-and-volley-effectively-in-tennis/</link>
					<comments>/how-to-serve-and-volley-effectively-in-tennis/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chad Walner]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 26 Sep 2018 08:46:18 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Theory]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[serve]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[volley]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=477</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Are you looking to add the serve and volley game to your tennis arsenal? Or maybe you currently serve and volley but just want some tips to improve that part of your game. This post is all about how to &#8230; <a class="kt-excerpt-readmore" href="/how-to-serve-and-volley-effectively-in-tennis/" aria-label="How To Serve And Volley Effectively In Tennis &#8211; Complete Guide">Read More</a></p>
<p>The post <a href="/how-to-serve-and-volley-effectively-in-tennis/">How To Serve And Volley Effectively In Tennis &#8211; Complete Guide</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Are you looking to add the serve and volley game to your tennis arsenal? Or maybe you currently serve and volley but just want some tips to improve that part of your game. This post is all about how to effectively serve and volley in singles. Some of the information here will work well for doubles, but we’re going to focus primarily on singles.</p>
<p><strong>In order to serve and volley effectively, it’s essential to have a serve with spin and pace that can be placed accurately. It also requires solid volley technique and the ability to hit overheads. Finally, it requires athleticism, good hand-eye coordination and the right strategy.</strong></p>
<p>We talk a lot about the serve and volley game on this blog, hence the name of it. I am a big proponent of the serve and volley style and I use it in singles and doubles matches consistently. It’s very effective against players slightly lower in level and a good way to change things up when facing players your level and above. Like most players, I started off as a baseliner who added the serve and volley game later on.</p>
<p>While pro tennis has proved (at least for now) that serve and volley is not as effective as the baseline game, it’s still very effective at the club level. I believe you should be using the serve and volley in doubles, and if you have the ability, it can work wonders for your singles game as well. Keep in mind that it takes years to build up a good serve and volley game, so give it some time.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>It All Starts With A Good Serve</h2>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignright wp-image-1177 size-full" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/IMG_0152startswithserve.jpg" alt="" width="400" height="439" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/IMG_0152startswithserve.jpg 400w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/IMG_0152startswithserve-273x300.jpg 273w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" />Let’s face it. You absolutely need a good serve with spin, speed and placement to use the serve and volley as a weapon. If you don’t have a good serve, you’ll be a sitting duck at the net &#8211; even at the club level. A poor serve with little pace and spin means players are going to pass you, hit to your feet and lob you. You’ll eventually get frustrated, abandon the serve and volley game, and retreat to the comfortable confines of the baseline.</p>
<p>If your serve is weak, you’ll need to improve it if you want to consider adding the serve and volley game to your tennis arsenal. How much you need to improve your serve is really for you to judge. I’ve seen players with 70 mph first serves come in and volley effectively because they’re playing at a 3.0-3.5 level. If you play at that level, you can get away with a subpar serve. At the 4.0 level and above, probably not.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>If you wonder about the level of your serve, here is a simple way to tell if you can use it to serve and volley. Try to serve and volley on every first serve for a whole set against someone at your level. If you get passed every other shot and lose most of the points you come in, then you need work on your serve. If you want to take your serve to the next level, we have articles like <a href="/learn-how-to-serve-in-10-minutes-with-the-servemaster/">this (basic)</a>, <a href="/how-to-hit-a-second-serve-in-tennis/">this (2nd serve)</a> and <a href="/how-to-have-a-reliable-serve-toss-in-tennis/">this (serve toss)</a>, and also videos showing you how to serve. Take a look at our<a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCHaY0w7QtG205o4ByUHXkEg" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"> youtube channel</a>.</p>
<p>This post is intended to provide you with strategies to serve and volley effectively. It assumes you have the ability to hit good serves and decent volleys at your level of play.</p>
<p>Assuming this is the case, we can now talk strategy. Here is a breakdown of what this guide will offer:</p>
<ol>
<li>Choosing the <a href="#serve-type">type of serve</a>.</li>
<li>Choosing a <a href="#serve-target">target for your serve</a>.</li>
<li>How to <a href="#approach-net">approach the net</a>.</li>
<li>How to <a href="#meet-return">meet the return</a> at the net.</li>
<li>Choosing the <a href="#volley-type">type of volley</a> to hit.</li>
<li>Choosing a <a href="#volley-target">target for our first volley</a>.</li>
<li><a href="#subsequent-volleys">Subsequent volleys</a>.</li>
<li>Considerations when <a href="#serving-to-ad">serving to the ad side</a>.</li>
<li>Chip and Charge: a <a href="#strategy-for-receiver">strategy for the receiver</a>.</li>
</ol>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="serve-type"></a></p>
<h2>Mix Up Your Serves</h2>
</div>
<p>For singles, it’s best to start your serve about 2-4 feet from the mid-line. If we set up further away, we give up too much space on the court. From this position we have several options to choose from:</p>
<p>It’s very effective to mix up your serve speed and spin. You should be hitting three types of serve throughout the whole match:</p>
<ol>
<li>Flat serve – This is your fastest serve which has little spin.</li>
<li>Kick serve – Your topspin serve, which “kicks” or bounces high off the court.</li>
<li>Slice serve – This serve has side spin and usually stays low and spins in the opposite direction of your hitting arm.</li>
</ol>
<p>There is a difference between a kick serve and a slice serve. A kick serve has topspin, which makes the ball “kick” or bounce high in the air after hitting the ground. This serve can be very difficult to return, especially to the backhand of your opponent. A slice serve has side spin and usually stays low and spins to the left (if you’re a righty) and vice-versa if you’re a lefty. This serve can also be very effective because it can slide away from the returner – or even directly into them.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1180" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/IMG_0111serve.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/IMG_0111serve.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/IMG_0111serve-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/IMG_0111serve-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p>When I was a kid, I used to love playing and watching baseball. The best pitchers of my day (like Roger Clemens and Greg Maddux) always varied their speeds and spins, which made them so tough to figure out. I suggest you do the same when you serve. Here are the benefits of doing so:</p>
<ul>
<li>Your opponent will always be left guessing which serve (flat, kick, slice) you will be serving.</li>
<li>It will disrupt the return game of your opponent. A kick serve and flat serve can vary in speed by as much as 30-40 mph. These extremes make it difficult for your opponent to time your serve.</li>
<li>After hitting all three serve types, you can assess which one your opponent has the most trouble with and key in on it. For example, maybe the flat serve into the body on the deuce court is problematic for your opponent while the kick serve to the backhand gives them trouble on the ad side. You can determine this as the match progresses. This is a good way to figure out players you have never previously faced.</li>
</ul>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="serve-target"></a></p>
<h2>The Three Different Targets To Serve To On The Deuce Side</h2>
</div>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="wp-image-504 size-full aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-sv-3-targets-1.jpg" alt="Three targets for the serve and volley." width="800" height="407" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-sv-3-targets-1.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-sv-3-targets-1-300x153.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-sv-3-targets-1-768x391.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p>When serving to the deuce side, you should be aiming for one of three specific targets or zones on the baseline. Take a look at the diagram here for a visual. Imagine the baseline of the deuce side is divided into three equal widths.</p>
<p>The three different targets are <em>out wide</em>, <em>into the body</em>, and <em>up the middle</em>. When using the serve and volley, you should know the answer to two questions before you toss the ball.</p>
<ul>
<li>First, will the serve be flat, kick or slice?</li>
<li>Second, which zone will you aim for?</li>
</ul>
<p>You should definitely be mixing up the serves and zones. Take note during the match which zone gives your opponent the most difficulty. You can then hit to that zone during important points, like break and ad points. You would also want to hit a majority of your serves to that zone, perhaps 50-60% with the other 40-50% split between the other two zones.</p>
<p>Now let’s talk specifically about serving to each zone. For the sake of brevity, the following information assumes a righty is serving to a righty. Obviously, this information will change if a lefty is involved.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><em>Serving Out Wide</em> – <strong>This can be a very rewarding serve.</strong> If you can hit a wide enough angle, you can secure an ace. At the least, you can force your opponent to return way off the court. This usually results in a weak return that you can put away at the net. It’s best to volley the return to the opposite side of the court (ad side) when your opponent is so wide. Anyone of the three serves, flat, kick or slice, will work when serving out wide. The danger in serving out wide is that if you don’t hit a good angle, you are serving right into your opponent’s strength: their forehand. Your opponent can then rip a return in which they can pass you down-the-line or cross court. So make sure to aim near the line when going out wide.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p><em>Into The Body</em> – <strong>This is the safest and highest percentage serve</strong> but your chance of securing an ace is almost zero. You’ll want to hit a fast, flat serve directly at your opponent. If done right, your opponent will not be able to return the serve to your side of the court. Or, at the least, you’ll get a weak return that can be put away easily. If you try to hit a kick or slice serve to this zone, your opponent may be able to move out of the way and blast a return. Likewise, if your serve does not have enough pace, your opponent can do the same. So make sure you have some zing on your serve when going into the body.</p>
<p><em>Up The Middle</em> – <strong>You’ll probably use your fast, flat serve here most of the time.</strong> A kick serve can also work very well (if it has enough pace). And a slice serve can be effective up the middle too, as it would slide into the body of your opponent. What I like about going up the middle on a righty is that the ball is directed into their backhand, which for 90% of club players is their weaker wing. You can definitely hit an ace on a good up the middle serve. Or, if you can kick the ball up high to the backhand, you’ll most likely receive back a weak return. Personally, I feel targeting a serve up the middle is the most difficult spot to hit for a right-handed server at the club level on the deuce side. Still, you should be targeting this area.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>What Happens After The Serve?</h2>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignleft size-full wp-image-1182" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/IMG_0031.jpg" alt="" width="400" height="380" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/IMG_0031.jpg 400w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/IMG_0031-300x285.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" />You’ve chosen one of the three different serve types (flat, kick or slice) and selected a zone (out wide, into the body, out wide). You then step up to the line and hit a great serve. Now what? As most of you already know if you play tennis, you’re going to run forward toward the net. It’s called “following the ball”.</p>
<p>When done right, the serve and volley is one blended motion. It consists of the serve, landing on the left foot after the ball is struck and running in. This part of the serve and volley should be seamless and quick. Your footwork here is essential. Without good footwork, you’ll never get close enough to the service line to stick your first volley. I therefore want to mention a couple of important points about it before we move on.</p>
<blockquote><p>Almost all right-handed players will want to land on their left foot after serving. This holds true for any and all types of serve by righties. By landing on your left foot, you’ll thrust your weight forward which makes for a bigger serve. You’re also creating forward momentum that will propel you towards the net. Take a look at any right-handed player on the ATP or WTA tour. You’ll see all of them land on their left foot when serving.</p></blockquote>
<p>Once you land on your left foot, your upper body should be slightly over your left leg, which will cause you to “fall” forward. You want to use this forward movement to take your first step with your right leg. You then run toward the net as quickly as possible. An important key here is to stay slightly lower on your run than you normally would. This means arching your back slightly forward, maybe 10 degrees. By doing so, you get to net quicker and split-step easier.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="approach-net"></a></p>
<h2>Follow The Path Of The Ball</h2>
</div>
<p>We know we will come to net after the serve. But what’s the best path to come to the net?</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-521 alignleft" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/structure-france-2013-tennis-rolandgarros-sports-238222-pxhere.jpg" alt="Following the ball." width="400" height="300" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/structure-france-2013-tennis-rolandgarros-sports-238222-pxhere.jpg 400w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/structure-france-2013-tennis-rolandgarros-sports-238222-pxhere-300x225.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" />When the serve is performed correctly, our momentum takes us forward into the court. So where do we go from here? <strong>The rule of thumb for almost all serve and volley points is to follow the path of the ball.</strong> The wider the serve on the deuce side, the sharper our angle of approach. See the diagrams I included above for a good visual description of how to approach each zone.</p>
<p>If we are going into the body, then we run at a less sharp angle. Since the serve is being directed into the body, our opponent will not be able to hit down the line as easily as when we go out wide. We can, therefore, approach further from the line, covering more of the middle of the court.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>But what if we serve up the middle? Again, we follow the path of the ball. Our line of approach will be at a very slight angle, running almost up the middle of the court. If you hit a well-struck serve to your opponent’s backhand (which will happen if you hit this zone), you should receive a weak return, ripe for a put-away. Be careful though. If your opponent has time they can pass you in either direction. It’s much more likely they pass you by hitting to your ad court (left side of your court) than to the deuce side (to the right of you). This is because hitting a good, inside-out backhand on a return is difficult – plus you are approaching from the deuce side.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="meet-return"></a></p>
<h2>Decisions At The Net</h2>
</div>
<h4>1) The Hop And Split Step</h4>
<p>When you see your opponent go into their backswing for the return, you’ll want to stop and split step. The stop is not abrupt though. That would be inefficient and will never work in a real-world scenario. Instead, it involves a hop. At first, it may seem challenging to do, but after some practice, it becomes second nature.</p>
<p>As your opponent goes into their backswing, you’ll literally hop off one leg (I like to hop off my left) and “jump” into the split step. I see so many club players miss doing the hop, which causes them to split step a little too far from the net. Just a foot or two difference from the net can mean hitting a volley off the ground (half volley), which is not preferable, or catching it in the air (preferable). The hop allows you to cover more distance and spring forward out of the split step easier.</p>
<p>What exactly is the split step? The split step occurs when you come to a full stop with both feet directly under you, slightly wider than shoulder width. The split step is used by professional players everywhere on the court, but when close to the net, you’ll want to adopt a wider than normal stance and get slightly lower. This allows you to push off in any direction quicker.</p>
<p>Key Point:</p>
<blockquote><p>When approaching the net after the serve, keep the racquet in front of you and maintain the continental grip (like gripping a hammer). I like to keep the racquet in a neutral position about chest high. A neutral position means it will take the same amount of time to hit a forehand volley as it does a backhand volley.</p></blockquote>
<p>I see way too many players run with the racquet on one side of their body, which makes it nearly impossible to volley a high-velocity return on the other side. You should also keep the racquet head slightly higher than the hands. This will set you up to volley in the correct position.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h4>2) The Flowing Volley</h4>
<p>In tennis, there are very few black and white protocols, such as always do this and never do that. Some players ask me where they should follow through on their forehands. The answer is that it depends and varies on the situation. The same is true of the split step.</p>
<div id="attachment_534" style="width: 410px" class="wp-caption alignleft"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-534" class="wp-image-534 size-full" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2359254792_e9bfa3f745_c.jpg" alt="" width="400" height="286" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2359254792_e9bfa3f745_c.jpg 400w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2359254792_e9bfa3f745_c-300x215.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" /><p id="caption-attachment-534" class="wp-caption-text"><a title="Naby backhand volley" href="https://flickr.com/photos/togasaki/2359254792">&#8220;Naby backhand volley&#8221;</a> by <a href="https://flickr.com/people/togasaki">toga</a> is licensed under <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/">CC BY</a></p></div>
<p>Most of the time you’ll split step in the manner I described above. But sometimes you’ll want to keep running and not hop or split step. <strong>This is called the flowing volley</strong> and it requires more hand-eye coordination and timing. We can define the flowing volley as hitting a volley while still moving forward. You’ll want to incorporate the flowing volley in your game, even though it is more of an advanced way to approach the net. Here’s how to do it.</p>
<p>Simply continue to run forward but slow down some to hit the volley. Only after the ball is struck will you stop. It’s important you start setting up the racket before you get to the ball. When is the best time to use the flowing volley? I’ll outline them below.</p>
<ul>
<li>The return is hit so slow that you don’t need to split step. Instead, you continue to run towards the ball and use a drive volley to put it away. In some instances, you can hit a swinging volley. You can also employ a drop volley. If you want to know about the seven volley types, you can read an entire article we wrote on the subject here.</li>
<li>If you see the ball starting to drop low, you may want to continue running to take it out of the air. This is usually the case on soft-to-medium hit returns. On hard hit returns to your far right or left, it’s not advisable to use the flowing volley.</li>
<li>If you don’t have enough time to move up to the service line, you may want to sacrifice the split step to get closer and better position. This is a gamble though. If the return is hard hit or is near the lines, you’re in trouble. But if the return is medium pace, or even fast pace but directly to you, you can still recover and hit back a defensive or decent volley. On a slow-paced return, you should have no problem adjusting.</li>
</ul>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>What To Do On The First Volley</h2>
<p>You serve, hit your zone, and your opponent returns at a medium pace right to your direction. Whether you split step or not, you have a great chance to hit a good first volley. So which type of volley do you hit? And where do you place the volley? We will define four targets for the first volley. The target you choose is dependent on where your opponent and yourself are on the court. Additionally, the speed and height of the return will determine the volley response.</p>
<p>One more quick word on the first volley. While our goal is to always hit an unreturnable first volley and win the point outright, we need to be prepared to hit a second volley. It might be better to think about your first volley as a shot that sets up the second volley. This will take some pressure off your first volley. Remember, whether it takes one volley or five volleys, if you win the point, then goal accomplished.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="volley-type"></a></p>
<h4>Which Volley Do I Hit?</h4>
</div>
<p>I wrote a long and detailed article with photos showing the <a href="/seven-volley-types-you-must-know-to-master-your-net-game/">seven different volley types</a>. I won’t repeat the information again here, but I will touch on which volleys to use and when. If you don’t know the seven different volley types, I highly recommend reading that post. It will be very helpful to your volley game.</p>
<div id="attachment_532" style="width: 410px" class="wp-caption alignright"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-532" class="wp-image-532 size-full" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/480px-Novak_Djokovic_Volley_01.jpg" alt="" width="400" height="400" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/480px-Novak_Djokovic_Volley_01.jpg 400w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/480px-Novak_Djokovic_Volley_01-150x150.jpg 150w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/480px-Novak_Djokovic_Volley_01-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" /><p id="caption-attachment-532" class="wp-caption-text">By IvanAndreevich [<a href="http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/fdl.html">GFDL</a> or <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0">CC BY 3.0 </a>], <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Novak_Djokovic_Volley_01.jpg">from Wikimedia Commons</a></p></div><strong>1. Drive Volley</strong> – Use this volley on slow-hit shots. It’s vital you use the drive volley to decisively put away slow. If not, the point is likely to continue and the chances of you being passed increase. You can always tell if you’re playing against an expert volley player by how easily or not he puts away sitters. The greats do it 9 out of 10 times and often the returner will have no chance to even get a racket on the ball.</p>
<p><strong>2. Swinging Volley</strong> – I like to use the swinging volley when I get a looping shot with little pace. Usually, the shot will be too low to hit an overhead smash, so I set up for a swinging forehand volley. The swinging volley should easily end the point and has a bit more power than the drive volley. I don’t recommend hitting a backhand swinging volley to beginner and intermediate players, but if you can manage it, then go for it.</p>
<p><strong>3. Punch Volley</strong> – Hit this volley when you receive a medium-paced return. All we’re doing is blocking with a little “punch” or forward movement of our racket. Optionally, you can step forward with the opposite leg when volleying to give the ball some pace.</p>
<p><strong>4. Block Volley</strong> – Use this volley when your opponent hits a screaming groundstroke in your direction. With this volley, you’re just blocking or deflecting the ball to your opponent’s side of the court. Make sure to hold the racket with a loose grip and allow it to have some give when impact is made (how much will depend on how far you’re volleying from the net). I see many club players make the mistake of trying to hit a punch volley on high-paced returns. Sometimes the less you do, the more you accomplish. The same is true for the volley – less movement and take back is often better.</p>
<p><strong>5. Half Volley</strong> – If you serve and volley a lot, you’re going to be forced into half volleys on many occasions. A half volley is when the ball hits the ground before you volley it. Since half volleys are generally defensive shots (though they can be turned into offense as well), your first goal is to get the shot back and over the net. Most of the time you’ll be volleying up and directly off the rise. If you feel like you have a good chance of returning the half volley, your best bet is to just place it well. Don’t worry about hitting it hard. Often a dropper right at the net can win you the point.</p>
<p><strong>6. Drop Volley</strong> – This brings us to the drop volley, which I mentioned before. It is simply a volley that you place close to the net. This volley works best when your opponent is behind the baseline, not fleet of foot, tired or flat-footed. However, even the fastest players can’t get a racket on a well-placed drop volley. They are subtle can be very effective.</p>
<p><strong>7. Overhead Smash</strong> – If you serve and volley, you’re going to get lobbed. You have to be willing to hit overheads and work on that part of your game. When an overhead is hit, turn to your side and get your racket into the “trophy” position. Use proper footwork to back up and when you set, place your weight on your back foot. When hitting the overhead, try to transfer weight onto the front foot. Keep in mind you need to have some racket speed to hit a decisive winner, though placement (with a slower struck shot) can be your best friend on an overhead as well.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="volley-target"></a></p>
<h4>Where Do I Place My Volley?</h4>
</div>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignright size-full wp-image-1184" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/IMG_0005a.jpg" alt="" width="400" height="358" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/IMG_0005a.jpg 400w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/IMG_0005a-300x269.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" />Let&#8217;s define four locations, as each is effective in different circumstances:</p>
<p><strong>Location # 1: Behind</strong> &#8211; The first location is <strong>behind your opponent</strong>, out wide. From your perspective, you’re volleying to the left of your opponent.</p>
<p><strong>Location # 2: At</strong> – The second location is <strong>directly at your opponent</strong>. This sounds like a bad idea, but it can work great if you hit a fast-paced volley to an opponent who has returned from out wide.</p>
<p><strong>Location # 3: Ad</strong> – The third location is <strong>to the open ad court</strong>.</p>
<p><strong>Location # 4: Drop</strong> – The fourth location is a <strong>drop volley close to the net</strong>.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h4>Regrouping After You Volley</h4>
<h4><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-523 alignleft" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/girl-ready-to-return-a-volley-in-tennis.jpg" alt="" width="400" height="286" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/girl-ready-to-return-a-volley-in-tennis.jpg 400w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/girl-ready-to-return-a-volley-in-tennis-300x215.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" /></h4>
<ul>
<li>Always return to the ready position after hitting a volley or an overhead. It’s important you get right back into the ready position as soon as possible. Not doing so is the most common cause of missing the net shot.</li>
<li>After getting back to the ready position remain alert. Stay on your toes and look like you are ready to move anywhere to hit the ball. This alone will intimidate your opponent and make him miss more often. I find the opposite to be true. If you stand straight up and flat-footed, your opponent will have a much easier time passing you.</li>
<li>Never assume the point is over until it’s clearly over. I see net players often caught by surprise when the opponent hits yet another groundstroke or lob, forcing them to hit a ball when not ready. Play the point until the end.</li>
<li>Try to anticipate where your opponent is going to hit the ball by watching how he sets up. Often you can tell if he is going to hit a hard groundstroke or lob in this way. Sometimes you can anticipate direction as well.</li>
<li>Learn to have a good eye. This means to be aware when a return might be going out or long. If it’s going out, just let the ball go without touching it. If you are not certain, I recommend you hit it. You will soon develop a feel for where the ball is going.</li>
</ul>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>A Brief Recap</h2>
<p>If you’ve read this far, congratulations. You’ve learned a lot of information on the serve and volley game. No doubt, these tips will benefit you for the rest of your playing days. Let’s sum up what we learned and continue on.</p>
<ol>
<li>We saw that a good serve is essential if we want to use the serve and volley game.</li>
<li>We have three different serves to choose from.</li>
<li>We have three different zones we can serve to.</li>
<li>Once the serve is made and we run in, we can either split step or continue running and use the flowing volley.</li>
<li>The path we take into the net is determined by where we serve the ball.</li>
<li>If our first volley is hit at us, we can choose four different locations to place the ball.</li>
<li>The type of return we receive (varying height, pace and spin) will determine which volley to use from one of the seven different volley types.</li>
</ol>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>I think that’s a pretty good summary of how to look at the serve and volley. There are still a few more points of info to discuss. I’ll try to word them as briefly as possible. Let’s take a look at our specific options for the volley in each case: if you serve out wide, into the body or up the middle.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Your Options When Serving Out Wide</h2>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-507 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-out-wide.jpg" alt="Volleys from an out wide serve." width="800" height="407" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-out-wide.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-out-wide-300x153.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-out-wide-768x391.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>If you serve out wide and receive a return to the middle of the court, you have all four options for where to place the first volley.</p>
<p><strong>Location # 1: Behind</strong> &#8211; This is a volley behind your opponent, which is out wide again. Keep in mind we’re taking a bit of a chance here by volleying near our opponent. How is this location effective? If your opponent is off the court he’ll immediately try to recover to the middle of the court after making his return. You’ll know he’ll do this because his entire court is exposed. You then volley behind him so that your shot is in the opposite direction of his momentum. This makes it very difficult for him to hit back. After you volley here, slide over to your left a bit to cover anything down the line – just in case your opponent hits a forehand.</p>
<blockquote><p>**Helpful hint: This location works especially well against fast players. Slower players or lazy players tend to linger outside the court, making it difficult to hit behind them. In that case, simply hit to the open court to easily win the point.</p></blockquote>
<p><strong>Location # 2: At</strong> – Firing a volley directly at my opponent can work because I know my opponent will likely move to his left (my right) after returning out wide. My goal on this volley is to hit a fast-paced shot right near his feet. As the opponent will be on the run, he won’t be able to set up in time to hit a good passing shot. This also catches a lot of players off-guard because they are not expecting a volley right back to them.</p>
<p><strong>Location # 3: Ad</strong> – Volleying to the open ad court makes sense if your opponent is off the court on the deuce side, as he may be after a serve out wide. If you hit a low, hard volley, you should win the point without your opponent getting a racket on the ball. But if hit too soft, then a fast opponent may return your volley. Remember, the opponent is anticipating we will volley to the ad side. If he has the chance to recover, he’ll be sprinting in that direction. Still, it’s the most logical place to hit and quite effective. I use this location when my opponent is way off court or when I want to fatigue him.</p>
<p><strong>Location # 4: Drop</strong> – I would suggest dropping the volley over the net to your right, the furthest location from your opponent. But really, this is such an effective technique it will work anywhere close to the net. The key here is to have soft hands and make sure you have a lot of “give” on your racket. If you hold a firm grip, hit the ball too high or too deep, your opponent can run in and easily put the ball away. I use the drop volley around 10-20% of the time when playing singles. In doubles, it’s a little tougher because there is another person at the net.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Your Options When Serving To The Body</h2>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-506 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-into-body.jpg" alt="Volleys from an into body serve." width="800" height="407" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-into-body.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-into-body-300x153.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-into-body-768x391.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>When you serve to the body and receive a return, most likely your opponent will remain still. As a possibility, he may move slightly to his left (to the center of the court). We will need to see exactly where he is before hitting our first volley. Hitting out wide to our opponent’s forehand is not preferable here, so it limits us to three locations.</p>
<p><strong>Location # 2: At</strong> – We can direct the ball right back at our opponent. This is the safest volley to hit for us, because we’re hitting cross court. But our opponent has a great chance to hit back the ball unless we completely jam them. I would recommend hitting to the two other locations first.</p>
<p><strong>Location # 3: Ad</strong> – The third location is to the open court on the ad side, preferably close to the sideline. Since our opponent is not off the court, he might be able to get to this volley if not fast-paced or angled off enough. So be ready for a second volley. Remember, your mentality as a beginner or intermediate player should be that the first volley sets up the second volley for a put-away.</p>
<p><strong>Location # 4: Drop</strong> – The fourth location is close to the net using a drop volley. The drop volley can be effective anywhere your opponent is, as long as he is returning near the baseline.</p>
<p>I should mention that you can try angling off a volley to your opponent’s deuce side. However, beginner and intermediate players might find that a challenge. You’ll also be hitting dangerously close to the sideline. Your best chance to angle off the volley to this area is by using a drive or hard punch volley. Anything less and you are hitting into your opponent’s forehand.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Your Options When Serving Up The Middle</h2>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-509 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-up-middle.jpg" alt="Volleys from an up middle serve." width="800" height="407" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-up-middle.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-up-middle-300x153.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-up-middle-768x391.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>A good serve up the middle will stretch your opponent out and put him near the middle of the court. I would not advise you go straight back to him though. From the center of the court there are too many options. He can pass you on either side, lob you or even hit a dipping shot at your feet.</p>
<p>Most of the time a good serve up the middle will produce an ace or a weak return, ripe for a put-away volley. If you do receive back a medium or fast-paced return, use one of these three locations:</p>
<p><strong>Location # 1: Behind</strong> – Out wide to the deuce side. This will make the opponent scramble to his right to hit a forehand. The benefit is you drag him away from the center of the court to set up the next volley, which will be to the far ad court. The danger here is in not hitting a good enough volley. If not, then you are hitting right into your opponent’s strength, which is his forehand. It’s important that you move a few steps to your left when hitting here so you can cover the down-the-line shot.</p>
<p><strong>Location # 3: Ad</strong> – To the far ad court. This will put the volley on your opponent’s backhand side. He’ll have to scramble to hit a backhand pass, which is much tougher than a forehand. This is a safer bet for us and better than hitting to the deuce side (location # 1). After hitting this volley, scoot to your right a few steps. You’ll want to cover any possible down-the-line backhands (which it would come down the right side of your court).</p>
<p><strong>Location # 4: Drop</strong> – Near the net. Yup, another drop volley. They’re always effective and can really dishearten the opposition. I used to play against a great net player named Seth who had tremendous drop volleys and overheads but not much in between. He could “deaden” almost any groundstroke and place the ball within two feet of the net, where it would die quickly. There’s just no chance to return a volley like that!</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="subsequent-volleys"></a></p>
<h2>What Happens After The First Volley?</h2>
</div>
<p>You’ll either end the point with the first volley or not. If the point continues, then hopefully you’ve done enough with the first volley to set up a put away second volley. If not, then you’re in a dogfight, as your opponent is likely scrambling around the court, desperately trying to pass or lob you.</p>
<p>Remember to keep getting back into the ready position after each volley. Keep cool and try to anticipate where your opponent is hitting. It’s also vital that you move forward after each volley. If your first volley is struck at the service line, you should be able to at least take several steps in so that you’re closer to the net for the second volley. The closer you are to net, the more angles you can cut off from your opponent.</p>
<p>I should point out that leaving a couple of feet of space from you and the net is advisable. If you play with your nose over the net, you can be very easily lobbed. Not only that, you stand a good chance of hitting the net with your racket or body. Doing so will automatically lose you to the point.</p>
<p>Here is one more important take away when being in a dogfight at the net. Don’t back off the net and attempt to run back to the baseline, please. There’s no time for that, and besides, that behavior is contrary to what we are looking to do here. We want to keep pressure on our opponent and end the point quickly and decisively with a volley or overhead. If it takes 10 volleys to win the point, then so be it. Keep closing in and angling off the volleys. The only time you should ever back up is when being lobbed.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="serving-to-ad"></a></p>
<h2>What About Serving To The Ad Side?</h2>
</div>
<p>You can use the same strategy of choosing which serve to use and to what location. After serving, you still follow the ball in on the same trajectories, just the reverse of the deuce side. If going out wide, you’ll need to run on the sharpest angle. If to the body, then less sharp. And if going up the middle, then you’ll run nearly down the middle of the court, with not much angle.</p>
<p>I want to touch on each location for the ad side before ending this post. I’ll mention the most important things you need to know about serving to each zone. Again, this all assumes a righty is serving to a righty.</p>
<p><strong><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-524 alignright" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/novak_jokovic_mens_tennis_wimbledon_lawn_serve-538594.jpg" alt="" width="400" height="267" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/novak_jokovic_mens_tennis_wimbledon_lawn_serve-538594.jpg 400w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/novak_jokovic_mens_tennis_wimbledon_lawn_serve-538594-300x200.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/novak_jokovic_mens_tennis_wimbledon_lawn_serve-538594-272x182.jpg 272w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" />Serving Out Wide</strong> – This is a great place to serve since the ball is being directed at your opponent’s backhand. Fast, flat serves and kick serves work great in this zone. Most likely you’ll receive back a weak return or floater. If so, don’t even worry about going behind them. Simply hit the return to the far deuce side of the court, far from your opponent. You can also hit a drop volley on the deuce side. A kick serve to this zone probably won’t get you an ace, but it will most often produce a weak return. A kick serve out wide is one of the safest plays you can make when attempting to serve and volley.</p>
<p><strong>Serving Into The Body</strong> – Any type of serve (fast, slice or kick) will work in this zone. Most players prefer hitting a fast serve to the body though. Most returns that are directed into the body are weak, making a put away easy. If you receive back a medium or fast-paced return, you may have the option of hitting back to the ad side if your opponent moves to the middle of the court quickly. But most of the time I recommend volleying to the far deuce side or just hitting a drop volley. Your worst place to volley back to is the middle of the court (right into your opponent’s forehand), so try not to at all costs.</p>
<p><strong>Serving Up The Middle</strong> – This zone can produce a lot of aces. I believe it’s easier to ace someone up the middle than out wide, especially for club players. But, with that said, remember, you are serving right into your opponent’s forehand. For that reason, I do not recommend many up the middle serves on the ad side, unless you serve with a big kick, with a lot of velocity or have excellent placement. Let’s say you receive back a medium-to-fast-paced return. My ultimate play is to hit a drop volley on either the deuce or ad side. If you can’t do that, here are three other options.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>Hit a fast-paced volley out wide to the deuce side. Or, do the same to the ad side. One additional option is to hit a fast-paced volley directly at your opponent. Try to edge it slightly more to the backhand side if you can. You do this in the hopes of jamming your opponent and making him miss or send back a weak return. While this is the easiest volley to hit, you expose yourself in the middle of the net if your opponent can set up for a blast return.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="strategy-for-receiver"></a></p>
<h2>Chip And Charge</h2>
</div>
<p>Before we wrap up, I’d like to say a few things about your return game. You obviously know the serve and volley can only be employed when you’re serving. But how can we be aggressive at the net while returning serve? The answer is the chip and charge. We can do this off the serve or on a groundstroke. The chip is the slice, which can be done on either the forehand or backhand side. By slicing, preferably to the sidelines, we keep the ball low and make it difficult to hit. We then charge the net, following the path of the ball. This will drive our opponent’s crazy, as they at least thought we’d stay back when returning.</p>
<p>You can also come in on most well-hit or deep groundstrokes. I like to come in on a groundstroke to my opponent’s backhand. Usually, he’ll be on the run when I start coming in. Another play is to hit a looping, topspin shot to your opponent’s backhand and just come in immediately behind it. Despite returning, there are plenty of opportunities to come to net.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>A Final Word On The Serve And Volley</h2>
<p>I’m very glad you’ve come this far. Soon the serve and volley game will be second nature to you. With practice, you’ll be winning points from the net with ease. Your opponents will find you incredibly difficult to play and your doubles game will grow leaps and bounds.</p>
<p>I want to leave you with a few more tips. I didn’t have a chance to include them earlier in the post, but nonetheless, they are important as well.</p>
<ul>
<li>When serving and volleying, make sure to use a loose grip. This gives you more snap on the serve and more feel on the volley.</li>
<li>Practice your serve often and practice your volleys all the time. I noticed that the level of both declines if not used or practiced.</li>
<li>Practice your footwork. Go through your serve and practice moving into net with a split step. Then practice your volley step and your move back for the overhead. Do this many times without using a ball. All that’s required is you and your racket.</li>
<li>Watch youtube videos of the greatest serve and volley players of all time. Notice how they use the techniques and strategies I discussed in this article. Watch the way they play and learn and be inspired by it.</li>
<li>Play entire sets where you serve and volley on first and second serve. Try to chip and charge on return games. Come to net every chance you have. Do this against players lower than your level and see if you can win. The more you come to net, the more comfortable you’ll feel.</li>
<li>If your volley game seems like it’s falling apart during a match, use the <a href="/seven-volley-types-you-must-know-to-master-your-net-game/#block">block volley</a> until your feel returns. The block volley will put the ball back on your opponent’s side of the court and at least make him hit another shot.</li>
</ul>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>The post <a href="/how-to-serve-and-volley-effectively-in-tennis/">How To Serve And Volley Effectively In Tennis &#8211; Complete Guide</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/how-to-serve-and-volley-effectively-in-tennis/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The 9 Best Tennis Drills For Improving Your Volley Game</title>
		<link>/the-nine-best-tennis-drills-for-improving-the-serve-and-volley/</link>
					<comments>/the-nine-best-tennis-drills-for-improving-the-serve-and-volley/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chad Walner]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 12 Sep 2018 10:04:02 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Training]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[volley]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=196</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>So you want to improve your net game but you’re not sure exactly what to do. In this post we’re going to give you the absolute best serve and volley drills you can do. These are drills I’ve used to &#8230; <a class="kt-excerpt-readmore" href="/the-nine-best-tennis-drills-for-improving-the-serve-and-volley/" aria-label="The 9 Best Tennis Drills For Improving Your Volley Game">Read More</a></p>
<p>The post <a href="/the-nine-best-tennis-drills-for-improving-the-serve-and-volley/">The 9 Best Tennis Drills For Improving Your Volley Game</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>So you want to improve your net game but you’re not sure exactly what to do. In this post we’re going to give you the absolute best serve and volley drills you can do. These are drills I’ve used to improve my game as well as that of my students.</p>
<p><strong>Listed by name, they are <a href="#ghost">Ghost Doubles</a>, the <a href="#volley-to-volley">Volley-To-Volley drill</a>, the <a href="#three-volley">Three-Volley drill</a>, the <a href="#mad-volley">Mad-Volley drill</a>, <a href="#volley-overhead">Volley-Overhead Alternates</a>, the <a href="#catch-and-volley">Catch-And-Volley</a>, the <a href="#half-court">Half-Court Volley</a> game, <a href="#hit-the-target">Hit the Target</a> and the <a href="#service-line-touch">Service Line Touch.</a></strong></p>
<p>Now keep in mind that I made up the names to some of these drills, so you may have never heard them before. We’re going to review each one and by the end of this post, you’ll know how to do all of them. Every drill here is helpful, but you’ll probably narrow it down to a couple of favorites when you practice. I particularly like the half-court volley game. This drill really sharpens my reflexes and simulates a point at the net very well (more on it to come).</p>
<p>Keep in mind that we made a video of all these drills so you can see them played out. It helps to read about them as well, which is the reason for this post. Watch the video and read this post for the best overview of each drill/game. Our blog posts go into more detail than our videos do.</p>
<p>You may be wondering how advanced you need to be to do these drills. If you have basic volley technique and can serve, these drills are within reach of any level player. Even children can use these drills to improve their game. I often use them with my younger students, as most are great fun. You can incorporate these drills in a full practice session or do a couple before or after a match. Without further talk, let’s get into it.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="ghost"></a></p>
<h2>Drill # 1 &#8211; Ghost Doubles</h2>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="wp-image-217 size-full aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-ghost.jpg" alt="Ghost volley drill demonstration." width="800" height="407" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-ghost.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-ghost-300x153.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-ghost-768x391.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
</div>
<p>I first learned ghost doubles from my tennis coach in college. We used it quite a lot in our practices. It’s a great drill for doubles but can also hone your singles play.</p>
<p>This drill requires two people – one will be serving and the other will be returning. There are two rules to the game that make it different from a regular tennis match.</p>
<p>First, the server has to serve and volley. He or she must keep pressing into the net or else lose the point. The only time the server is allowed to back up is to field a lob. After the lob is hit, the server must move in again.</p>
<p>The other rule is that only half the court is used. If you are serving from the deuce side, only the deuce side is in play for both players. Any ball hit into the ad court is automatically out. The doubles allies are in play in this drill, so anything hit into the doubles alley counts.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>After the point is over, alternate to the the ad side (just like in a normal tennis match) and the same rules apply in reverse – any ball hit into the deuce side is considered out. Keep playing points until the game is over. You can play up to a certain amount, like 10 points, or just play a full set.</p>
<p>This drill realistically simulates doubles play and is great for improving your serve and volley doubles game. It also helps the returner develop good passing shots.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="volley-to-volley"></a></p>
<h2>Drill # 2 – The Volley-To-Volley Drill</h2>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-209 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-volleyvolley.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="407" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-volleyvolley.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-volleyvolley-300x153.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-volleyvolley-768x391.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
</div>
<p>This drill is one of the best for improving your volley game. It should be used in every practice and will definitely sharpen your reflexes if used consistently.</p>
<p>Two people are required for this drill. Each person will stand at the service line – one on each side of the net. I like to set up in the middle of the court to afford plenty of space to the left and right of me.</p>
<p>Start by hitting the ball to your partner. Ideally, your partner will volley the ball in the air and hit it right to you. You will then volley it back (out of the air) and hit it back to your partner. This will continue until one of you miss. When that occurs, just start again.</p>
<p>You want to hit the ball at each other so you can practice your volleys. Don’t try to be a hero and see if you can win the point by hitting away. That’s not the point of this drill.</p>
<p>It’s perfectly fine to hit half volleys too, as sometimes the ball will not reach you. You can move in a bit to volley, but if you go too far past the service line, the drill will become very difficult for both of you, as the ball will be going too fast.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="video-container"><iframe class="size-full aligncenter" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/BVSUl65cGrk?rel=0&amp;modestbranding=1&amp;start=38&amp;end=120" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen"></iframe></div>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>When you first learn this drill, it may be difficult to get more than several volleys back. Hit slow to each other at first and use a continental grip. Return to the ready position as soon as possible after each volley.</p>
<p>In time, you will get better and better. With consistent practice, it won’t be long before you will be able to hit many volleys before you miss. Keep in mind, this is not a game but a drill. The idea is not to blast the ball past your partner but to keep the ball in play for as long as possible.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="three-volley"></a></p>
<h2>Drill # 3 – The Three Volley Drill</h2>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="wp-image-264 size-full aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-3volley-1.jpg" alt="Three volley drill demonstration." width="800" height="407" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-3volley-1.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-3volley-1-300x153.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-3volley-1-768x391.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
</div>
<p>This is more of an advanced volley drill that is great for the serve and volley.</p>
<p>Only one player will be doing the drill, but another person is needed to feed the balls.</p>
<p>For the player doing the drill, start about three feet in back of the service line. The player on the other side of the net feeds you three quick volleys. The first volley is taken from the starting point. Once you hit the first volley you quickly move in, hit another volley, move in again and then hit your final volley. By the time you hit your third and last volley, you should be within 5-6 feet of the net, if not closer.</p>
<p>The person feeding the ball is advised to feed one after another with no delay. For beginners, feed slowly and hit higher shots that are easy to volley. If a player is more advanced, feed faster and lower shots to make the volley more challenging.</p>
<p>The person feeding can hit all three volleys to the forehand, all three to the backhand or make them random.</p>
<p>Once all three balls are volleyed, the player returns to the spot three feet in back of the service line and goes through the drill again. As an option, after the three volleys are made, the feeder can hit a lob for an overhead smash.</p>
<p>This drill can make you tired if done quickly but it’s a fantastic one to work on your volleys as you move in. The split-step is advised for this drill. However, advanced players can forgo it in favor of a flowing volley. When performing this drill quickly, your mechanics can get sloppy, so videoing yourself to monitor your progress is a good idea.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="mad-volley"></a></p>
<h2>Drill # 4 – The Mad Volley Drill</h2>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-219 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-mad.jpg" alt="Mad volley drill demonstration." width="800" height="407" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-mad.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-mad-300x153.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-mad-768x391.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
</div>
<p>This drill is one of my favorites to do with my students. I don’t use it much in my own practice, but I find it works great with beginners to really challenge them. Children especially love this drill.</p>
<p>This drill is performed by one player and requires another person to do the feeding. The player performing the drill will stand about 2-4 feet from the net, depending on their height. Shorter people can move closer, taller people can move back a bit.</p>
<p>For the feeder, it’s best to have a hopper with at least 50-75 balls for this drill, as they will be used quickly. For an enhanced effect, play uplifting music on your portable speakers or phone. I do this with the children sometimes and they go crazy for it.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>The person feeding the balls will be positioned around mid-way between the service line and the baseline. The feeder should hit random shots to the player volleying at the net, one after another until all the balls are gone. I suggest varying the shots. Hit some fast, some slow, some high, to the left, to the right and even right at the volleyer.</p>
<p>The player at the net gets inundated with shots they have to volley, one after the other for about a minute straight. This is a great drill to sharpen the reflexes and make the player hit a ton of volleys in a very short period of time. It can work wonders for anyone’s volley game. Try it out for yourself.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="volley-overhead"></a></p>
<h2>Drill # 5 – Volley-Overhead Alternates</h2>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-220 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-alternating.jpg" alt="Alternating volley drill demonstration." width="800" height="407" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-alternating.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-alternating-300x153.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-alternating-768x391.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
</div>
<p>This drill is simple and straightforward, but very effective for improving the overhead.</p>
<p>One player performs the drill &#8211; although two players can do it too. One person is needed to feed the balls from the other side of the court. The person feeding will stand between the service line and baseline on one side of the court. On the other side, the player or players performing the drill will start about half-way between the net and service line.</p>
<p>If one player will be doing the drill, he or she can stand in the middle of the court. If two players do the drill, have one stand on the ad court and the other on the deuce court. The feeder will start by hitting a shot that has to be volleyed.</p>
<p>Once the volley is hit, the feeder will then give the player a lob. Keep alternating between a volley and a lob until the player gets tired. The feeder can vary the speed of the volley shots and lobs to adjust for the player’s skill level</p>
<p>If the overhead forces the player in back of the service line, he or she needs to move in towards the net again for the next volley. This drill requires good coordination and will improve the overhead smash.</p>
<p>If two players are performing the drill, you can make it a game by keeping score. Simply alternate giving a volley and overhead to the player on the deuce court and then a volley and overhead to the player on the ad court and keep repeating. A volley that goes over the net is worth one point and an overhead smash is worth two. Play up to 11 or 15 points.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="catch-and-volley"></a></p>
<h2>Drill # 6 – The Catch-And-Volley Drill</h2>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-222 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-catchvolley.jpg" alt="Catch volley drill demonstration" width="800" height="407" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-catchvolley.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-catchvolley-300x153.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-catchvolley-768x391.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
</div>
<p>The catch-and-volley drill is ideal for intermediate level players and those looking to add touch to their volleys.</p>
<p>We’re often taught to “punch” the volley, which does not involve a lot of touch. The catch-and-volley drill requires very soft hands by “catching” the ball on our racquet. This helps us to learn feel on the volley.</p>
<p>Children can and should be encouraged to perform this drill as well.</p>
<p>Basic volley technique is needed to perform this drill, and it may be difficult for beginners at first. It involves two players, one on each side of the net, both standing near the service line. This is really the same drill as the volley-to-volley drill with a couple of exceptions.</p>
<p>First, both players must “catch” the ball on their racquets. This is done by getting the racquet under the incoming volley causing it to bounce straight up from their racquet. While the ball is in mid-air, the player will hit a volley to the other player across the net. The player across the net will do the same. They’ll slow the ball by volleying with the racquet under the ball in a slice position (racquet face open) and this will cause the ball to move directly upwards. Once in mid-air, the player will volley the ball back across the net and the point continues.</p>
<p>This is a complicated drill to explain in words, so if it’s not clear to you, please watch our accompanying video. This is a great drill for improving your drop volley. You can increase the level of difficulty by adding a variation. If you “catch” the ball on your backhand side, try using a forehand volley to hit across the net. Do the inverse for catching on the forehand side. This requires great dexterity and requires fast reaction times.</p>
<div class="video-container"><iframe class="size-full aligncenter" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/BVSUl65cGrk?rel=0&amp;modestbranding=1&amp;start=120&amp;end=168" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen"></iframe></div>
<p>One additional note – if you receive a half volley, treat it like a regular volley and bounce it up off your racquet and then proceed to volley as usual. This drill can take a few times to learn for a beginner. Keep at it and make this drill a part of your practice sessions.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="half-court"></a></p>
<h2>Drill # 7 – The Half Court Volley Game</h2>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-223 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-half.jpg" alt="Half court volley game drill." width="800" height="407" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-half.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-half-300x153.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-half-768x391.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
</div>
<p>This is one of my favorite volley drills and I like to use it in warmups instead of mini tennis.</p>
<p>It requires two players. The players will be on opposite sides of the net, positioned at the service line. In this game, only one half of the court will be used. You can choose to play on the left side of the court or the right side – it really doesn’t matter. You can switch sides (left to right or right to left) after the game is over if you choose.</p>
<p>For the duration of the point and game, you need to stay around the service line. A point is won or lost the same as in a real tennis match with the exception that it is out if hit on the opposite side of the court. For example, if you play on the left side of the court, everything hit to the left of the center line is good. Any shot that lands to the right of the centerline is out. The doubles alley is considered out.</p>
<p>Player one starts out by hitting a shot to player two. Once player two volleys back, the point is live. You can hit groundstrokes, swinging volleys, half volleys, drop volleys and overheads if you can. Just don’t kill your partner! If you want to keep it cordial, just stick to punch volleys and half volleys.</p>
<p>I play up to 11 points and play 2-3 games in warmup.</p>
<p>This is an interesting and challenging game that makes warm-up fun. The harder you can volley and keep the ball in play, the better you’ll do. Try it out and add it your practice sessions as well.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="hit-the-target"></a></p>
<h2>Drill # 8 – Hit The Target</h2>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="wp-image-261 size-full aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-target.jpg" alt="Hit the target volley demonstration." width="800" height="407" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-target.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-target-300x153.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-target-768x391.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
</div>
<p>This drill involves one player hitting three different targeted areas on the court.</p>
<p>To delineate the areas, use cones. If you don’t have cones, tennis cans are good substitutes. Place three cones on the baseline 12 feet apart. The player doing the drill will stand on the other side of the net, near the middle of the court and about 3-6 feet from the net.</p>
<p>The use of a hopper is a good idea with this drill. The person feeding the balls will hit a forehand to the player volleying at the net. Before feeding the ball, the feeder will call out “left, right, or middle”. You can also say, “one, two or three,” to differentiate the three zones. After the forehand is hit by the feeder, the volleyer must try to hit the targeted area called out by the feeder.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>The feeder can vary the speed of the shot depending on the skill level of the player. Overheads can be thrown into the mix in the same way, with the feeder calling out the zone to aim for. Each time the player hits the right zone, they get a point.</p>
<p>I usually feed 20 balls to the net player and count the points. If you use this drill with the same person often, you can record their scores to come up with an average and personal best. In the next practice session, they can aim to beat it.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="service-line-touch"></a></p>
<h2>Bonus Drill – Service Line Touch Volley</h2>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="wp-image-228 size-full aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-servicelinetouch-1.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="407" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-servicelinetouch-1.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-servicelinetouch-1-300x153.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-servicelinetouch-1-768x391.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
</div>
<p>I can’t let you go without a bonus drill.</p>
<p>This one involves two players. In this drill one player stands at the service line, around the middle of the court. This player will only hit volleys.</p>
<p>The other player stands on the opposite side of the net, also around the service line and middle of the court. But this player can only hit groundstrokes.</p>
<p>The key to this drill is for the volley player to use touch to control the ball. If touch is not used it will be difficult to control the ball. For example, if touch is not used, the ball will fly off the volleyer’s racquet and not allow the player on the other side of the net to hit a groundstroke back.</p>
<div class="video-container"><iframe class="size-full aligncenter" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/BVSUl65cGrk?rel=0&amp;modestbranding=1&amp;start=120&amp;end=168" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen"></iframe></div>
<p>This drill works when there is a continuous flow of groundstroke and volley, groundstroke and volley, etc. This is another favorite drill of mine for learning to have soft hands at the net.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Summary – Putting It All Together</h2>
<p>There you have it. Nine awesome drills you can use to improve your serve and volley skills while having fun doing it. Use them with your children or employ them with your hitting partners. Tennis coaches can also use these drills with their clients to achieve definite improvement over time.</p>
<p>You can watch our youtube videos for visual demonstrations of all the drills. Until the next post, have fun, practice hard and keep coming to net!</p>
<p>The post <a href="/the-nine-best-tennis-drills-for-improving-the-serve-and-volley/">The 9 Best Tennis Drills For Improving Your Volley Game</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/the-nine-best-tennis-drills-for-improving-the-serve-and-volley/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>How Do I Beat A Serve And Volley Player In Tennis?</title>
		<link>/how-do-i-beat-a-serve-and-volley-player-in-tennis/</link>
					<comments>/how-do-i-beat-a-serve-and-volley-player-in-tennis/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chad Walner]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 09 Sep 2018 06:24:41 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Theory]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[volley]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=96</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>You look forward to playing almost all your matches, but the next one is against that dreaded serve and volley player at your club you can’t figure out. He or she rushes the net, doesn’t give you time to set &#8230; <a class="kt-excerpt-readmore" href="/how-do-i-beat-a-serve-and-volley-player-in-tennis/" aria-label="How Do I Beat A Serve And Volley Player In Tennis?">Read More</a></p>
<p>The post <a href="/how-do-i-beat-a-serve-and-volley-player-in-tennis/">How Do I Beat A Serve And Volley Player In Tennis?</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>You look forward to playing almost all your matches, but the next one is against that dreaded serve and volley player at your club you can’t figure out. He or she rushes the net, doesn’t give you time to set up on your shots, takes away your rhythm, and demoralizes you by ending the point with quick, decisive volleys.</p>
<p>So how to beat the serve and volley player?</p>
<p><strong>We must use a strategy that involves making the first volley extremely difficult to hit, if not impossible. If we take away that first volley, then the rest of the point should be easy. Our strategy to accomplish this will be to rush them by returning from close into the baseline, choosing targets uncomfortable for them, and either lobbing or driving hard and low to kill their first volley.</strong></p>
<p>We often talk about how to use the serve and volley game to your advantage, but now we’re going to focus on how to beat it. We’ll detail the various ways you can make the first volley extremely difficult for your opponent thereby giving you a great chance to win the match. By the end of this post, you’ll have a very clear idea of what’s needed to beat the serve and volley game.</p>
<p>No longer will you cower at the thought of your opponent rushing the net like a mad bull. We’re going to give you proven techniques to stop that charging bull in his or her tracks!</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Things To Keep In Mind</h2>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-929 alignright" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/thinker.jpg" alt="" width="400" height="327" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/thinker.jpg 400w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/thinker-300x245.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" />Before we talk about specific strategies to beat the serve and volley game, it’s key that you keep the following things in mind before you start your match. I think about them before every match and it allows me to dictate which strategies to employ. If you’re like me and want to give yourself the best chance of winning, any little edge cannot be overlooked. Here they are in no order of importance.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Wind</strong> – The wind will affect all shots in tennis. How windy is it during the time of the match? Which way is the wind blowing? By using the wind against your opponent, you can gain a slight edge. For example, by lobbing with the wind, you can force your opponent into a difficult overhead. You would not want to lob against the wind, as it could hold up your ball to be easily smashed. If the wind is moving sideways, it may not be advisable to hit in that direction, as your ball might go out. Hitting into the wind (to the other sideline) would be more advantageous.</li>
<li><strong>Know Your Opponent</strong> – The more you know about your opposition, the better you’ll fare. The three main things I want to know are: how good is their forehand volley, their backhand volley and their overhead? Whichever stroke is the weakest, is the one we’ll key in on most of the time. If we hit to their weakness all the time, we would become too predictable, which is why we need to vary our attack slightly.</li>
<li><strong>Court Surface</strong> – Are you playing on hardcourt, red clay or Har-Tru? How slow or fast are the courts? In general, the faster the court, the more it favors the serve and volley player. This is the reason we hardly ever see serve and volley play on red clay, which is the slowest surface. Hardcourt is the fastest with Har-Tru in between. If you’re a club player, you’ll probably never play on grass, which is extremely fast. If you’re playing on hardcourt, the serve and volley game can still be beat, so don’t worry about that.</li>
<li><strong>Lighting Conditions</strong> – If you’re playing a daytime match, the sun can be a factor. I would want to know the position of the sun so I can lob into the sun when it’s most difficult for my opponent to hit the overhead. As far as night conditions are concerned, they generally will have no effect on play except for older people with poor eyesight. Those players would benefit more playing daytime matches.</li>
<li><strong>Righty or Lefty?</strong> – Is your opponent a righty or lefty? This does matter. Most players (80-90%) will be righty. But playing a lefty can throw a monkey wrench into the equation. Everything is reversed. So where you set up for the return and where you place the return will be altered. The basic rule is to do the opposite of playing a righty. So if you planned on setting up to the right side of the court for a righty, now you’ll stand on the left side. If you play a few lefties, you’ll soon get used to the difference.</li>
</ul>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>It All Starts With The Return</h2>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="wp-image-940 size-full alignleft" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/portrait-of-a-tennis-player.jpg" alt="" width="400" height="267" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/portrait-of-a-tennis-player.jpg 400w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/portrait-of-a-tennis-player-300x200.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/portrait-of-a-tennis-player-272x182.jpg 272w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" />Beating the serve and volley player will rely largely on your return game. Serve and volley players always approach the net after a good, first serve. Some players even approach the net on a second serve as well, depending on its quality. Your first line of defense, or offense, to beating the serve and volley player is your return game.</p>
<p>When returning, we basically have the option of hitting with topspin or slice. Topspin is the easier shot for most people, but a good slice can work wonders on the return, especially on serves that &#8220;kick&#8221; or jump up high. This is especially true on the backhand side. Most players feel way more comfortable hitting a backhand slice at shoulder height or higher, rather than trying to deal with hitting a flat or topspin backhand at those heights.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>The slice can be very effective against the serve and volley game, but it must have pace and be relatively low over the net. A slice that floats high or does not have pace will be eaten up for breakfast by any skilled volley player. The slice shot return can work for all the strategies mentioned in this post except for lobs and topspin shots we want dipping to the feet of the opponent. You can even hit a very hard return right into the body of the rushing opponent.</p>
<p>A very well-struck slice with a tight rotation can be very difficult to volley, as the reverse spin can be hard to handle and most volley players are used to flat or topspin shots, and not slices.</p>
<p>The serve and volley player feasts on a weak return game, so we need our returns to be accurately struck for any hope of beating them. If we float our returns or don’t put them in the right place, we can kiss our hopes of winning goodbye. The techniques in this article are proven to work, but improving your return game goes hand-in-hand with it.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Move In On The Serve</h2>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-322 alignright" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/Mental1.jpg" alt="Moving in on the serve." width="400" height="572" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/Mental1.jpg 400w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/Mental1-210x300.jpg 210w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" />The first thing we can do to improve our chances is to stand close to the baseline on the return, preferably slightly inside. At most, you should set up 2-3 feet behind the baseline – and only against huge servers.</p>
<p>You may have seen Rafael Nadal (one of the greatest players of our age) standing 15 feet behind the baseline on the return and think it a good strategy. But he’s not facing serve and volley players on the pro tour.</p>
<p>Or, maybe you feel comfortable standing 6-7 feet behind the baseline to give yourself plenty of time to hit the return. That’s fine against baseline players who glue themselves to the baseline and dare not venture past it. You can float your returns and hit almost anywhere on the court without much retribution. However, all that goes out the window with a skilled volley player rushing the net behind a good serve.</p>
<p>Standing far behind the baseline does give you more time to hit the ball. Yes, that much is true. But guess what? It also gives your charging opponent more time to set up for that all-important first volley.</p>
<p>By standing 6 feet in back of the baseline on the return, the ball has to travel an extra 12 feet (6 feet to you and 6 feet back) before your opponent hits their first volley. This can allow as much as one second extra for your opposition to move in and set up. And a one-second difference means everything in tennis. It can easily be the reason you win or lose.</p>
<p>So what are the benefits of returning a serve close to the baseline? By standing close to it, we rob our opposition of time, forcing them to hit a return further from the net than they would like. This keeps them from advancing their position and allows us to create more angles of attack. It also gives us more time to set up for that very important first volley.</p>
<p>If you don’t like standing by the baseline on your returns, try it in practice matches. Do it there first, before you play an important match. You’ll soon get used to it and see how crucial it is to beating the serve and volley game.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Pick Your Targets</h2>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-938 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/target2.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/target2.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/target2-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/target2-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p>Now that you understand the importance of returning close to the baseline, let’s talk about where that first strike or return is going in terms of location. I like to think we have three clear-cut options for location on the return. It’s important we know them, understand which ones will work best on our opponent and when to use them. I’m going to break down each one.</p>
<p>When you return, you’ll want to choose one of these options. Keep in mind this will work against a serve we can control and place. Sometimes that isn’t possible because the serve comes in with too much placement or speed. If you play an opponent at your level, chances are 50-75% of the serves will be controllable – meaning within your reach.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h4>Target 1 – The Sidelines</h4>
<p>Hitting close to the sideline is a great way to diffuse and dismantle the charging serve and volley player. After all, he or she can’t be everywhere. The serve and volley player is banking on a return somewhere near the middle of the court, from where they can hit an effective volley. However, a well-placed shot to the sideline makes it nearly impossible for the opposition to volley. Even if they manage to get a racquet on the ball, and hit it over the net, it will be a weak shot easily put away by you.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>Now, the side of the court (deuce or ad) will dictate which sideline you will target. On the deuce side (right side), you’ll want to hit down the line, meaning the right side of the court, or the closest sideline to you. On the ad side (left side), the same rule applies – hit to the closest sideline to you, which will be the left side of the court. If you hit to the opposite sideline (from either the deuce or ad side), you run the risk of placing the ball in the middle of the court, where the ball can be easily picked off by your opponent.</p>
<p>As we can see, going down the closest sideline is your best chance to end the point quickly. However, with great opportunity comes great danger. The danger in employing this strategy is the difficulty level of hitting to close to the sideline. It takes skill and good timing on the return, but it can be done. Specifically, the danger in going down the line is that we must hit over the high part of the net and our ball can more easily go outside the court. Still, this is a strategy absolutely necessary to beat a good serve and volley player and should be used throughout the match.</p>
<p><strong>A Word About Height Of The Ball On The Return</strong><br />
A final point that is key for the return, but not often discussed, is the height of the shot. When you hit a return, in general, the lower and faster the ball, the better for you. A low shot means that the volleyer needs to volley up to get the ball over the net. This does not allow him or her to drive the ball like on a high shot. By forcing your opponent to volley from under the net, you will have a great chance at hitting the volley return and winning the point.</p>
<p>Just by managing to return hard and low, more than half the battle against the serve and volley player is won. When the ball goes low over the net it is also harder to read and makes the degree of difficulty rise for the volleyer. To boot, you also increase your chance of making the opponent miss the volley entirely or hit into a half volley, which is more of a defensive shot.</p>
<p>So when playing a good serve and volley player, try to hit hard, keep the shot as low as possible, and away from the volleyer. This is a great rule of thumb to follow. Keeping the ball in play during that first return is essential, so if you start hitting the return to net or out, tone down the power to keep your returns in play.</p>
<p>You want to at least make your opponent volley that first ball instead of handing over the point. There is a fine line between going for too much and hitting your spots. This is a constant judgment call in tennis that all players face. Much of the time, this judgment is dictated by how well or not you are hitting on that particular day and how skilled your opponent is.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h4>Target 2 – Directly At Your Opponent</h4>
<p>Now, you might think it contrary to common sense to hit directly at your opponent, but there is good reason to do so. By going right at the serve and volley player, you force them to volley from two odd positions that play into your advantage. We’ll go into both in detail below. Either way will work (and it’s advised to mix them up) but a definite factor in this strategy is how hard you hit and how well your opposition can volley.</p>
<p><strong>Method #1 Ping Them In The Chest Ivan Lendly Style</strong></p>
<p>Back in the 80s and early 90s, Ivan Lendl (one of the better men’s professional tennis players from that era) ruled the game with his pelting forehand. If you tried to serve and volley Lendl, he would often go right at you with a 90 mph forehand that discouraged future attempts to the net. While club players can rarely generate such speeds on their forehands, a well-struck return (either forehand or backhand) to the chest of the rushing opposition will definitely not be an easy shot for him or her.</p>
<p>In particular, you want to aim for the side of their chest with their dominant arm. The reason for this is because it’s easier to hit a backhand volley in the middle of your body but way more difficult on the forehand side. So for example, if a right-handed player is rushing the net, I’d want to hit a hard return to their right shoulder or chest area. Of course, we’re not looking to actually hit and hurt someone, but the volley player usually understands the risks of coming to net. We need room to hit and so a cannot be afraid to hit a hard shot in the direction of our opponent.</p>
<p>This method does work, especially if you can generate pace of 70 mph or more on your shots. If the shot is too slow, most good volley players will adjust in mid-stride and put the ball away. Still, give this method a try and see if it can work for you.</p>
<p><strong>Method #2 – Place The Ball At Their Feet</strong></p>
<p>Another general rule of thumb in beating a good serve and volley player is to place the ball at their feet.</p>
<p>If you can’t go around them or over them, a well-placed ball to the feet of the volleyer will cause all kinds of problems. First, it is difficult to time for the volley player. Second, it will most likely be a defensive shot from below the net. And third, it will impinge their forward movement to the net, briefly stopping them in their tracks. It’s incredibly difficult to hit a half volley on the run, even for the top professional players, much less club players.</p>
<p>The great thing for you in using this strategy is that it does not require a huge amount of pace. If you hit at a medium speed with some top-spin, the ball should dip right to the feet of the opponent as they reach the service line. Accordingly, the player will either miss the ball entirely, dump it into the net or give you a sitter (easy put away shot) not far from the net.</p>
<p>This strategy works at every level on every surface but can be especially effective on Har-Tru and red clay due to the uneven bounces. Try it out. Remember if you hit too deep, the ball will be in perfect position for the volleyer, since we are hitting down the middle of the court. Take something off the ball and add more topspin than you typically do to force the ball to dip.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>The Lob – The Serve And Volley Players Worst Nightmare</h2>
<p>A good lob can be the serve and volley players worst nightmare. This is especially true in sunny and windy conditions or if the player has trouble hitting overheads. The lob is a ball that is hit high to very high in the air, with top-spin, and optimally lands close to the baseline.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>I’ve beaten countless foe by using the lob. It offsets the opposition’s rhythm and causes them to stop, back-peddle and hit a shot of high difficulty (if placed far back on the court). What’s great for us is that a high skill level is not needed to hit the lob – anyone can do it. But good feel for the ball is essential, as you are lobbing off the return of serve, not a normal groundstroke.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h4>Three Caveats For The Lob You Must Know</h4>
<p>There are three caveats with the lob that must be mentioned.</p>
<p><strong>First,</strong> do not use it all the time. If you become predictable with it, your opponent will adjust by staying back a bit longer and wait for the lob and then smash it.</p>
<p><strong>Secondly,</strong> you must hit a deep lob (past the service line) in order for it to be effective against good players. A short lob that’s close to the net is put-away city for your opponent. Aim within a few feet of the baseline on every lob you hit. It will take time to develop a great lob, but it’s a fantastic weapon to have in your arsenal, not only off the return but on any shot.</p>
<p><strong>Third,</strong> you need to hit the ball high enough in the air to make the degree of difficulty high enough for your opponent to miss. Hitting an overhead smash on a ball 50 feet in the air is definitely more challenging than hitting a ball that is 20 feet in the air. However, if you can clearly hit the ball over your opponent and keep the ball in play, than any height lob will do. But on the return, and since your opponent will most often be near the service line when you strike the ball, it will be difficult to hit over them, so hitting high up is your next best option.</p>
<p>Hitting a high lob also gives you more time to set up for the smash. After you hit the lob, get to the middle of the court and keep close eye on how your opponent is setting up. You can then anticipate where the smash is headed and hit it back in play. I should also mention that forcing your opponent to hit a lob on their backhand side is often far more effective than the forehand side. You do this by lobbing to the side of their body with the non-hitting arm. Of course, the player can still step to the side and hit a normal overhead smash, but sometimes they can’t and you end up easily winning the point.</p>
<p>The overhead works particularly well in doubles when you lob the closer net player.</p>
<p>Check out more on the lob in this <a href="/how-to-hit-a-tennis-lob/">dedicated post on the lob</a>.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>What Happens After The First Volley?</h2>
<p>Let’s suppose your opponent serves to you, you make the return, and your opponent than volleys or hits an overhead somewhere on your side of the court. What’s next?</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="wp-image-942 size-full aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/question-mark-2405207_960_720.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/question-mark-2405207_960_720.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/question-mark-2405207_960_720-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/question-mark-2405207_960_720-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p>Most likely, your opponent will have moved in closer to the net in a more aggressive position to end the point; serve and volley players are taught to keep moving in until near the net and can easily put the ball away on a weak return. Being this is most likely the case, we can still go down-the-line, hit right at them or make a great lob. What is probably taken away from us is the option of hitting at their feet, since they are closed in on the net now. That strategy will usually end badly for us when our opponents are within 6-7 feet of the net or closer. But, what does open up to us is the cross court pass.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h4>The Cross Court Pass</h4>
<p>If you receive back a volley and have time to set up, your opposition has closed in to a more aggressive position. Both of you are now in position to end the point with the next shot. Most likely the serve and volley player will be near the middle of the net or <b>edged sli<span class="gmail_default">ghtly</span> over to protec<span class="gmail_default">t</span> the side line you are closest to. When this happens, they are ripe for a cross court pass</b>, often catching them off-guard. The angle needs to be fairly sharp, so it does require some precision hitting and skill. This is a great play that works well for me against all level of volley players</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h4>The End Of The Point</h4>
<p>If you or your opponent does not end the point after one or two volleys, then the point is probably favoring you, the returner. With your opponent at net, all you need is some time to set up for a pass (cross court or down-the-line), a good lob or even a direct hard shot right at their body. Some key points to remember if you find yourself in this part of the point.</p>
<p>Keep your cool and do not panic. You have the various options mentioned above to work with. Choose one and be decisive in your play. If you decide to lob, just do it and hit it well.</p>
<p>Footwork is key. Too many players stand around and watch their shots, not resetting for the next one. Being that the net player can quickly volley back, you need to be on your toes and ready for the next shot. Great footwork in this situation is essential.</p>
<p>Remember, when the player is right at the net, soft shots won’t win the point. You need to hit fast paced shots, well-placed medium paced shots or a good lob. Resist the temptation to just get the ball back softly and hope the opposition will miss at the net. It’s far better for us to control our own fate than leave it in the hands of the volley player.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Putting It All Together</h2>
<p>Now that you know what it takes to beat a serve and volley player, you can at least feel confident in having a good game plan going into your next match. Often club players have no idea of how to beat a serve and volley player and hit anywhere only to lose badly.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>You are now way ahead of the average club player in knowing what to do. All that is needed is to apply this information in the match. Remember, you’re going to lose points, some decisively, but keep coming back to the strategies outlined in this post. Never feel discouraged out there and keep a positive attitude on every point. It sounds hokey, but it truly does work. I simply brush off bad points, knowing that I’m a good player and have a great shot at winning the next one. I have a friend named Leon, who always tells me to &#8220;hit the delete button&#8221; after a bad shot, and he’s totally right.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-92" style="margin-bottom: 0px; padding-bottom: 0px;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/practice-tips220x40.png" alt="" width="220" height="40" /></p>
<blockquote><p>Knowing how to beat the serve and volley game is not enough to do it on the court. You need to practice your down-the-line shots, your high-pace shots, your top-spin shots and your lob every chance you get. Push the pace in practice and go past your comfort zone. This will help you during the match. I heard that Rafael Nadal misses as much as 50% of his groundstrokes in practice because he’s pushing the the envelope on almost every shot he hits. Instead of avoiding the serve and volley player, seek them out and play against them as much as possible. Doing so will allow you to feel more comfortable hitting under pressure. And through experience you’ll begin to find the right shots to win the point – and ultimately, the match.</p></blockquote>
<p>We have a host of articles in this blog to help your tennis game. If you have any questions, feel free to drop us a comment and we’ll respond. Additionally, we have dozens of high-quality videos on our youtube channel where you can learn every part of tennis. If you can learn to consistently beat the serve and volley game, you’ll soon become one of the most feared and respected players at your club!</p>
<p>The post <a href="/how-do-i-beat-a-serve-and-volley-player-in-tennis/">How Do I Beat A Serve And Volley Player In Tennis?</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/how-do-i-beat-a-serve-and-volley-player-in-tennis/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>7 Volley Types You Must Know To Master Your Net Game</title>
		<link>/seven-volley-types-you-must-know-to-master-your-net-game/</link>
					<comments>/seven-volley-types-you-must-know-to-master-your-net-game/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chad Walner]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 08 Sep 2018 07:20:33 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Training]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[volley]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=52</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>You may have always believed there is only one volley in tennis. However, that’s not the case, as we’ll soon see. The volley game is a bit more intricate and in-depth than most people realize. To serve and volley effectively, &#8230; <a class="kt-excerpt-readmore" href="/seven-volley-types-you-must-know-to-master-your-net-game/" aria-label="7 Volley Types You Must Know To Master Your Net Game">Read More</a></p>
<p>The post <a href="/seven-volley-types-you-must-know-to-master-your-net-game/">7 Volley Types You Must Know To Master Your Net Game</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>You may have always believed there is only one volley in tennis. However, that’s not the case, as we’ll soon see. The volley game is a bit more intricate and in-depth than most people realize.</p>
<p><strong>To serve and volley effectively, you need to be aware of the seven volley types and when and how to use them.</strong></p>
<p><strong>The seven volley types are the <a href="#punch">punch volley</a>, the <a href="#block">block volley</a>, the <a href="#drop">drop volley</a>, the <a href="#drive">drive volley</a>, the <a href="#half">half volley</a>, the <a href="#swinging">swinging volley</a>, and lastly, the <a href="#overhead">overhead</a>. </strong></p>
<p>While the overhead is not really classified as a type of volley by most teaching pros, it should be thought of as one, as the ball is taken directly out of the air in most instances. The one instance where that’s not true is when a player allows the ball to bounce first and then uses the overhead smash stroke to put the ball away.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>What Exactly Is A Volley?</h2>
<p><em>In tennis terms, a volley occurs when a player hits the ball directly out of the air, not allowing the ball to bounce on the court first.</em></p>
<p>If the ball hits the ground and the player uses a groundstroke (forehand or backhand) that is considered a rally. Many people confuse the two terms – rally and volley – believing that rallies are called volleys. So next time you go to the court, you will now know the proper tennis terminology to use.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1168" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/IMG_0002-backhandvolley.jpg" alt="Backhand Volley." width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/IMG_0002-backhandvolley.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/IMG_0002-backhandvolley-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/IMG_0002-backhandvolley-768x432.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/IMG_0002-backhandvolley-560x315.jpg 560w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p>There are a couple of additional points of information to know about volleys. If the ball hits the ground first, it can still be volleyed in some sense. This is because it can depends on the type of swing used to hit the ball.</p>
<p><strong>A volley “swing” is usually short and compact</strong> and does not involve a take-back.</p>
<p>On typical forehand and backhand ground strokes, players <strong>follow through by finishing with the racquet on the other side of their body</strong>. On the volley, that follow through is not present. This is another feature that distinguishes the volley from the groundstroke.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>One exception to the above “rule” is when a player uses a full groundstroke swing to hit the ball out of the air. This is technically a volley (<a href="#swinging">swinging volley</a>) because the ball is taken out of the air before it bounces, even though a groundstroke is used.</p>
<p>We will get into more detail on this volley type soon. If all this sounds confusing, don’t worry. We will address each volley type below with pictures so it is straightforward to understand. As an added teaching aid, a video will accompany this blog post showing you exactly how to hit each volley type. By reading this post and watching the video, you’ll have a comprehensive knowledge of the volley game and be well on your way to a budding net game.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="punch"></a></p>
<h2>The Punch Volley</h2>
</div>
<p><em>The punch volley is executed by taking a very short and compact swing.</em></p>

<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Punch-Volley.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="449" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Punch-Volley.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="A front-on view of a punch volley" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Punch-Volley.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Punch-Volley-300x168.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Punch-Volley-768x431.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Punch-Volley-560x314.jpg 560w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></a>

<p>Keep in mind that on most volleys, the racquet is never taken back past the shoulders. In the punch volley, the racquet is moved quickly forward and slightly down, giving a bit of underspin to the ball. This is the volley most people think of when talking about a traditional net game.</p>
<p>You may have heard coaches telling you to “punch” the ball. While the word “punch” is a bit of a misnomer, it is called a punch volley because you need to supply a bit of forward momentum to the racquet to give the ball some pace. Additionally, stepping forward and into the ball with the opposite foot helps generate even more pace.</p>
<div class="video-container"><iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/NBLgs-4JF3s?rel=0&amp;modestbranding=1&amp;" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen"></iframe></div>
<p>This volley type is most often used on medium pace balls that are higher than the net. If the ball drops under the net and is volleyed the punch volley becomes very difficult, if not impossible, to hit. In doubles, this is the type of volley that will be used the most by the person playing the net. The punch volley is a crucial volley for executing a great net attack.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-92" style="margin-bottom: 0px; padding-bottom: 0px;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/practice-tips220x40.png" alt="" width="220" height="40" /></p>
<blockquote><p>To practice the punch volley, stand 3-6 feet from the net and have your partner hit medium paced shots to you that go at least a foot or two above the net. You can consider this volley as the bread and butter of your net game.</p></blockquote>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="block"></a></p>
<h2>The Block Volley</h2>
</div>
<p><em>The block volley is as its name suggests: a block.</em></p>

<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Block-Volley.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="449" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Block-Volley.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="A block volley (forehand)." srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Block-Volley.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Block-Volley-300x168.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Block-Volley-768x431.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Block-Volley-732x410.jpg 732w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Block-Volley-366x205.jpg 366w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Block-Volley-560x314.jpg 560w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></a>
<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Block-Volley-Backhand.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="449" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Block-Volley-Backhand.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="A block volley (backhand)." srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Block-Volley-Backhand.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Block-Volley-Backhand-300x168.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Block-Volley-Backhand-768x431.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Block-Volley-Backhand-732x410.jpg 732w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Block-Volley-Backhand-366x205.jpg 366w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Block-Volley-Backhand-560x314.jpg 560w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></a>

<p>On this type of volley, we simply place the racquet in position to intercept a very fast struck ball with no take-back or forward swing (punch). Your body does not need to move forward at all on this type of volley either.</p>
<p>The block volley is most often used when your opponent hits a very fast shot in your direction. If a punch volley is used on a very fast shot, the ball will be difficult to control and often be hit out. So on very fast shots, we use what is called the block volley and it’s extremely effective.</p>
<p>When small children first learn the net game, this is often the type of volley taught, as it requires very little technique. However, executing a great block volley can be very tricky, as hard-struck balls are extremely difficult to control. Anyone who has tried to volley a tennis ball moving at 80 mph or more knows that.</p>
<div class="video-container"><iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/xwJTKU1n2vM?rel=0&amp;modestbranding=1&amp;" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen"></iframe></div>
<p>To counter that speed, great volley players allow some give to the racquet by holding it very loosely when making contact with the ball. If you look at some block volleys in slow motion, you can actually see the racquet forced back several inches or more by the speed of the ball. This is only accomplished with a very loose grip.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>Most beginner, and even intermediate level players, will hold the racquet way too firmly on the block volley. By holding the racquet loosely, it slows the ball down enough so that it remains in the court.</p>
<p>While this is by far the simplest volley technique to employ, it can be the most tricky. Many club players get into the habit of moving the racquet forward on every volley and holding the grip firmly, as done in the punch volley. Doing so on the block volley only spells disaster.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-92" style="margin-bottom: 0px; padding-bottom: 0px;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/practice-tips220x40.png" alt="" width="220" height="40" /></p>
<blockquote><p>To practice the block volley, have your partner hit very fast balls to you at the net. If your partner cannot hit fast, have them stand closer to you or use a tennis ball machine on a fast speed setting.</p></blockquote>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="drop"></a></p>
<h2>The Drop Volley (The Touch Volley)</h2>
</div>
<p><em>The drop volley is hit softly, dropping the shot closely, out of the baseline players range.</em></p>

<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Drop-Volley.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="449" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Drop-Volley.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="A drop volley (front view)." srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Drop-Volley.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Drop-Volley-300x168.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Drop-Volley-768x431.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Drop-Volley-560x314.jpg 560w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></a>
<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Drop-Volley-3.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="449" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Drop-Volley-3.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="A drop volley (side view)." srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Drop-Volley-3.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Drop-Volley-3-300x168.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Drop-Volley-3-768x431.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Drop-Volley-3-560x314.jpg 560w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></a>

<p>The drop volley, also called the touch volley, is similar to the block volley technique but with a few differences. In the block volley, we hit a hard-paced shot back on our opponent’s court with similar pace, redirecting their power. However, on the drop volley, our aim is to hit a very soft volley close to the net. The point of doing this is to place the ball far from our opponent, who is usually camped out on the baseline or beyond.</p>
<p>By placing the ball close to the net, your opponent will have to run all the way from the baseline in order to make contact with the ball. Many times, he or she will not be able to get a racquet on the ball. Even if they do, a well placed drop volley will cause your opponent to lunge at the ball and hit into the net.</p>
<p>The drop volley is a great way to fatigue your opponent and end the point quickly. The major danger of hitting a drop volley is that if not done well, it can easily be put away by your opponent. This typically happens when your intended &#8220;drop” volley lands close to the middle of the court and bounces too high, with your opponent being able to easily pounce on it like a hungry tiger.</p>
<p>It’s very important that you use a very loose grip and allow the racquet to have a lot of give. Against big hitters, you’ll probably find it difficult to use the drop volley, as it’s more of an advanced technique – albeit extremely effective. However, it’s not impossible to use the drop volley on high-velocity shots.</p>
<p>Pros and advanced players can still hit the drop volley on shots of those speeds (usually 70 mph +). For beginner and intermediate players, fast paced shots should be handled almost exclusively by the block volley.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-92" style="margin-bottom: 0px; padding-bottom: 0px;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/practice-tips220x40.png" alt="" width="220" height="40" /></p>
<blockquote><p>To practice the drop volley, have someone hit you medium paced shots at the net. Keep a loose grip and allow plenty of give on the racquet. The ball should be forcing your racquet backwards. On the drop volley the point is to put as little pace on the ball as possible. Just a light touch or a little backspin is all that’s needed. If your balls are landing with almost no pace a couple of feet from the net, you’re doing it correctly.</p></blockquote>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="drive"></a></p>
<h2>The Drive Volley</h2>
</div>
<p><em>The drive volley uses the longest swing path of all the volleys and is ideally used on slow shots that are a couple of feet or more above the net.</em></p>

<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Drive-Volley-1.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="449" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Drive-Volley-1.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="Forehand Drive Volley (1)" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Drive-Volley-1.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Drive-Volley-1-300x168.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Drive-Volley-1-768x431.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Drive-Volley-1-538x302.jpg 538w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Drive-Volley-1-269x151.jpg 269w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></a>
<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Drive-Volley-2.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="449" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Drive-Volley-2.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="Forehand Drive Volley (2)" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Drive-Volley-2.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Drive-Volley-2-300x168.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Drive-Volley-2-768x431.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Drive-Volley-2-538x302.jpg 538w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Drive-Volley-2-269x151.jpg 269w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></a>
<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Drive-Volley-3.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="449" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Drive-Volley-3.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="Forehand Drive Volley (3)" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Drive-Volley-3.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Drive-Volley-3-300x168.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Drive-Volley-3-768x431.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Drive-Volley-3-538x302.jpg 538w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Drive-Volley-3-269x151.jpg 269w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></a>
<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Drive-Volley-4.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="449" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Drive-Volley-4.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="Forehand Drive Volley (4)" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Drive-Volley-4.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Drive-Volley-4-300x168.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Drive-Volley-4-768x431.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Drive-Volley-4-538x302.jpg 538w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Drive-Volley-4-269x151.jpg 269w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></a>
<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Drive-Volley-A.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="449" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Drive-Volley-A.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="Backhand Drive Volley (1)" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Drive-Volley-A.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Drive-Volley-A-300x168.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Drive-Volley-A-768x431.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Drive-Volley-A-538x302.jpg 538w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Drive-Volley-A-269x151.jpg 269w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></a>
<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Drive-Volley-B.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="449" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Drive-Volley-B.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="Backhand Drive Volley (2)" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Drive-Volley-B.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Drive-Volley-B-300x168.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Drive-Volley-B-768x431.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Drive-Volley-B-538x302.jpg 538w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Drive-Volley-B-269x151.jpg 269w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></a>
<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Drive-Volley-C.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="449" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Drive-Volley-C.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="Backhand Drive Volley (3)" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Drive-Volley-C.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Drive-Volley-C-300x168.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Drive-Volley-C-768x431.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Drive-Volley-C-538x302.jpg 538w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Drive-Volley-C-269x151.jpg 269w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></a>
<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Drive-Volley-D.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="449" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Drive-Volley-D.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="Backhand Drive Volley (4)" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Drive-Volley-D.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Drive-Volley-D-300x168.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Drive-Volley-D-768x431.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Drive-Volley-D-538x302.jpg 538w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Drive-Volley-D-269x151.jpg 269w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></a>

<p>The less pace the ball has when it comes to us, the more we need to swing to generate pace. Pace allows us to put the ball away so our opponent cannot return it. Advanced players that anticipate well can use the drive volley on medium-paced shots, but it’s not recommended for beginner or intermediate players to try.</p>
<p>To hit the drive volley, the shoulders are turned and the racquet is usually taken back and held up high. However, it is still advised not to take the volley past the point of the shoulders, as this is likely to cause a miss and is unnecessary.</p>
<p>On the drive volley, we have time to set up into a power position because the ball is coming in slow. The objective of this volley is to hit the ball with pace and placement while finishing the point immediately. Any advanced net player will end the point 9 out of 10 times with the drive volley in singles.</p>
<p>This volley is crucial to taking your net game to the next level. If you can’t put away the slow, easy shots, the game becomes very hard for you at the net. We need to be able to decisively end the point with the drive volley.</p>
<div class="video-container"><iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/4Whkg8eHSTI?rel=0&amp;modestbranding=1&amp;" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen"></iframe></div>
<p>On this volley you can also take a nice step in and get your weight into the shot. Remember, since the incoming ball has little pace, you need to move your racquet quickly forward and slightly down (creating backspin).</p>
<p><strong>The two most common issues when hitting the drive volley that I see is not coming up to the ball and not moving the racquet forward with enough velocity to volley with pace.</strong></p>
<p>The drive volley is one of the easier volleys to practice, as the ball comes to you slowly. You must be equally adept on both the forehand and backhand drive volley to control the net effectively. When your opponent sees you effortlessly put away a drive volley far out of their reach, it strikes fear into them and makes coming to the net easier the next time around for you.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-92" style="margin-bottom: 0px; padding-bottom: 0px;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/practice-tips220x40.png" alt="" width="220" height="40" /></p>
<blockquote><p>To practice the drive volley have your opponents hit you slow-paced shots at least 2-3 feet above the net. Try aiming to the corners and down the middle, as these are the most common places you’ll want to hit the drive volley.</p></blockquote>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="half"></a></p>
<h2>The Half Volley</h2>
</div>
<p><em>The half volley is defined as a volley stroke used on a ball that has already bounced.</em></p>

<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Half-Volley-Backhand.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="449" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Half-Volley-Backhand.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="A half volley backhand." srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Half-Volley-Backhand.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Half-Volley-Backhand-300x168.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Half-Volley-Backhand-768x431.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Half-Volley-Backhand-560x314.jpg 560w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></a>
<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Half-Volley.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="449" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Half-Volley.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="A half volley forehand." srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Half-Volley.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Half-Volley-300x168.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Half-Volley-768x431.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Half-Volley-560x314.jpg 560w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></a>

<p>The half volley is most often used when we can’t get up to the ball fast enough to volley it out of the air. This volley can be very effective, as in some ways it can be easier to place than a traditional volley. This is because the court surface, especially clay, can reduce the speed of the ball, allowing us to more easily control it.</p>
<p>Hitting a drop shot off a half volley is especially effective and usually surprises the baseline-bound opponent. On the flip side, half volleys can be incredibly challenging as well and even give advanced players fits. This can happen on hard-struck balls that bounce very close to your body. The best way to deal with these types of shots is to simply block the ball to hit your half volley. So it would be similar to hitting a block volley, but the ball hits the ground first.</p>
<p>You can also employ the drop volley technique on slower hit half volley shots. These two volley techniques are the most common ones used on half volleys. However, the drive volley can be used on slow balls that bounce up high at the net, though this is much rarer.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>The half volley requires good hand-eye coordination and lots of practice to master. If you are planning on being a serve and volley player, it’s essential you can hit half volleys.</p>
<p>Many times while coming into the net off the serve, you’ll be forced to hit them. Since half volleys are usually hit from under the net, it’s difficult put them away with drive. So best to think about using placement when half volleying, especially at the beginner and intermediate levels. When you’re forced to half volley hard-struck balls, just aim for keeping the ball in play and then get to the net and set up for next shot.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-92" style="margin-bottom: 0px; padding-bottom: 0px;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/practice-tips220x40.png" alt="" width="220" height="40" /></p>
<blockquote><p>To practice the half volley, stand 6-10 feet from the net and have your partner feed you medium-paced shots that land right in front of you. Good racquet feel is essential to hitting effective half volleys.</p></blockquote>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="swinging"></a></p>
<h2>The Swinging Volley</h2>
</div>
<p><em>This is an advanced level volley that is employed when a player uses a forehand or backhand groundstroke to hit the ball directly out of the air.</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>

<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/4.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="450" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/4.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="Forehand Swinging Volley (1)" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/4.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/4-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/4-768x432.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/4-538x302.jpg 538w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/4-269x151.jpg 269w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/4-560x315.jpg 560w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></a>
<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/5.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="450" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/5.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="Forehand Swinging Volley (2)" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/5.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/5-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/5-768x432.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/5-538x302.jpg 538w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/5-269x151.jpg 269w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/5-560x315.jpg 560w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></a>
<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/6.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="450" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/6.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="Forehand Swinging Volley (3)" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/6.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/6-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/6-768x432.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/6-538x302.jpg 538w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/6-269x151.jpg 269w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/6-560x315.jpg 560w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></a>
<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/7.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="450" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/7.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="Forehand Swinging Volley (4)" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/7.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/7-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/7-768x432.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/7-538x302.jpg 538w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/7-269x151.jpg 269w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/7-560x315.jpg 560w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></a>
<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/8.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="450" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/8.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="Backhand Swinging Volley (1)" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/8.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/8-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/8-768x432.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/8-538x302.jpg 538w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/8-269x151.jpg 269w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></a>
<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/9.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="450" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/9.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="Backhand Swinging Volley (2)" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/9.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/9-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/9-768x432.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/9-538x302.jpg 538w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/9-269x151.jpg 269w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></a>
<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/10.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="450" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/10.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="Backhand Swinging Volley (3)" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/10.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/10-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/10-768x432.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/10-538x302.jpg 538w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/10-269x151.jpg 269w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></a>
<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/11.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="450" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/11.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="Backhand Swinging Volley (4)" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/11.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/11-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/11-768x432.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/11-538x302.jpg 538w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/11-269x151.jpg 269w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></a>

<p>The swinging volley is rare to see at the club level, but it’s personally one of my favorite volleys to hit. It can end the point decisively and is beautiful to watch. However, it requires great hand-eye coordination and the margin for error is much greater than a traditional compact volley technique.</p>
<p>The swinging volley is almost exclusively executed on slow-paced balls above the net, however, it can be used for balls that drop below the height of the net as well – though seldom seen. As the net player takes a full swing at the ball, the ball is usually struck with such pace that it cannot be returned by the opponent. Every tour-level player, men and women both, can hit the swinging volley to abruptly end the point.</p>
<p>While volleys can technically be hit from anywhere on the court &#8211; the net, the service line, the baseline – most compact volleys are hit inside the service line. However, the swinging volley can be hit effectively from anywhere on the court, with most being struck a few feet in back or front of the service line. The big wind up of the swinging volley makes it difficult for an opponent to read as well.</p>
<p>Simply by practicing the swinging volley, even if you never use it in a match, you’ll improve your racquet speed and hand-eye coordination. While not imperative to learn, as the other volley techniques mentioned here will do fine for you, the swinging volley can be like a secret weapon you take out once in while to nuke your opponent and demoralize their spirits. Okay, maybe that sounds a little too dramatic, but trust me, it’s the most fun volley to hit in tennis.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-92" style="margin-bottom: 0px; padding-bottom: 0px;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/practice-tips220x40.png" alt="" width="220" height="40" /></p>
<blockquote><p>To practice the swinging volley have a player toss a ball to you and use your forehand groundstroke to hit the ball directly out of the air. Make sure the person tossing the ball is off to the side and not directly in front of you. You wouldn’t want to accidentally hit them and ruin your whole practice session (plus they wouldn’t like you anymore). Do as many reps as needed and then switch to the backhand side. Keep in mind the swinging volley takes much more energy to hit than the volleys previously mentioned, so you may find yourself getting tired after not too long. Don’t worry, that ‘s normal. Make the swinging volley a part of your volley arsenal if you can. You won’t regret it.</p></blockquote>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="overhead"></a></p>
<h2>Bonus Volley: The Overhead Smash</h2>
</div>
<p><em>This is the one technique that professional coaches and players dispute being a true volley. We are going to say it is here. The overhead smash occurs when a player takes the ball directly out of the air (usually on a lob), hitting the ball from above their head.</em></p>

<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Overhead7.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="449" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Overhead7.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="Overhead Smash (Right side view)" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Overhead7.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Overhead7-300x168.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Overhead7-768x431.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Overhead7-732x410.jpg 732w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Overhead7-366x205.jpg 366w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Overhead7-560x314.jpg 560w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></a>
<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Overhead-8.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="449" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Overhead-8.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="Overhead Smash (Right side view)" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Overhead-8.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Overhead-8-300x168.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Overhead-8-768x431.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Overhead-8-732x410.jpg 732w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Overhead-8-366x205.jpg 366w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Overhead-8-560x314.jpg 560w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></a>
<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Overhead-5.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="449" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Overhead-5.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="Overhead Smash (Front view)" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Overhead-5.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Overhead-5-300x168.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Overhead-5-768x431.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Overhead-5-732x410.jpg 732w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Overhead-5-366x205.jpg 366w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Overhead-5-560x314.jpg 560w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></a>
<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Overhead-6.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="449" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Overhead-6.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="Overhead Smash (Front view)" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Overhead-6.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Overhead-6-300x168.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Overhead-6-768x431.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Overhead-6-732x410.jpg 732w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Overhead-6-366x205.jpg 366w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Overhead-6-560x314.jpg 560w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></a>
<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Overhead-3.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="449" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Overhead-3.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="Overhead Smash (Left side view)" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Overhead-3.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Overhead-3-300x168.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Overhead-3-768x431.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Overhead-3-732x410.jpg 732w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Overhead-3-366x205.jpg 366w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Overhead-3-560x314.jpg 560w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></a>
<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Overhead-4.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="449" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Overhead-4.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="Overhead Smash (Left side view)" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Overhead-4.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Overhead-4-300x168.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Overhead-4-768x431.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Overhead-4-732x410.jpg 732w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Overhead-4-366x205.jpg 366w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/2018-09-09Overhead-4-560x314.jpg 560w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></a>

<p>The player moves the racquet quickly over head (similar to some parts of a serve motion) and hits a very fast paced shot that hopefully ends the rally. There is one exception to this rule &#8211; yes, there are many exceptions in tennis. The one exception happens when the player allows the ball to bounce first and then employs the overhead smash to put away the ball. This is quite common and is advised for many beginner players, as it is far easier to hit a smash after the ball hits the ground.</p>
<p>The exception – again, here we go with the exceptions – is if the ball is moving quickly backwards or if the ball does not bounce up high enough to hit the overhead smash (but you still try anyway).</p>
<p>The overhead smash can be one of the most challenging shots in tennis for a variety of reasons. For one, if you play daytime tennis there is this nasty thing called the sun that often blinds you when you look to the sky. For this reason, you should be aware of the position of the sun from your side of the court so you can plan accordingly.</p>
<p>Additionally, night tennis can be tough too, as the ball can be hit so high that it goes outside the space of the lights and can be lost from sight for a couple of seconds.</p>
<p>The other major challenge is the wind, which can play havoc with that 2-ounce tennis ball before it reaches your racquet.</p>
<p>These are factors that all players contend with, so just accept them and get used to them. It’s par for the course for any good volley player. For beginners, the overhead smash will most likely be the toughest shot to hit due to the precise timing needed to hit the shot. Practice makes close to perfect here.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>Some tips on the overhead are to turn to the side, get your racquet into the power position early and use your non-dominant hand to act as a guide for tracking the ball. Moving can also be an issue for beginners. Use the cross step and shuffle to move back. Many players I see at the club level, walk backwards to hit an overhead, which is technically incorrect and can cause you to fall.</p>
<p>A well-hit overhead is a thing of beauty and can and should decisively end the point. The overhead can be struck effectively from anywhere on the court and is an often-used technique at every level of tennis.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-92" style="margin-bottom: 0px; padding-bottom: 0px;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/practice-tips220x40.png" alt="" width="220" height="40" /></p>
<blockquote><p>To practice the overhead smash, have your partner feed you low, easy-to-handle lobs from the other side of the net. As you improve your overhead, your partner can slowly increase the difficultly level by hitting higher lobs and making you move more.</p></blockquote>
<p>The post <a href="/seven-volley-types-you-must-know-to-master-your-net-game/">7 Volley Types You Must Know To Master Your Net Game</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/seven-volley-types-you-must-know-to-master-your-net-game/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
