<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Training Archives - Serve and Volley Tennis</title>
	<atom:link href="/category/training/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/category/training/</link>
	<description>Your secret weapon on the court.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 15 Aug 2019 10:02:02 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	

<image>
	<url>/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/cropped-ted_svt_favicon-32x32.png</url>
	<title>Training Archives - Serve and Volley Tennis</title>
	<link>/category/training/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>What Gym Exercises Will Improve My Tennis Serve?</title>
		<link>/what-gym-exercises-will-improve-my-tennis-serve/</link>
					<comments>/what-gym-exercises-will-improve-my-tennis-serve/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chad Walner]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 04 Mar 2019 14:49:11 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Training]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=2023</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>When it comes to serving in tennis, we all want more power. While placement and consistency are just as important, power seems to be all that people talk about on the serve. We marvel at watching Serena Williams and John &#8230; <a class="kt-excerpt-readmore" href="/what-gym-exercises-will-improve-my-tennis-serve/" aria-label="What Gym Exercises Will Improve My Tennis Serve?">Read More</a></p>
<p>The post <a href="/what-gym-exercises-will-improve-my-tennis-serve/">What Gym Exercises Will Improve My Tennis Serve?</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>When it comes to serving in tennis, we all want more power. While placement and consistency are just as important, power seems to be all that people talk about on the serve.</p>
<p>We marvel at watching Serena Williams and John Isner hit 120-140 mph serves. Yet most club players can’t even break the 100 mph mark. Is it because they lack power?</p>
<p>Well, yes and no. Some players have power and others don’t, but technique is also definitely a big factor when it comes to hitting fast serves.</p>
<p><strong>But some players have solid technique and still lack the serve velocity they wish to achieve. You may be one of those people. So what can we do to increase serve power?</strong></p>
<p><strong>The solution can be found in doing certain gym exercises that will increase the fast twitch muscle fibers in our bodies. These serve exercises will improve our explosiveness, helping us achieve higher serve velocities.</strong></p>
<p>It’s important to point out that serve velocity comes from three distinct phases of the serve motion. I’ve listed them below.</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Racket Drop</strong></li>
<li><strong>Pronation</strong></li>
<li><strong>Knee bend and explosion upwards of body</strong></li>
</ol>
<p>These three parts of the serve account for almost all the power. If you lack in one, you’ll never achieve your maximum potential for serve power. If you lack in two, you have your work cut out for you.</p>
<p>I could get into a long discussion of each one. But I’ll give a quick summary of each. My point is that we need to do gym exercises that will improve the ability to do each phase better.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p><strong>Racket Drop</strong> – This is the part of the serve swing where the tip of the racket will drop near the server’s lower back. Generally, the deeper the racket drop, the more power is produced. Flexibility is key here in the shoulder.</p>
<p><strong>Pronation</strong> – I’ve discussed pronation in many <a href="/5-steps-to-a-great-tennis-serve-for-beginners-with-pics-and-video/">other blog posts</a> and videos. It’s basically swiveling of the radius and ulna bones in the forearm. If you place your arm straight out in front of you with palm up, that’s called supination. Now turn your palm down by just swiveling your arm. When your palm is down, that’s called pronation. Pronation can produce tremendous racket head speed in a very short space.</p>
<p><strong>Knee Bend And Explosion Of The Body Upward</strong> – This is the most crucial part of the serve motion and the one we can improve the most with gym exercises. This is also the phase that almost all club players struggle with. If you watch a professional tennis player’s serve motion compared with a club player, this part is the most glaring difference.</p>
<p>Why is that true? Because most club players don’t bend their knees enough and explode up into the air. They also don’t jump forward enough. Doing so requires strength, power, and explosion from the legs.</p>
<p>So why do club players suffer in this part of the serve? I believe there are several good reasons. One is that they weren’t trained to do so. Professional players are trained from an early age to explode into the serve.</p>
<p>The second reason is that club players don’t possess the energy and athleticism to consistently explode up into the ball. Many club players are older people with less-than-perfect knees. The upward explosion into the ball is an athletic move that many club players can’t perform.</p>
<p>I think we see pro players on TV so often that we take for granted how much they are actually jumping up to hit the ball. And that takes a lot of energy to do over 3-5 sets. Most club players barely get off the ground.</p>
<p>I’ve personally worked with older players (age 50-70) who had solid technique on their serve motion but could barely break 80-85 mph. Why? Because they had little knee bend and almost zero explosion in this third phase of the serve.</p>
<p>While players of all ages can benefit from these simple gym exercises for the serve (that I’m about to go into), those with the weakest legs may benefit the most.<br />
I’m going to recommend the best gym exercises for the serve for each of the three phases. The third phase (upward explosion) is the most important so that one will have the most exercises for you to do.</p>
<p>Practice these exercises twice a week if possible. After 4-5 weeks, you should start to see and feel a difference in your serve. I believe it’s possible for everyone to achieve a 5 mph increase in their serve after 5-6 weeks of doing these exercises twice a day.</p>
<p>If you continue doing them and increase the resistance while working on your form, there’s no reason why a 10-15 mph increase can’t be made within three months.<br />
Alright, let’s get into the serve exercises starting with the ones for the racket drop phase first.</p>
<h2></h2>
<h2>Racket Drop Exercises</h2>
<p>1. <strong>One Arm Cable Triceps Extension</strong> – This is a great exercise to build up the triceps muscle of the upper arm. The triceps is responsible gets worked when we bend the arm and then straighten it. For this exercise, a cable machine is needed. Work each arm with the same intensity, but of course, the hitting arm is where we’ll see results on the serve. If you don’t have access to a cable machine, you can use a light dumbbell.</p>
<p>2. <strong>Over The Head Medicine Ball Throws</strong> – In this one you hold a medicine ball in back of your head and throw it as far as you can in front of you. It would be best if you have a wall you can throw it at. This works the fast-twitch muscle fibers of the arms and shoulders and simulates the action of the arm on the serve.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Pronation Exercises</h2>
<p>1. <strong>Forearm Pronates</strong> &#8211; Hold a light weight in your hand with arm outstretched in front of you and palm up. Your arm should be straight. If you don’t have a light weight, you can use your racket. Now turn your palm down. Repeat over and over until you feel the burn in your forearm. This exercise will build the muscles in your forearm required for faster pronation on the serve.</p>
<p>2. <strong>Motorcycle Revs</strong> – Hold a barbell or dumbbell in your hands. Your arms can hang down in front of your thighs. Now flex your wrists so that your palms move towards you as if you were revving a motorcycle. Hold for a second and return to the neutral position you started in. Then repeat and continue until you feel a burn in your forearm. This exercise really built up the underside of my forearms and grip strength, which is ideal for really hitting any shot in tennis.</p>
<p>3. <strong>Reverse Motorcycle Revs</strong> – Start in the same place, with you holding weights with arms hanging straight down your body. Your palms should be facing you. Now instead of using flexion, move your wrists the opposite way, which is called extension. This exercise works the top side of your forearm. Do as many reps as you can until your forearm burns. These forearm exercises will really help you to pronate quicker.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<h2>Knee Bend and Explosion (Jumping) Exercises</h2>
<p>This segment will have the most exercises, since this is the most important phase of the serve, as already mentioned. These exercises will take more out of you physically but are necessary to build the explosion you need for a powerful serve.</p>
<p>1. <strong>Squat and Jumps</strong> – Grab two light dumbbells (10-20 lbs) and hold one in each hand. Stand on a padded or soft floor with both hands holding the weights by your sides. Now squat down as far as you can go. Once your knees are fully bent and you can’t go down anymore, explode upwards as hard as you can. The point is to jump into the air as high as you can go. When you land, quickly drop down and repeat the process. I recommend doing no more than 10 reps per set and 2-3 sets max. This exercise is great for creating an explosion on the jump phase of the serve.</p>
<p>2. <strong>One Legged Box Step Ups</strong> – Stand in front of a platform or stable box. The height should be around 12-20 inches, depending on your height. Place one foot on the box with knee slightly bent; the other foot should be on the ground. Now, spring upwards by pushing off with the foot on the box – the other foot will leave the floor. The foot on the box will be on the toes when you spring up. Once you do this, return the foot (that’s in the air) to the floor and repeat. Do 10-15 reps and then alternate your feet so you push off with the opposite foot. This exercise is especially good because it trains each leg at a time. On the tennis serve, you push off with more force on your front leg (the left leg for righties), so make sure you train the left leg especially hard.</p>
<p>3. <strong>Frog Jumps</strong> – For this exercise, no gym or equipment is needed. You’re basically going to be jumping forward as far as you can and keep repeating until your legs are tired. To do this exercise, squat down half way to the floor. Put your hands to the sides and slightly behind you. Now jump upwards and outwards as far as possible. Your arms should cast forward in sequence with the jump. This builds plyometric strength in your legs and simulates the forward jump of the serve. My recommendation would be to do 6-8 jumps in one set and 2-3 sets per session.</p>
<p>These are all the exercises you should do to improve your tennis serve power. As an option, you can do squats, leg press, deadlifts, and calf raises. I would recommend doing them as fast as you can with weights that are 40-50% of your max.</p>
<p>By doing that, you train your body to be more explosive. If you do heavy, slow lifts with near max weight at low reps, that’s not bad, but explosive movements is more of what you want.</p>
<p>If you look at the most powerful servers on tour, they’re mostly guys and girls with wire-like frames. More muscle does not always equate to more power.<br />
You can probably do all of the exercises featured in this post (with the exception of the four leg exercises I just mentioned) in one session. If you can, do two sessions per week, spacing them three days apart.</p>
<p>If I didn’t mention the rep range for a specific exercise, just do it until you are tired, or your muscles burn. You can then stop and that’s the rep range you should shoot for on each set – at least initially.</p>
<p>If you can complete two sessions per week, I think you’ll see a difference in your serve in just a few weeks. These exercises are designed to hit all the muscles that play into the key phases of the serve.</p>
<p>Let me know how these gym exercises for the serve help you. If you have any questions about them, let me know in the comment section below.</p>
<p>The post <a href="/what-gym-exercises-will-improve-my-tennis-serve/">What Gym Exercises Will Improve My Tennis Serve?</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/what-gym-exercises-will-improve-my-tennis-serve/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Tennis Warm Ups For Maximum Performance</title>
		<link>/tennis-warm-ups-for-maximum-performance/</link>
					<comments>/tennis-warm-ups-for-maximum-performance/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chad Walner]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 03 Mar 2019 13:57:03 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Training]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=2020</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>If you’re new to tennis, you may be unaware that there are typical regimens tennis players employ to warm up. And if you’ve been playing tennis for a while and are not quite sure how to warm up properly, this &#8230; <a class="kt-excerpt-readmore" href="/tennis-warm-ups-for-maximum-performance/" aria-label="Tennis Warm Ups For Maximum Performance">Read More</a></p>
<p>The post <a href="/tennis-warm-ups-for-maximum-performance/">Tennis Warm Ups For Maximum Performance</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>If you’re new to tennis, you may be unaware that there are typical regimens tennis players employ to warm up. And if you’ve been playing tennis for a while and are not quite sure how to warm up properly, this post will tell you how.</p>
<p>When I first started playing tennis, I wasn’t sure of how to warm up, so I’d hit the ball a few times and just start. But when I joined my college tennis team, everyone warmed up the same way.</p>
<p>This is the basic structure of what a proper tennis warm up looks like. Overall, it shouldn’t take more than 10-15 minutes. I’m listing the events in sequential order.</p>
<p>The first one is mini tennis and it’s optional. Some people like to start with it and some skip it.</p>
<ul>
<li>Mini Tennis</li>
<li>Groundstroke practice (both players on the baseline)</li>
<li>Volley practice (one player at net and one on baseline – then alternate)</li>
<li>Overheads (one player at net and one on baseline – then alternate)</li>
<li>Serve practice (each player takes turns serving from both the deuce and ad sides)</li>
</ul>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>That’s really it. For the remainder of the article, I’ll go into more detail on the warm up and how to properly perform each part of it.</p>
<p>I’ll also give you a few tips you can use during the warm up to make it easier for you during the match. Some players take the warm up for granted, but it’s a very important factor in gauging your opponent, court conditions and your level of play that day.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Stretching And Mini Tennis</h2>
<p>Before you even step onto the court, it’s a wise idea to stretch. Personally, I never stretch because I never feel the need to. I’m like a gazelle who’s always ready to sprint away from an attacking lion – I just go!</p>
<p>But most weekend warriors and even long-time athletes like to stretch. Tennis uses all the muscles in the body so for that reason a full-body stretch is helpful.</p>
<p>When I was on the tennis team, we would stretch our arms, shoulders, back, hips, and legs. You also might want to warm up by doing light jogging or moving exercises before starting the “official” warm up.</p>
<p>Once you feel loose, you are your partner can take to the court for mini tennis. Again, mini tennis is an optional way to start the warm up; some people (like me) prefer going straight to the baseline.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>If you want to begin with mini tennis, both you are your partner should stand at the service line (usually near the midline) and gently rally back and forth. If a ball comes to you in the air, just lightly volley it back.</p>
<p>When doing mini tennis, pay attention to your forehand and backhand form. Make sure it’s smooth and relaxed with a full follow through. Since it’s mini tennis, you’ll generally be swinging slower than normal.</p>
<p>Remember, mini tennis is mostly a control drill. Do mini tennis for no more than two minutes and then move back to the baseline.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Groundstroke Practice At The Baseline</h2>
<p>Almost all professional tennis players start their warm ups at the baseline. Most people prefer to warm up this way – forgoing mini tennis.</p>
<p>This is not to say that professional players never do mini tennis. Most do but they’ll typically do it during practice sessions or in their pre-match warm up.</p>
<p>When you start this part of the warm up, it’s best to be in the middle of the court and a few feet in back of the baseline. It’s important that you hit to your partner and not try to hit winners.</p>
<p>When playing tennis, you’ll run into players of varying skill and levels. Some people have little control over where they hit and will spray balls during this part of the warm up.</p>
<p>If so, it can be difficult to establish a good rhythm. In that case, you either need to find people to play at a higher level or just cut this part of the warm up short.</p>
<p>Chances are you’ll win the match if your opponent has that much trouble hitting down the middle to you.</p>
<p>But some opponents do have good control but try to hit winners in the warm up. That’s a selfish way to warm up and doesn’t help you at all. When this happens, I’ll say something to my opponent.</p>
<p>If he persists in hitting to the sidelines, I’ll just say, “I’m ready to start playing – I don’t need to warm up anymore”. If my opponent insists he needs more warm up, I’ll refuse. There’s no rule that says you have to participate in a warm up.</p>
<p>Typically, this scenario doesn’t happen, but it can. The best warm ups are when both players can hit relaxed groundstrokes down the middle of the court.</p>
<p>Doing so gives you a chance to work on your forehands and backhands. You can definitely throw some slices in as well. Towards the end of this part of the warm up, feel free to hit some hard shots as well.</p>
<p>For me, this should be the longest part of the warm up at about 4-5 minutes. During this phase of the warm up, take note of the court conditions. Are they playing fast? What direction is the wind? Is the sun a factor and on which side?</p>
<p>Also, take note of your opponent. If you’re playing someone new, which side is their strength and which their weakness? For most players, their backhand is their weaker side.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Volley Practice</h2>
<p>Once you complete the groundstroke part of the warm up, one player will move to the net – the other can stay at the baseline. The player at the net will take volley practice.</p>
<p>This part of the warm up can be made better if both players hit to each other. It takes some control, but the volley player has to be skilled enough to hit volleys that can be handled by the baseliner.</p>
<p>It’s not uncommon for both players to make more mistakes at this point in the warm up. If so, just move on and hit another shot. When I’m on the baseline, I like to hit to both my opponent’s forehand volley and backhand volley.</p>
<p>I also like to give them high volleys and low volleys (close to the net). I’ll also hit directly into their body. In this way, I can gauge how good of a volley player they are and where they have a weakness.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>When it’s your turn to come to net, work on practicing your volleys on both sides. Hit most of the volleys back to your opponent, but towards the end, you can direct a few volleys away from your opponent. You may also want to throw in a couple of drop volleys.</p>
<p>Remember, you practice like you play, so make sure you’re not being lackadaisical in your warm ups. Move your feet and volley like you would in a match.<br />
For this part of the warm up, each player should volley for no more than two minutes.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Overhead Practice</h2>
<p>After completing groundstroke warmup, one player will come to the net. That player will take volley practice. Before returning to the baseline to allow the other player to come up, he or she will stay at the net for overhead practice.</p>
<p>The player will take a couple of minutes of overhead practice and then return to the baseline. Then the other player will come to the baseline for volley practice and then overhead practice.</p>
<p>Once that’s done, both players can move onto the final part of the warm up, which is serve practice. I wanted to point that out to you in case you were confused.</p>
<p>Basically, the volley and overhead practice go in sequential order where one player practices both and then the other player practices both. I just broke them into different segments in this post to clearly illustrate the different parts of the warm up.</p>
<p>During the overhead part of the warm up, the net player will work only on hitting overheads. The baseline player will hit only lobs. As a baseline player, try to hit your lobs to the forehand side of the opponent.</p>
<p>Lobs to the backhand are too difficult for most players. Also, keep your overheads from going too short (falling right by the net) or too long (landing near the baseline). Aiming for the service line is a good idea.</p>
<p>You can hit lobs right off the returns – if your opponent hits in your direction. If your opponent doesn’t hit right to you, it’s fine, as overheads can be difficult to control.</p>
<p>When you’re at the net for overhead practice, keep your feet moving and do the best job you can at setting up early. Turn your shoulders right away and move into position to hit the perfect overhead.</p>
<p>I like to hit the first few overheads directly to my opponent and the last few to the corners. This gives me a good warm up on my overheads.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Serve Practice</h2>
<p>Once you complete the groundstroke, volley, and overhead practice, you’re ready for serve practice. At the professional level, both players hit serves at the same time.</p>
<p>Professional players do this to save time and because they have an unlimited number of balls with ball kids to help. But at the club level, we don’t have that luxury, so one player at a time will practice their serve.</p>
<p>It doesn’t matter which player goes first. Usually, the person with more balls in their pocket can start serving first.</p>
<p>If that’s you, start on the deuce side and hit three serves. Typically, the returner will just collect the balls without hitting them back.</p>
<p>The returner should then serve three serves to you – on the deuce side again. You’ll collect the balls and then the process repeats. You serve three times and your opponent will serve three times – all on the deuce side.</p>
<p>Once complete, both you and your opponent will switch to the ad side. Go ahead and hit three serves to your opponent. Your opponent will collect each serve and then serve three times back to you.</p>
<p>Repeat the process once more (so you each hit three more serves on the ad side) and then the warm up is complete. There’s no hard-fast rule saying you can’t take even more serve practice.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>I’m just giving you the protocol that most tennis players go through as a ritual during warm up. After both me and my partner each take six serves on both sides of the court, I’ll always ask them if they’re ready to play.</p>
<p>It’s a good idea to ask your opponent this then just assuming they’re ready. Sometimes your opponent will ask you if they can serve a few more times. It’s always a good idea to let them do so, as long as it’s just a minute or two more of warm up.</p>
<p>Once both you and your opponent agree that warm up is complete, you’re ready to begin the match. At this point, you can spin your racket to see which player goes first in deciding whether to serve or receive.</p>
<p>The player who wins the toss can also forgo that decision and just choose which side they want. Whichever option the player who wins the toss decides (serve/return or side) the other player gets to choose the other.</p>
<p>For example, if I win the toss and elect to serve first, my opponent gets to decide which side of the court they want to return from.</p>
<p>However, if I win the toss and decide which side of the court I want to begin on, my opponent gets to decide if they want to serve or return first.</p>
<p>During the serve warm up, it’s a good idea to practice both your first and second serve. You only have six serves on each side during a traditional tennis warm up, so it’s a wise idea to hit three first serves and three second serves.</p>
<p>I also like to vary the placement of the serves, hitting both sides of the service box. It’s also important to take note of the sun in the day time, any wind, and the lights at night.</p>
<p>If the side you’re serving on is particularly bad because of the lighting or sun, do your best to start serving on the other side of the court.</p>
<p>During serve practice, you can also gauge how good your opponent serves to a degree. He or she might not be serving at 100% yet, but often you can get a good sense of the speed, spin, and placement you’ll be dealing with.</p>
<p>By the way, during serve practice, if you serve into the net, just pick the balls up and give them to your opponent to serve. If you need to take more serve practice, tell your opponent after you both take all your serves (six on each side).</p>
<p>Some players like to hit six consecutive serves and then give you a chance to hit six consecutive serves. That’s fine too, as there is no one set rule or way to warm up.</p>
<p>The main point of warm up is to loosen the body and be able to play better during the match. The total time of the warm up should not exceed 15 minutes, but if it does, there’s no penalty.</p>
<p>However, in tournament and league matches (or when paying a lot of money for courts), time is often at a premium. In those cases, limiting the warm ups to 10-15 minutes is essential.</p>
<p>The post <a href="/tennis-warm-ups-for-maximum-performance/">Tennis Warm Ups For Maximum Performance</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/tennis-warm-ups-for-maximum-performance/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>How To Become A Tennis Coach</title>
		<link>/how-to-become-a-tennis-coach/</link>
					<comments>/how-to-become-a-tennis-coach/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chad Walner]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 31 Dec 2018 10:07:45 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Training]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[coaching]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1763</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>If you’ve been thinking about becoming a tennis coach, you’re in the right place. In this blog post I’m going to outline the keys to becoming a successful tennis coach and why you should be one. I know you probably &#8230; <a class="kt-excerpt-readmore" href="/how-to-become-a-tennis-coach/" aria-label="How To Become A Tennis Coach">Read More</a></p>
<p>The post <a href="/how-to-become-a-tennis-coach/">How To Become A Tennis Coach</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>If you’ve been thinking about becoming a tennis coach, you’re in the right place. In this blog post I’m going to outline the keys to becoming a successful tennis coach and why you should be one.</p>
<p>I know you probably have a lot of questions on what it takes to be a paid tennis instructor. I’m going to give you a lot of answers here, so you can learn from my experience.</p>
<p>You may have been wondering if you have what it takes to coach tennis. The truth is, if you play tennis at a 4.5 level or higher and possess a friendly personality, you probably do.</p>
<p>I’ve been a tennis coach on and off for 25 years. Over the last four years, I’ve been consistently coaching part-time (average of 10 lessons per week) and it’s been incredibly rewarding.</p>
<p><strong>It’s an awesome feeling to use your tennis skill and knowledge to make someone’s game better. As a coach, you’ll be working with all kinds of people: kids, young adults, people aged 20s-50s, and even seniors.</strong></p>
<p><strong>In this post, I’ll tell you about my experience as a tennis coach in South Florida. I’m going to share how much money I make, how you much you can expect to earn, and the pros and cons of being a tennis coach.</strong></p>
<p>My hope is that you’ll have a much better understanding of it all by the time you finish this article. If you want a more comprehensive guide, check out my book on<strong> How To Be A Tennis Coach – The Definitive Guide For 2019</strong></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-1771 size-full" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/coaching-with-laptop.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/coaching-with-laptop.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/12/coaching-with-laptop-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/12/coaching-with-laptop-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Why Become A Tennis Coach?</h2>
<p>I got into coaching because I love tennis and I needed extra money. I thought, “Why not use my tennis skills to help other people become better while earning a living at the same time?”</p>
<p>I can honestly tell you I love working with all my students. As a result, the same students have been with me for years.</p>
<p>You know that you’re providing value and getting results for clients when they stick with you for the long-term. That’s the mark of a great coach.</p>
<p>Being a tennis coach has other benefits as well. You can set your own hours, choose the clients you work with, and not have to answer to a boss (if you coach privately).</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>One of my favorite parts of being a tennis coach is getting to meet different types of people. Most are successful, educated, and well-mannered. This also makes it a great way to network with people who have money and possible connections.</p>
<p>I love talking with my clients and discovering their stories, and sharing a passion for tennis.</p>
<p>Coaching is just fun. You travel to different courts, make connections, and generally brighten people’s day. If you have good tennis skills and like being around people, being a tennis coach is an awesome business.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>How Much Do Tennis Coaches Earn?</h2>
<p>How much a tennis coach earns depends on a lot of factors. On the low end, tennis instructors who work for a college or tennis camp can expect to earn about $15 per hour.</p>
<p>These are typically entry level coaching jobs. This is what I made when I used to coach at my college (I was in college and playing on the team at the time).</p>
<p>On the high side, and in the most lucrative markets, coaches can charge $300 per hour or more. In my county, the better coaches charge around $60-$75 per hour.</p>
<p>As you can see, there is quite a disparity in range. I don’t know of any private coaches who charge less than $30 per hour in my area (South Florida). I personally charge clients an average of $40-$50 per lesson, depending on several factors. I go in depth a lot more on pricing in my e-book and course.</p>
<p>The coaches who can charge and collect more than $100 per hour usually have decades of experience, work at famous tennis academies, and have coached young students to the pro ranks.</p>
<p>One such example is Rick Macci, who owns an academy in South Florida and charges $300 per hour for private lessons. He’s now a multi-millionaire and one of the most successful coaches in American tennis.</p>
<p>In my ebook and course, I break down how you should price your clients. Your skill level as a player will be a factor, as well as the gear you have and your experience and credentials.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>The Cost To Start Coaching</h2>
<p>Most businesses require a sizable amount of startup cash. But you can start off coaching for less than $50 and no formal training! This is another aspect of coaching tennis that I love &#8211; the small financial barrier to entry.</p>
<p>I would suggest you budget a bit higher though if you want to attract and retain clients. You definitely don’t need a huge investment to start coaching – a few hundred dollars will take you far at the start.</p>
<p>You can really scale up coaching too. And the more clients you have, the easier it is to attract more business. This is because clients will refer you to their friends, family, and associates if they like you.</p>
<p>When I started giving lessons again four years ago, all I had was a hopper and 75 used tennis balls. My total invest was $30, which was for the <a href="https://amzn.to/2SoTMtz" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">75-ball hopper</a> (Amazon link). I saved 75 balls from the matches I was playing, and bam, I was in business!</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>While I could coach effectively from my previous years of working with clients, it wasn’t until I began investing in needed tennis equipment that my coaching services became more valuable. In my ebook and course, I list out all the equipment you’ll need, from the bare minimum gear up to the gear needed for serious coaches.</p>
<p>Depending on how involved you want to get with coaching, you should budget from several hundred dollars to a couple of thousand to start. If you have the required gear, you’ll look more professional and you’ll be able to teach more effectively.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-1778 size-full" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/5a.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/5a.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/12/5a-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/12/5a-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Coaching Children</h2>
<p>While I like working with adults, it’s the children that motivate and inspire me the most. Their tennis future is dependent on my coaching expertise.</p>
<p>Most children come to you as blank slates and it’s up to you to mold them into competent players. Every child has different levels of ability.</p>
<p>Some pick tennis up quickly while others take a lot longer. If you like kids, you’ll love coaching, but you’ll need patience.</p>
<p>It’s always a thrill when you teach a new technique to a child and he or she can pick it up. It’s very rewarding to see a child make steady improvement under your wing.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1775" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/map-client.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/map-client.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/12/map-client-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/12/map-client-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>How Do I Find Clients?</h2>
<p>Finding clients as a private tennis instructor can be challenging in the beginning. This is especially true if you’re not familiar with the local tennis circuit in your area.</p>
<p>If you’re brand new to coaching or new to your area, posting ads on craigslist is a great place to start. There are also a half dozen tennis websites (like <a href="https://mytennislessons.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">mytennislessons.com</a>) where you can post free profiles.</p>
<p>In my e-book and course, I teach you how to create awesome profiles that stand out and attract customers. It took me a long time to figure out the best way to structure my profile. But once I did, I saw a 60% increase in sign-ups.</p>
<p>Posting on these websites is free, but the websites take a cut for every client they refer. For example, if a client signs up for six hours of lessons with you, the website takes a percentage of every hour you teach. That’s how they make money.</p>
<p>Of course, you can make business cards, post flyers, or do paid advertising. If you’re on a budget, this may not be an option. In my e-book and course, I’ll show you 10 unconventional methods for attracting new clients – most of which are free.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>How To Retain Clients</h2>
<p>The best clients you have are the ones that take lessons week-after-week and year-after-year. These are the clients that build the foundation of your business.</p>
<p>For me, these clients are a combination of kids and adults. Tennis is a sport that takes a long time to learn. Parents know this and the ones with money don’t mind investing in weekly or biweekly tennis lessons for their kids.</p>
<p>The adults who stick with me the longest are ironically not interested in lessons. They are only interested in hitting or playing matches. For this reason, it’s important you are consistent with your strokes, in good shape, and a level 4.5 player or better.</p>
<p>Just this morning I had three one-hour lessons with three different clients. All of them wanted to hit and play sets. This can be quite exhausting, especially in the heat of South Florida, where I teach.</p>
<p>For me, the most important way to retain clients is to be very consistent (hitting-wise), friendly, and professional. This means listening to them, complimenting them, and allowing them to win some points and games.</p>
<p>In my e-book and course, I have an entire subject discussing the dos and don’ts when dealing with clients. Not to toot my own horn, but I have an excellent rapport with my students.</p>
<p>I’ll tell you exactly how I do it. When your students like you, they’ll stick with you for years. This means cash in your pocket week-after-week.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1774" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/marissa1.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/marissa1.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/12/marissa1-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/12/marissa1-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>How To Actually Coach Clients</h2>
<p>When it comes to coaching tennis, I view it in two completely separate categories. The first category is everything but the actual coaching of the client. This involves the marketing of your services, the rates you charge, the markets you should target, how to deal with clients, billing, and scheduling.</p>
<p>I go over all of these in extensive detail in my e-book and course. The second category is the coaching and teaching. You may have played tennis for most of your life, but that doesn’t make you a good coach.</p>
<p>Since this is only a blog post, I can’t teach you how to best coach students from words. At best, I can give you some guidelines.</p>
<p>In my years of coaching, I developed a complete system for teaching every tennis stroke. This makes it so much easier to work with any level of client. These strokes include:</p>
<ul>
<li>Forehand</li>
<li>Backhand – one and two-handed</li>
<li>Backhand and forehand slice</li>
<li>Volleys</li>
<li>Overheads</li>
<li>First and second serve</li>
<li>Footwork</li>
<li>Mental aspect of tennis</li>
</ul>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>In my course, I’ll show you exactly how to teach each of these strokes. Now keep in mind that teaching beginners and intermediate/advanced players is quite different.</p>
<p>I explain the differences in my course. I also show you how to work with players who have a lot of tennis experience.</p>
<p>It’s one thing to take a player from scratch and show them how to hit a proper forehand. It’s a totally different thing to work with players who already know how to hit.</p>
<p>In my course, you’ll learn things like how to diagnose a player’s strokes and improve them. That’s the main reason people are paying you to coach them. They want results.</p>
<p>If you don’t know what to look for, or which drills will correct their issues, you’re not going to be very effective. We go over all of that in the course.</p>
<p>After taking my course, you’ll be able to diagnose any stroke from any level player. You’ll know exactly what the player needs to change to improve. You’ll also learn how to effectively make those changes.</p>
<p>These are all skills I learned from years of coaching. In the beginning, I was like a blind man. I’d see someone serve or hit and couldn’t figure out what their issue was. Two decades and thousands of tennis lessons later, it’s crystal clear.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1773" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/beginnertennisballs.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/beginnertennisballs.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/12/beginnertennisballs-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/12/beginnertennisballs-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Summary</h2>
<p>If you’re thinking about coaching tennis, I urge you to give it a try. As I said earlier, there’s a low barrier of entry in terms of money and you don’t even need qualifications or certificates.</p>
<p>While having a small budget and a few qualifications to your name helps, it’s not essential to start earning money as a local tennis coach. All you need is a hopper and balls to get started. That’s how I did it.</p>
<p>If you post an ad on craigslist today and put up several free profiles on the tennis websites, you might even get your first client within the next week or two. At a rate of $40 per hour, if you attract just one new client per month (that stays with you) you’ll have 12 paying clients after a year.</p>
<p>If these clients take a lesson with you once a week, that’s $480 per week – most of which is cash! You might be thinking $480 per week is not much. But remember, that’s only 12 hours of court time.</p>
<p>If you could earn $480 every week, that’s $2,000 per month. That money could be a huge difference-maker in your life.</p>
<p>From there, you could either scale up or keep coaching a part-time source of income. That’s the beautiful thing about coaching – you’re in control. If you want to stay part-time and work another job, that’s up to you.</p>
<p>I know another local coach who works full time. Last year he made around $75,000 for his efforts. He sets the hours he coaches, has plenty of time for his family, and just bought a new house with the money he’s earning.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>If you want to learn more about coaching, check out my e-book or course. There’s a ton of information in them that will make your coaching journey seamless.</p>
<p>In the beginning, I made mistakes that cost me clients and money. Once I figured out how to correct my mistakes, my revenue quadrupled. In my e-book and course, I’ll show you how to earn a full-time income from tennis coaching in less than six months.</p>
<p>If you want to learn my entire tennis coaching system, you’ll definitely want to sign up for my coaching course. In it, I show you everything you’ll need to know to be one of the best and highest-paid coaches in your area.</p>
<p>If you have any questions about becoming a tennis coach, feel free to ask. Thank you for coming to my blog. Don’t forget to sign-up to my newsletter for all the latest blog posts, videos, and offerings!</p>
<p>The post <a href="/how-to-become-a-tennis-coach/">How To Become A Tennis Coach</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/how-to-become-a-tennis-coach/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>3</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>How To Have A Reliable Serve Toss In Tennis</title>
		<link>/how-to-have-a-reliable-serve-toss-in-tennis/</link>
					<comments>/how-to-have-a-reliable-serve-toss-in-tennis/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chad Walner]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 28 Nov 2018 12:44:44 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Training]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[serve]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1441</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The serve toss in tennis gives many players problems. This is because it is accomplished with the nondominant hand and is an unnatural motion. Furthermore, the toss needs to be placed in a certain location to hit the ball. If &#8230; <a class="kt-excerpt-readmore" href="/how-to-have-a-reliable-serve-toss-in-tennis/" aria-label="How To Have A Reliable Serve Toss In Tennis">Read More</a></p>
<p>The post <a href="/how-to-have-a-reliable-serve-toss-in-tennis/">How To Have A Reliable Serve Toss In Tennis</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><strong>The serve toss in tennis gives many players problems. This is because it is accomplished with the nondominant hand and is an unnatural motion. </strong></p>
<p><strong>Furthermore, the toss needs to be placed in a certain location to hit the ball. If you cannot toss accurately, you cannot serve, period. You can have the best service motion in the world and it won’t make a difference.</strong></p>
<p>For this reason, the serve toss is of critical importance on the serve. Most coaches and players don’t emphasize it enough, focusing on other aspects of the tennis serve instead.</p>
<p>To have a reliable serve toss, we need to focus on the following components.</p>
<ol>
<li><a href="#holding"><strong>Holding the ball in the correct manner</strong></a></li>
<li><a href="#starting"><strong>Starting the toss from the proper position</strong></a></li>
<li><a href="#keeping"><strong>Keeping the tossing arm straight</strong></a></li>
<li><a href="#moving"><strong>Moving the tossing arm in the correct direction at a medium pace</strong></a></li>
<li><a href="#releasing"><strong>Releasing the ball at the right height</strong></a></li>
<li><a href="#tossing"><strong>Tossing the ball to the proper height</strong></a></li>
<li><a href="#leaving"><strong>Leaving the tossing arm and hand in the air until the swing initiates</strong></a></li>
</ol>
<p>Do these seven components correctly, and you’re guaranteed of a great service toss every time. If even one of these components is not carried out correctly, the toss placement will be sacrificed.</p>
<p>I will go over each component in this post. Before we are done, I’ll give you three tossing drills you can do to practice your toss on or off the court.</p>
<p>If the toss is something that has been troubling your serve read on. If you’re new to tennis and want to know the best way to toss on the serve, read on as well.</p>
<div class="kad-youtube-shortcode videofit"  ><iframe loading="lazy" width="600" height="400" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/F9qslEzIQJU?autoplay=0&controls=1&fs=1&modestbranding=1&theme=dark&rel=0&loop=0&showinfo=1" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="true"></iframe></div>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="holding"></a></p>
<h2>Holding The Ball In The Correct Manner</h2>
</div>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1452" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/1.jpg" alt="How to hold the tennis ball." width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/1.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/11/1-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/11/1-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p>The best way to hold a tennis ball during your serve toss is in the fingertips. You should never let your palm touch the tennis ball.</p>
<p>If your palm touches the tennis ball, you won’t have as much control. All great servers toss from the fingertips.</p>
<p>You don’t need to squeeze the ball too tightly or hold it too loose. Just a medium squeeze is fine. I like to use all five fingertips to hold the ball.</p>
<p>It’s very important that you keep the hand and wrist allotted in the same position during the toss. The position of the hand and wrist will be the same at the beginning and end of the toss.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="starting"></a></p>
<h2>Starting The Toss From The Proper Position</h2>
</div>
<p>Once you set your feet in the proper position and align your shoulders away from the net, you’ll be ready to start the serve and the toss. I’ll assume everyone is right-handed. If you’re a lefty, do the opposite.</p>
<p>Start with your left arm (the tossing arm) at your left thigh. The back of your hand should rest on your thigh, with the ball in your fingertips, like we mentioned in step 1.</p>
<p>Some players like to start with the hand on the inner thigh. Some start from more directly on the thigh. And some players start their toss a few inches off the thigh.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>If you feel more comfortable starting a few inches off the thigh, that’s fine. As long as your arm is perfectly straight at this point, you’ll be in a good position to make a great serve.</p>
<p>I teach beginners and children to start from the thigh because it’s easier to toss from a fixed object then in the air. However, I typically start a few inches off the thigh myself and make accurate tosses, so it can work as well.</p>
<p>When you begin the toss, keep your arm loose and resist tightening up your muscles. Breath and visualize the perfect toss.</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="keeping"></a></p>
<h2>Keeping The Tossing Arm Straight</h2>
</div>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1453" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/2.jpg" alt="Keeping the tossing arm straight." width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/2.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/11/2-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/11/2-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p>The tossing arm (your left arm) must be kept straight through the duration of the toss. This means from the beginning at the thigh until the arm is fully outstretched over your head.</p>
<p>If the arm bends at any point before the ball is released, this will almost ensure you never toss accurately. If the arm bends after the ball is released, the toss can still be made accurately, but it’s poor technique and doesn’t look good.</p>
<p>I see a lot of players bend their arms right after releasing the ball. You can get away with it if you’ve been playing a while and have practiced your toss hundreds or thousands of times.</p>
<p>But if you’re a new player, or trying to correct your toss, why not just keep your arm straight until the swing is initiated, like the pros do? It may seem uncomfortable at first, but with enough practice, it will feel more natural.</p>
<p>Practice tossing with a straight arm for many reps (at least 100). I would suggest not even using a ball at first. Just get the feeling of what it’s like to move your arm completely straight from your thigh to straight above your head.</p>
<p>Once it begins to feel natural, you can add the ball and toss it. Have someone watch your toss, or video yourself, to make sure you are not bending your arm.</p>
<p>Keeping a straight arm throughout the toss is the distinguishing characteristic of an excellent service motion. Remember, it’s absolutely crucial not to bend the arm before the hand releases the ball.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="moving"></a></p>
<h2>Moving The Tossing Arm In The Correct Direction At A Medium Pace</h2>
</div>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1454" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/3.jpg" alt="Explaining the speed of the tossing arm." width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/3.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/11/3-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/11/3-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p>Now that you know how to hold the ball, the ideal place to start the toss, and that you need to keep your arm straight, in what direction does the arm move?</p>
<p>While there is no one right direction, I am going to suggest a 45-degree angle from the baseline. The extremes would be tossing parallel to the baseline or tossing directly out in front of your body.</p>
<p>My recommendation is to toss right in the middle of those two extremes. This would have the arm raise in alignment with the right net post.<br />
I find this best in my own toss, and my students, because it allows the ball to travel in front and to the right of us. This is where we want the ball to be – in about the one o’clock position to our head.</p>
<p>You can use the right net post as your guide. Simply raise your arm in that direction. The next part is knowing at what speed to raise our arm.<br />
Most people move the tossing arm way too fast. If you do that, you certainly won’t control the ball. If the tossing arm is raised too slowly, then the ball will not have enough lift.</p>
<p>The solution is to toss in the middle, at a medium pace. After the ball leaves your hand, you’ll want the apex of the toss to be about twice your height. For that to happen, your arm needs to be moving at the correct speed.</p>
<p>Only you can judge this speed. If the ball is going to low, you’ll need to move your arm faster. If the ball is too high, you’ll need to move it slower.</p>
<p>We’ll talk about how to find the ideal height on the toss soon. For now, know it’s about twice your height. So if you’re 6 feet tall, you’ll want to toss close to 12 feet in the air.</p>
<p>Practice tossing until you begin to hit the right height. Sometimes the right height is determined by your swing.</p>
<p>Abbreviated servers can toss lower while players with long sweeping service motions usually need to toss higher (as they need more time to complete their serve motion).</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="releasing"></a></p>
<h2>Releasing The Ball At The Right Height</h2>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1469" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/tossRelasing-The-Ball-At-The-Right-Height.jpg" alt="Releasing the ball at the right height." width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/tossRelasing-The-Ball-At-The-Right-Height.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/11/tossRelasing-The-Ball-At-The-Right-Height-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/11/tossRelasing-The-Ball-At-The-Right-Height-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
</div>
<p>At this point all the fundamentals are in place for a great serve toss. You may be wondering the best position to release the ball on the toss? It’s the top of your head.</p>
<p>Most professional tennis players release the serve toss right near top of head height. This seems to be the best place to achieve an accurate serve toss. This is where I release my serve toss too.</p>
<p>If you release the ball lower or higher than top of head height, you will diminish your chances of tossing accurately. You can probably get away with a few inches difference, but any more is running a risk.</p>
<p>It’s best to release the ball at the same height on every serve toss. If you can cut down on randomness on the toss, it will make the toss exponentially better.</p>
<p>I look at serve toss as a science. If we can perform the same action over and over in the same manner, we should get the same result. Good fundamentals equal a good serve toss.</p>
<p>One thing more here. When we release the ball, the ball should still be in the fingertips. Simply open your hand when releasing the ball. It should look like a flower opening its pedals.</p>
<p>Keep your arm and hand pointed in the same direction through the duration of the toss. Resist turning the hand or wrist. It is unnecessary and harmful to do.</p>
<p>This might seem like a lot of information for a simple toss, but the devil is in the details. I just want to make sure you know all of the specifics.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="tossing"></a></p>
<h2>Tossing The Ball To The Proper Height</h2>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1476" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/How-To-Have-A-Reliable-Serve-Toss-In-Tennis-Serve-and-Volley-Tennis.jpg" alt="Toss to about twice your height." width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/How-To-Have-A-Reliable-Serve-Toss-In-Tennis-Serve-and-Volley-Tennis.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/11/How-To-Have-A-Reliable-Serve-Toss-In-Tennis-Serve-and-Volley-Tennis-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/11/How-To-Have-A-Reliable-Serve-Toss-In-Tennis-Serve-and-Volley-Tennis-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
</div>
<p>As I already mentioned, tossing to twice your body height is a good place to target for the apex of the toss. One good way to find that point is to toss near an object (like a fence) that is around twice your height.</p>
<p>In my serve toss video, you can see me doing that next to a fence. The fence post will also serve as a good guide for where your arm and the ball should be moving along.</p>
<p>Everyone’s serve motion is different. Some people need more time to hit the ball and others need less. Only you can decide that for yourself.<br />
Once you have developed your service motion and can hit a serve, you’ll have a good idea if you need to toss higher or lower – or maybe the apex of the toss is just right.</p>
<p>If you feel rushed to hit the ball, you’re likely tossing too low and need to toss a bit higher. On the inverse, if it seems like you are stalling out momentum in the trophy pose, you might be tossing too high. In this case, tossing lower might be better for you.</p>
<p>Videoing your serve is a great way to determine the best tossing height for you. A good coach can also help with this. Even an experienced, advanced level player would have good insight on this.</p>
<p>If you feel your toss is not ideal, keep tweaking the apex of your toss until your serve motion is fluid and you don’t feel rushed. Everyone gets it in time, so keep practicing.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="leaving"></a></p>
<h2>Leaving The Tossing Arm Up</h2>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1470" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/tossKeep-The-Tossing-Arm-Up.jpg" alt="Keep the tossing arm up." width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/tossKeep-The-Tossing-Arm-Up.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/11/tossKeep-The-Tossing-Arm-Up-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/11/tossKeep-The-Tossing-Arm-Up-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
</div>
<p>Once the ball leaves the hand, the arm should continue rising until it is straight over your head, as high as you can extend it. If you watch the best professional players with the best serves (Roger Federer, Kevin Anderson, John Isner), you’ll see them keep their tossing arm high up in the air until the swing initiates.</p>
<p>I would say 75-80% of the recreational players I see drop the tossing arm too quickly during the serve. While players can get away with this and still hit a good serve, it will affect the service motion negatively to a degree.</p>
<p>There’s a reason why the top servers leave their tossing arm up in the air that long. If it works for them, we should model their technique and do the same.</p>
<p>It may feel unnatural at first, but again, with practice it will feel more natural. You only drop the tossing arm when the swing begins.<br />
At that point, the tossing arm will bend and retract to the left side of the body. You’ll want to keep the tossing arm close to the body, so the right arm and racket can move past it at the completion of the swing.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="hrule clearfix" style=" height:1px"></div>
<div class="pullquote-center">
<h3>Use these three drills to nail down your serve toss consistency</h3>
</div>
<div class="hrule clearfix" style=" height:1px"></div>
<h2><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1467" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/tossUse-These-Three-Drills2.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/tossUse-These-Three-Drills2.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/11/tossUse-These-Three-Drills2-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/11/tossUse-These-Three-Drills2-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></h2>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Toss Drill # 1 – Toss And Catch</h2>
<p>In this drill, you’ll set up in the proper serve stance with a tennis ball. This drill can be done anywhere you have the room to toss.<br />
You can do it at the tennis court, in your home, your backyard or anywhere outdoors. All you need is one tennis ball; a racket is not needed but you can hold one in your dominant hand if you want.</p>
<p>Toss the ball utilizing all the fundamentals we’ve talked about. After the toss is made, keep your tossing arm fully extended to the sky and catch the ball when it drops.</p>
<p>You do not swing your racket in this drill. You’re simply tossing and catching the ball with your tossing arm. But your tossing arm remains fully extended in the air on the catch.</p>
<p>This drill helps with two aspect of the toss. First, it helps you keep your tossing arm extended. Second, it helps with toss accuracy, as you must toss in the same location to catch the ball.</p>
<p>It’s okay to move your arm slightly to catch the ball. But resist turning your hand or wrist, moving your feet, or bending your arm at any point during the drill.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Toss Drill # 2 – Meet Me At The Apex</h2>
<p>In this drill, you’ll toss a ball to the perfect apex, which is around twice your height. You’ll need to set up by a fence or object that is twice your height. All you need is one tennis ball.</p>
<p>Simply toss the ball and make sure it is close to the high object. You do not swing at the ball or go into your service motion. It’s only a tossing drill.<br />
At first it can be challenging. But slowly you should see steady improvement in toss accuracy.</p>
<p>This drill is effective because it gives you a great visual of how high the toss should be and where it should be. I like to do this drill next to a fence, along one of the posts.</p>
<p>I mentioned this drill earlier in the blog post and made a video on it. It’s a drill I have all my students do who need help with the serve toss.<br />
You have the option of catching the ball high (like in drill #1) or letting the ball drop. But you should keep the tossing hand extended throughout the drill.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Drill #3 – Trap The Ball Drill</h2>
<p>In this serve toss drill, you’ll need a fence that is at least 4-5 feet taller than yourself. Go over to the fence and set up as if you were going to serve towards it.</p>
<p>You’ll want to be close to the fence, so your lead foot should only be about a foot away. You’ll need a racket and one tennis ball.</p>
<p>Toss the ball as you normally would, doing all the fundamentals we discussed. Then initiate the serve motion and swing your racket into the ball.</p>
<p>You’ll want to swing less than 100% speed. The point of this drill is to trap the ball between your racket and the fence with your right arm extended to the ideal height.</p>
<p>Your right arm should be fully extended during the trap, but not directly over your head. It should be a bit out to the side, at about the one o’clock position.</p>
<p>Once you trap the ball, let it down, and begin the next rep in the same way. The point of this drill is to find the correct height to hit the toss.<br />
This is a great drill to do for kids. While it doesn’t directly improve the toss, it does help give a great visual for how high the toss needs to be in order to extend the right hitting arm up to contact.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Summary</h2>
<p>Go through all the steps I outlined in this post. These are the same steps all the top servers do.</p>
<p>Then put them all together and practice your serve toss at least a hundred times 3-4 times per week for the next 2-3 weeks. I guarantee you’ll see positive results after that time if you do the reps.</p>
<p>Most people never improve their toss because they don’t follow the fundamentals. Even if they know them, they don’t practice them or their tosses.<br />
You can add the serve toss drills to fast-track your progress. By being one of the few who practice your toss, you’ll fly past your competition in terms of toss accuracy and serve quality.</p>
<p>Once you feel comfortable and have the toss down pat, you can forget about it and focus more on your serve motion. Building the perfect serve is a step-by-step process and takes time.</p>
<p>But it need not take you more than a few weeks to develop a great serve toss. I hope you actually follow my advice, use the information I provided, and practice.</p>
<p>If you have any questions for me, leave them in the comment section below. I’ll be glad to answer them for you.</p>
<p>The post <a href="/how-to-have-a-reliable-serve-toss-in-tennis/">How To Have A Reliable Serve Toss In Tennis</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/how-to-have-a-reliable-serve-toss-in-tennis/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>3</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>How To Effortlessly Generate More Power On Your Groundstrokes</title>
		<link>/how-to-effortlessly-generate-more-power-on-your-groundstrokes/</link>
					<comments>/how-to-effortlessly-generate-more-power-on-your-groundstrokes/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chad Walner]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 11 Oct 2018 16:02:33 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Training]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[backhand]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[forehand]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=683</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Let’s be real. Every serious tennis player aspires to hit huge forehands and powerful backhands. We see the pros doing it on TV and we want it for ourselves. Many club players I know have tried all kinds of tricks &#8230; <a class="kt-excerpt-readmore" href="/how-to-effortlessly-generate-more-power-on-your-groundstrokes/" aria-label="How To Effortlessly Generate More Power On Your Groundstrokes">Read More</a></p>
<p>The post <a href="/how-to-effortlessly-generate-more-power-on-your-groundstrokes/">How To Effortlessly Generate More Power On Your Groundstrokes</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Let’s be real.</p>
<p>Every serious tennis player aspires to hit huge forehands and powerful backhands. We see the pros doing it on TV and we want it for ourselves.</p>
<p>Many club players I know have tried all kinds of tricks and gimmicks to improve power, but with little or no results.</p>
<p>Well, I’ve got a permanent solution you can take to the bank.</p>
<p><strong>If you haven’t given much thought to rotation of the body while hitting, then this article is going to be a serious wake-up call.</strong></p>
<p><strong>Body rotation on both the forehand and backhand sides are what really generate effortless power in tennis. In this post, I am going to talk about three specific rotations you can use on each side to measurably increase your groundstroke speed. </strong></p>
<p>In my opinion, there are two major contributing factors to groundstroke velocity: racket head speed and body rotation. Achieving high levels of racket head speed like Rafael Nadal or Jack Sock is a skill most club players will never approach. It requires great technique, fast-twitch muscles and athleticism. If you don’t have those traits, your basically out of luck. Now that sounds a bit discouraging for your average club tennis player. But don’t despair. I have a solution that will work for everyone!</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-702 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/rotation.jpg" alt="rotation" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/rotation.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/rotation-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/rotation-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<h2>The Solution For Power Is Rotation</h2>
<p>What’s the solution? It’s <strong>body rotation</strong> and anyone can do it no matter age, athletic ability or skill level. If you can learn to rotate your body and sequence it with hitting the ball at the correct time, you can boost your pace by as much as 20-30%! That’s the difference between hitting a full out winner or just another shot your opponent gets back.</p>
<p>For a long time, I thought that keeping both feet on the floor was very important for hitting consistent groundstrokes. After all, we derive most of our power from the ground. This fact cannot be disputed; we need the ground to push off from to achieve power. As a result, I thought both feet on the ground would provide more power when hitting.</p>
<p>But when I carefully studied the professional players hitting their groundstrokes, I saw different.</p>
<blockquote><p>I discovered it’s actually more advantageous to hit on one leg in most situations.</p></blockquote>
<p>Hitting on one leg allows for better body rotation. The foot that remains on the floor acts as a pivot, swiveling around so the body can rotate. If that’s the case, the body acts like a top being spun. I noticed a big difference in my power when using one-foot rotations. I started teaching them to my students and the difference in power was night and day.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>The best players in the world all use various rotations to maximize their power. When Novak Djokovic hits his two-handed backhand (perhaps the best in the world), he swivels on his front leg, allowing his full body weight to be distributed into the ball. You would rarely see a club player hit like that.</p>
<p>I think a lot of people who watch professional tennis only focus on the ball. They should focus on the players’ footwork and rotations instead. This is where the true power comes from. The racket head speed is just the cherry on the cake. If you swing with medium-paced racket speed but use a heavy racket and rotate your body effectively, you can still hit heavy groundstrokes.</p>
<p>We’re going to get into the details of rotation now on both the forehand and backhand wings. While there are many different rotations that can be used, I want to talk about<strong> two on the forehand side and one on the backhand side.</strong> I believe anyone can do this (from kid to senior) and it can be learned quite quickly. If you’ve been lacking power in your groundstrokes, the rest of this post is a must-read for you. <strong>Your tennis game will never be the same after using this information! </strong></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Forehand Stances For Proper Rotation</h2>

<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0158.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="450" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0158.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="Open Stance." srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0158.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0158-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0158-768x432.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0158-560x315.jpg 560w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></a>
<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0159.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="450" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0159.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="Semi-Open Stance." srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0159.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0159-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0159-768x432.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0159-560x315.jpg 560w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></a>
<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0160.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="450" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0160.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="Neutral Stance." srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0160.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0160-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0160-768x432.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0160-560x315.jpg 560w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></a>
<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0161.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="450" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0161.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0161.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0161-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0161-768x432.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0161-560x315.jpg 560w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></a>

<p>A lack of rotation on the forehand side is common among club players. Even when I do see rotation, it’s often not done the correct way. This is usually because of one of three mistakes:</p>
<ol>
<li>The player does not set up in the correct stance to allow proper rotation.</li>
<li>The timing of the rotation is too early or too late to allow for maximum power.</li>
<li>The player does not raise the non-pivoted foot off the floor enough to allow the body to fully rotate.</li>
</ol>
<p>While these errors are quite common at the club level, we’re going to correct them by learning the ideal technique. You can correct error number one by becoming familiar with the chart below, showing the four basic stances:</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="wp-image-707 size-full aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/four-stances2.jpg" alt="The four common stances." width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/four-stances2.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/four-stances2-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/four-stances2-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Semi-Open Stance Forehands</h2>
<p>Let’s talk about the first type of rotation, which is the basic forehand that you have time to set up for.</p>
<p><strong>In this type of forehand, we’re going to use a semi-open forehand stance.</strong> To achieve the semi-open forehand stance, face the net and place both feet slightly wider than shoulder width. For right-handed players (lefties do the opposite of all instructions in this blog post), move your left foot forward so it’s several inches in front of your right foot.</p>
<p>This is the basic position of the feet. Next, we’re going to make sure our toes are pointed in the right direction. The right foot should be at a 45-degree angle to the baseline. The left foot will be pointed slightly more to the net at around a 60-degree or more angle off the baseline.</p>
<p>Once we achieve the semi-open forehand stance, <strong>we should be in our full power positio</strong>n. The power position is the last position we take with our body and racket before the forward movement into the ball.</p>
<p>This blog post is all about the footwork and rotation of the groundstrokes, so I won’t get into the details of forehand mechanics. If you want to know how to hit a proper forehand, please see my <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OzLIBLQHg4U" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">youtube video series on how to hit an ATP style forehand</a>.</p>
<p>At this point, you’ll be in the semi-open stance and your power position. As you poise to strike the ball, the majority of your weight should be on your right foot (again, lefties do the opposite of all instructions in this post). We’re going to transfer our weight to the front (left) foot soon. Now here’s the part that takes coordination and timing.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="wp-image-705 size-full aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/semi-open-forehand.jpg" alt="Semi-open stance with rotation for a forehand shot." width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/semi-open-forehand.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/semi-open-forehand-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/semi-open-forehand-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p><strong>Right before you strike the ball, you’ll raise your right foot off the ground.</strong> This will take your weight off the right foot and distribute it into the ball. This is where the true power comes from – your entire body. The moment you make impact, and for perhaps a short time after (a quarter to half a second), you may even be off your left foot too. This is perfectly fine. If you watch Djokovic rotate out of the semi-open stance in slow motion, you’ll notice he does the same.</p>
<p>If you’re left foot remains on the ground during the shot, don’t worry. That’s perfectly acceptable. You just want the majority of your weight going from the right foot to left foot. The key takeaway is that your right foot needs to leave the ground with your left foot acting as the pivot.</p>
<p>If your left foot leaves the ground (like Djokovic), when it touches down it will be facing about 90 degrees around. For example, say it was facing 60 degrees to the right when setting up to hit the ball. After the stroke is completed, it will be facing about 150 degrees to the left. The same can be said for the right foot. At the completion of the stroke, almost all your weight will be on the left foot. Most players find their right foot returns to the ground only on the front toe (with the foot almost perpendicular to the ground).</p>
<p>How about the shoulders? When in the power position, the shoulders will be more corked than the feet. A great shoulder rotation is 145 degrees away from the net. Slightly less is acceptable, but not less than 100 degrees. At the completion of the stroke, the shoulders should be approximately 80 degrees to the net in the opposite direction!</p>
<p>If we can rotate our shoulders that far, they would move an incredible 225 degrees during the stroke. That’s a lot of rotation into the ball. Club players will likely achieve less rotation, but if you can manage near 200 degrees, that would still be very effective. If you suffer from power issues on your groundstrokes, your shoulders are probably rotating a lot less than that amount.</p>
<p>I know this is a lot of information to take in. Two things though. One is that <strong>rotation into the ball is quite natural if you play tennis</strong>. We just need to do it correctly. Second is <strong>seeing pictures and video of the correct way to rotate</strong> in the semi-open forehand stance will give you a much clearer understanding of what needs to be done.</p>
<p>I urge you to practice this over and over, as it requires a lot of time to get right. While this can be thought of as a pivot shot off the left foot, it can also be seen as a transfer of weight, jumping from the right foot onto the left foot. Remember, the key objective is to transfer your weight into the ball to hit with more power. Whether you jump or pivot does not matter so much. The rotation is what’s important.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Forehand Rotation Out Wide</h2>
<p>This is one of my favorite rotations to do. It happens when your opponent hits a wide forehand that you hit on a slow-to-medium speed run. Here’s how it usually happens. You’re around the mid-line when someone hits a shot near the sideline or a little inside it. It’s on your forehand side, so you run to your right (lefties do the opposite) and hit the forehand with almost no power. Why?</p>
<p>The most probable answer is that you didn’t prepare early and didn’t transfer your weight into the ball. I see this happen at the club level all the time. I would say most club players don’t know much about footwork and body position. This is why their technique is often so poor.</p>
<p>The information I’m going to share here will enable you to hit a forehand on the run with a lot of power. You’ll know exactly what steps to take after reading this post. Best of all, you’ll actually be able to turn defense into offense with this one rotation. So don’t overlook it.</p>
<p>Alright, first thing’s first. Say you’re at the mid-line, by the baseline. As soon as you see the ball hit wide to your forehand, you should pivot onto your outside foot (for righties, it’s the right foot). As the pivot is being made, lift your racket up and to the right side of your body, slightly away from your body. This helps prepare you to hit the forehand when you get to the ball.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>Now take a crossover step and run to the ball. As you set up for the ball, keep in mind your right foot will be the pivot foot. Wherever you plant your right foot, that’s where you’ll hit from. As you plant your right foot, place most or all your weight on it. As you set up to hit the forehand, almost all your weight will now be on the right foot.</p>
<p>While taking your swing, you’ll be entirely on one foot (the right foot). Allow that right foot to act as a pivot by placing most of your weight on the ball of the foot. If you plant your foot with too much weight on the heel, it won’t pivot and turn.</p>
<p>As you make contact with the ball, really allow your body to turn with the right foot, which is serving as the pivot. The right foot should be turning with your body so that the toe will be facing to the left when the shot is complete – as should your body. Once you complete the stroke, quickly get to the ready position and then cross-step back to the middle.</p>
<p>I know many teaching pros don’t teach this particular rotation, but it’s very effective. For this rotation, unlike the first one we learned out of the semi-open stance, your right foot will remain on the floor the whole time. You should not be jumping on this rotation for several reasons. One is that you’ll likely be off balance, affecting your timing on the shot. The second is that you’ll probably be taken too far off court to effectively recover. The third is that it takes too much energy to jump.</p>
<p>This rotation relies heavily on the right foot to act as a pivot. You can even use it on forehands where you need to back straight up or diagonally (out wide and back). Practice this rotation by making slow shadow movements over and over until you feel the footwork is grooved into memory. Then have someone feed you slow-to-medium paced shots out wide so you can practice it.</p>
<p>I personally use this rotation quite often in my play. I find it makes hitting passing shots a lot easier. It also takes my opponents by surprise often, as they are not expecting how much power I can generate off the run. I taught this rotation to a few of my best child students (both 10-years-old) and they experienced great results with it too. Try it out and see for yourself.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>The Djokovic Two-Handed Backhand Rotation</h2>
<p>Most tennis coaches and analysts would agree that Novak Djokovic has the best two-handed backhand in tennis. Yes, his form and racket speed are superb. But the true key to his mastery of the backhand is how beautifully he rotates his body into the ball with precision timing. I truly believe if we want to play like the pros, we must try and hit like them.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="wp-image-737 size-full alignright" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/djokavic2.jpg" alt="Two-handed backhand stroke." width="400" height="542" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/djokavic2.jpg 400w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/djokavic2-221x300.jpg 221w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" /></p>
<p>The backhand rotation I’m going to talk about here is valid for two-handers only. A one-hander does not have to rotate nearly as much. This rotation is good for any backhand that you require more power on. It could be on a shot near you or a bit further away. In a way, it’s similar to the forehand rotation out wide. This backhand rotation will require you to hit out of a closed or neutral stance &#8211; slightly closed is preferred.</p>
<p>Here’s how it works. When the ball is hit to your backhand, move to it. As you begin to set up, make a unit turn with most of the weight on your back foot (your left foot). Your right foot will be off the ground and stepping forward. As your right foot (front foot) lands on the court, your left foot will come off. At this point, your front foot (right) will act as the pivot, so make sure you’re mostly on the ball of the foot. It’s very important you get these steps correct, because it initiates the weight transfer forward.</p>
<p>All of this is easier said than done. It may take some time to get right, but it’s well worth the effort with the amount of power you can generate. For most players taught from an early age, this footwork is completely natural. If you are learning it as an adult after playing for many years, it will be a challenge. Keep at it though!</p>
<p>Now back to the stroke. As you swing forward, you’ll be on your front foot. Allow it to swivel along with your body. Your body should finish with your chest facing the right net post. As you finish the stroke, your left (rear) leg will come around to your left side and you may finish close to feet parallel (like in the ready position).</p>
<p>Every stroke in tennis is slightly different, so there’s no one hard rule on where your body and foot position should finish all the time. Again, the key point for this rotation is to allow the body to provide the power and not the racket or arms. You really need to allow the foot to act as a pivot for this to happen, so hit on the ball of the foot only.</p>
<p>One other important point. I see some players hitting their two-handed backhands by coordinating their rackets and bodies to move at the same speed. That’s incorrect. You always want to move the racket faster. The body comes through last as a result of the momentum created in hitting the stroke. I just wanted to mention this, as it’s a common problem with two-handed backhand players at the club level.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Wrapping It Up</h2>
<p>While there are many rotations you can use in tennis, I find these three to be the most common and most useful. Read this post again, look at the pictures and watch the videos for best learning. Practice the footwork alone first and then do it in a controlled environment with someone feeding you. A ball machine like the Lobster Elite Liberty works great too.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>The next step would be to try out the rotations in practice and then finally in a match. Imagine how great the feeling will be when you use one of these rotations to hit a clean winner with almost effortless power? You’ll certainly think it was well worth the work and effort at that point. As a club player who learned tennis on my own, I can tell you these rotations absolutely took my game to the next level. Try them. Practice them. And use them to defeat your foes!</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>The post <a href="/how-to-effortlessly-generate-more-power-on-your-groundstrokes/">How To Effortlessly Generate More Power On Your Groundstrokes</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/how-to-effortlessly-generate-more-power-on-your-groundstrokes/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>3</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Duds to Aces: 8 Must-Know Tips To Increase Tennis Serve Power</title>
		<link>/duds-to-aces-8-must-know-tips-to-increase-tennis-serve-power/</link>
					<comments>/duds-to-aces-8-must-know-tips-to-increase-tennis-serve-power/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chad Walner]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 07 Oct 2018 11:07:11 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Training]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[serve]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=667</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>We all want more power in our tennis serve. We see professional players on TV hitting serves 120 mph+ and they make it look easy. Yet the average club player has difficulty serving more than 90 mph. Why? It comes &#8230; <a class="kt-excerpt-readmore" href="/duds-to-aces-8-must-know-tips-to-increase-tennis-serve-power/" aria-label="Duds to Aces: 8 Must-Know Tips To Increase Tennis Serve Power">Read More</a></p>
<p>The post <a href="/duds-to-aces-8-must-know-tips-to-increase-tennis-serve-power/">Duds to Aces: 8 Must-Know Tips To Increase Tennis Serve Power</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>We all want more power in our tennis serve. We see professional players on TV hitting serves 120 mph+ and they make it look easy. Yet the average club player has difficulty serving more than 90 mph.</p>
<p>Why?</p>
<p><strong>It comes down to the fundamentals – but they’re often misunderstood. These little things can and do make all the difference. To add more power to our tennis serve, here we will isolate 8 elements and make small improvements in each, which together will give a huge boost to your serve power.</strong></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>We need to take a look at:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="#starting-stance">starting stance</a></li>
<li><a href="#body-rotation">body rotation</a></li>
<li><a href="#power-position">power position</a></li>
<li><a href="#shoulder-alignment">shoulder alignment</a></li>
<li><a href="#racket-drop">racket drop</a></li>
<li><a href="#pronation">pronation</a></li>
<li><a href="#forward-movement">forward movement</a></li>
<li><a href="#follow-through">follow through</a></li>
</ul>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>I’m going to touch on each fundamental in this post, explaining how you can use them to add power to your serve. Afterward, you’ll have a greater understanding of what produces a fast-paced tennis serve. Professional tour level players are simply combining all these fundamentals together into one fluid motion to produce their huge serves. While you may never serve 120 mph, you can certainly add 10-15 mph to your serve and possibly break the 100 mph barrier, which few club players achieve.</p>
<p>If you have a beginner’s serve, I have a series of videos detailing how to achieve an advanced serve on my youtube channel.  Reading this entire post then watching the videos will be very beneficial. I also have a great article on this blog explaining the differences between a <a href="/beginners-serve-vs-advanced-tennis-serve-what-are-the-differences/">beginner and advanced serve</a>.</p>
<p>While my videos are great for visual learning, the blog posts are excellent for relaying the longer technical details. I can provide a lot more information in these posts as opposed to a five-minute video. But the combination of both video and blog posts are by far the best way to learn, so stay tuned to each one.</p>
<p>Now back to the serve. We’ve all heard the saying “the serve is the most important shot in tennis”. It’s true. The serve starts off every point and if you can’t hold serve, you can’t win in tennis. A weak serve will cause you to be on the defensive most of the time. That’s no way to play tennis. So let’s dive into the eight ways you can optimize power on your serve.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="starting-stance"></a></p>
<h2># 1 &#8211; Starting Stance</h2>
</div>
<p>There are only two basic ways to stand when serving: the <strong>platform stance</strong> and the <strong>pinpoint stance</strong>. Let’s define each to make it easy to understand.</p>
<div id="attachment_1283" style="width: 810px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1283" class="size-full wp-image-1283" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0050.jpg" alt="Tennis platform stance." width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0050.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0050-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0050-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /><p id="caption-attachment-1283" class="wp-caption-text">Tennis platform stance.</p></div>
<p><strong>Platform Stance:</strong> The server starts the serve with both feet apart and jumps into the air off both feet. Most of the power on the jump comes from the front foot. The lead foot should be positioned at a 45-degree angle to the baseline. The back foot should be parallel to the baseline. The toes of the back foot should be near the heel of the front foot.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div id="attachment_1284" style="width: 810px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1284" class="size-full wp-image-1284" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0052.jpg" alt="Tennis pinpoint stance." width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0052.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0052-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0052-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /><p id="caption-attachment-1284" class="wp-caption-text">Tennis pinpoint stance.</p></div>
<p><strong>Pinpoint Stance:</strong> The serve starts with both feet apart but upon entering the power position, bring both feet together so they are touching, or nearly touching, and jump off both feet. The power from the jump is more evenly proportioned between both feet.</p>
<p>Let’s talk about the pros and cons of each stance. The platform stance is easier to learn, requires less timing and is better for serving and volleying than the pinpoint. This is because it has fewer moving parts and propels you forward into the court more than the pinpoint. I teach all new players and kids the platform serve first as it&#8217;s easier to learn. Its major drawback is that it&#8217;s less powerful.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>The pinpoint stance produces more power, as the force in the jump is distributed equally in both legs. The momentum of bringing the rear leg forward also provides additional power in the serve, as there is movement involved, rather than starting from a static position like in the platform stance. The pinpoint stance generates more of a vertical explosion in the jump, which will produce more pace on the serve.</p>
<p>If you play with a platform stance, try experimenting with the pinpoint. It may take a few practice sessions to get used to the timing. I have moved intermediate players from the platform to the pinpoint and they have seen good results.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="body-rotation"></a></p>
<h2># 2 – Body Rotation</h2>
</div>
<p>Many players with beginner and advanced serves orient their body way too straight-on to the court. This means they are facing the court, or net, rather than facing away from it. Ideally, your opponent should even see your back some of the time during your serve motion. The best examples of great body rotation on the serve I can think of are John McEnroe and Pete Sampras. Check out their service motions on youtube for examples. Play them in slow motion if you can.</p>

<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0106.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="450" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0106.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="Body rotation for the serve (starting position)." srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0106.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0106-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0106-768x432.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0106-732x412.jpg 732w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0106-366x206.jpg 366w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0106-538x302.jpg 538w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0106-269x151.jpg 269w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0106-560x315.jpg 560w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></a>
<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0107.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="450" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0107.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="Body rotation for the serve (power position)." srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0107.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0107-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0107-768x432.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0107-732x412.jpg 732w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0107-366x206.jpg 366w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0107-538x302.jpg 538w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0107-269x151.jpg 269w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0107-560x315.jpg 560w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></a>
<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0093.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="450" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0093.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="Body rotation for the serve (power position)." srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0093.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0093-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0093-768x432.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0093-732x412.jpg 732w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0093-366x206.jpg 366w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0093-538x302.jpg 538w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0093-269x151.jpg 269w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0093-560x315.jpg 560w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></a>
<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0100.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="450" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0100.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="Body rotation for the serve (with racket drop)." srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0100.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0100-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0100-768x432.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0100-732x412.jpg 732w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0100-366x206.jpg 366w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0100-538x302.jpg 538w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0100-269x151.jpg 269w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0100-560x315.jpg 560w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></a>

<p>If you have a beginner’s serve, you can orient slightly away from the court, but not too much because of your eastern forehand grip. You’ll definitely want to work on developing an advanced serve if you desire strong power on your serve. A beginner’s serve (or waiter’s serve) will only get you so far in tennis. There’s a reason why you won&#8217;t see a waiter’s serve from anyone (male or female) on the pro tour. It doesn’t generate enough pace or spin to compete with advanced service motions.</p>
<p>Advanced servers with a continental grip can orient away from the net to an extreme extent. The rotation of the shoulders will ideally be greater than 90 degrees (perpendicular to the net) but less so in the hips. This disparity between shoulders and hips creates torque in the core of the body, storing up kinetic energy. The uncoiling of the core during the serve motion is what triggers the arm, shoulder and wrist movements that come afterward. Doing it all correctly results in serve speeds in excess of 100 mph.</p>
<p>Without good rotation, the serve becomes more of an arm and shoulder shot. As I just demonstrated, it’s essential to create a coil with the body to add significant pace to your serve. If you have an advanced serve, turn your shoulders more than you normally rotate them. It may feel very uncomfortable at first, but that’s typical.</p>
<p>Get used to the increased shoulder rotation by turning slightly (10-20 degrees) more than normal at first. Continue practicing and shadow-stroking until your shoulders are 110-130 degrees away from the net. This will allow you to begin generating the higher serve speeds you crave.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="power-position"></a></p>
<h2># 3 – Power Position</h2>
</div>
<div id="attachment_1292" style="width: 810px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1292" class="size-full wp-image-1292" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0152.jpg" alt="The Power Position, also known as the Trophy Position." width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0152.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0152-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0152-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /><p id="caption-attachment-1292" class="wp-caption-text">The Power Position, also known as the Trophy Position.</p></div>
<p><strong>All groundstrokes and serves have a power position in tennis.</strong> This is the position you hold briefly before making your forward movement into the ball. I see a lot of club players with no power positions on their groundstrokes and serves. On the serve, the power position is often referred to as the “trophy position”.</p>
<div id="attachment_714" style="width: 410px" class="wp-caption alignright"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-714" class="size-full wp-image-714" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/3888716168_55398d3bc8_z.jpg" alt="" width="400" height="515" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/3888716168_55398d3bc8_z.jpg 400w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/3888716168_55398d3bc8_z-233x300.jpg 233w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" /><p id="caption-attachment-714" class="wp-caption-text"><a title="mathieu serve" href="https://flickr.com/photos/charliecowins/3888716168">&#8220;mathieu serve&#8221;</a> by <a href="https://flickr.com/people/charliecowins">chascow</a> is licensed under <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/">CC BY</a></p></div>
<p>I always recommend taking video of your serve. If you play back the video in slow motion, or even regular speed, you may notice you lack a power position. If so, it would benefit you to achieve it. Or, if you think you do hit a power position, it may be very weak compared to where it could be. If it doesn’t look athletic (knees bent, tossing hand straight up, racket in an L-shape to the forearm, shoulders slanted), you probably have a very poor power position.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>While I can’t go into extreme detail on the power position of the serve here, you can begin to make corrections simply by sight. If you pause the video of your serve in the power position and compare it to the current best servers in the world (or any pro in the top 20), you’ll see considerable differences. Notice those differences and begin to try and close the gap.</p>
<p>Once you identify how to achieve a better power position, begin practicing but without hitting the ball. You can do it with racket in hand or even without a racket. I often practice my serve form at home in front of a mirror with no racket or ball. Make sure you are hitting all the key points of the power position and then hold it for 3-5 seconds. Once you are done holding it, you can continue the rest of the serve motion. I find this really helps my service motion when I really serve.</p>
<p>Almost every great server achieves a great power position. They almost seem to pause there for just a few milliseconds before completing the remainder of their motion. I can all but guarantee you if you improve your power position, you’ll improve the power in your serve. Give it a try. It’ll be a challenge at first but keep working at it. If you have a coach or someone who can keep a trained eye on you while you serve, all the better.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="shoulder-alignment"></a></p>
<h2># 4 – Shoulder Alignment</h2>
</div>
<p>When I talk about shoulder alignment, I mean the angle of the shoulders relative to the ground. Think of a line that’s about 45 degrees in relation to the floor. I had shoulder rotation earlier in the post, but in relation to the court or net. What we are talking about here is different.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-1296 size-full" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0152angle.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0152angle.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0152angle-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0152angle-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p>I’ve studied many of the great servers of the last two generations. In case-after-case, I noted almost all of them have at least a 45-degree angle of alignment in their shoulders (to the ground) in the power position. One of the sharpest angles I saw was in Pete Sampras (nearly 60 degrees on some serves).</p>
<p>At the club level, most of the servers I see don’t even come close to a 45-degree angle on their shoulder alignment. For example, if you’re a right-handed player, your left shoulder should be much higher than your right shoulder in the power position. All you need do is take a video or picture in the power position and then draw a line through your shoulders. You’ll easily be able to see the angle in relation to the ground.</p>
<p>A big reason for a poor angle in club players’ serves is the early dropping of the tossing arm. If the arm drops too early, so do the shoulders. Another reason for a poor angle is that club players don’t achieve the stretch in their side obliques that make the correct shoulder alignment possible. If you ever notice, great servers flair out their hip (the one closest to the baseline) into the direction of the court. This makes their bodies appear like a bow, constricted and coiled. When uncoiled it unleashes massive power in comparison to not using the body properly.</p>
<p>If you want to gain effortless power on your serve, keep your tossing arm up longer than usual, flair out your front hip, and make sure your rear shoulder really dips much closer to the ground. I’m a big believer in exaggerating postures until they become habit. Try going through your service motion with these ideas in mind. You don’t even need to be on a court or use a racket or ball.</p>
<p>Check your form in a mirror and make sure you see a strong dip (the tossing shoulder much higher than the hitting shoulder) in the power position. Keep working on this until you become comfortable and then practice it in serves with a racket and ball. If you can achieve even a 10-15 degree increase in your dip, it will certainly add a few miles per hour to your serve.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="racket-drop"></a></p>
<h2># 5 – Racket Drop</h2>
</div>
<p>The racket drop is a very big deal when it comes to effortless serve power. This is the part of the serve where the racket inverts (even if for a millisecond) and the butt cap is facing the sky. Without exception, every top professional player has a deep racket drop (strong inversion).</p>
<div id="attachment_712" style="width: 410px" class="wp-caption alignright"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-712" class="wp-image-712 size-full" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/877694390_ba616ed92d_z.jpg" alt="" width="400" height="306" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/877694390_ba616ed92d_z.jpg 400w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/877694390_ba616ed92d_z-300x230.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" /><p id="caption-attachment-712" class="wp-caption-text"><a title="Andy Roddick serving at Wimbledon" href="https://flickr.com/photos/koltregaskes/877694390">&#8220;Andy Roddick serving at Wimbledon&#8221;</a> by <a href="https://flickr.com/people/koltregaskes">Kol Tregaskes</a> is licensed under <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/2.0/">CC BY-NC-ND</a></p></div>
<p>One of the deepest racket drops ever seen on the pro tour was that of Andy Roddick. If you have a chance to check out his serve in slow motion, I advise you to take note how deep is racket drop is. It was even deeper than Federer, which is why Andy averaged serve speeds about 10 mph more than Federer.</p>
<p>I find that club players either completely lack a racket drop or they have a very shallow one. Of all nine fundamentals mentioned in this post, the racket drop was my biggest problem for years. I corrected it using several drills that I recommend in this blog and my youtube channel. I’m sorry to say, but if you don’t have a deep racket drop, you’re likely never going to reach your potential in terms of serve speed.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>The reason for this is simple. A deep racket drop allows the racket to travel a longer distance to the target than no racket drop or a shallow one. A longer distance (for the racket to travel) translates into more momentum and a much stronger impact. I’ve noticed a huge difference when the racket drop is done correctly and when there is none.</p>
<p>The only way to tell what kind of racket drop you have is to video your serve. The racket typically moves to fast to tell, unless it’s blatantly obvious you have none. If your racket drop is non-existent or very poor, check out this video I made on <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=yvL5mXGEkuo" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">how to improve your racket drop</a>. By developing a deep racket drop, you’re sure to add good velocity to the serve. It may take time to develop, but it’s worth it. This is one of the most important factors in hitting powerful serves. It’s also crucial for being able to generate topspin serves.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="pronation"></a></p>
<h2># 6 – Pronation</h2>

<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/mSuppination1.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="450" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/mSuppination1.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="Supination" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/mSuppination1.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/mSuppination1-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/mSuppination1-768x432.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/mSuppination1-560x315.jpg 560w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></a>
<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/Pronation1.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="450" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/Pronation1.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="Pronation" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/Pronation1.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/Pronation1-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/Pronation1-768x432.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/Pronation1-560x315.jpg 560w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></a>

</div>
<p>I’ve said a lot about pronation in <a href="/10-tennis-drills-you-can-practice-without-a-court/#serve-pronation">previous articles</a>. It’s basically rotating the forearm 180 degrees. I’ll show you how to do it now. Put your arm straight in front of you with palm facing up (called supination). Now turn your palm down, twisting your forehand but keeping your arm in the same position. Congratulations, you just pronated.</p>
<p>This is what’s happening on the serve just before impact and just after impact. Pronation alone can gain you an extra 5-10 mph if timed perfectly right. It allows the racket face to move in two dimensions to the ball – towards it and turning into it. If you don’t pronate, then you’ll always be hitting the ball in one dimension and never be able to generate the kind of pace professional players do.</p>
<p>If you’ve been playing tennis a long time with a beginner’s serve or no pronation whatsoever, it’s going to be difficult to pick up. I can’t lie about that. Early on in my playing days, I didn’t pronate. I was never taught how to serve properly so I hit a waiter’s serve with an eastern forehand grip. When I learned about pronation and saw the great benefits, I decided to teach it to myself after years of playing without it.</p>
<p>It took me a couple of months of constant practice to get used to the continental grip and twisting the forearm at just the right time. I’m glad to say that now it has become as natural for me to use as driving a car or tying my sneakers. One easy way to learn pronation (and the racket drop) is to use the ServeMaster, created by Lisa Dodson. I have a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=PA5rfvjj7L4" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">ServeMaster video</a> on youtube devoted to using it. You should also <a href="/learn-how-to-serve-in-10-minutes-with-the-servemaster/">check out my post all about it</a> to see if it might be for you.</p>
<p>If you don’t pronate on your serve and you’re serious about tennis, I highly recommend you give it a try. Remember, it can take weeks or months to learn, so give it time. Or, who knows, maybe you’ll pick it up right away. I can guarantee you it will make a difference in your serve speed. But you’ll need to develop a racket drop and use the continental grip to make it work. So many of these fundamentals go hand-in-hand with each other it seems.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="forward-movement"></a></p>
<h2># 7 – Forward &amp; Upward Movement</h2>
</div>
<p>This section is what most people think of as a &#8220;jump into the serve&#8221;. After striking the ball on the serve, our momentum should cause our body weight to move upward and forward, following the path of the ball. Most professional tennis players get at least 4-5 inches off the ground. This is actually the result of momentum from a violent body motion rather than jumping.</p>
<div id="attachment_718" style="width: 385px" class="wp-caption alignright"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-718" class="size-full wp-image-718" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/235443062_af625f9a90_z.jpg" alt="" width="375" height="500" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/235443062_af625f9a90_z.jpg 375w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/235443062_af625f9a90_z-225x300.jpg 225w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 375px) 100vw, 375px" /><p id="caption-attachment-718" class="wp-caption-text"><a title="Leaning into serve" href="https://flickr.com/photos/75449583@N00/235443062">&#8220;Leaning into serve&#8221;</a> by <a href="https://flickr.com/people/75449583@N00">upabreak.com</a> is licensed under <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/">CC BY</a></p></div>
<p>If your mechanics are poor in the previous fundamentals, you’ll likely not experience this upward and forward movement. I almost feel it’s a very violent strike of the ball with the whole body. When I do it right, I can see and feel my opponents flinching on the other side of the net just before I hit the ball. If you never experience this, don’t worry. You can still hit fast-paced serves by trying to direct your body forward.</p>
<p>For sure, the upward movement comes mostly from bending your knees are pressing on the ground. If you lack a good knee bend or just can’t do it, you can at least initiate a forward movement by leaning forward the moment of contact. Just allow your body to fall forward a bit when you strike the ball. You’ll notice your serve is slightly faster and a bit heavier – meaning it doesn’t lose as much pace after hitting the ground.</p>
<p>On the serve, it’s best to land on the opposite leg of your dominant hand. A right-handed player will land on his left leg (and vice-versa for lefties). You typically want your weight slightly over the leg you land on. But if this doesn’t seem possible, just make sure you are finishing the serve inside the baseline. Even six inches of forward movement is better than none at all.</p>
<p>I honestly find this fundamental to be quite difficult if one doesn’t have that initial upward explosion. Whenever I serve and lack that explosion, jumping upward and forward always feels manufactured and forced. Even worse it throws my timing off the serve. Resist the temptation to jump only for the sake of jumping. You can still hit hard serves with forward movement. Before the modern era of tennis, the server was not allowed to jump or leave the ground, and they still hit fast serves – even with wooden rackets!</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="follow-through"></a></p>
<h2># 8 – Follow Through</h2>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1347" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0111.jpg" alt="Follow through." width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0111.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0111-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0111-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
</div>
<p>When I talk about follow through, I’m talking about the hitting arm. I see many club players abruptly stop their arms after hitting the ball. It kind of looks like an invisible force field has frozen their arms, bringing them from a swinging motion to a dead stop. This kind of follow through, or lack of it, is caused by tensing the muscles of the arm way too tight.</p>
<p>The sooner you stop the hitting arm, the less racket speed you generate. The less racket speed you generate, the slower the serve. Make sense? This is also true on groundstrokes. That’s the reason why professional tennis players follow through so far; it keeps the racket speed high upon impact of the ball. When serving, follow through is just as important.</p>
<p>I like to follow through with my right arm slightly bent at the elbow and on the left side of my body – just like you’d see from a major league pitcher. This is especially true of first serves. On second serves, it’s also important to follow through, except the path of the racket is going out to the side. rather than into the court. I find that whether it be a first serve or a second serve, the follow-through is crucial to generating higher speeds and spins.</p>
<p>I know I might sound like a broken record, but the ServeMaster is an excellent tool for the serve and to get you following through. This is because the weighted balls at the end almost force your arm to keep going. It’s only natural that your arm will swing to the other side of your body.</p>
<p>If you are having difficulty with this during your real serves, practice swinging with only your racket. Try to keep your arm and grip super-loose on the serve motion and follow through. Just let the arm finish where it naturally wants to go. If this doesn’t help, swing slower.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>I can almost promise you that if you serve full speed, this will be a challenge for you to change. You must first start out using slow shadow swings (with and without the racket) and build up the muscle memory for it. This is the best way to elongate the follow through. I know this through my own experience and that of my clients. I always use slow swings first (in all strokes) to build the muscle memory before going full speed. Trust me on this.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Putting It All Together</h2>
<p>If you only use brute force to increase serve speed, you’ll tire yourself out, potentially injure your body, and never reach the speeds your capable of reaching. But by focusing on the fundamentals I outlined in this article, you can begin to see some nice changes pretty quickly. Pick one or two fundamentals that will be the easiest to change and start working on them. Perhaps you’ll soon notice the improvement in your serve pace and want to pick up the other fundamentals.</p>
<p>Building a great serve takes time, lots of practice, and sometimes going back to the drawing board before lasting improvement is made. Don’t ever give up. Video your serve every practice session if you can. Take a hopper of balls and practice serving on your own. Have a goal for the practice session. Maybe you’ll work on rotating your shoulders more or following through better. Pick one thing at a time and then work on it for a while.</p>
<p>Trying new things in a match usually doesn’t work. You need to set aside time to practice alone or with your coach. Consistent practice with specific and measurable goals are game-changers. If tennis is your passion, take your craft seriously and put in the work. I do. The most fun you can have in tennis is to see the fruit of your practice labors fulfilled in match play. Trust me, it’s well worth it.</p>
<p>The post <a href="/duds-to-aces-8-must-know-tips-to-increase-tennis-serve-power/">Duds to Aces: 8 Must-Know Tips To Increase Tennis Serve Power</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/duds-to-aces-8-must-know-tips-to-increase-tennis-serve-power/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>9 Plyometric Exercises For Explosive Tennis</title>
		<link>/9-plyometric-exercises-for-explosive-tennis/</link>
					<comments>/9-plyometric-exercises-for-explosive-tennis/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chad Walner]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 05 Oct 2018 10:58:57 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Training]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=636</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>If you want to take your tennis game to the next level, you need skill, endurance and speed. You can learn new skills through applying technique. Endurance comes from conditioning. And speed? Plyometrics are your ticket to explosive movement and power. &#8230; <a class="kt-excerpt-readmore" href="/9-plyometric-exercises-for-explosive-tennis/" aria-label="9 Plyometric Exercises For Explosive Tennis">Read More</a></p>
<p>The post <a href="/9-plyometric-exercises-for-explosive-tennis/">9 Plyometric Exercises For Explosive Tennis</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>If you want to take your tennis game to the next level, you need skill, endurance and speed.</p>
<p>You can learn new skills through applying technique.</p>
<p>Endurance comes from conditioning.</p>
<p><strong>And speed? Plyometrics are your ticket to explosive movement and power.</strong></p>
<p><strong>Plyometrics are all about speed. They are specific types of exercises that train the muscles to use their natural elasticity for explosive movement. There is nothing else you can do that will add more power and explosion to your movements, which is ideal for tennis.</strong></p>
<p><strong>Basically, plyometric tennis uses quick, explosive movements that cause a rapid lengthening of the muscle followed by a short contraction. Olympic athletes, MMA fighters, gymnasts and all serious athletes use some form of plyometrics in their training routines.</strong></p>
<p>While there are over 100 different plyometric exercises, we’re going to focus on the top nine for tennis. I chose these specific exercises because they train all the muscles required for a great tennis game.</p>
<p>These are:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="#frog-jumps">frog jumps</a></li>
<li><a href="#squat-jumps">weighted squat jumps</a></li>
<li><a href="#one-legged-hops">one-legged hops</a></li>
<li><a href="#jumping-lunges">jumping lunges</a></li>
<li><a href="#box-jumps">box jumps</a></li>
<li><a href="#clapping-pushups">clapping pushups</a></li>
<li><a href="#medicine-ball-throws">medicine ball throws</a></li>
<li><a href="#resistance-bands">resistance band drills</a></li>
<li><a href="#agility-ladder">agility ladder drills</a></li>
</ul>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Some of you might be wondering where weight training fits into tennis. I believe moderate weight training is fine if you have the time and inclination to do it. But in my own experience, and that of my clients, it is almost completely unnecessary. This is because weight training uses slow, static movements which are not relevant to an explosive sport like tennis. Plyometrics, on the other hand, use rapid movements, which more closely mimic the quick motions needed in tennis and most sports.</p>
<p>Now that we have a clear idea of what plyometrics is, and how it can benefit our game, let’s jump into the nine best plyometric drills for tennis. Get ready to sweat.</p>
<blockquote><p>Oh, one caveat before we continue. These exercises require varying degrees of athleticism and joint fitness. If you physically can’t do an exercise, skip it, or modify it to your level of ability and age. If you have a problem doing all the exercises in this post, better to start with fewer reps and steadily increase over time.</p></blockquote>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="frog-jumps"></a></p>
<h2>#1 &#8211; Frog Jumps</h2>
</div>
<p>These are one of my favorite plyometric exercises for tennis because anyone can do them. They build up leg strength and help with your explosion coming out of the split step position. I often have my kids do frog jumps and I perform these exercises right along with them. This exercise activates all the muscles in the legs and takes a lot out of you, so start slow.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-92" style="margin-bottom: 0px; padding-bottom: 0px;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/howto220x40.png" alt="how to" width="220" height="40" /></p>
<ol>
<li>Start with your feet about shoulder width apart.</li>
<li>Bend your legs about 90 degrees, thrust arms back and lean forward.</li>
<li>Take as big a leap as you can forward. Do not move your feet at any time during the jump; simply jump from where your two feet are positioned.</li>
<li>After you jump, you should land on two feet. Simply repeat until you finish.</li>
</ol>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-92" style="margin-bottom: 0px; padding-bottom: 0px;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/reps220x40.png" alt="reps" width="220" height="40" /></p>
<p>I would suggest starting with jumping from one doubles side-line to another – basically one side of the court to the other going parallel to the net. Rest for 15 seconds and then frog jump back to the starting position. As you build up endurance, you can do another half round or full round</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="squat-jumps"></a></p>
<h2># 2 – Weighted Squat Jumps</h2>
</div>
<p>I love doing squat jumps as they increase vertical leap and the speed of your jump. These are especially helpful on high shots. For example, when I’m playing the net and a high shot approaches (and it’s going in), I will typically jump up quickly to reach the ball. If I’ve been doing weighted squat jumps, I definitely feel like I get up quicker and higher. This exercise will also help with the serve or any stroke requiring you to jump in the air.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-92" style="margin-bottom: 0px; padding-bottom: 0px;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/howto220x40.png" alt="how to" width="220" height="40" /></p>
<ol>
<li>You’ll need dumbbells to perform these to best effect. I like to use 20 lb. dumbbells in each hand, but you can start with the amount appropriate to your age, weight and ability. Stand with feet shoulder-width apart and your arms hanging at your sides, holding a dumbbell in each hand.</li>
<li>Bend down all the way to the ground so you are in a full squat position.</li>
<li>Now explode up into the air as fast and high as you can.</li>
<li>Land on your toes and then slowly descend again to the full squat position. Explode up again in a quick jump.</li>
</ol>
<p>Continue repeating.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-92" style="margin-bottom: 0px; padding-bottom: 0px;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/reps220x40.png" alt="reps" width="220" height="40" /></p>
<p>I suggest starting with 5 reps of 3 sets if you are fit. For those in super-good shape, you can do 3 sets of 8-10 reps. This exercise, like most plyometric drills, take a lot out of you. After I do 3 sets, I’m done with this exercise for at least a couple of days.</p>
<p>If you don’t have dumbbells, still do the jumps. You can add a few more reps. For those with joint issues who want to do this exercise, perform them on a soft surface that is friendly to your knees. I can usually find a padded surface at the gym in which to do these. It works much better than hard tile or wood floors.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="one-legged-hops"></a></p>
<h2># 3 &#8211; One Legged Hops</h2>
</div>
<p>In tennis, strong legs are essential for good movement and power. This drill will work on each leg, one at a time. Most of us, even if we don’t know it, have a strong leg and a weaker leg. This exercise will quickly inform you which leg is your weaker one while improving your balance.</p>
<p>In tennis, we often hit off one leg. I love this drill because it strengthens both legs, allowing us to effectively hit off either leg. The result is increased forehand, backhand and serve power. Just a warning, but this drill can be very tiring on the legs, so start slow.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-92" style="margin-bottom: 0px; padding-bottom: 0px;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/howto220x40.png" alt="how to" width="220" height="40" /></p>
<p>A simple chalk mark, string or agility ladder on the ground is all that’s necessary. If you have access to a court, you can do this drill on it without those things. Several variations are possible of this exercise. I will go over the three I use the most.</p>
<h4>The First Variation – Sideline to Sideline.</h4>
<ol>
<li>Stand one leg at one side of the court.</li>
<li>Hop on the same one leg to the other side of the court. You can move parallel to the net – going from one sideline to the other.</li>
<li>Return back to the same side you started hopping on the same leg.</li>
<li>You can then switch legs and do the same circuit on that leg.</li>
</ol>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<h4>Second Variation – Hopping over the sideline, service line or baseline is fine.</h4>
<ol>
<li>On one leg hop forward over a line.</li>
<li>Then hop back over the line, into the same position you started.</li>
<li>Repeat at least 5-6 times. Then perform this drill on the other leg.</li>
</ol>
<h4>Third Variation – will have you moving side-to-side on one leg.</h4>
<ol>
<li>Turn 90 degree so you’re looking down the line. You should be on one leg.</li>
<li>Hop to your side, over the line.</li>
<li>Then quickly hop back over the line to the same you started.</li>
<li>Repeat at least 5-6 times. Do this drill on the other leg too.</li>
</ol>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-92" style="margin-bottom: 0px; padding-bottom: 0px;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/reps220x40.png" alt="reps" width="220" height="40" /></p>
<p>If you are just starting out, I would suggest doing all three variations but taking it easy. You might hop on your right leg from sideline-to-sideline once and then return on your left leg once. For the other two variations, you can do 2 sets of 5-6 reps on each leg.</p>
<p>Remember, your body is the greatest indicator of your physical well-being. If you feel like you can do more, do them. It not, cut back some and build up your rep range over time.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="jumping-lunges"></a></p>
<h2># 4 &#8211; Jumping Lunges</h2>
</div>
<p>This is an awesome drill for helping you get down on the low shots. I think all of us struggle with getting low, so this drill is great for everyone who plays tennis. When I play, I am often forced to hit low volleys. The dipping topspin shots from today’s rackets translates into a lot of low volleys.</p>
<p>Sometimes I get so low my knee is almost touching the ground. Whenever I get this low, I feel like I’m doing a lunge, which is the basis of this plyometric drill. If you’re one of those players who doesn’t get low enough, this is the one exercise you can’t skip!</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-92" style="margin-bottom: 0px; padding-bottom: 0px;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/howto220x40.png" alt="how to" width="220" height="40" /></p>
<ol>
<li>Start in a lunge position with right foot forward and left foot back. Your left leg knee should be on or near the ground and your right leg bent at a 90-degree angle.</li>
<li>Jump off both feet into the air as high as you can.</li>
<li>In mid-air, adjust your feet into the opposite lunge position – left foot forward and right foot back.</li>
<li>Continue repeating until the drill is completed.</li>
</ol>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-92" style="margin-bottom: 0px; padding-bottom: 0px;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/reps220x40.png" alt="reps" width="220" height="40" /></p>
<p>For beginners, I recommend doing 5-6 reps and 2-3 sets. A rep is two jumps, where you basically return to the same starting spot. Intermediate and advanced athletes can raise the rep count but I wouldn’t recommend going past 3 sets to start. With any plyometric exercise, you don’t want to overdo it. If you play tennis, it’s important to not feel exhausted on the court. So keep your plyometric drills in moderation and space them out over a couple of days.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="box-jumps"></a></p>
<h2># 5 – Box Jumps</h2>
</div>
<p>When people think of plyometrics, box jumps are one of the first exercises they envision. No doubt, box jumps are one of the 3-4 core exercises in plyometrics. I see them used in almost every sport that requires explosion, including basketball, football, volleyball and MMA. Tennis is no different. The box jump will improve explosiveness from a starting position. It will also increase jumping ability for the serve and your reach on high shots.</p>
<p>Most gyms have platforms to jump onto. If you don’t belong to a gym or own a platform, you can improvise and jump onto something that can support your weight. There are many variations of box jumps. I want to focus on three here. I recommend choosing a box height that you can comfortably jump onto. You want it to be slightly challenging but not too easy. The height is dependent on your height, athletic ability, and flexibility.</p>
<blockquote><p>Please note that if you have joint issues with your knees, box jumps should be avoided, as they heavily stress the knees.</p></blockquote>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-92" style="margin-bottom: 0px; padding-bottom: 0px;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/howto220x40.png" alt="how to" width="220" height="40" /></p>
<h4>Variation 1 – Double Leg Box Jumps</h4>
<ol>
<li>Stand about one foot in front of the box with feet shoulder width apart.</li>
<li>From that position jump with both feet onto the box.</li>
<li>Jump down to the floor and then repeat until all reps are completed.<br />
Note, if you can’t jump from a standing position, take a step back with one foot and use that momentum to jump onto the box. It’s easier taking one step back.</li>
</ol>
<h4>Variation 2 – One Step Double Leg Box Jumps</h4>
<ol>
<li>Stand about 6-8 feet from the box.</li>
<li>Take one step forward and make a small jump off both feet.</li>
<li>After landing on both feet, jump again onto the box.</li>
<li>Jump back down, step back and repeat.</li>
</ol>
<h4>Variation 3 – Multiple Box Double Leg Box Jumps</h4>
<p>For this variation, you’ll need two boxes. Optimally the first box will be roughly half the height of the second box. Line them up, shorter box first, about 4-5 feet apart.</p>
<ol>
<li>Stand in front of the first (shorter) box with feet shoulder-width apart.</li>
<li>Jump onto the box, landing on it with two feet.</li>
<li>Without stopping jump forward onto the floor on both feet.</li>
<li>Without taking a step, just off both feet onto the higher box.</li>
<li>Jump forward and down from the second (higher) box. This is one rep.</li>
<li>Walk back to the first (shorter) box and repeat until all reps are done.</li>
</ol>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-92" style="margin-bottom: 0px; padding-bottom: 0px;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/reps220x40.png" alt="reps" width="220" height="40" /></p>
<p>Box jumps can take a lot out of you, but they’re also a lot of fun. I suggest starting with one set of each variation. Beginners can do 5-7 reps and intermediate athletes can do 8-10 reps. Advanced athletes should stick with the 8-10 rep range but do a second set if desired. Box jumps, like most plyometrics, should be done twice a week. You can go three times per week if you have the energy and recover fast.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="clapping-pushups"></a></p>
<h2># 6 – Clapping Pushups</h2>
</div>
<p>The first five plyometric exercises focused on lower body, which is very much needed in tennis. Now we’ll turn our attention to the upper body. Plyometric pushups are awesome for working the chest, arms and shoulders. Unlike heavy weight lifting, the quick movements needed in a plyometric clapping pushup recruit a different type of muscle fiber – the one responsible for explosion, not pure strength.</p>
<p>These pushups can be tough for beginners and some women, whose upper bodies are typically not as developed as males. If you can’t manage to do these clapping pushups, you can use a wall instead of the floor. The resistance is less but you will still gain from it.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-92" style="margin-bottom: 0px; padding-bottom: 0px;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/howto220x40.png" alt="how to" width="220" height="40" /></p>
<ol>
<li>Get down on the floor into a pushup position with arms extended. You should be on your toes with your body as straight as possible. Your head and chest should be about as far from the ground as the length of your arms.</li>
<li>Lower yourself to the floor so that your body is almost touching it.</li>
<li>With a burst, push off the floor and clap both hands together.</li>
<li>After clapping both hands together, return your hands to the same position on the floor. At this point your arms should be nearly full extended.</li>
<li>This is one rep. Repeat continuously without stopping until all reps are completed.</li>
</ol>
<p>Again, if this is too difficult, you can lean against a wall and do them. If you can only do a few on the floor, do one and wait 3-5 seconds, then do another and so on until you go to failure. With consistent practice, almost everyone can build up to at least 5 reps of clapping pushups on the ground.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-92" style="margin-bottom: 0px; padding-bottom: 0px;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/reps220x40.png" alt="reps" width="220" height="40" /></p>
<p>Try going to failure on your first set. Take a minute to rest and then do another set to failure. Failure means performing reps until you can no longer carry out a single rep. Unlike heavy weights, this exercise won’t make you sore, strain your muscles or injure you. You can do this exercise every day if you want, but 2-3 times per week is fine for any level.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="medicine-ball-throws"></a></p>
<h2># 7 &#8211; Medicine Ball Throws</h2>
</div>
<p>For this drill, you’ll need a medicine ball. A 5-8 lb. ball is good for most people; kids can use a 3-5 lb. ball. I wouldn’t recommend using anything other than a medicine ball for the resistance. If a medicine ball drops, it won’t damage the floor and it’s soft enough that it won’t hurt anyone.</p>
<p>What I like about the medicine ball is that you can mimic tennis strokes with it from all different stances. Unlike resistance bands (which we’ll get to soon) you can fling the medicine ball away from you, which builds up core strength. This is a great plyometric exercise for tennis and one of the best for improving weight transfer on groundstrokes.</p>
<p>There are three variations of this exercise. We’ll go through all of them. Children and adults both can benefit greatly from this drill. If you can incorporate it into your routine twice a week, you’ll see improved technique and power on both your forehand and backhand groundstrokes.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-92" style="margin-bottom: 0px; padding-bottom: 0px;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/howto220x40.png" alt="how to" width="220" height="40" /></p>
<h4>Variation 1 – Closed Stance Medicine Ball Throws</h4>
<ol>
<li>Set up in forehand stance in a slightly closed position. For righties, your front foot should be slightly to the right (6-10 inches) of your back foot. For lefties, do the opposite. If you were playing tennis in the closed stance, your body would be facing the sideline, not the net.</li>
<li>Hold a medicine ball with two hands on your forehand side.</li>
<li>Twist your core so that the medicine ball is behind you, still holding it with both hands.</li>
<li>From this position, explode forward, uncorking and throwing the medicine ball as far in front of you as you can. Your back foot should be slightly off the ground or on your toes.</li>
</ol>
<p>Note – If your coach, trainer or another person can stand in front of you to catch the ball, that would be ideal. They can toss the ball back to you and you will repeat the above steps. After completing all reps on the forehand side, do the same drill on the backhand side, also in the closed stance.</p>
<h4>Variation 2 – Open Stance Medicine Ball Throws</h4>
<p>You’re basically doing the same movement in this drill (so I won’t repeat the steps) except out of the open stance. The open stance is much different than the closed stance, so pay attention to the next segment.</p>
<p>To find the open stance, face forward with feet greater than shoulder-width apart. If you were playing tennis, you’d be directly facing the net. When you toss the medicine ball forward, it’s important to pivot on the balls of your feet, bend your knees, and get low. This will help you elicit power from the ground. Use your core to rotate your trunk – don’t just take back the ball with your arms. Complete reps on the forehand side and the backhand side, remaining in the open stance for both strokes.</p>
<h4>Variation 3 – Medicine Ball Throw Off Back Foot</h4>
<p>In this variation, you will be doing the same movement of throwing the ball forward. Set up for your forehand in the closed stance. Your back leg will be on the ground and your front leg will be completely off the ground, about a foot in the air. Take the medicine ball back and throw it forward as far as you can. Your momentum will take you forward. This will cause you to hop forward, but land on your back foot only. Repeat until the desired rep range is reached then do backhands in the same way. You’ll be on your back foot on the backhand side too, and in the closed stance.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-92" style="margin-bottom: 0px; padding-bottom: 0px;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/reps220x40.png" alt="reps" width="220" height="40" /></p>
<p>This is a drill you can perform 2-3 times per week if you want. For beginner and intermediate athletes, I suggest doing one set of 6-8 reps per side (forehand and backhand) per variation. For example, for variation 1, do 6-8 reps on the forehand side and then 6-8 reps on the backhand side. Then do the same for variations 2 and 3. That equates to 6 total sets for all three variations. This is a great drill for increasing power and learning proper weight transfer for groundstrokes.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="resistance-bands"></a></p>
<h2># 8 – Resistance Band Training</h2>
</div>
<p>I love resistance band training and serious athletes in every sport use them. No other device can match the type of resistance they provide the body while it’s in motion. There are over a hundred different variations that can be done with resistance bands. I selected three excellent variations that will specifically benefit tennis players. The consistent use of these three drills will improve your explosiveness from a starting position, especially moving forward and laterally. It will also improve your leg drive on serves, overheads and jumping shots.</p>
<p>You’ll need resistance bands to perform these drills. You can find cheap resistance bands for under $10 and they can work. But I prefer the brand <a href="https://amzn.to/2BB8FBS">Kbands Training</a> because its resistance bands are more durable and they have bands for all types of movements. They’re a little more expensive, but if you’re serious about your training (like I am), they’re worth it.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-92" style="margin-bottom: 0px; padding-bottom: 0px;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/howto220x40.png" alt="how to" width="220" height="40" /></p>
<h4>Variation 1 – Lateral Jumps</h4>
<p>For this drill, you’ll need one long resistance band and a short cone or object to jump over. If you can add a leg resistance band (placed around the thighs) that would be ideal. However, it’s not necessary for the drill to still be effective.</p>
<ol>
<li>Put a long resistance band around your waist and attach the other side to a fence or immovable object. You will be standing to the side of it (not facing it).</li>
<li>Now jump over the cone with both feet. You’ll be jumping laterally (to the side). Land on both feet and then jump back to the starting position on the other side of the cone.</li>
<li>Keep jumping side-to-side as fast as possible with no stopping. Once the desired rep range is completed you can stop.</li>
</ol>
<h4>Variation 2 – Front to Back Jumps</h4>
<p>You’ll need the same materials and props for this drill. Set up the same way but this time place the cone in front of you. Instead of jumping laterally, you’ll be jumping forward (over the cone) and jumping backward (over the cone). Jump off two feet and continue going over the cone, jumping forward and back.</p>
<h4>Variation 3 – Groundstroke Resistance Pulls</h4>
<p>For this drill, you’ll need the long resistance band (a bungee cord also works great), your racket, and a fence or person to hold the cord. If you use a bungee cord, have someone else hold one end to apply resistance. If using the resistance band, attach to a fence or immovable object.</p>
<ol>
<li>Place the resistance band or bungee cord around your waist. Stand close to the object or person the other end is attached to. Set up in the ready position. Your body should be facing forward, feet wider than shoulder-width apart.</li>
<li>Step out to your right (if you’re right-handed) for 3-4 steps and then set up in the open forehand stance. You should feel a lot of resistance at this point. Left-handers will move to their left.</li>
<li>Take a forehand swing and then return to the ready position and cross-step or shuffle back to your starting point. This is one rep.</li>
</ol>
<p>Once you complete your desired number of reps on the forehand side, switch to the backhand side. Again, you’ll start from the ready position and take 3-4 steps to your left (for righties). Lefties will move to their right. Set up in the open stance for the backhand, take a swing, and then return to the ready position. You can cross step or shuffle back to the starting point. You should feel a strong resistance when making your swing.</p>
<p>If a person is holding the bungee cord, they can add resistance by pulling you a bit more when you make the swing. This drill will improve footwork speed and ability to hit out of the open stance, which is so necessary in modern tennis.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-92" style="margin-bottom: 0px; padding-bottom: 0px;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/reps220x40.png" alt="reps" width="220" height="40" /></p>
<p>For the first two variations (lateral jumps and front to back jumps) I suggest starting with one set of 10-12 reps for each exercise. You can do a second set as you build up your fitness. For the last variation, do 2 sets of 5-7 reps for each side (forehand and backhand). Perform all these drills twice a week for best results.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="agility-ladder"></a></p>
<h2># 9 – Agility Ladder Drills</h2>
</div>
<p>The agility ladder is another tool that has become ubiquitous in sports training. Plyometric ladder drills are most often used in football, but tennis players can benefit tremendously as well. How quickly you can move your feet and get on and off the ground account for a lot in tennis (and sports).</p>
<p>The serve and volley game has special demands on your agility as you need to be able to quickly cover a lot of ground when you rush the net. Your serve and volley drills will all benefit from the use of an agility ladder.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>If you look at the best players in the world like Novak Djokovic, you’ll see him taking many quick, small steps to adjust his body to the ball. You’ll also see him split stepping, which is jumping slightly off the ground and back onto it repeatedly throughout a point. Nothing helps us better with this kind of footwork than the agility ladder. While there are dozens of agility ladder variations, I want to touch on the three that most help with tennis. For this drill, you’ll need an <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Pro-Footwork-Training-Adjustable-Agility-Ladder/dp/B076ZTJ1P1/ref=as_li_ss_il?ie=UTF8&amp;linkCode=li3&amp;tag=aim078-20&amp;linkId=77207551c7506d84e378175152856f02&amp;language=en_US">agility ladder, like this set on Amazon</a>.</p>
<h4>Variation 1 – Hop Scotch</h4>
<ol>
<li>Place the agility ladder on the ground and start on one side. You’ll be facing the long side of the ladder.</li>
<li>Start off with both feet together and jump to a position so that both feet are wider than the ladder.</li>
<li>Next jump into the first open space or square on the ladder. You should be landing with both feet together.</li>
<li>Jump forward with both feet apart landing outside the ladder. Then jump into the next open space with both feet together.</li>
<li>Repeat until all the way through the ladder. Your feet should land inside every open space on the ladder.</li>
</ol>
<p>I picked this drill because it simulates the split step very well. If you only have time for one agility ladder drill, do this one.</p>
<h4>Variation 2 – Lateral Runs</h4>
<ol>
<li>Start off in the same position as the last variation but turn your body 90 degrees. You’ll be going through the ladder laterally (or to the side).</li>
<li>Put your right foot in the first open space and then take out and put into the next open space.</li>
<li>While doing that, simultaneously put the left foot in the space the right foot just came out of. This needs to be done fluidly and quickly.</li>
<li>Repeat until all the way through the ladder.</li>
</ol>
<p>This drill is good for lateral movement and making very small steps. It works to increase ground-to-contact speed.</p>
<h4>Variation 3 – One Legged Hop Scotch</h4>
<p>This drill is similar to variation 1 except you’ll be landing on just one foot in each open square.</p>
<ol>
<li>Start with feet together facing the long end the ladder.</li>
<li>Jump forward with both feet landing wider than the ladder.</li>
<li>Land on the first square with your left foot.</li>
<li>Jump so that both feet land outside the ladder.</li>
<li>Then jump again so that only your right foot lands in the next square.</li>
<li>Jump off your right foot and land on both feet outside the ladder.</li>
<li>Jump back onto your left foot in the next square and keep alternating feet until you reach the end of the ladder.</li>
</ol>
<p>This drill looks cool when done fast and will isolate each leg. I believe it’s important to isolate the legs on at least some drills. Try to move through the ladder as fast you can through all three variations – but without sacrificing form.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-92" style="margin-bottom: 0px; padding-bottom: 0px;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/reps220x40.png" alt="reps" width="220" height="40" /></p>
<p>I consider one time through the agility ladder as a rep. If you have never used an agility ladder, or it’s been a while, you’ll need a few times using it to coordinate your feet and movements. Once you do, perform 3 reps of each variation per session.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="sprints"></a></p>
<h2>Special Mention – Sprints</h2>
</div>
<p>Whether you know it or not, sprinting is a form of plyometric exercise. I didn’t mention it in the nine listed exercises because almost everyone knows that sprinting is important. My tennis game only took off after I started implementing a sprinting routine in my training.</p>
<p>A month or two after consistently sprinting, I was able to beat players I never had beaten before. I also discovered I could use sprinting in place of all other cardio! I did away with the 3-mile runs and 20-minute sessions on the Stairmaster in favor of twice-weekly sprint sessions.</p>
<p>Not to downplay any of the exercises in this post, because they’re all of tremendous benefit, but nothing is better than sprinting. In my opinion, it’s the single most important plyometric exercise to increase athletic ability in any sport. It builds conditioning, works the entire body and will absolutely take your game to the next level.</p>
<p>Kids and young adults can do a lot of sprinting without fear of hurting their joints. When we get older, our bodies get stiffer, things hurt and so we stop running at full speed. I believe this is a mistake. You should be doing wind sprints at least once a week, and optimally twice per week. More than that is unnecessary.</p>
<p>If you haven’t sprinted in a while, start off 60-70% speed and work your way up to 100% after 3-5 training sessions. If you go 100% from the start, you’re likely to strain or pull a muscle. At a minimum, you’ll be very sore the next few days. Learn from my mistakes and start off 60-70%.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-92" style="margin-bottom: 0px; padding-bottom: 0px;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/howto220x40.png" alt="how to" width="220" height="40" /></p>
<p>I like to sprint on a track because it’s softer than pavement, it’s meant only for running, and there are no obstacles. But if you can only sprint on pavement, that will work too. I like to get down into a sprinter’s crouch. From there, I explode forward (I’m no Usain Bolt, but I do my best) and run for 50-100 meters. I’ll typically walk for 30-60 seconds as soon as I’m done sprinting. I then get down into a sprinter’s crouch again and run for another 50-100 meters, repeating the process until all reps are done. If I feel tired, I’ll take additional time between reps, but not too much.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-92" style="margin-bottom: 0px; padding-bottom: 0px;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/reps220x40.png" alt="reps" width="220" height="40" /></p>
<p>I do a minimum of 6 sprints per session and a maximum of 10. Anything more and I feel like I’m really slowing down. I think 6-8 reps per session is ideal for the intermediate to advanced athlete. Twice a week is good enough for sprints. If you’re advanced, you could go three, but you run the risk of overtraining.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Summing It Up</h2>
<p>The exercises in this post are my all-time favorites for tennis. Try them all out and stick with the ones you derive the most benefit. Or, you could vary them, as I do.</p>
<p>For example, suppose you do three training sessions per week of 45 minutes each. In the first session, use three of the drills listed here. In the next training session, use three more. And in the final training session, utilize the remaining three. In this way, you can hit all the muscle groups in one week.</p>
<p>You can also vary the combinations of drills used in each training session from week-to-week. This keeps your training fresh and interesting by always changing it up. I find that my tennis students like variety in their training as well.</p>
<p>Don’t forget to include sprinting when the opportunity presents. If you can’t make it to a place where you can sprint, just do it on the court. I’ll typically run from fence to fence in parallel to the net. I guarantee if you sprint and do at least one training session per week of the listed drills, your game will reach a level you’ve never known before.</p>
<p>Keep at it and let me know how it goes. If you have any questions, leave them below in the comment section. Until then, train hard and strive to be the best. I know I do!</p>
<p>Featured Photo: <a title="La classe di Roger Federer: magici i due pallonetti contro Zverev!" href="https://flickr.com/photos/tennisstreaming/32499766285">&#8220;La classe di Roger Federer: magici i due pallonetti contro Zverev!&#8221;</a> by <a href="https://flickr.com/people/tennisstreaming">TennisStreaming</a> is licensed under <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/">CC BY</a></p>
<p>The post <a href="/9-plyometric-exercises-for-explosive-tennis/">9 Plyometric Exercises For Explosive Tennis</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/9-plyometric-exercises-for-explosive-tennis/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Beginner Serve Vs. Advanced Tennis Serve – Simple Tips To Unlock Your Potential</title>
		<link>/beginners-serve-vs-advanced-tennis-serve-what-are-the-differences/</link>
					<comments>/beginners-serve-vs-advanced-tennis-serve-what-are-the-differences/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chad Walner]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 03 Oct 2018 10:35:33 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Training]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[serve]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=614</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>In the world of tennis, there are two types of serves: the beginner serve and the advanced serve. The beginner’s serve is often referred to as the “waiter’s tray serve” or just the &#8220;waiter&#8217;s serve&#8221;. The advanced serve is the &#8230; <a class="kt-excerpt-readmore" href="/beginners-serve-vs-advanced-tennis-serve-what-are-the-differences/" aria-label="Beginner Serve Vs. Advanced Tennis Serve – Simple Tips To Unlock Your Potential">Read More</a></p>
<p>The post <a href="/beginners-serve-vs-advanced-tennis-serve-what-are-the-differences/">Beginner Serve Vs. Advanced Tennis Serve – Simple Tips To Unlock Your Potential</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/checklist.jpg"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignright wp-image-629 size-full" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/checklist.jpg" alt="" width="400" height="688" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/checklist.jpg 400w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/checklist-174x300.jpg 174w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" /></a></p>
<p>In the world of tennis, there are two types of serves: the beginner serve and the advanced serve. The beginner’s serve is often referred to as the “waiter’s tray serve” or just the &#8220;waiter&#8217;s serve&#8221;. The advanced serve is the technique used by ALL professional tennis players. Which one do you have? After reading this post, you’ll have a very clear answer to that question.</p>
<p><strong>I’ve isolated six major elements that you can use to distinguish the beginner serve from an advanced serve: grip, body orientation to the court, racket drop, coming up with the racket flat or on edge, pronation, and jump. </strong></p>
<p><strong>We’ll look at these six categories and explore how they’re different in the two serves. If you have a waiter’s serve, don’t despair. You can still play tennis and serve quite effectively at the club level. At the same time, if you’re willing to make changes, you absolutely can develop an advanced serve. By knowing the differences, you’ll be able to start making those changes. </strong></p>
<p>This post is not a guide on exactly how to serve, but rather on the various options you have, and why some are better than others. I have videos on my youtube channel that take these points and show clearly how to put them into practice. Perhaps one of the easiest ways to learn the advanced serve is with the<a href="/10-common-second-serve-issues-and-how-to-fix-them/"> ServeMaster tennis training aid by Lisa Dodson.</a> It’s great for changing a beginner’s serve to an advanced one or teaching a new player the correct way to serve. If you currently have a beginner’s serve, it’s important to know the differences between it and an advanced serve. So without further delay, let’s get right into it.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Know Your Tennis Grip</h2>
<p>A rackets handle is shaped like an octagon and so has 8 faces around which your fingers find their grip. To describe the various tennis grips we begin by noting how your hand fits around the tennis racket handle and exactly which face you wrap your index finger around.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>The proper tennis grip for an advanced serve is the <strong>continental grip</strong>. The continental grip is a very natural grip, similar to how you hold a hammer. It has the position of the racket nearly perpendicular to the ground. Typically, the index knuckle is going to be on the second face with the heel pad on the bottom face. There is very little deviation in this grip for all advanced serves, as it allows for pronation (more on this below) and different types of spins.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div id="attachment_617" style="width: 404px" class="wp-caption alignleft"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-617" class="wp-image-617 size-full" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/RacketEndCapFaces.jpg" alt="Tennis racket end used to find grip." width="394" height="400" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/RacketEndCapFaces.jpg 394w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/RacketEndCapFaces-296x300.jpg 296w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 394px) 100vw, 394px" /><p id="caption-attachment-617" class="wp-caption-text">Tennis racket end cap.</p></div>
<p>The beginner&#8217;s serve utilizes what is called an &#8220;eastern forehand grip&#8221;. This grip rotates the hand around the racket so that the index knuckle grips around face three. Instead of the racket being perpendicular to the ground, the strings of the racket are directly facing the ground. This means there’s almost a 90-degree difference in the racket face in the two serve grips.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>The eastern forehand grip allows the beginner to keep the strings aligned with the ball all the way through the serve. This is the most logical way to hit a tennis ball. If you handed a racket to someone who never played tennis before, this is likely the grip they would use to hit the ball. The drawback of this grip is it does not allow for pronation and much variety of spin. The ball can only ever be hit “flat” with hardly any side or forward spin. However, I have seen club players use the eastern forehand grip to hit backspin on their serves, which I do not recommend.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>To develop an advanced serve, you absolutely MUST use the continental grip. That’s the first step. Doing so will open the floodgates to better tennis. Not only will you serve better, you’ll hammer out more effective overheads. If you have a beginner’s serve and change to the continental grip, at first you’re very likely to hit the ball off the court. This is because the extreme change in the racket face will cause you to hit the ball almost on the side of the racket. This is only an issue if you do not correct the other elements of the serve.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-92" style="margin-bottom: 0px; padding-bottom: 0px;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/practice-tips220x40.png" alt="" width="220" height="40" /></p>
<blockquote><p>Learn to use the <strong>continental grip</strong> in your server for much better ball control, power and spin.</p></blockquote>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Body Orientation To The Court</h2>

<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0089.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="400" height="400" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0089.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="Beginner stance." srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0089.jpg 400w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0089-150x150.jpg 150w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0089-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" /></a>
<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0087.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="400" height="400" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0087.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="Advanced stance." srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0087.jpg 400w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0087-150x150.jpg 150w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0087-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" /></a>

<p>Almost all beginners orient their body directly to the net post. This means their chest is facing the net. Again, they do this because it’s the most logical way to serve a tennis ball. There’s no easier way to hit than to align your body and racket face directly to the ball. That’s the way all kids and beginners hit until they properly learn to serve. The main drawback is it does not allow for maximum power, as there is no body torque.</p>
<p>In contrast, advanced tennis serves require you to face your body away from the court. Most professionals will angle their bodies at least 90 degrees from the net. Some players, like Pete Sampras and John McEnroe, will go well beyond 90 degrees. They’re almost at 150 degrees! This creates an excessive amount of body torque, which translates into serve power. When advanced players serve, their opponents can basically see their backs – if only for a second.</p>
<p>If a beginner player uses the eastern forehand grip (and they almost all do), he or she cannot orient away from the court. This type of player must face the court to hit with the eastern grip. Almost the same can be said for an advanced player. Almost no player using a continental grip can face the court and serve. It would feel very uncomfortable and limited on power.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-92" style="margin-bottom: 0px; padding-bottom: 0px;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/practice-tips220x40.png" alt="" width="220" height="40" /></p>
<blockquote><p>Face your body <strong>away from the net</strong> to effectively use the continental grip in your serve.</p></blockquote>
<p>As we now see, grip determines body orientation to the court. The serve can be compared to a chain. If the first link is broken, the rest of the chain will be compromised. An advanced serve starts with the proper grip (continental) and body orientation (away from the court). Once we have these first two steps down, which anyone can do, we can look at the third element.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Racket Drop</h2>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-1199 size-full" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0108.jpg" alt="Racket drop." width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0108.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0108-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0108-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p>The racket drop occurs after hitting the “trophy pose” during the serve. What I’m about to describe are the mechanics for the advanced serve. For righthanded players, the arm will move from right-to-left behind the player’s head and the opposite holds true for lefties.</p>
<p>As the arm moves to the left of the player’s head, the elbow will be high (shoulder level or higher) and the racket will invert so that the butt, or very bottom of the racket, faces the sky. This all happens very quickly but once the racket is fully inverted, it’s known as the <strong>racket drop position</strong>.</p>
<p>The deeper the racket drop, the more power one will achieve in the serve. If you look at any professional player, you’ll see deep racket drops. This allows for the racket to travel a longer path before striking the ball. Why is this important? It’s because the racket head can build up maximum momentum and speed before impacting the ball.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>In contrast, the beginner’s serve has a very slight racket drop or sometimes none at all. This results in much less power on the serve. Simply put, the grip and body orientation of the beginner serve doesn’t allow a proper racket drop to occur.</p>
<p>Throughout this article, I’ve been fairly simple in my use of tennis jargon. I like to take complex ideas and make them simple to understand. But I’m going to get a little technical here and mention wrist mechanics because I think it’s important to point out.</p>
<p>An advanced serve utilizes the wrist movement of radial flexion and ulnar flexion on the racket drop and swing up to contact. The beginner serve, however, uses hyperextension and flexion (with the wrist) on the same parts of the serve swing. This not nearly as effective as radial and ulnar flexion.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-92" style="margin-bottom: 0px; padding-bottom: 0px;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/practice-tips220x40.png" alt="" width="220" height="40" /></p>
<blockquote><p>Learn to use a deep <strong>racket drop</strong> to greatly increase power on your serves.</p></blockquote>
<p>In summary, if we can use the continental grip, orient away from the court and make a deep racket drop, we are well on our way to hitting an advanced tennis serve. As we can see, there is a marked difference between each element so far. Now we get into the swing-up-to-contact part of the serve.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="kad-youtube-shortcode videofit"  ><iframe loading="lazy" width="600" height="400" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/hMR18Pp-qrM?autoplay=0&controls=1&fs=1&modestbranding=1&theme=dark&rel=0&loop=0&showinfo=1" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="true"></iframe></div>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Racket Face Position – Flat vs On Edge</h2>

<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0098.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="400" height="400" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0098.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="Racket flat." srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0098.jpg 400w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0098-150x150.jpg 150w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0098-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" /></a>
<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0101.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="400" height="400" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0101.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="Racket on edge." srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0101.jpg 400w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0101-150x150.jpg 150w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0101-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" /></a>

<p>An advanced serve will have a deep racket drop so that the racket is inverted (butt cap to the sky) before it begins its swing path to the ball. Once the swing path initiates, the racket will move, or lead, to the ball with the racket edge facing first. To anybody watching, it looks like the server is trying to hit the ball with the side of his or her racket. This is very evident when we see the advanced serve in slow motion.</p>
<p>When the advanced server begins the forward swing to the ball, the palm of the hand will be facing in the opposite direction. For example, a righty’s palm will face to the left when swinging up. This causes the racket to lead on edge with the racket face perpendicular to the ground for some time.</p>
<p>In contrast, the beginner initiates the swing with his palm facing upward. This places the racket in the “waiter’s serve” position with the racket face parallel to the ground, like a waiter holding a tray. Again, this occurs because it is much easier to hit a ball square on by aligning the strings to the ball long before contact.</p>
<p>When the two serves are shown side-by-side in slow motion video, the differences become very obvious. I should point out that even players using an advanced serve can have difficulty with racket position on the serve. It is not uncommon for someone to use the continental grip, orient away from the ball and have a decent racket drop but still swing the racket straight on with no rotation, and all their hard work still leaves them with a waiter’s tray serve. This happens to players trying to use an advanced serve because they don’t trust the process of pronation.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-92" style="margin-bottom: 0px; padding-bottom: 0px;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/practice-tips220x40.png" alt="" width="220" height="40" /></p>
<blockquote><p>Imagine hitting the ball <strong>with the racket edge</strong>. Combine this with the next step, pronation, to develop a complete and powerful serve.</p></blockquote>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Pronation</h2>

<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0019.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="450" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0019.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="Supination" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0019.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0019-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0019-768x432.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0019-560x315.jpg 560w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0019-732x412.jpg 732w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0019-366x206.jpg 366w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></a>
<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0020.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="450" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0020.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="Pronation" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0020.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0020-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0020-768x432.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0020-560x315.jpg 560w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0020-732x412.jpg 732w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0020-366x206.jpg 366w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></a>

<p>You’ve probably heard coaches and players telling you to “snap the wrist” for more spin and power on your serve but they don’t explain what it means in detail.  You are left wondering and you try to “snap your wrist” on your serve. But after doing so a few times, it hurts your wrist and doesn’t work. You then give up, mystified at the wrist snap and never understanding how pronation plays a part in the serve.</p>
<p>It took me months of study before I finally realized how advanced players are getting so much racket head speed in their serves. I’ll reveal the secret now:<strong> it’s a combination of radial and ulnar flexion with pronation.</strong></p>
<p>Still a mystery? Well don&#8217;t worry, you don&#8217;t need to be a doctor or a Latin scholar to master the tennis serve.</p>
<p>Basically, this just describes specific arm movements that you can use to generate that extra racket speed that is impossible to manufacture by swinging the arm from the shoulder alone. The arm is basically acting like a whip, and the wrist holding the racket finishes the job.</p>
<p>Now that we know that, we can move on to defining pronation, and along with it, supination. Here’s one of the clearest definitions I found on google:</p>
<blockquote><p>Pronation and supination are a pair of unique movements possible only in the forearm and hands, allowing the human body to flip the palm either face up or face down.</p></blockquote>
<p>So &#8220;twisting&#8221; seems like a more accessible word to use, right? Pronate by twisting a right arm counterclockwise, supinate by twisting clockwise.</p>
<p>To give you an easy visual, do the following easy exercise. Put your dominant arm straight out in front (not to the side) of you around shoulder level. Your palm should face up to the sky. Now turn your hand down so your palm is facing the floor. This rolling motion is called &#8220;pronation&#8221;. Rolling the hand back to the palm up position is called &#8220;supination&#8221;.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>All advanced serves are using pronation while striking the ball. But it’s occurring while the arm is extending upwards toward the ball. This allows the racket to move in a second dimension when contacting the ball. The racket is moving towards the ball from one angle (first dimension) and the face is rotating in another (second dimension). This speeds up the racket head and causes a stronger impact resulting in more spin and power.</p>
<p>In contrast, the beginner serve has zero pronation. The only wrist movement that can occur with a beginner serve is hyperextension and flexion, which again, is not good for the wrist. This is the main reason a lot of players with beginner serves hurt their wrist.</p>
<p>Since I moved to Florida almost 12 years ago, I’ve been playing an average of 2-3 hours per day. Some days I play 5-6 hours. Not once have I sustained a tennis related injury.</p>
<p>Good form begets an injury-free tennis life. There is no reason you should ever suffer injuries from the movement of your body if your form is ideal.</p>
<p>If you use a beginner serve, pronation is simply impossible. The player with the beginner serve cannot align their strings in the direction of the ball while simultaneously pronating. Pronation is only possible by approaching the ball with the edge of the racket. If a beginner player thinks he can snap his wrist with hyperextension and flexion, he is headed down a bad road. That limited movement can lead to injury and will never match the speed and efficiency of pronation.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-92" style="margin-bottom: 0px; padding-bottom: 0px;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/practice-tips220x40.png" alt="" width="220" height="40" /></p>
<blockquote><p><strong>Pronate</strong>, or twist, the racket face as it moves to contact the ball.</p></blockquote>
<p>Up to this point, we’ve discussed five components of the serve. Let’s look at the last one, which is the jump.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>The Jump</h2>
<p>The jump typically occurs in advanced serves and rarely in beginner serves. It’s the final part of the serve, where the server jumps for height and lands on the leg opposite his dominant arm. For example, a right-handed player will jump onto his left leg and the opposite is true of a lefty. Beginner serves usually have no jump, or at best, one foot stays on the ground and one shifts forward.</p>
<p>If an advanced server utilizes all five components, the end result is the jump. It’s produced by the forward and upward momentum of the stroke. This advanced serve has an explosive element that a beginner’s serve completely lacks. That explosive element naturally produces a motion that moves the player off the ground. Almost all good advanced servers will land on one foot inside the baseline from this jump.</p>
<p>You may not have ever realized this to be true. But look at the best servers in the game – or any professional players on TV. Notice how they all land on one foot inside the court, with their momentum going forward. However, when you watch a beginner’s serve, it looks like they start and finish their serve in the same spot. The forward movement of the body adds power to the serve, which makes advanced serves so difficult to return.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-92" style="margin-bottom: 0px; padding-bottom: 0px;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/practice-tips220x40.png" alt="" width="220" height="40" /></p>
<blockquote><p><strong>Jump into your serve</strong> for explosive power.</p></blockquote>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Summing It All Up</h2>
<p>If you’ve made it this far, you can see there are huge differences in the technicalities of a beginner serve and an advanced one. Truly, an advanced serve takes a long time to master. Most players using an advanced serve today started off learning it as children. If taught early and correctly, the advanced serve feels completely natural for the trained player later in life.</p>
<p>On the other hand, if you’ve been playing with a beginner’s serve your whole life and want to transition to the advanced serve, it’s going to take a lot of work. I’m not going to lie. I’ve worked with older players who have either complete beginner serves or many aspects of a beginner’s serve. It’s nearly impossible to change their muscle memory without doing thousands of reps of ingraining the new swing. Usually, though, older players don’t want to put in that time and effort. As a result, we work on improving their beginner or waiter’s serve.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>If you are absolutely intent on learning the advanced serve, whether you currently use a beginner’s serve or are new to tennis, it’s completely possible to learn, especially with the advanced tools available today. I think the ServeMaster is a great tool for learning the advanced serve. It will teach you to hold the correct grip, show you how to transition into a good racket drop and pronate. It does this for you naturally, without you having to think about it.</p>
<p>Once you feel comfortable with the Servemaster, you can replicate the swing with a racket. It should drastically improve your overall serve motion. In the future, I plan to make a long blog and video series on how to learn the advanced serve – so stay tuned. Thanks for reading and leave me a comment below if you have any questions.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>The post <a href="/beginners-serve-vs-advanced-tennis-serve-what-are-the-differences/">Beginner Serve Vs. Advanced Tennis Serve – Simple Tips To Unlock Your Potential</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/beginners-serve-vs-advanced-tennis-serve-what-are-the-differences/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>5</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>10 Fun Tennis Drills You Can Practice Without A Court</title>
		<link>/10-tennis-drills-you-can-practice-without-a-court/</link>
					<comments>/10-tennis-drills-you-can-practice-without-a-court/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chad Walner]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 01 Oct 2018 12:01:57 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Training]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=585</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Consistently practicing your tennis strokes on a court is easily the best way to improve your tennis game. However, getting to a court can be a challenge for some people. Perhaps you don’t have the time, a willing partner to &#8230; <a class="kt-excerpt-readmore" href="/10-tennis-drills-you-can-practice-without-a-court/" aria-label="10 Fun Tennis Drills You Can Practice Without A Court">Read More</a></p>
<p>The post <a href="/10-tennis-drills-you-can-practice-without-a-court/">10 Fun Tennis Drills You Can Practice Without A Court</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Consistently practicing your tennis strokes on a court is easily the best way to improve your tennis game. However, getting to a court can be a challenge for some people. Perhaps you don’t have the time, a willing partner to hit with, or it’s the winter months and conditions are not amenable.</p>
<p>Maybe you just want to practice tennis alone?</p>
<p>What then?</p>
<p><strong>You can still practice your tennis game alone at home, in your garage, at a gym or even your backyard. You don’t need a partner and you don’t need a court. In this post, I’m going to reveal my top 10 tennis drills you can perform without a court. Many of them are tennis drills you can do by yourself, while some make use of an off-court partner. </strong></p>
<p>Most are indoor tennis drills, so you can do them even when the weather isn&#8217;t cooperating. These drills will help improve your game so when you step on a court, you’ll perform noticeably better.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="#serve-pronation">Work on Serve Pronation</a></li>
<li><a href="#serve-toss">Practice your Serve Toss</a></li>
<li><a href="#racket-drop">Enhance your Racket Drop</a></li>
<li><a href="#bouncing-ball">Practice ball/racket Coordination</a></li>
<li><a href="#volley-to-volley">Do the Volley-To-Volley Drill</a></li>
<li><a href="#shadow-swing">Do some Shadow Swings</a></li>
<li><a href="#footwork-overhead">Work on your Overheads</a></li>
<li><a href="#pivot-rotation">Practice Pivot and Rotation</a></li>
<li><a href="#five-volley">Review the Volley Types</a></li>
<li><a href="#footwork-game">Practice Footwork</a></li>
<li><a href="#off-the-wall">Hit Solo (Off the Wall)</a></li>
</ul>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>I’ll go over each drill one-at-a-time so you understand how to do it and what the particular benefits can be. I guarantee if you spend even 10 minutes per day practicing them, you’ll see a marked improvement in your tennis game. For most of these drills, all you need is a racket and a ball. So without further ado, let’s get started!</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="serve-pronation"></a></p>
<h2>#1 – The Serve Pronation Drill</h2>
</div>
<p>This is an excellent drill for building up the forearm muscles and practicing pronation.</p>

<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0019.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="450" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0019.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="Supination" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0019.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0019-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0019-768x432.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0019-560x315.jpg 560w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0019-732x412.jpg 732w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0019-366x206.jpg 366w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></a>
<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0020.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="450" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0020.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="Pronation" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0020.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0020-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0020-768x432.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0020-560x315.jpg 560w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0020-732x412.jpg 732w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0020-366x206.jpg 366w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></a>

<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-92" style="margin-bottom: 0px; padding-bottom: 0px;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/requirements220x40.png" alt="" width="220" height="40" /></p>
<blockquote><p>All it requires is a racket and very little room, just a few feet of space.</p></blockquote>
<p>Here’s how to do it.</p>
<ol>
<li>Hold your racket in your hitting arm. Your arm should be straight out in from of you with your palm facing up. This is called supination</li>
<li>Simply turn your hand upside down. This will cause the racket to flip from right to left for right-handed players. This is called pronation.</li>
<li>Continue alternating between supination and pronation until your forearm tires.</li>
</ol>
<p>Start with 10 reps and build up to at least 25 without stopping. You can add a racket weight for increased resistance. This is a great exercise to do in the morning and evening – or any free time you have.<br />
<img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-92" style="margin-bottom: 0px; padding-bottom: 0px;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/benefits220x40.png" alt="" width="220" height="40" /></p>
<blockquote><p>You’ll see the improved benefit in your serves and overheads. The tennis serve pronation drill is one drill you’ll want to continually do. It’s easy to do for children as well.</p></blockquote>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="serve-toss"></a></p>
<h2>#2 – The Serve Toss Drill</h2>
</div>
<p>Most club players have trouble with their serve toss. So why not practice it away from the court? If you have high ceilings, you can do this drill inside, otherwise it can be done almost anywhere outside.<br />
<img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-92" style="margin-bottom: 0px; padding-bottom: 0px;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/requirements220x40.png" alt="" width="220" height="40" /></p>
<blockquote><p>It requires just one tennis ball. You can choose to hold your racket in your dominant hand if you want – but it’s not necessary.</p></blockquote>
<ol>
<li>Get into your normal serve stance.</li>
<li>Toss the ball in the air with your non-dominant hand as if you were going to serve.</li>
<li>After the ball leaves your hand, keep your arm in the air and try to catch the ball with your arm still extended (resist the temptation to turn your hand to catch the ball. Your palm should remain facing your direction).</li>
</ol>
<p>Do at least 20 tosses per session. Since this is not a strenuous exercise, you could even do 50 tosses in one session and do them twice per day. Imagine how much better your toss would be after one week or one month?<br />
<img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-92" style="margin-bottom: 0px; padding-bottom: 0px;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/benefits220x40.png" alt="" width="220" height="40" /></p>
<blockquote><p>A much-improved serve toss that is more accurate and reliable. As a result, you’ll have a much-improved serve.</p></blockquote>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="racket-drop"></a></p>
<h2>#3 – The Racket Drop Drill</h2>
</div>
<p>Around half the club players I see do not have racket drops on their serve. The racket drop is the part of the serve where the racket is completely inverted in what some people think of as the “scratch your back position”.</p>
<p>It’s very important to achieve this position to generate momentum on your swing and pace on the serve. Many people struggle with this part of the serve, as did I early in my playing days. This is one of the many great tennis drills to do alone and is fantastic at correcting that issue. Here’s how to do it.<br />
<img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-92" style="margin-bottom: 0px; padding-bottom: 0px;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/requirements220x40.png" alt="" width="220" height="40" /></p>
<blockquote><p>Your tennis racket.</p></blockquote>
<ol>
<li>Stand in your normal serve stance with your racket in hand and hold the continental grip.</li>
<li>Raise your hitting arm to your side with elbow bent. Your racket should flair out to your right (if a righty) and vice versa for lefties.</li>
<li>Move your hand and racket upwards by bending your elbow joint. The racket will then move behind your head.</li>
<li>Move your elbow higher up and use radial deviation to allow a full racket drop. For the sake of this exercise, allow the edge of the racket to touch your back. Your racket should be completely inverted at this point.</li>
<li>Begin to raise the racket upward by straightening your elbow joint. It’s key here to bring the racket up on edge.</li>
<li>Just before the racket is fully extended pronate so that the strings face the ball. Your torso should be slightly to the side. Once contact with the ball is achieved (there is no contact in this drill, you’re just visualizing it) continue pronating until your palm or the hitting side of the racket is facing away from you. You can stop there or continue the serve motion, following through at your side.</li>
</ol>
<p>This drill really helped me overcome my shallow racket drop. For those people with a “waiter’s” serve who want to transition to advanced serve, this drill will be indispensable to you.</p>
<p>I would suggest doing as many reps as you want, morning and evening. You can also do this as a warm-up on the court when you do get to play. Even now, I’ll do 25-50 reps at a time while watching tennis on TV (I have high ceilings), just to keep my motion sharp.<br />
<img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-92" style="margin-bottom: 0px; padding-bottom: 0px;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/benefits220x40.png" alt="" width="220" height="40" /></p>
<blockquote><p>Will help players with a waiter’s serve develop an advanced serve. Will help people with a shallow racket drop to develop a deep one. Will add mph to your serve speed and with less effort.</p></blockquote>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="bouncing-ball"></a></p>
<h2>#4 &#8211; The Bouncing Ball Racket Drill</h2>
</div>
<p>This is one of the oldest solo tennis drills but it still works great – especially for kids developing their game. It’s a little challenging at first but can be mastered in a short time.</p>

<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0075bouncebackhand.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="450" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0075bouncebackhand.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="Backhand bounce." srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0075bouncebackhand.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0075bouncebackhand-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0075bouncebackhand-768x432.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0075bouncebackhand-732x412.jpg 732w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0075bouncebackhand-366x206.jpg 366w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0075bouncebackhand-560x315.jpg 560w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></a>
<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0075bounceforehand.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="450" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0075bounceforehand.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="Forehand bounce." srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0075bounceforehand.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0075bounceforehand-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0075bounceforehand-768x432.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0075bounceforehand-732x412.jpg 732w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0075bounceforehand-366x206.jpg 366w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0075bounceforehand-560x315.jpg 560w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></a>

<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-92" style="margin-bottom: 0px; padding-bottom: 0px;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/requirements220x40.png" alt="" width="220" height="40" /></p>
<blockquote><p>A racket and tennis ball. It can be done indoors or outside.</p></blockquote>
<ol>
<li>Hold your racket, palm up, in front of you. The hitting side of the racket strings should be facing skywards. Bounce a ball off the strings as many times as possible without stopping. I consider this the forehand side.</li>
<li>Pronate your hand so that your palm is now facing down. I consider this the backhand side. Now to try to do the same, bouncing the ball of this side of the racket strings as many times as possible.</li>
<li>Once you master the forehand and backhand side, alternate between each one as the ball is in mid-air. Do as many as possible without stopping. For a little additional challenge see if you can also add in hitting the ball with the edge of the racket a la Roger Federer.</li>
</ol>
<p>Some children may find this drill difficult. In that case, you can have them do one hit, bounce the ball off the floor and then bounce it off their rackets again. They can keep repeating until they master this. Then they can try the regular drill again. Most kids master this drill after doing it several times. This drill is good for adults too and I still do it.<br />
<img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-92" style="margin-bottom: 0px; padding-bottom: 0px;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/benefits220x40.png" alt="" width="220" height="40" /></p>
<blockquote><p>Increases hand-eye coordination and builds up the forearm muscles. Also increases ball sensitivity on the racket and will improve feel on the volleys.</p></blockquote>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="volley-to-volley"></a></p>
<h2>#5 – Volley-To-Volley Drill</h2>
</div>
<p>This is perhaps my all-time favorite drill. It improves your volleys and reflexes like no other drill.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-1474 size-full" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/Volley20-2.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/Volley20-2.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/Volley20-2-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/Volley20-2-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-92" style="margin-bottom: 0px; padding-bottom: 0px;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/requirements220x40.png" alt="" width="220" height="40" /></p>
<blockquote><p>For this drill, you’ll need two people, each with a racket, and one tennis ball.</p></blockquote>
<p>Unless you have a huge indoor space, you’ll want to do this drill outside. Doing it on smooth pavement is the easiest. Make sure to use the continental grip.</p>
<ol>
<li>Stand about 15-18 feet apart, facing each other.</li>
<li>Volley the ball to each other. Try to take the ball out of the air. If the ball hits the ground just half volley it and continue on.</li>
<li>As you both build up feel, you can increase the pace or hit different spots. For example, do forehand volley to forehand volley. Or try going backhand-to-backhand.</li>
<li>Try to keep the ball going as long as possible. If you get to the point of being super-advanced with this drill, you can alternate moving side-to-side while volleying.</li>
</ol>
<p>You can also make this drill a game. If you miss the volley you lose the point. Play games up to 11. This is also a wonderful game to do on court. If you want to know the specifics of that game, we discuss it in <a href="/the-nine-best-tennis-drills-for-improving-the-serve-and-volley/#volley-to-volley">this post on volley drills</a>.  Advanced children can also play this game. It may benefit them to you do it with an orange or green ball, making the drill easier. Practice this drill 5-10 minutes at a time or even more.<br />
<img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-92" style="margin-bottom: 0px; padding-bottom: 0px;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/benefits220x40.png" alt="" width="220" height="40" /></p>
<blockquote><p>Improves volley technique and hand-eye coordination. If this drill is practiced consistently, it increases reflexes quite noticeably.</p></blockquote>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="shadow-swing"></a></p>
<h2>#6 &#8211; Shadow Swing Drills</h2>
</div>
<p>When you can’t play tennis, doing shadow swings of your forehand and backhand can keep your form sharp and even improve it. This means your simply swinging the tennis racket with no ball.<br />
<img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-92" style="margin-bottom: 0px; padding-bottom: 0px;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/requirements220x40.png" alt="" width="220" height="40" /></p>
<blockquote><p>You can do these by yourself with only a racket. If you don’t have a racket, you can still perform them but it won’t be as effective.</p></blockquote>
<p>I’m a stickler for perfection on my strokes. I want my form to be efficient, effective and look great. By practicing shadow swings over and over, I can ingrain good habits and movements that are impossible when hitting a tennis ball. With shadow swings, I can slow my swing down, stop at any point to check form and even hold certain positions (like the power position) to impress it into my muscle memory.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>One caveat though. If you do not have good technique to begin with, shadow swings may not help you. You’ll just be reinforcing the same poor technique. In this case, I advise you to get a coach who can show you good form, copy your favorite pro player’s form, or watch a video tutorial on how to hit proper groundstrokes. I have a few helpful groundstroke videos on my youtube channel. Once your form is good, you can shadow stroke.</p>
<p>You can do this exercise at home, but just make sure you have enough space. I once broke a lamp doing a forehand shadow stroke! I really like to do these in front of the TV when watching tennis. You can do them morning and night.</p>
<ol>
<li>From the ready position, start shadow stroking your forehand. Do at least 50 complete swings. You can swing slowly at first to make sure your form is grooved. Then gradually speed up the swing. You can use a racket weight to increase resistance.</li>
<li>Next shadow stroke the backhand for at least 50 reps in the same way.</li>
<li>Practice swinging for low shots, medium height shots and high shots.</li>
<li>Make sure your feet are rotating. You can rotate off the front foot, back foot, both feet, or do jumping groundstrokes (for advanced players).</li>
<li>You can also experiment with open stances, closed stances and neutral stances.</li>
<li>I also like to shadow stroke my backhand slice. I suggest you throw in 50 reps of this stroke as well. Swing at different heights: low, medium height and near your head.</li>
<li>If you have a lot of room, like a big garage or a studio, you can incorporate side-to-side movement with your shadow swings and even move back and forwards. Pretend you are playing points.</li>
</ol>
<p>For the best result, do at least 50 reps on the forehand, backhand and slice each morning (150 total reps). In the evening you can do repeat this. To really supercharge this drill, record yourself swinging, make improvements and then take video again and compare.<br />
<img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-92" style="margin-bottom: 0px; padding-bottom: 0px;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/benefits220x40.png" alt="" width="220" height="40" /></p>
<blockquote><p>Improves your forehand and backhand form and groundstrokes. If you shadow stoke with a racket weight, you’ll be able to generate more racket speed, giving you more spin and pace on your shots. If you incorporate movement in the shadow swings, you’ll have better footwork on court.</p></blockquote>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="footwork-overhead"></a></p>
<h2>#7 – Footwork and Shadow Stroke For Overhead Drill</h2>
</div>
<p>How many times have you walked backward to hit an overhead? And how many times did you miss easy overheads that ended up costing you the game and even the match? If the answer is “too many” then this is the drill you can’t live without. I’ve seen substantial improvements in my overheads with five minutes of practice in the morning and evening.</p>
<p>Most club players lack good footwork on their overheads. Their swing path, timing and weight transfer are also incorrect. The purpose of this drill is to permanently etch good form in your muscle memory. By doing so, the overhead will become a shot you’ll actually want to hit.<br />
<img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-92" style="margin-bottom: 0px; padding-bottom: 0px;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/requirements220x40.png" alt="" width="220" height="40" /></p>
<blockquote><p>Only your racket is necessary &#8212; and you can even do without it in a pinch.</p></blockquote>
<ol>
<li>Start in the ready position with a continental grip and turn to your dominant side.</li>
<li>Get your racket up in the power position and put your non-dominant hand up towards the sky. The non-dominant hand serves as a guide to hit the ball and helps achieve balance.</li>
<li>To hit good overheads we need to practice turning to the side and covering distance with cross-over steps &#8211; rather than walking or running backwards. At this point, you will begin taking crossover steps and go back about 3-5 steps (depending on the amount of room you have).</li>
<li>When you stop and set up for the overhead (try to envision it), make sure your weight is on the back foot. Then initiate the swing with a racket drop and pronation, transferring your weight to the front foot.</li>
<li>Complete the swing and then get back to the ready position. Wasting no time, move forward to the same spot you started in. By doing so, you train yourself to quickly return to the correct position and advance forward.</li>
</ol>
<p>This is by far the best drill you can use to improve your overheads. Practice it often but make sure your form is tight. Start off with 20 reps and increase to 50 over time. I would suggest doing 50 reps every day or every other day for two weeks. Then do it on a real court with actual overheads in practice until you are hitting the best overheads of your life.<br />
<img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-92" style="margin-bottom: 0px; padding-bottom: 0px;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/benefits220x40.png" alt="" width="220" height="40" /></p>
<blockquote><p>Improved footwork, especially at the net. You’ll also see a dramatic improvement in the pace and consistency of your overheads.</p></blockquote>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="pivot-rotation"></a></p>
<h2>#8 – Pivot And Rotation Drills</h2>
</div>
<p>If you watch professional players closely during a match, you’ll see they all pivot on their feet and rotate their bodies. They’re doing it nearly every shot to maximize power. However, most club players don’t pivot and rotate, or they don’t do it enough.<br />
<img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-92" style="margin-bottom: 0px; padding-bottom: 0px;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/requirements220x40.png" alt="" width="220" height="40" /></p>
<blockquote><p>Only your racket is needed. If you have no racket available, you can still mimic the movement in this drill.</p></blockquote>
<p>The pivot of the feet and rotation of the body are large factors in hitting fast, heavy groundstrokes. The discovery of this fact made a huge difference in my game. Once I began focusing on it, my groundstrokes really improved, especially when moving out wide. And that’s why I bring attention to it here. Trust me, if you want more power on your groundstrokes, few other drills compare!</p>
<p>When playing there are four ways we can cause body rotation. I want to mention them first, so you understand the action steps in the drill.</p>
<ul>
<li>Rotate on the front foot (back foot is off the ground)</li>
<li>Rotate on back foot (front foot is off the ground)</li>
<li>Rotate on two feet (both feet are on the ground)</li>
<li>Jumping forehand or backhand (both feet are off the ground)</li>
</ul>
<p>If you watch a professional tennis match, you’ll see the pros using all these rotations throughout the match. For them, it’s subconscious. They use the one that makes the most sense in the moment. But for us, especially if we have never thought about rotation, we need to practice it. Here are the action drills for pivot and rotation.</p>
<ol>
<li>Do shadow swings hitting only on the front foot – both forehand and backhand. You should be on the ball of your front foot, which acts as the pivot. Allow your body to swing around. The pivot and rotation occurs just before you would make contact with the ball.</li>
<li>Shadow swing on the forehand and backhand side but use your back foot as the pivot now. The front foot should be completely off the ground.</li>
<li>Shadow swing on the forehand and backhand side in an open stance and allow both feet to act as the pivot. The two-foot pivot can only work in an open stance.</li>
<li>The jumping forehand and backhand are more advanced shots, so practice them if you have no joint problems or physical limitations. Do shadow swings with both feet off the ground. Remember that your torso needs to rotate in the air.</li>
</ol>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>I would suggest starting off with doing 20 reps of each rotation (10 forehand and 10 backhand). That would give you 80 reps in all. You can practice these once per day or once every other day. Trust me, they are going to be very helpful to you in generating a lot more pace on your groundstrokes. You can use the backfoot pivot very well when going out wide to hit a forehand. And you can use the front foot pivot on most of your backhands – especially two-handed backhands.<br />
<img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-92" style="margin-bottom: 0px; padding-bottom: 0px;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/benefits220x40.png" alt="" width="220" height="40" /></p>
<blockquote><p>Improves both forehand and backhand groundstrokes by allowing for a lot more power. Also helps to improve footwork on the court and makes groundstrokes more efficient.</p></blockquote>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="five-volley"></a></p>
<h2>#9 – Five Volley Types Drill</h2>
</div>
<p>In this exercise, you’ll be practicing the five different volley types (we&#8217;ll leave out the combo types of swinging volley and overhead). It’s a very simple drill but will really aid your volley form on the court. It will also help you understand the five different volleys you can use at the net. If you don’t know what they are, I’ve listed them below with basic definitions.  You can check each one out in detail <a href="/seven-volley-types-you-must-know-to-master-your-net-game/">here</a>.</p>
<ul>
<li>Block Volley – As the name implies, you’re literally blocking the ball with your racket. There is no movement of the racket.</li>
<li>Punch Volley – This is like a block volley, but you move the racket slightly forward and down to give it a bit more zip.</li>
<li>Drive Volley – This is the longest swing path of the five volleys listed here. You can take the racket back just a little further, follow through a little more, plus step into the ball.</li>
<li>Drop Volley – A volley where you “drop” the ball lightly over the net so your opponent cannot get to it. It’s like a block volley but with a lot more give in the racket head.</li>
<li>Half Volley – Volleys that occur after the ball hits the ground. Typically you’ll be getting down low on these.</li>
</ul>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-92" style="margin-bottom: 0px; padding-bottom: 0px;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/requirements220x40.png" alt="" width="220" height="40" /></p>
<blockquote><p>You can practice these at home with only a racket and your imagination.</p></blockquote>
<p>Now that you know the five basic volley types, we can lay out the drill. This drill may seem so easy that there’s no benefit. But don’t be fooled. This drill will really improve your volley game. I think of these as “shadow swings” but for volleys. After each rep is completed, quickly move back to the ready position and perform the next rep.</p>
<ol>
<li>Start off in the ready position. Imagine a very fast paced shot is directed to your forehand side. Use the forehand block volley to return it (in your mind). You’ll then alternate to the backhand side. The key is to make sure there is no movement of the racket on the block.</li>
<li>Begin in the ready position and do the same thing as in step one, but this time with punch volleys. Remember, the movement of the racket is slight. Try to really imagine the ball coming to you before you volley.</li>
<li>Again, start in the ready position and then practice forehand drive volley swings and backhand drive volley swings. Make sure you are not taking the racket back excessively far. You should be stepping into the ball with your opposite foot (left foot on forehand side and right foot on backhand side).</li>
<li>Start in the ready position. Pretend a ball is hit directly to your forehand. You’re going to block volley the ball but with a loose wrist and angle the racket up slightly to hit a drop volley. Imagine the ball pushing your racket back. Do backhand drop volleys as well.</li>
<li>Assume the ready position. Imagine a shot is hit to you that bounces in front – called a half volley. For this exercise, you’ll need to really bend down (like doing lunges) to volley the ball. I think of the half-volley as lunges with a racket in my hand while doing a block volley. Perform forehands and backhands.</li>
</ol>
<p>Since these drills are not strenuous, there’s no rep limit. I would say 20 reps of each volley is the minimum you’ll want to do (10 on the forehand side and 10 on the backhand side). That would have you doing 100 total reps for all five volley types.</p>
<p>The key on this drill is to use your imagination and use good form. If you practice these every day for a week and then come to net, you’ll see a very noticeable difference in your volleys.<br />
<img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-92" style="margin-bottom: 0px; padding-bottom: 0px;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/benefits220x40.png" alt="" width="220" height="40" /></p>
<blockquote><p>Dramatically improves forehand and backhand volleys. If you have a great imagination and can really visualize a tennis ball being hit to you, this drill can actually improve your hand-eye coordination.</p></blockquote>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="footwork-game"></a></p>
<h2>#10 – The Footwork Game</h2>
</div>
<p>I’ve given you drills for improving serve, groundstrokes, overheads and volleys. I’m leaving the last one for footwork, which is extremely important in tennis. Tennis is a movement game, and if you’re not willing to move this game is not for you. With that, I introduce one of my favorite footwork drills for children and adults.<br />
<img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-92" style="margin-bottom: 0px; padding-bottom: 0px;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/requirements220x40.png" alt="" width="220" height="40" /></p>
<blockquote><p>You’ll need two people for this drill and a tennis ball.</p></blockquote>
<p>Optimally, you’ll want to do it on a tennis court when you have court time. But this drill can be done anywhere you have about 15-20 feet of space to move. Keep in mind the exercises require catching the ball on one bounce unless stated otherwise. Use proper footwork including cross-over steps, side-steps and always return to a ready position. Here’s how it works.</p>
<p>One person will be feeding the ball. The other person will be performing the drill. The feeder will stand in one spot with the other person facing him or her (almost directly in front). The feeder will toss a tennis ball to their left side about 6-10 feet away. The performer will move to the side (their right side) and collect the ball on one bounce and then quickly return to the middle spot (from where they started). The performer gives the ball back to the feeder. The action is then repeated.</p>
<p>After tossing to the right side of the performer, the feeder will then toss to the performer’s left side and the process repeats itself. Once the feeder has tossed to both sides, here are some additional exercises you can do for this drill.</p>
<ol>
<li>The feeder can vary tosses to the forehand and backhand, making them random. You can make it a game and see how many catches the performer can make in 10 tries. Kids love games like this.</li>
<li>The feeder can stand about 8-10 feet away from the performer (but still facing each other) and toss so that the feeder must back up to catch the ball no higher than chest height. This simulates backing up to hit a groundstroke.</li>
<li>In the same position of being 8-10 feet away, the feeder can toss the ball near him or herself so the performer has to sprint in to catch the ball (on one bounce).</li>
<li>The feeder can then randomize tossing in all four directions.</li>
</ol>
<p>A game can be made from this drill in many ways. As a feeder, I like doing random tosses in all four directions to the kids I work with. You can also toss the ball high and the performer needs to catch the ball in their dominant hand held up high (like they are hitting an overhead). This is the only time they will catch the ball out of the air.</p>
<p>If you are doing this drill with kids, have them do a few reps to each side and then make a game out of the drill as I described above. For adults, it depends on their level of conditioning and physical ability. For someone young and mobile, 6-8 reps in each direction works with a 10-second rest in between directions.<br />
<img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-92" style="margin-bottom: 0px; padding-bottom: 0px;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/benefits220x40.png" alt="" width="220" height="40" /></p>
<blockquote><p>Improves footwork and quickness in all directions. Also improves conditioning.</p></blockquote>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="off-the-wall"></a></p>
<h2>#11 – Bonus Drill – Hit Off The Wall</h2>
</div>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-92" style="margin-bottom: 0px; padding-bottom: 0px;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/requirements220x40.png" alt="" width="220" height="40" /></p>
<blockquote><p>For this drill, you’ll need a wall, a racket, and a tennis ball.</p></blockquote>
<p>Simply go to a wall and practice all your strokes. Here is how I practice on the wall, which is typically a 25-minute session.</p>
<ol>
<li>5 minutes of forehand groundstrokes (topspin)</li>
<li>5 minutes of backhand groundstrokes (topspin)</li>
<li>3 minutes of forehand slice</li>
<li>3 minutes of backhand slice</li>
<li>3 minutes of serves (first and second)</li>
<li>5 minutes of volley practice</li>
</ol>
<p>I particularly love the wall for hitting volleys. Stand about 4-6 feet from the wall and practice forehand volleys first. Then do backhands. Finally, alternate between forehand and backhand volleys. I feel even a five-minute volley session on the wall improves my volley reflexes when on court.</p>
<p>When hitting groundstrokes on the wall, make sure you are using your pivot and rotations. If the ball comes off the wall too lively, use a ball that is not new or less lively.<br />
<img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-92" style="margin-bottom: 0px; padding-bottom: 0px;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/benefits220x40.png" alt="" width="220" height="40" /></p>
<blockquote><p>This will help you etch good fundamentals into your strokes and improves conditioning.</p></blockquote>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Putting It All Together</h2>
<p>I’ve given you 11 practice exercises you can do without a court. Some are easier than others. Some require two people. But there’s no excuse for at least performing the solo drills at home in your spare time.</p>
<p>The only drills that require two people are the volley-to-volley drill and the footwork game. You probably don’t have a wall at home either, but that still leaves eight drills you can practice at home or outside any time you want.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>The more you practice these drills, the better you’ll perform on court. If you can practice all the drills with the rep scheme I laid out once or twice per week, you’ll see amazing improvements in your game or that of your student or child.</p>
<p>It takes hard work to be the best. When you don’t feel like doing the drills, remember that Roger Federer, Novak Djokovic and Rafael Nadal are all doing similar drills. If they need to perform drills at their skill level, how about you?</p>
<p>If time is limited, choose the drill that can benefit you the most and perform it five minutes a day. Even 2-3 times per week will make a small difference but measurable difference in your game.</p>
<p>Hey, thank you for reading this far. I appreciate you stopping by my blog. If you have any questions about the exercises in this post, drop me a comment below and I’ll respond.</p>
<p>The post <a href="/10-tennis-drills-you-can-practice-without-a-court/">10 Fun Tennis Drills You Can Practice Without A Court</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/10-tennis-drills-you-can-practice-without-a-court/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>9</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The 9 Best Tennis Drills For Improving Your Volley Game</title>
		<link>/the-nine-best-tennis-drills-for-improving-the-serve-and-volley/</link>
					<comments>/the-nine-best-tennis-drills-for-improving-the-serve-and-volley/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chad Walner]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 12 Sep 2018 10:04:02 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Training]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[volley]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=196</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>So you want to improve your net game but you’re not sure exactly what to do. In this post we’re going to give you the absolute best serve and volley drills you can do. These are drills I’ve used to &#8230; <a class="kt-excerpt-readmore" href="/the-nine-best-tennis-drills-for-improving-the-serve-and-volley/" aria-label="The 9 Best Tennis Drills For Improving Your Volley Game">Read More</a></p>
<p>The post <a href="/the-nine-best-tennis-drills-for-improving-the-serve-and-volley/">The 9 Best Tennis Drills For Improving Your Volley Game</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>So you want to improve your net game but you’re not sure exactly what to do. In this post we’re going to give you the absolute best serve and volley drills you can do. These are drills I’ve used to improve my game as well as that of my students.</p>
<p><strong>Listed by name, they are <a href="#ghost">Ghost Doubles</a>, the <a href="#volley-to-volley">Volley-To-Volley drill</a>, the <a href="#three-volley">Three-Volley drill</a>, the <a href="#mad-volley">Mad-Volley drill</a>, <a href="#volley-overhead">Volley-Overhead Alternates</a>, the <a href="#catch-and-volley">Catch-And-Volley</a>, the <a href="#half-court">Half-Court Volley</a> game, <a href="#hit-the-target">Hit the Target</a> and the <a href="#service-line-touch">Service Line Touch.</a></strong></p>
<p>Now keep in mind that I made up the names to some of these drills, so you may have never heard them before. We’re going to review each one and by the end of this post, you’ll know how to do all of them. Every drill here is helpful, but you’ll probably narrow it down to a couple of favorites when you practice. I particularly like the half-court volley game. This drill really sharpens my reflexes and simulates a point at the net very well (more on it to come).</p>
<p>Keep in mind that we made a video of all these drills so you can see them played out. It helps to read about them as well, which is the reason for this post. Watch the video and read this post for the best overview of each drill/game. Our blog posts go into more detail than our videos do.</p>
<p>You may be wondering how advanced you need to be to do these drills. If you have basic volley technique and can serve, these drills are within reach of any level player. Even children can use these drills to improve their game. I often use them with my younger students, as most are great fun. You can incorporate these drills in a full practice session or do a couple before or after a match. Without further talk, let’s get into it.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="ghost"></a></p>
<h2>Drill # 1 &#8211; Ghost Doubles</h2>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="wp-image-217 size-full aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-ghost.jpg" alt="Ghost volley drill demonstration." width="800" height="407" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-ghost.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-ghost-300x153.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-ghost-768x391.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
</div>
<p>I first learned ghost doubles from my tennis coach in college. We used it quite a lot in our practices. It’s a great drill for doubles but can also hone your singles play.</p>
<p>This drill requires two people – one will be serving and the other will be returning. There are two rules to the game that make it different from a regular tennis match.</p>
<p>First, the server has to serve and volley. He or she must keep pressing into the net or else lose the point. The only time the server is allowed to back up is to field a lob. After the lob is hit, the server must move in again.</p>
<p>The other rule is that only half the court is used. If you are serving from the deuce side, only the deuce side is in play for both players. Any ball hit into the ad court is automatically out. The doubles allies are in play in this drill, so anything hit into the doubles alley counts.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>After the point is over, alternate to the the ad side (just like in a normal tennis match) and the same rules apply in reverse – any ball hit into the deuce side is considered out. Keep playing points until the game is over. You can play up to a certain amount, like 10 points, or just play a full set.</p>
<p>This drill realistically simulates doubles play and is great for improving your serve and volley doubles game. It also helps the returner develop good passing shots.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="volley-to-volley"></a></p>
<h2>Drill # 2 – The Volley-To-Volley Drill</h2>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-209 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-volleyvolley.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="407" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-volleyvolley.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-volleyvolley-300x153.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-volleyvolley-768x391.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
</div>
<p>This drill is one of the best for improving your volley game. It should be used in every practice and will definitely sharpen your reflexes if used consistently.</p>
<p>Two people are required for this drill. Each person will stand at the service line – one on each side of the net. I like to set up in the middle of the court to afford plenty of space to the left and right of me.</p>
<p>Start by hitting the ball to your partner. Ideally, your partner will volley the ball in the air and hit it right to you. You will then volley it back (out of the air) and hit it back to your partner. This will continue until one of you miss. When that occurs, just start again.</p>
<p>You want to hit the ball at each other so you can practice your volleys. Don’t try to be a hero and see if you can win the point by hitting away. That’s not the point of this drill.</p>
<p>It’s perfectly fine to hit half volleys too, as sometimes the ball will not reach you. You can move in a bit to volley, but if you go too far past the service line, the drill will become very difficult for both of you, as the ball will be going too fast.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="video-container"><iframe class="size-full aligncenter" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/BVSUl65cGrk?rel=0&amp;modestbranding=1&amp;start=38&amp;end=120" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen"></iframe></div>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>When you first learn this drill, it may be difficult to get more than several volleys back. Hit slow to each other at first and use a continental grip. Return to the ready position as soon as possible after each volley.</p>
<p>In time, you will get better and better. With consistent practice, it won’t be long before you will be able to hit many volleys before you miss. Keep in mind, this is not a game but a drill. The idea is not to blast the ball past your partner but to keep the ball in play for as long as possible.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="three-volley"></a></p>
<h2>Drill # 3 – The Three Volley Drill</h2>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="wp-image-264 size-full aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-3volley-1.jpg" alt="Three volley drill demonstration." width="800" height="407" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-3volley-1.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-3volley-1-300x153.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-3volley-1-768x391.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
</div>
<p>This is more of an advanced volley drill that is great for the serve and volley.</p>
<p>Only one player will be doing the drill, but another person is needed to feed the balls.</p>
<p>For the player doing the drill, start about three feet in back of the service line. The player on the other side of the net feeds you three quick volleys. The first volley is taken from the starting point. Once you hit the first volley you quickly move in, hit another volley, move in again and then hit your final volley. By the time you hit your third and last volley, you should be within 5-6 feet of the net, if not closer.</p>
<p>The person feeding the ball is advised to feed one after another with no delay. For beginners, feed slowly and hit higher shots that are easy to volley. If a player is more advanced, feed faster and lower shots to make the volley more challenging.</p>
<p>The person feeding can hit all three volleys to the forehand, all three to the backhand or make them random.</p>
<p>Once all three balls are volleyed, the player returns to the spot three feet in back of the service line and goes through the drill again. As an option, after the three volleys are made, the feeder can hit a lob for an overhead smash.</p>
<p>This drill can make you tired if done quickly but it’s a fantastic one to work on your volleys as you move in. The split-step is advised for this drill. However, advanced players can forgo it in favor of a flowing volley. When performing this drill quickly, your mechanics can get sloppy, so videoing yourself to monitor your progress is a good idea.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="mad-volley"></a></p>
<h2>Drill # 4 – The Mad Volley Drill</h2>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-219 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-mad.jpg" alt="Mad volley drill demonstration." width="800" height="407" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-mad.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-mad-300x153.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-mad-768x391.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
</div>
<p>This drill is one of my favorites to do with my students. I don’t use it much in my own practice, but I find it works great with beginners to really challenge them. Children especially love this drill.</p>
<p>This drill is performed by one player and requires another person to do the feeding. The player performing the drill will stand about 2-4 feet from the net, depending on their height. Shorter people can move closer, taller people can move back a bit.</p>
<p>For the feeder, it’s best to have a hopper with at least 50-75 balls for this drill, as they will be used quickly. For an enhanced effect, play uplifting music on your portable speakers or phone. I do this with the children sometimes and they go crazy for it.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>The person feeding the balls will be positioned around mid-way between the service line and the baseline. The feeder should hit random shots to the player volleying at the net, one after another until all the balls are gone. I suggest varying the shots. Hit some fast, some slow, some high, to the left, to the right and even right at the volleyer.</p>
<p>The player at the net gets inundated with shots they have to volley, one after the other for about a minute straight. This is a great drill to sharpen the reflexes and make the player hit a ton of volleys in a very short period of time. It can work wonders for anyone’s volley game. Try it out for yourself.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="volley-overhead"></a></p>
<h2>Drill # 5 – Volley-Overhead Alternates</h2>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-220 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-alternating.jpg" alt="Alternating volley drill demonstration." width="800" height="407" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-alternating.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-alternating-300x153.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-alternating-768x391.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
</div>
<p>This drill is simple and straightforward, but very effective for improving the overhead.</p>
<p>One player performs the drill &#8211; although two players can do it too. One person is needed to feed the balls from the other side of the court. The person feeding will stand between the service line and baseline on one side of the court. On the other side, the player or players performing the drill will start about half-way between the net and service line.</p>
<p>If one player will be doing the drill, he or she can stand in the middle of the court. If two players do the drill, have one stand on the ad court and the other on the deuce court. The feeder will start by hitting a shot that has to be volleyed.</p>
<p>Once the volley is hit, the feeder will then give the player a lob. Keep alternating between a volley and a lob until the player gets tired. The feeder can vary the speed of the volley shots and lobs to adjust for the player’s skill level</p>
<p>If the overhead forces the player in back of the service line, he or she needs to move in towards the net again for the next volley. This drill requires good coordination and will improve the overhead smash.</p>
<p>If two players are performing the drill, you can make it a game by keeping score. Simply alternate giving a volley and overhead to the player on the deuce court and then a volley and overhead to the player on the ad court and keep repeating. A volley that goes over the net is worth one point and an overhead smash is worth two. Play up to 11 or 15 points.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="catch-and-volley"></a></p>
<h2>Drill # 6 – The Catch-And-Volley Drill</h2>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-222 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-catchvolley.jpg" alt="Catch volley drill demonstration" width="800" height="407" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-catchvolley.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-catchvolley-300x153.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-catchvolley-768x391.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
</div>
<p>The catch-and-volley drill is ideal for intermediate level players and those looking to add touch to their volleys.</p>
<p>We’re often taught to “punch” the volley, which does not involve a lot of touch. The catch-and-volley drill requires very soft hands by “catching” the ball on our racquet. This helps us to learn feel on the volley.</p>
<p>Children can and should be encouraged to perform this drill as well.</p>
<p>Basic volley technique is needed to perform this drill, and it may be difficult for beginners at first. It involves two players, one on each side of the net, both standing near the service line. This is really the same drill as the volley-to-volley drill with a couple of exceptions.</p>
<p>First, both players must “catch” the ball on their racquets. This is done by getting the racquet under the incoming volley causing it to bounce straight up from their racquet. While the ball is in mid-air, the player will hit a volley to the other player across the net. The player across the net will do the same. They’ll slow the ball by volleying with the racquet under the ball in a slice position (racquet face open) and this will cause the ball to move directly upwards. Once in mid-air, the player will volley the ball back across the net and the point continues.</p>
<p>This is a complicated drill to explain in words, so if it’s not clear to you, please watch our accompanying video. This is a great drill for improving your drop volley. You can increase the level of difficulty by adding a variation. If you “catch” the ball on your backhand side, try using a forehand volley to hit across the net. Do the inverse for catching on the forehand side. This requires great dexterity and requires fast reaction times.</p>
<div class="video-container"><iframe class="size-full aligncenter" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/BVSUl65cGrk?rel=0&amp;modestbranding=1&amp;start=120&amp;end=168" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen"></iframe></div>
<p>One additional note – if you receive a half volley, treat it like a regular volley and bounce it up off your racquet and then proceed to volley as usual. This drill can take a few times to learn for a beginner. Keep at it and make this drill a part of your practice sessions.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="half-court"></a></p>
<h2>Drill # 7 – The Half Court Volley Game</h2>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-223 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-half.jpg" alt="Half court volley game drill." width="800" height="407" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-half.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-half-300x153.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-half-768x391.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
</div>
<p>This is one of my favorite volley drills and I like to use it in warmups instead of mini tennis.</p>
<p>It requires two players. The players will be on opposite sides of the net, positioned at the service line. In this game, only one half of the court will be used. You can choose to play on the left side of the court or the right side – it really doesn’t matter. You can switch sides (left to right or right to left) after the game is over if you choose.</p>
<p>For the duration of the point and game, you need to stay around the service line. A point is won or lost the same as in a real tennis match with the exception that it is out if hit on the opposite side of the court. For example, if you play on the left side of the court, everything hit to the left of the center line is good. Any shot that lands to the right of the centerline is out. The doubles alley is considered out.</p>
<p>Player one starts out by hitting a shot to player two. Once player two volleys back, the point is live. You can hit groundstrokes, swinging volleys, half volleys, drop volleys and overheads if you can. Just don’t kill your partner! If you want to keep it cordial, just stick to punch volleys and half volleys.</p>
<p>I play up to 11 points and play 2-3 games in warmup.</p>
<p>This is an interesting and challenging game that makes warm-up fun. The harder you can volley and keep the ball in play, the better you’ll do. Try it out and add it your practice sessions as well.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="hit-the-target"></a></p>
<h2>Drill # 8 – Hit The Target</h2>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="wp-image-261 size-full aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-target.jpg" alt="Hit the target volley demonstration." width="800" height="407" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-target.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-target-300x153.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-target-768x391.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
</div>
<p>This drill involves one player hitting three different targeted areas on the court.</p>
<p>To delineate the areas, use cones. If you don’t have cones, tennis cans are good substitutes. Place three cones on the baseline 12 feet apart. The player doing the drill will stand on the other side of the net, near the middle of the court and about 3-6 feet from the net.</p>
<p>The use of a hopper is a good idea with this drill. The person feeding the balls will hit a forehand to the player volleying at the net. Before feeding the ball, the feeder will call out “left, right, or middle”. You can also say, “one, two or three,” to differentiate the three zones. After the forehand is hit by the feeder, the volleyer must try to hit the targeted area called out by the feeder.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>The feeder can vary the speed of the shot depending on the skill level of the player. Overheads can be thrown into the mix in the same way, with the feeder calling out the zone to aim for. Each time the player hits the right zone, they get a point.</p>
<p>I usually feed 20 balls to the net player and count the points. If you use this drill with the same person often, you can record their scores to come up with an average and personal best. In the next practice session, they can aim to beat it.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="service-line-touch"></a></p>
<h2>Bonus Drill – Service Line Touch Volley</h2>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="wp-image-228 size-full aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-servicelinetouch-1.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="407" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-servicelinetouch-1.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-servicelinetouch-1-300x153.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/blue-court-demonstration-servicelinetouch-1-768x391.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
</div>
<p>I can’t let you go without a bonus drill.</p>
<p>This one involves two players. In this drill one player stands at the service line, around the middle of the court. This player will only hit volleys.</p>
<p>The other player stands on the opposite side of the net, also around the service line and middle of the court. But this player can only hit groundstrokes.</p>
<p>The key to this drill is for the volley player to use touch to control the ball. If touch is not used it will be difficult to control the ball. For example, if touch is not used, the ball will fly off the volleyer’s racquet and not allow the player on the other side of the net to hit a groundstroke back.</p>
<div class="video-container"><iframe class="size-full aligncenter" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/BVSUl65cGrk?rel=0&amp;modestbranding=1&amp;start=120&amp;end=168" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen"></iframe></div>
<p>This drill works when there is a continuous flow of groundstroke and volley, groundstroke and volley, etc. This is another favorite drill of mine for learning to have soft hands at the net.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Summary – Putting It All Together</h2>
<p>There you have it. Nine awesome drills you can use to improve your serve and volley skills while having fun doing it. Use them with your children or employ them with your hitting partners. Tennis coaches can also use these drills with their clients to achieve definite improvement over time.</p>
<p>You can watch our youtube videos for visual demonstrations of all the drills. Until the next post, have fun, practice hard and keep coming to net!</p>
<p>The post <a href="/the-nine-best-tennis-drills-for-improving-the-serve-and-volley/">The 9 Best Tennis Drills For Improving Your Volley Game</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/the-nine-best-tennis-drills-for-improving-the-serve-and-volley/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
