<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>serve Archives - Serve and Volley Tennis</title>
	<atom:link href="/tag/serve/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/tag/serve/</link>
	<description>Your secret weapon on the court.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 15 Aug 2019 09:58:32 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	

<image>
	<url>/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/cropped-ted_svt_favicon-32x32.png</url>
	<title>serve Archives - Serve and Volley Tennis</title>
	<link>/tag/serve/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>What Are The 8 Basic Tennis Shots?</title>
		<link>/what-are-the-8-basic-tennis-shots/</link>
					<comments>/what-are-the-8-basic-tennis-shots/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chad Walner]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 04 Jan 2019 19:56:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Theory]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[backhand]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[dropshot]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[forehand]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[lob]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[overhead]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[serve]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[slice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[volley]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1862</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The game of tennis might seem complicated for those new to it, but it can essentially be broken down into 8 basic shots. All 8 shots need to be mastered to excel and proceed to the higher levels of tennis. &#8230; <a class="kt-excerpt-readmore" href="/what-are-the-8-basic-tennis-shots/" aria-label="What Are The 8 Basic Tennis Shots?">Read More</a></p>
<p>The post <a href="/what-are-the-8-basic-tennis-shots/">What Are The 8 Basic Tennis Shots?</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The game of tennis might seem complicated for those new to it, but it can essentially be broken down into 8 basic shots. All 8 shots need to be mastered to excel and proceed to the higher levels of tennis.</p>
<p>In this blog post, I discuss all 8 basic shots in the game of tennis. By the time you finish this article, you’ll know all of them inside and out. You’ll also have a much better understanding of the game of tennis.</p>
<p>Here are the 8 basic shots in the game of tennis:</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<ol>
<li><a href="#forehand">Forehand</a></li>
<li><a href="#backhand">Backhand</a></li>
<li><a href="#serve">Serve</a></li>
<li><a href="#volley">Volley</a></li>
<li><a href="#slice">Slice</a></li>
<li><a href="#overhead">Overhead</a></li>
<li><a href="#dropshot">Drop shot</a></li>
<li><a href="#lob">Lob</a></li>
</ol>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Most tennis newbies wonder, “What are the basic strokes in tennis?” Well now you know. And by knowing all the basic strokes, you can learn them and use them in your own game.</p>
<p>This will make you a more versatile and dangerous player to face. It’s ironic, but I see club players with decades of experience who never utilize all 8 shots in their game.</p>
<p>I believe there are a lot of players out there who never quite learned some of them, so they just don’t use them. If you’re new to tennis, I implore you to learn all 8 basic shots.</p>
<p>Certainly, the forehand, backhand, and serve are essential to playing tennis.</p>
<p>Other shots, like the slice and dropshot, are not part of the arsenal of some club players. I honestly don’t know how they cope in tennis without a slice. To me, the slice on both the forehand and backhand wings are a must-know stroke.</p>
<p>Without more talk, let’s get into the details of each stroke, so you know what each one entails.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="forehand"></a></p>
<h2>The Basic Forehand Shot</h2>
</div>
<p><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-1867 size-full" src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/forehand.jpg" alt="Pat Cash forehand" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/forehand.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/01/forehand-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/01/forehand-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>The forehand is the most basic and often-used shot in tennis. It’s also the easiest to learn and the shot beginners pick up the quickest.</p>
<p>Think of the forehand as akin to the queen in the game of chess. The forehand is your most versatile shot. Good players can hit with power, spin, and place the ball where they want.</p>
<p>Being the most basic stroke in tennis, it’s often the one everyone learns first. Professional players can dominate matches primarily with their forehand (a la Roger Federer).</p>
<p>The strength and placement of the forehand is often what separates great players at the highest levels. In my experience, the forehand is the most comfortable shot to hit and the most enjoyable too.</p>
<p>The forehand is hit on the dominant side of your body and is typically struck with one arm (your dominant arm). It’s possible to hit a two-handed forehand as well, but I would estimate less than 2% of recreational and professional players use it.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>On the men’s pro tour, there have only ever been two players to use the two-handed forehand. And this is out of thousands of players since 1940.</p>
<p>Those two players are the legendary Pancho Segura, and more lately, Fabrice Santoro. Segura was a lot more successful than Santora but played in the 40s and 50s when the game and racket technology was a lot different.</p>
<p>Santoro played in the 90s and 2000s. He reached a career high of 17 and his best result at a major was the quarterfinals of the 2006 Australian Open.</p>
<p>On the women’s side, the two-handed forehand had much more success, with players such as Monica Seles (10 career grand slam titles) and Marion Bartoli. Bartoli won Wimbledon in 2013 and then promptly and unexpectedly retired. She was my favorite woman to watch.</p>
<p>If you’re just starting out in tennis, hire a qualified pro to teach you the basics of the forehand. With just a couple of lessons, you’ll at least know the correct technique.</p>
<p>If you can’t afford lessons or don’t have a qualified pro near you, you can <a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCHaY0w7QtG205o4ByUHXkEg/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">check out my youtube channel</a> for free forehand lessons.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="backhand"></a></p>
<h2>The Basic Backhand Shot</h2>
</div>
<div id="attachment_1869" style="width: 810px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img decoding="async" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1869" class="size-full wp-image-1869" src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/backhand.jpg" alt="Pablo Cuevas" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/backhand.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/01/backhand-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/01/backhand-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /><p id="caption-attachment-1869" class="wp-caption-text">Carine06 from UK [<a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.0">CC BY-SA 2.0</a>], <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Pablo_Cuevas_backhand_(14536242152).jpg">via Wikimedia Commons</a></p></div>
<p>The backhand is hit on the non-dominant side of your body. For example, if you’re a righty and strike the ball on the left side of your body, it’s considered a backhand.</p>
<p>Most player’s backhands are not as strong as their forehand. This is because it’s more difficult to achieve the same level of racket speed on the backhand wing as the forehand side.</p>
<p>However, some players do have better backhands than forehands. If you’re one of those players, then you’re fortunate. Most club players dread hitting their backhands.</p>
<p>I find that most women have better two-handed backhands than forehands. This is likely due to them using more of their core and legs on the backhand. For men, I find most have much better forehands.</p>
<p>The backhand can either be hit with one hand or two. Examples of players with one-handed backhands are Roger Federer, Stan Wawrinka, Carla Suarez Navarro, and Justine Henin (now retired). Some would argue Henin had the best one-handed backhand in the women’s game.</p>
<p>The one-handed backhand offers some pros an advantage over the two-handed backhand. The pros using the one-handed backhand would have greater range of motion, slightly more drive and power, and more versatility with spin.</p>
<p>The cons of the one-handed backhand (compared to the two-) are less control, it’s more difficult to hit high shots, and there’s less ability to hit the ball late. Additionally, it’s more difficult to return serve with a one-hander.</p>
<p>These cons are enough to have persuaded most players and coaches to only teach and hit the two-handed backhand. For this reason, most of the players on the pro level (for both men and women) use a two-handed backhand.</p>
<p>If you wish to reach the upper levels of tennis, it’s essential you develop your backhand into a reliable shot. You’ll need to be able to hit it with depth, spin, placement, and a decent amount of pace.</p>
<p>While it’s not essential you smash winners from the baseline with your backhand, it is essential that it keeps you in the rally. Most professional players use their backhand to stay in a rally long enough to set up their forehand.</p>
<p>If you wish to learn the backhand, I suggest the two-hander. Get a qualified coach to teach you the basics of the shot and then just keep practicing it. I have videos on my youtube channel showing how to hit both the two-hander and the one-hander.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="serve"></a></p>
<h2>The Basic Serve</h2>
</div>
<p>Along with the forehand and backhand, the serve is one of the three primary shots in tennis you must know to begin playing. If you can effectively execute all three shots, you can play tennis.</p>
<p>The next shot in tennis you should learn is the volley. If you know these four shots (forehand, backhand, serve, volley) you can play matches, even in tournaments.</p>
<p>It sounds amazing, but you can literally choose to avoid the other four basic shots (drop shot, overhead, slice and lob) and still play competitive tennis. I wouldn’t suggest it though.</p>
<div id="attachment_1871" style="width: 410px" class="wp-caption alignleft"><img decoding="async" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1871" class="size-full wp-image-1871" src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/serve1.jpg" alt="Andre Agassi serve" width="400" height="610" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/serve1.jpg 400w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/01/serve1-197x300.jpg 197w" sizes="(max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" /><p id="caption-attachment-1871" class="wp-caption-text">Srinayan Puppala [<a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.0">CC BY-SA 2.0</a>], <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Agassi_serve_US_open_05.jpg">via Wikimedia Commons</a></p></div>All tennis players (whether in singles or doubles) get two serves on each point. The first serve is usually hit flat and hard.</p>
<p>The second serve is often hit with topspin or kick. These types of serves have more margin of error and are about 15-20% slower in speed than first serves.</p>
<p>Of the 8 basic shots in tennis, the serve is by far the most difficult to learn and the most complicated. This is for a few reasons.</p>
<p>First, the serve is the only shot in tennis where you start and finish the stroke. All other strokes rely on the ball coming to you.</p>
<p>Second, the serve requires you to toss the ball high in the air (usually twice your height) and strike it on the way down. This requires split-second timing.</p>
<p>The toss can also be problematic. This is because it’s done with the non-dominant hand, which can be very difficult for uncoordinated people and beginners.</p>
<p>Third, the serve is a complicated series of movements that must be performed in about two seconds. It also requires knee-bend, flexibility, and high racket speed.</p>
<p>Due to these factors, many club players never develop anything beyond a mediocre serve. This means their serves typically don’t break the 100-mph barrier or possess enough spin to hurt opponents.</p>
<p>If you are just starting out in tennis, realize the serve is a shot that will take you months or years to master. Everyone is limited on the serve by their physical ability, so be aware of that too.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>If you have dreams of serving 120-mph, unless you’re young and very talented, it’s not likely to happen. Instead, your goal should be a very consistent serve with excellent placement.</p>
<p>The serve is one of those shots you’ll need to continually practice. It requires perfect timing and tremendous hand-eye coordination when hit well.</p>
<p>Some of you may just want to play tennis for the exercise, or for the fun. If that’s your goal, you can use a very simple beginner’s serve to get the ball in the box and start the point.</p>
<p>If that sounds like you, I would advise you to check out my youtube video on the abbreviated serve motion. It’s a beginner’s serve, but slightly more advanced, offering more power and spin.</p>
<p>For those who aspire to hit their serve like Roger Federer, check out my video on Roger Federer’s serve motion. In this video, I explain how to hit your serve like Roger. Just don’t blame me if you can’t.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="volley"></a></p>
<h2>The Basic Volley</h2>
</div>
<div id="attachment_1873" style="width: 810px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1873" class="size-full wp-image-1873" src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/volley.jpg" alt="Jo-Wilfried Tsonga" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/volley.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/01/volley-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/01/volley-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /><p id="caption-attachment-1873" class="wp-caption-text">Kate from UK [<a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.0">CC BY-SA 2.0</a>], <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Jo-Wilfried_Tsonga_Wimbledon_2011_jump_volley.jpg">via Wikimedia Commons</a></p></div>
<p>The volley is unique all to itself. At its most basic element, it doesn’t require any swing of the racket or much body movement at all. Yet, it can be one of the most difficult shots in tennis to master.</p>
<p>What is a volley? A volley is when a player hits the ball directly out of the air, instead of letting the ball bounce first. When the ball bounces first, it’s called a “rally”. When taken in the air, it’s called a volley.</p>
<p>The volley is a very short compact “block” of the ball, most often close to the net. The volley can be hit on either the forehand side or the backhand side.</p>
<p>One of the reasons so few players master the volley is the very short amount of time provided to hit the ball. When you’re up at net, the ball is coming to you much sooner than at the baseline.</p>
<p>This makes it largely a reflexive shot, while baseline groundstrokes are much more deliberate.</p>
<p>Even the best players in the world today prefer not to come to net. The pace of groundstrokes at the pro level is just too much to handle, even for the best volley players.</p>
<p>With groundstroke speeds coming in excess of 80-90 mph, it’s very difficult to hit effective volleys, much less get a racket on the ball. For this reason, we have seen a trend away from net play over the last generation.</p>
<p>If you want to read more about this, I wrote an article entitled <a href="/why-did-serve-and-volley-die-out/">Why Did The Serve And Volley Die Out</a>?  It’s an interesting look at why the volley declined in both the women’s and men’s game over the last 20 years.</p>
<p>Despite the volley dying out, all players must learn to volley. This is because if you’re forced into net, you’ll have no choice but to eventually volley. The volley is also an essential part of doubles, which many people play.</p>
<p>If you’ve been struggling with your volleys, have no fear. I wrote a great blog post about the <a href="/seven-volley-types-you-must-know-to-master-your-net-game/">7 types of volleys</a> to use in your game. By knowing all 7 types and how to hit them, you’ll instantly improve your net game.</p>
<p>I also have a bunch of volley videos on my youtube channel. I recommend starting off with the block volley and then working your way through the other 6 volley types.</p>
<p>On the volley, always remember less is more. Most people over-complicate the volley and do too much swinging. The volley is more about great footwork and less about what you do with your racket.</p>
<p>If you want to play good doubles, or be an offensive player in singles, it’s imperative you learn to hit volleys with pace, spin, touch, and placement. It all comes in time.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="slice"></a></p>
<h2>The Basic Slice</h2>
</div>
<p>Traditional forehand and backhand strokes are hit with topspin (forward rotation of the ball). However, the slice employs backspin, which is a backward rotation of the ball.</p>
<p>Interestingly, it can also involve side spin.</p>
<p>The slice can be hit on either wing: the forehand or backhand. It can also be hit with either two hands or one. However, most players (probably more than 95%) hit their slice with one hand.</p>
<p>The slice generally refers to the downward motion of the racket when contacting the ball. The downward motion is what causes the backspin on the ball.</p>
<p>This is in contrast to traditional groundstrokes, which use a low-to-high swing path. In my opinion, it’s more difficult to learn the slice though.</p>
<p>I can teach a child or adult to make solid contact on a traditional forehand or backhand, but the slice is a different animal. For this reason, it can take a long time to develop a penetrating, effective slice shot on both wings.</p>
<p>One of the reasons for the difficulty level is the downward motion of the swing. Most beginners aren’t used to contacting the ball like that. The continental grip used on the slice also throws people off.</p>
<div id="attachment_1875" style="width: 410px" class="wp-caption alignright"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1875" class="size-full wp-image-1875" src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/slice.jpg" alt="Federer hitting a slice." width="400" height="404" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/slice.jpg 400w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/01/slice-297x300.jpg 297w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" /><p id="caption-attachment-1875" class="wp-caption-text">Steve Collis from Melbourne, Australia [<a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0">CC BY 2.0</a>], <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Federer_2009_Australian_Open_crop.jpg">via Wikimedia Commons</a></p></div>Most players open the racket face too much, or too early, and float the ball on their slice. For this reason, I teach my students to hit the ball completely flat but with a high-to-low trajectory of the racket.</p>
<p>If the slice is hit well, it can be a very damaging shot to the opponent. A good slice will skid on the ground and stay low. It can also be difficult to volley a tightly rotating slice.</p>
<p>Most players use the slice as a defensive shot, but it can certainly be used offensively as well. One example of an offensive slice shot is the approach shot. This is a hard, low slice away from the opponent.</p>
<p>On an approach shot, a player will quickly come to net in hopes of putting away an easy volley. The former greats like Pete Sampras, Patrick Rafter, and Stefan Edberg all used this tactic.</p>
<p>Many players also use the slice on the return of serve. I find the slice to be an excellent way to neutralize fast serves. It’s also much easier to control a slice return than a topspin return on fast or high serves.</p>
<p>The downside of returning a serve with a slice is that your opponent could volley it for a winner. But that’s only if they are a serve and volley type player. If you’re playing a strict baseliner, it’s a good tactic for the return.</p>
<p>The slice is an excellent way to handle high shots too (balls higher than your shoulder level). This is especially true on the backhand side, where there is less flexibility and strength to hit the ball high up.</p>
<p>For this reason, you’ll see many professional players turn to the slice on the high backhand. I personally use the slice to great effect on my forehand wing too – mostly on high shots.</p>
<p>The slice is also a great way to change up the spin on the ball. In this way, you offer different looks to your opponent, so they never know what to expect.</p>
<p>Lastly, the slice is often used as a last resort when the ball is far from the body. This typically happens when a ball is hit far from us and we are on the run to it.</p>
<p>Being it’s nearly impossible to hit a traditional groundstroke when so out of position, players will simply slice the ball back, as it’s the only option. When done on the forehand side, some call it a “squash shot”.</p>
<p>Roger Federer probably hits the best “squash shot” in the game. He also has one of the best slices the game has ever seen, period.</p>
<p>If you play tennis but haven’t developed a slice – or a good slice – work with a coach who can show you the shot. I have a great blog post here on <a href="/how-to-backhand-slice-in-tennis-the-right-way/">how to hit a backhand slice</a>.  I’ll be adding one for the forehand slice soon.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="overhead"></a></p>
<h2>The Basic Overhead Shot</h2>
</div>
<p>The overhead is a shot you hit above your head. It’s very similar to the serve motion, except the ball will be hit at you, instead of you initiating the stroke.</p>
<p>Overheads can be hit directly out of the air or after they hit the ground. If taken out of the air, exquisite timing is necessary to hit an effective overhead.</p>
<p>On occasion, it’s wise to let the ball hit the ground first and not take it out of the air. If the ball bounces high enough, you can strike the ball over your head.</p>
<p>Allowing the ball to hit the ground first is a lot easier than taking it out of the air. However, most of the time you’ll want to hit the ball out of the air.</p>
<div id="attachment_1877" style="width: 410px" class="wp-caption alignright"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1877" class="size-full wp-image-1877" src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/overhead.jpg" alt="Rafael Nadal hitting an overhead shot." width="400" height="599" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/overhead.jpg 400w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/01/overhead-200x300.jpg 200w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" /><p id="caption-attachment-1877" class="wp-caption-text">Carine06 from UK [<a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.0">CC BY-SA 2.0</a>], <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Flickr_-_Carine06_-_Rafa_overhead.jpg">via Wikimedia Commons</a></p></div>It’s really a judgment call which one you choose. The more you play, the easier it becomes to decide. You’re much more likely to hit the ball out of the air when you’re at net and lobbed.</p>
<p>It&#8217;s my belief that if you have a good serve motion, you’ll have a good overhead. The fundamentals of the serve and overhead are basically the same.</p>
<p>However, if your serve fundamentals are lacking, your overheads are going to be spotty at best. I believe a good racket drop is crucial to hitting great overheads. The racket drop is when your racket inverts before swinging up to contact.</p>
<p>If you have a beginner’s serve, also known as a waiter’s serve, you’ll likely never have world-class overheads. But you can still make do and place the ball well.</p>
<p>The overhead requires good footwork and great timing. Most people miss their overheads because their footwork does not put them in proper position to hit the ball well.</p>
<p>When you see a ball lobbed to you, your first instinct should be to turn to your forehand side and get your racket up. This is the side from which you hit your forehands and serves.</p>
<p>From here, you’ll want to use a cross-step as your first move. Once done, side-step back into position to hit the perfect overhead.</p>
<p>A major mistake I often see is people walking backwards to hit the overhead. They clearly missed the first step of turning to their side. This rarely works and can result in you falling over and hurting yourself.</p>
<p>With the right footwork and practice, you can make the overhead one of your best shots. If you can put your overheads away with pace and placement, it’ll put a ton of pressure on your opponents – especially when you come to net.</p>
<p>I should mention that the overhead can be hit on the backhand side as well. It’s rare, but most professional players can put away balls using a backhand overhead. A lot of it involves a flick of the wrist.</p>
<p>However, most club players find the backhand overhead shot to be very difficult. It’s still worth practicing, as you’ll experience hitting it from time-to-time in your matches. It involves using a combination of your arm and wrist.</p>
<p>The normal overhead is an important shot to learn in tennis and will serve you well in both singles and doubles. Most people don’t practice the overhead enough. I suggest working on it every practice session, if even for 5-10 minutes.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="dropshot"></a></p>
<h2>The Basic Drop Shot</h2>
</div>
<p>When done right, the drop shot is an extremely effective shot that can win you a point outright. It is often made from the baseline, whereby a player hits the ball very slowly with a lot of backspin.</p>
<p>Optimally, the ball will go barely over the net, not more than 5-6 feet into the court, and have very little forward movement. This will force the opposing player to sprint up to the ball and hit it.</p>
<p>This causes difficultly for the opposing player for several reasons. One is that the ball may be out of reach, whereby you win the point outright. Second, the opposing player must run fast and stop in time to avoid hitting the net.</p>
<p>If that player touches the net with their body or racket after hitting the ball, they automatically lose the point. Third, most good drop shots will cause the opposing player to lift the ball over the net, making it difficult to hit a good shot back on you.</p>
<div id="attachment_1865" style="width: 410px" class="wp-caption alignright"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1865" class="size-full wp-image-1865" src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/dropshot.jpg" alt="Boris Becker drop shot" width="400" height="267" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/dropshot.jpg 400w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/01/dropshot-300x200.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/01/dropshot-272x182.jpg 272w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" /><p id="caption-attachment-1865" class="wp-caption-text">James Phelps from USA [<a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0">CC BY 2.0</a>], <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Boris_Becker_in_action.jpg">via Wikimedia Commons</a></p></div>The drop shot can be hit off either side – forehand or backhand. It can be used at any time during the point, even off the serve. As a matter of fact, it can be very effective off the serve.</p>
<p>I like to throw in at least a few drop shots per set – usually in my baseline rallies. I do this for several reasons. One, it keeps the opposing player honest; he or she never knows what to expect from me.</p>
<p>Second, it makes the opposing player sprint to net, which expends their energy. This makes them just a bit more tired during the rest of the match.</p>
<p>I especially like to drop shot my opponent in the first set, as it will tire them out in the second set, and possibly the third (if we go there). If you want to compare it to boxing, drop shots are like body blows.</p>
<p>Even if the opponent gets to my drop shot and wins the point, it takes a small physical toll on them. In boxing, a fighter may land body shots early in the fight, but they typically don’t pay off until the later rounds. Same thing in tennis.</p>
<p>The drop shot can be used in these different scenarios: off the serve (as I just mentioned), during a baseline rally, and when you’re at net hitting a volley (called a drop volley). Another really good time to use the drop shot is off a drop shot.</p>
<p>That last scenario may sound confusing, so I’ll clarify. Let’s say your opponent drop shots you and you sprint up to the net to hit the ball. Usually your best option at that point is to drop your opponent right back.</p>
<p>Why? Because it’s often unexpected and your opponent will need to cover a large distance to get to the ball. It’s also easier to drop shot from the net rather than the baseline.</p>
<p>The drop shot requires a more delicate touch than any other shot in tennis. If you’re playing against a fast player who anticipates well, you’ll have a slim margin of success with the drop shot.</p>
<p>The danger of the drop shot occurs when it’s hit too deep or too high. If this happens, expect your opponent to easily get up to it and hit a clear winner on you.</p>
<p>As this can happen, it’s an excellent idea to disguise your drop shot. You do this by making it look like you’re going to hit your normal forehand or backhand.</p>
<p>At the last second you pull the rug out from under your opponent and slice the ball short. If you can learn to disguise your dropper, you’ll have a lot more success with it.</p>
<p>I think the number one reason players fail when using the drop shot is that they telegraph it. Most have no idea they’re showing their hand a mile away – as their opponents are usually mum to the fact.</p>
<p>One more point about the drop shot: It can be a great way to get a baseline player who hates the net out of his element.</p>
<p>By dropping such players, you force them to play the net, where their weakest. This is a great strategy to use against a perennial baseline player.</p>
<p>Practicing the drop shot is quite easy. Just rally at the baseline with your hitting partner. After one or two shots, hit a drop shot. You can also practice it on a ball machine.</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="lob"></a></p>
<h2>The Basic Lob</h2>
</div>
<div id="attachment_1880" style="width: 810px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1880" class="wp-image-1880 size-full" src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/lob2.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/lob2.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/01/lob2-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/01/lob2-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /><p id="caption-attachment-1880" class="wp-caption-text"><a title="Running down a lob" href="https://flickr.com/photos/mirsasha/5000452102">&#8220;Running down a lob&#8221;</a> by <a href="https://flickr.com/people/mirsasha">mirsasha</a> is licensed under <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/2.0/">CC BY-NC-ND</a></p></div>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>The lob is chiefly a defensive tennis shot. In tennis, a lob is a slow-moving shot hit at a high trajectory. Its purpose is to go over the head of a net player – or make the net player hit a difficult shot.</p>
<p>Some people even go so far as to use the lob in rallies. While that can work at the lower levels of tennis, it doesn’t work at the intermediate level &#8211; and certainly not at the advanced level.</p>
<p>I suggest only lobbing when the opposing player is at the net or when you’re far out of position and off the court. The latter works well to give yourself time to get back into the point.</p>
<p>Lobbing when you’re off the court is especially effective if the opposing player doesn’t like to move off the baseline. I use this tactic a lot when I’m strung wide against a perennial baseline player.</p>
<p>The lob can be hit off any side, forehand or backhand. It is most often hit with topspin but can be hit with slice as well. A topspin lob is much preferred and more effective for three distinct reasons.</p>
<p>One is that the topspin will help keep the ball in the court. Two, it’s more difficult for your opponent to hit a fast spinning ball that is dipping quickly; slice shots tend to float more and are much easier to hit.</p>
<p>Lastly, you can lob with more pace and margin of error with a topspin as opposed to slice. To hit the lob, simply brush on the bottom of the ball and finish your stroke up high. You’ll be taking almost all the pace off the ball and putting that energy into the “brush”.</p>
<p>Keep in mind it’s always more effective to lob your opponent on his or her backhand side. The backhand overhead is a much tougher shot to hit than the normal overhead.</p>
<p>You can make the lob more even more effective if you disguise it well. Do this by preparing the same way you would on any forehand or backhand. Instead of hitting with your normal stroke, put a lot of brush on the ball.</p>
<p>Lobbing is a good strategy but it’s not the cure-all to beat a player that likes to come to net on you. Instead, it’s best to mix in hard shots and heavy topspin shots with your lobs.</p>
<p>This throws your opponent off and will keep them guessing. If you’re playing outside and it’s very windy, take note of which way the wind is blowing.</p>
<p>My best advice on a windy day is not to lob into the wind. I find it to be very challenging to hit a lob when the wind is against me.</p>
<p>If I lob into the wind, the ball will not be very deep, and my opponent will crush it. On the contrary, lobbing with the wind is advisable.</p>
<p>You just need be careful not to put too much on the ball. When hitting a lob with the wind at your back, hit lightly and let the wind do the work.</p>
<p>You can practice your lobs as easily as your drop shots. Just have someone stand at the net and see how well you can lob them. Practice over-and-over on both forehand and backhand wings. Do this until you’re a master of the topspin lob off of both sides.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Conclusion</h2>
<p>This wraps up the 8 basic shots in tennis. I hope this post has given you a good insight into each stroke. My point was to give some information on each stroke to all level of players.</p>
<p>If you’re new to tennis, take your time learning each stroke. Tennis is a difficult game to learn and master. Give yourself several years to reach an intermediate level.</p>
<p>For those experienced players reading this, if you’re not using all 8 basic shots in your game, you’re selling yourself short. For example, if you’ve never sliced, or don’t believe you can do it well, take on the challenge of learning it.</p>
<p>It will add great depth to your game. Remember, always make sure you know the fundamentals and are executing them properly. If you can’t get a coach, at least video your strokes so you can see where corrections need to be made.</p>
<p>Hey, I have a lot of cool and interesting articles on this blog, so don’t be afraid to browse around and check them out. I’ve categorized most of them into “training” and “theory”.</p>
<p>Thanks for coming this far with me. If you have any questions on these basic strokes of tennis post them in the comment section below. And don’t forget to check out my youtube channel for great tips and tricks to accelerate your tennis game.</p>
<p>The post <a href="/what-are-the-8-basic-tennis-shots/">What Are The 8 Basic Tennis Shots?</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/what-are-the-8-basic-tennis-shots/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>How To Hit A Second Serve In Tennis</title>
		<link>/how-to-hit-a-second-serve-in-tennis/</link>
					<comments>/how-to-hit-a-second-serve-in-tennis/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chad Walner]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 23 Dec 2018 10:12:40 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Theory]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[serve]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1659</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The second serve in tennis is like a mystery to many club players. Sure, anyone can hit a slow second serve into the box with no spin, but I’m talking about a kick serve with pace and massive spin that &#8230; <a class="kt-excerpt-readmore" href="/how-to-hit-a-second-serve-in-tennis/" aria-label="How To Hit A Second Serve In Tennis">Read More</a></p>
<p>The post <a href="/how-to-hit-a-second-serve-in-tennis/">How To Hit A Second Serve In Tennis</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><strong>The second serve in tennis is like a mystery to many club players. Sure, anyone can hit a slow second serve into the box with no spin, but I’m talking about a kick serve with pace and massive spin that disrupts the opponent. Follow the five points laid out below and you&#8217;ll be on track with an aggressive, consistent second serve.</strong></p>
<p>So why is it so difficult to hit a tennis second serve the way the pros do? The second serve requires a special technique that is different than any other shot in tennis.</p>
<p>Everyone can learn to hit a forehand, a backhand, a volley, and a first serve. And the second serve too! But while all those first shots require technique, they are not as specialized as the second serve.</p>
<p><strong>If the second serve has alluded you, then read on. I am going to dispel the mystery and let you know the five most important keys you need to know to hit a great second serve.</strong></p>
<p>Don’t get me wrong. The second serve was a mystery for me too. When I first started playing, there were no youtube videos to learn from and I couldn’t afford lessons.</p>
<p>It was only later, when youtube came of age that I was able to see professional players hitting their serves in super slow motion. Wow, what a revelation that was!</p>
<p>Using youtube, I could study the pros’ mechanics carefully to see how they were imparting so much topspin on the ball. I watched many different players and noticed they were all doing the same basic movements.</p>
<p>Just in case it’s not clear, you want to put a massive amount of topspin on the ball when you hit a second serve. This will allow you to hit faster second serves with much more margin for error.</p>
<p>Topspin will cause the ball to dip into the service box and make it “jump” off the ground. When it jumps (or kicks as tennis people say) the ball will rise higher off the bounce. This makes it a much more difficult shot to return for your opponent.</p>
<div class="pullquote-center">
<p>A quick story for you. When I first started playing, I was trying to learn the topspin serve but not so successfully. I hit a bad second serve to my friend, Eric, who was my perennial hitting partner. Eric was a real comedian and loved to joke. Anyway, I asked him if my serve was kicking. He responded, &#8220;Man that f*%# wasn’t even walking!&#8221; I laughed pretty hard when he said that&#8230; Alright back to our tutorial.</p>
</div>
<p>Now, I narrowed the movements of the second serve down to five key takeaways. These are pretty much all must-dos to hit an effective second serve in tennis. Here they are.</p>
<div class="hrule clearfix" style="background:#81d742; height:1px"></div>
<ol>
<li><a href="#toss">The toss needs to be over the head</a></li>
<li><a href="#shoulders">The shoulders need to rotate more</a></li>
<li><a href="#racket-drop">The racket must have a full drop to achieve spin on the ball</a></li>
<li><a href="#ball">The ball needs to be struck below the apex</a></li>
<li><a href="#swing-path">The swing path and chest are directed to the side – not the front</a></li>
</ol>
<div class="hrule clearfix" style="background:#81d742; height:1px"></div>
These are the five mechanical keys that all professional players use to hit their second serves. Any deviations will result in a less-than-great second serve.</p>
<p>If you understand the mechanics of the tennis second serve, you’ll at least know how to hit it. Even if you can’t do it right away, you can begin to take the steps that will get you to a place where you can.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>Being a club player, trust me when I tell you that even today, I need to think of these mechanics when I hit my second serve. These movements are not intuitive or just come naturally to me.</p>
<blockquote><p>I believe the second serve is the most difficult shot to teach in tennis. It’s something you either get or you don’t. You can either do it or not. There is little in-between with the second serve.</p></blockquote>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Preparation</h2>
<p>At this point in my life, I must have taught and played more than several hundred club players. It always fascinates me when I see a very good club player unable to hit a real second serve.</p>
<p>But every time I do, it lends credence to my theory that players either can hit a second serve or they can’t. Those who can’t, either never learned, don’t understand the mechanics, or tried but gave up.</p>
<p>If the second serve has been the weak point in your game, then allow me to help you see the light. You’ll then be free to swing as fast as you want, generate a ton of spin, and keep the ball in the court.</p>
<p>If you could learn a great second serve, imagine how much pressure it would take off your first serve? It would free you up to go for the gusto on the first without worries.</p>
<p>By the way, I assume you’ll be using a continental grip every step of the way in this tutorial. If you have a waiter’s serve with an eastern forehand grip, get ready to throw your waiter’s tray away. Yup, just chuck it in the garbage – no waiter’s tray serves here!</p>
<p>You’ll absolutely need to use the <a href="/beginners-serve-vs-advanced-tennis-serve-what-are-the-differences/">continental grip</a> for these five keys to work for you. Yeah, it’s a big change for some of you. But you can do it – I know you can.</p>
<p>Alright, enough chatter. Let’s get into the nitty-gritty of the second serve and break down the mechanics in more detail. Stay with me. This post is going to be a game-changer for you!</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="toss"></a></p>
<h2>The Toss Needs To Be Over The Head</h2>
</div>
<p>Most of you are used to tossing to your side. That won’t cut it for the second serve so get ready to make some changes in your toss.</p>
<p>The toss is usually a problem for weak club players and beginners. We use our non-dominant hand to toss, so we don’t have the same level of control as our primary hand.</p>
<p>This is only in the beginning though. If you practice your toss thousands of times, it begins to feel completely natural.</p>
<p>Many of the kids I teach have a lot of issues with the toss because they’re new players and hardly ever practice it. The same can be said for adults.</p>
<p>If you never practice your toss and it’s not very accurate, I highly suggest you isolate the toss and practice it alone for a while. I wrote an <a href="/how-to-have-a-reliable-serve-toss-in-tennis/">entire blog post</a> on it with pictures and videos. Check it out if you need help on the toss.</p>
<p>If you can’t toss accurately, then I’m afraid your serve will always suffer. For the second serve, the toss needs to be accurately placed over your head in order to spin the ball.</p>
<p>The location we aim for on the serve toss is above the head. If you’re a righty, you’ll want to toss the ball around your right ear. If the ball drifts a few inches more to your left, you’ll still be okay. But a few inches to the right of the ear will not work for spin.</p>
<p>For this reason, it’s vital you practice your toss for at least 5-10 minutes during each practice session. I like the toss and catch drill. You’ll toss the ball, keep your tossing hand up, and catch the ball without bending the arm.</p>
<p>For the first serve, we catch the ball a bit out to our right. But the for the second serve, you’ll be catching the ball more over your head.</p>
<p>Tossing the ball over your head may not make sense to you right now. That’s okay. It’s most likely because you lack the correct fundamentals in the other parts of your serve.</p>
<p>We’ll go over those in this post and then it’ll all make sense. Just keep practicing your toss. Make sure the ball is going over your head. This is the only location from which we can put topspin on the ball.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="shoulders"></a></p>
<h2>The Shoulders Need To Rotate More</h2>
</div>
<p>In order to put spin on the ball, your shoulders need to rotate further away from the court than you’re probably used to. I would say 90 degrees is the minimum. This would have your chest facing completely to the side.</p>
<p>By turning more, it’s easier for the racket to brush on the ball when it makes contact. And more brush equals more spin. Trust me, it works.</p>
<p>To understand this, look at the pictures here. I also made a video going through all these steps, so it’s clearly spelled out. It’s essential we have more shoulder turn on the second serve than the first serve for it to work.</p>
<p>I know it’s going to feel awkward to many of you. If it does, turn only slightly more than you usually do. Practice that at least a hundred times.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>As that becomes comfortable, you can rotate a bit more and then repeat. Eventually, you’ll reach a point where your shoulders are in a position to hit a good second serve.</p>
<p>If you want to see a great example of extreme shoulder rotation, look at Pete Sampras’s second serve. It’s one of the highest degrees of rotation of any player I studied.</p>
<p>So let’s recap. You’re going to have a continental grip. Your toss will be over your right ear (if you’re a righty – lefties do the opposite of everything mentioned in this post). And you’re going to rotate your shoulders further away from the court than you usually do.</p>
<p>Practice doing only these two steps for now: the toss and shoulder rotation. Put them together and do at least 100 reps. Once completed, move on to the next step.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="racket-drop"></a></p>
<h2>The Racket Must Have A Full Drop To Achieve Spin</h2>
</div>
<p>You might be confused by what I mean here. I’ll explain, but the video I made will make it crystal clear, so watch that too.</p>
<p>After hitting the “<strong>trophy pose</strong>” your racket needs to completely invert so that the tip of the racket is pointed downward. Most coaches call this the “<strong>racket drop</strong>”.</p>
<p>This is not something done slowly or unevenly. It needs to happen in one smooth motion. You’ll go from trophy pose, to complete racket drop, to swinging up into the ball. This is one continuous motion.</p>
<p>If you have a waiter’s serve, this is going to be quite a drastic change for you. I would recommend you watch my video How to Achieve A Tennis Racquet Drop and Pronate The Correct Way</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="kad-youtube-shortcode videofit"  ><iframe loading="lazy" width="600" height="400" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/yvL5mXGEkuo?autoplay=0&controls=1&fs=1&modestbranding=1&theme=dark&rel=0&loop=0&showinfo=1" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="true"></iframe></div>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>This video will help you understand the racket drop and how to do it. If you don’t have a deep racket drop, you can forget about hitting a second serve with topspin – it ain’t going to happen.</p>
<p>For some of you, it could take days, weeks, or even months of practice to get your racket drop to a level good enough it hit a second serve. Tennis is a game of technique and one skill builds upon another. Hopefully, this is something you get and can do without much work.</p>
<p>I’m going to assume you have a nice, deep racket drop, so I can go on. Now, the racket drop is hugely important because it allows us to hit the second serve from low to high, which is how we generate topspin on the ball in tennis.</p>
<p>It’s very similar to groundstrokes. You swing low to high to produce topspin, right? Well, it’s the same principle on the second serve in tennis.</p>
<p>By executing all the fundamentals of the serve correctly (toss, shoulder rotation, racket drop), we automatically set ourselves up to hit a great topspin second serve.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="ball"></a></p>
<h2>The Ball Needs To Be Struck Lower Than The Apex</h2>
</div>
<p>One of the main differences between the first and second serve in tennis is where we contact the ball with the racket. On the first serve, we usually hit the ball at the apex of the arm and racket.</p>
<p>Anyone can hit the ball at the apex with little or no spin – even a beginner. This is the reason why players with a waiter’s serve can hit good first serves – but not great serves mind you.</p>
<p>But on the second serve we don’t want to hit the ball at the apex of our arm and racket. Instead, we make contact slightly lower – around 8-12 inches lower.</p>
<p>This allows us to make contact from underneath the ball instead of straight on, as we do on the first serve. On the second serve it’s vital you “hit up on the ball”.</p>
<p>I know you’ve probably heard that phrase before, especially if you’re a veteran player. But it’s true. I really do feel like I hit up on the ball when I hit a great second serve.</p>
<p>This is a key point to understand for hitting massive spin. By striking the ball below the apex, we will automatically provide spin to the ball.</p>
<p>I understand this may be a difficult concept to execute &#8211; at first. I definitely had trouble with it when I was learning the second serve.</p>
<p>It’s kind of like riding a bike. You either can or you can’t. Once you can, you’ll always be able to hit a second serve. This is one of the most important parts of this entire tutorial.</p>
<p>The way I instruct my students to get this part of the serve right is to ask them to wait for a second longer to hit the ball. You need to let the ball drop (on the toss) to put spin on the ball.</p>
<p>I also have them do a drill where they hold the ball with their left hand and use the racket (in their right hand) to brush the ball back and forth. This is not a hitting drill, but more of an exercise that helps them feel what it’s like to brush on the ball.</p>
<p>To summarize and make clear, let the ball drop longer on the second serve than you’re used to. If you hit the ball at the apex, like you do on first serves, you won’t be able to put topspin on the ball.</p>
<p>I hope this is sinking in. For this reason, it’s utterly important you develop a deep racket drop and hit the ball lower than the apex of the toss.</p>
<p>If you combine this with a well-placed toss and proper shoulder rotation, you’re well on your way to hitting a great second serve.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="swing-path"></a></p>
<h2>The Swing Path And Chest Are Directed To The Side – Not The Front</h2>
</div>
<p>What do I mean by this? First, your chest needs to remain facing the right side of the court while swinging (lefties face left). This is vital to hitting with spin on the second serve.</p>
<p>I see a lot of people execute the first four steps correct only to open too soon. By opening, I mean facing the court. Players open too soon because they’re so used to doing it on the first serve. This is a crucial mistake.</p>
<p>On the first serve, since we’re directing our energy into the court and behind the ball, it’s perfectly fine to turn the chest into the court a lot more. But on the second serve it’s essential to remain facing the side while hitting the ball.</p>
<p>Now you may be wondering why it looks like the professional players face the court when hitting their second serves. They’re actually not. Look at their second serves in super slow motion and you’ll notice when they contact the ball (and for split seconds afterwards) they’re still facing the side.</p>
<p>It’s only after the entire swing has been completed and the ball is 10-15 feet away that the player allows him or herself to rotate into the court. It’s natural to want to rotate into the court to see what’s going on.</p>
<p>Doing so allows the player to see the court and finish the serve in a position where they can reset. Bottom line here is to stay to the side while you swing.</p>
<p>Look, we need the racket to brush on the ball. If you see the racket face from a head-on perspective and a side perspective, it’s obvious only the latter will allow for spin.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>Now that we cleared that up, let’s talk about swing path. By staying to the side, your swing path “should” automatically finish out to your side – right side for righties and left side for lefties.</p>
<p>On the first serve, everyone swings forward, directing their arm into the court. However, on the second serve the arm will move to the side and not directly into the court.</p>
<p>This is another awkward change beginner and lower level players need to make on the second serve. I find a lot of people have trouble with this one. But it’s the final part of the serve.</p>
<p>If you stay to the side and don’t open up early, this shouldn’t be an issue. Your swing path will naturally direct to the side. However, open up even a bit too soon, and it could cause your swing path to deviate into the court.</p>
<p>If this happens, you’ll lose topspin on the ball. So stay to the side and swing out to the side. This is an easy concept to understand but can be a difficult one to execute – at least at first.</p>
<p>Keep practicing this. I would suggest practicing your serve without a ball. Just go through the whole second serve motion, putting these five steps together.</p>
<p>Once you do that dozens or hundreds of times, take a ball and try the entire serve. If you still can’t get it, try tossing the ball far from you and still complete the whole second serve motion.</p>
<p>This will take pressure off hitting the ball and allow you to focus only on the serve motion. Additionally, serve training aids like the ServeMaster will help you too.</p>
<h2></h2>
<h2>Conclusion</h2>
<p>For some of you, maybe most of you, the second serve in tennis will require you to dramatically change your serve mechanics. It’s going to feel awkward and you’re going to miss a ton of serves.</p>
<p>But I urge you to stay with it. Focus more on the process than the results at this stage.</p>
<p>Watching the video I made will definitely help. Think about the concept of the second serve. If you understand the concept, it makes it easier to hit as well.</p>
<p>Lastly, don’t take any shortcuts. Make sure you go through all the steps, one-by-one, in this post and the video.</p>
<p>Believe me, I used to be super-envious of players with great second serves. It was like they were magicians and the second serve was a trick I’d never learn.</p>
<p>But I did learn it and so can you. It’s a great feeling when you can hit a strong topspin second serve that wins the point easily. It also just feels great having a serve where players can’t tee off on you.</p>
<p>If you have any questions about the second serve, just ask me. If you want to send me a video of your second serve, and I have the time, I’ll give you some pointers on it.</p>
<p>Best thing to do is use <a href="https://wetransfer.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">wetransfer.com</a> (it’s free) and send it to my email address.</p>
<p>Thanks for reading and good luck.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Next Up:</h2>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div id="attachment_879" style="width: 310px" class="wp-caption alignleft"><a href="/10-common-second-serve-issues-and-how-to-fix-them/"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-879" class="size-medium wp-image-879" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/catapult-300x169.jpg" alt="10 Common Second Serve Issues And How To Fix Them" width="300" height="169" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/catapult-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/catapult-768x432.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/catapult-562x316.jpg 562w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/catapult-520x292.jpg 520w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/catapult-260x146.jpg 260w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/catapult.jpg 800w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-879" class="wp-caption-text">10 Common Second Serve Issues And How To Fix Them</p></div>
<p>The post <a href="/how-to-hit-a-second-serve-in-tennis/">How To Hit A Second Serve In Tennis</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/how-to-hit-a-second-serve-in-tennis/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>How To Have A Reliable Serve Toss In Tennis</title>
		<link>/how-to-have-a-reliable-serve-toss-in-tennis/</link>
					<comments>/how-to-have-a-reliable-serve-toss-in-tennis/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chad Walner]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 28 Nov 2018 12:44:44 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Training]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[serve]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1441</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The serve toss in tennis gives many players problems. This is because it is accomplished with the nondominant hand and is an unnatural motion. Furthermore, the toss needs to be placed in a certain location to hit the ball. If &#8230; <a class="kt-excerpt-readmore" href="/how-to-have-a-reliable-serve-toss-in-tennis/" aria-label="How To Have A Reliable Serve Toss In Tennis">Read More</a></p>
<p>The post <a href="/how-to-have-a-reliable-serve-toss-in-tennis/">How To Have A Reliable Serve Toss In Tennis</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><strong>The serve toss in tennis gives many players problems. This is because it is accomplished with the nondominant hand and is an unnatural motion. </strong></p>
<p><strong>Furthermore, the toss needs to be placed in a certain location to hit the ball. If you cannot toss accurately, you cannot serve, period. You can have the best service motion in the world and it won’t make a difference.</strong></p>
<p>For this reason, the serve toss is of critical importance on the serve. Most coaches and players don’t emphasize it enough, focusing on other aspects of the tennis serve instead.</p>
<p>To have a reliable serve toss, we need to focus on the following components.</p>
<ol>
<li><a href="#holding"><strong>Holding the ball in the correct manner</strong></a></li>
<li><a href="#starting"><strong>Starting the toss from the proper position</strong></a></li>
<li><a href="#keeping"><strong>Keeping the tossing arm straight</strong></a></li>
<li><a href="#moving"><strong>Moving the tossing arm in the correct direction at a medium pace</strong></a></li>
<li><a href="#releasing"><strong>Releasing the ball at the right height</strong></a></li>
<li><a href="#tossing"><strong>Tossing the ball to the proper height</strong></a></li>
<li><a href="#leaving"><strong>Leaving the tossing arm and hand in the air until the swing initiates</strong></a></li>
</ol>
<p>Do these seven components correctly, and you’re guaranteed of a great service toss every time. If even one of these components is not carried out correctly, the toss placement will be sacrificed.</p>
<p>I will go over each component in this post. Before we are done, I’ll give you three tossing drills you can do to practice your toss on or off the court.</p>
<p>If the toss is something that has been troubling your serve read on. If you’re new to tennis and want to know the best way to toss on the serve, read on as well.</p>
<div class="kad-youtube-shortcode videofit"  ><iframe loading="lazy" width="600" height="400" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/F9qslEzIQJU?autoplay=0&controls=1&fs=1&modestbranding=1&theme=dark&rel=0&loop=0&showinfo=1" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="true"></iframe></div>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="holding"></a></p>
<h2>Holding The Ball In The Correct Manner</h2>
</div>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1452" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/1.jpg" alt="How to hold the tennis ball." width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/1.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/11/1-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/11/1-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p>The best way to hold a tennis ball during your serve toss is in the fingertips. You should never let your palm touch the tennis ball.</p>
<p>If your palm touches the tennis ball, you won’t have as much control. All great servers toss from the fingertips.</p>
<p>You don’t need to squeeze the ball too tightly or hold it too loose. Just a medium squeeze is fine. I like to use all five fingertips to hold the ball.</p>
<p>It’s very important that you keep the hand and wrist allotted in the same position during the toss. The position of the hand and wrist will be the same at the beginning and end of the toss.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="starting"></a></p>
<h2>Starting The Toss From The Proper Position</h2>
</div>
<p>Once you set your feet in the proper position and align your shoulders away from the net, you’ll be ready to start the serve and the toss. I’ll assume everyone is right-handed. If you’re a lefty, do the opposite.</p>
<p>Start with your left arm (the tossing arm) at your left thigh. The back of your hand should rest on your thigh, with the ball in your fingertips, like we mentioned in step 1.</p>
<p>Some players like to start with the hand on the inner thigh. Some start from more directly on the thigh. And some players start their toss a few inches off the thigh.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>If you feel more comfortable starting a few inches off the thigh, that’s fine. As long as your arm is perfectly straight at this point, you’ll be in a good position to make a great serve.</p>
<p>I teach beginners and children to start from the thigh because it’s easier to toss from a fixed object then in the air. However, I typically start a few inches off the thigh myself and make accurate tosses, so it can work as well.</p>
<p>When you begin the toss, keep your arm loose and resist tightening up your muscles. Breath and visualize the perfect toss.</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="keeping"></a></p>
<h2>Keeping The Tossing Arm Straight</h2>
</div>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1453" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/2.jpg" alt="Keeping the tossing arm straight." width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/2.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/11/2-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/11/2-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p>The tossing arm (your left arm) must be kept straight through the duration of the toss. This means from the beginning at the thigh until the arm is fully outstretched over your head.</p>
<p>If the arm bends at any point before the ball is released, this will almost ensure you never toss accurately. If the arm bends after the ball is released, the toss can still be made accurately, but it’s poor technique and doesn’t look good.</p>
<p>I see a lot of players bend their arms right after releasing the ball. You can get away with it if you’ve been playing a while and have practiced your toss hundreds or thousands of times.</p>
<p>But if you’re a new player, or trying to correct your toss, why not just keep your arm straight until the swing is initiated, like the pros do? It may seem uncomfortable at first, but with enough practice, it will feel more natural.</p>
<p>Practice tossing with a straight arm for many reps (at least 100). I would suggest not even using a ball at first. Just get the feeling of what it’s like to move your arm completely straight from your thigh to straight above your head.</p>
<p>Once it begins to feel natural, you can add the ball and toss it. Have someone watch your toss, or video yourself, to make sure you are not bending your arm.</p>
<p>Keeping a straight arm throughout the toss is the distinguishing characteristic of an excellent service motion. Remember, it’s absolutely crucial not to bend the arm before the hand releases the ball.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="moving"></a></p>
<h2>Moving The Tossing Arm In The Correct Direction At A Medium Pace</h2>
</div>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1454" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/3.jpg" alt="Explaining the speed of the tossing arm." width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/3.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/11/3-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/11/3-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p>Now that you know how to hold the ball, the ideal place to start the toss, and that you need to keep your arm straight, in what direction does the arm move?</p>
<p>While there is no one right direction, I am going to suggest a 45-degree angle from the baseline. The extremes would be tossing parallel to the baseline or tossing directly out in front of your body.</p>
<p>My recommendation is to toss right in the middle of those two extremes. This would have the arm raise in alignment with the right net post.<br />
I find this best in my own toss, and my students, because it allows the ball to travel in front and to the right of us. This is where we want the ball to be – in about the one o’clock position to our head.</p>
<p>You can use the right net post as your guide. Simply raise your arm in that direction. The next part is knowing at what speed to raise our arm.<br />
Most people move the tossing arm way too fast. If you do that, you certainly won’t control the ball. If the tossing arm is raised too slowly, then the ball will not have enough lift.</p>
<p>The solution is to toss in the middle, at a medium pace. After the ball leaves your hand, you’ll want the apex of the toss to be about twice your height. For that to happen, your arm needs to be moving at the correct speed.</p>
<p>Only you can judge this speed. If the ball is going to low, you’ll need to move your arm faster. If the ball is too high, you’ll need to move it slower.</p>
<p>We’ll talk about how to find the ideal height on the toss soon. For now, know it’s about twice your height. So if you’re 6 feet tall, you’ll want to toss close to 12 feet in the air.</p>
<p>Practice tossing until you begin to hit the right height. Sometimes the right height is determined by your swing.</p>
<p>Abbreviated servers can toss lower while players with long sweeping service motions usually need to toss higher (as they need more time to complete their serve motion).</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="releasing"></a></p>
<h2>Releasing The Ball At The Right Height</h2>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1469" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/tossRelasing-The-Ball-At-The-Right-Height.jpg" alt="Releasing the ball at the right height." width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/tossRelasing-The-Ball-At-The-Right-Height.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/11/tossRelasing-The-Ball-At-The-Right-Height-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/11/tossRelasing-The-Ball-At-The-Right-Height-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
</div>
<p>At this point all the fundamentals are in place for a great serve toss. You may be wondering the best position to release the ball on the toss? It’s the top of your head.</p>
<p>Most professional tennis players release the serve toss right near top of head height. This seems to be the best place to achieve an accurate serve toss. This is where I release my serve toss too.</p>
<p>If you release the ball lower or higher than top of head height, you will diminish your chances of tossing accurately. You can probably get away with a few inches difference, but any more is running a risk.</p>
<p>It’s best to release the ball at the same height on every serve toss. If you can cut down on randomness on the toss, it will make the toss exponentially better.</p>
<p>I look at serve toss as a science. If we can perform the same action over and over in the same manner, we should get the same result. Good fundamentals equal a good serve toss.</p>
<p>One thing more here. When we release the ball, the ball should still be in the fingertips. Simply open your hand when releasing the ball. It should look like a flower opening its pedals.</p>
<p>Keep your arm and hand pointed in the same direction through the duration of the toss. Resist turning the hand or wrist. It is unnecessary and harmful to do.</p>
<p>This might seem like a lot of information for a simple toss, but the devil is in the details. I just want to make sure you know all of the specifics.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="tossing"></a></p>
<h2>Tossing The Ball To The Proper Height</h2>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1476" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/How-To-Have-A-Reliable-Serve-Toss-In-Tennis-Serve-and-Volley-Tennis.jpg" alt="Toss to about twice your height." width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/How-To-Have-A-Reliable-Serve-Toss-In-Tennis-Serve-and-Volley-Tennis.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/11/How-To-Have-A-Reliable-Serve-Toss-In-Tennis-Serve-and-Volley-Tennis-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/11/How-To-Have-A-Reliable-Serve-Toss-In-Tennis-Serve-and-Volley-Tennis-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
</div>
<p>As I already mentioned, tossing to twice your body height is a good place to target for the apex of the toss. One good way to find that point is to toss near an object (like a fence) that is around twice your height.</p>
<p>In my serve toss video, you can see me doing that next to a fence. The fence post will also serve as a good guide for where your arm and the ball should be moving along.</p>
<p>Everyone’s serve motion is different. Some people need more time to hit the ball and others need less. Only you can decide that for yourself.<br />
Once you have developed your service motion and can hit a serve, you’ll have a good idea if you need to toss higher or lower – or maybe the apex of the toss is just right.</p>
<p>If you feel rushed to hit the ball, you’re likely tossing too low and need to toss a bit higher. On the inverse, if it seems like you are stalling out momentum in the trophy pose, you might be tossing too high. In this case, tossing lower might be better for you.</p>
<p>Videoing your serve is a great way to determine the best tossing height for you. A good coach can also help with this. Even an experienced, advanced level player would have good insight on this.</p>
<p>If you feel your toss is not ideal, keep tweaking the apex of your toss until your serve motion is fluid and you don’t feel rushed. Everyone gets it in time, so keep practicing.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="leaving"></a></p>
<h2>Leaving The Tossing Arm Up</h2>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1470" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/tossKeep-The-Tossing-Arm-Up.jpg" alt="Keep the tossing arm up." width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/tossKeep-The-Tossing-Arm-Up.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/11/tossKeep-The-Tossing-Arm-Up-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/11/tossKeep-The-Tossing-Arm-Up-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
</div>
<p>Once the ball leaves the hand, the arm should continue rising until it is straight over your head, as high as you can extend it. If you watch the best professional players with the best serves (Roger Federer, Kevin Anderson, John Isner), you’ll see them keep their tossing arm high up in the air until the swing initiates.</p>
<p>I would say 75-80% of the recreational players I see drop the tossing arm too quickly during the serve. While players can get away with this and still hit a good serve, it will affect the service motion negatively to a degree.</p>
<p>There’s a reason why the top servers leave their tossing arm up in the air that long. If it works for them, we should model their technique and do the same.</p>
<p>It may feel unnatural at first, but again, with practice it will feel more natural. You only drop the tossing arm when the swing begins.<br />
At that point, the tossing arm will bend and retract to the left side of the body. You’ll want to keep the tossing arm close to the body, so the right arm and racket can move past it at the completion of the swing.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="hrule clearfix" style=" height:1px"></div>
<div class="pullquote-center">
<h3>Use these three drills to nail down your serve toss consistency</h3>
</div>
<div class="hrule clearfix" style=" height:1px"></div>
<h2><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1467" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/tossUse-These-Three-Drills2.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/tossUse-These-Three-Drills2.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/11/tossUse-These-Three-Drills2-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/11/tossUse-These-Three-Drills2-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></h2>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Toss Drill # 1 – Toss And Catch</h2>
<p>In this drill, you’ll set up in the proper serve stance with a tennis ball. This drill can be done anywhere you have the room to toss.<br />
You can do it at the tennis court, in your home, your backyard or anywhere outdoors. All you need is one tennis ball; a racket is not needed but you can hold one in your dominant hand if you want.</p>
<p>Toss the ball utilizing all the fundamentals we’ve talked about. After the toss is made, keep your tossing arm fully extended to the sky and catch the ball when it drops.</p>
<p>You do not swing your racket in this drill. You’re simply tossing and catching the ball with your tossing arm. But your tossing arm remains fully extended in the air on the catch.</p>
<p>This drill helps with two aspect of the toss. First, it helps you keep your tossing arm extended. Second, it helps with toss accuracy, as you must toss in the same location to catch the ball.</p>
<p>It’s okay to move your arm slightly to catch the ball. But resist turning your hand or wrist, moving your feet, or bending your arm at any point during the drill.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Toss Drill # 2 – Meet Me At The Apex</h2>
<p>In this drill, you’ll toss a ball to the perfect apex, which is around twice your height. You’ll need to set up by a fence or object that is twice your height. All you need is one tennis ball.</p>
<p>Simply toss the ball and make sure it is close to the high object. You do not swing at the ball or go into your service motion. It’s only a tossing drill.<br />
At first it can be challenging. But slowly you should see steady improvement in toss accuracy.</p>
<p>This drill is effective because it gives you a great visual of how high the toss should be and where it should be. I like to do this drill next to a fence, along one of the posts.</p>
<p>I mentioned this drill earlier in the blog post and made a video on it. It’s a drill I have all my students do who need help with the serve toss.<br />
You have the option of catching the ball high (like in drill #1) or letting the ball drop. But you should keep the tossing hand extended throughout the drill.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Drill #3 – Trap The Ball Drill</h2>
<p>In this serve toss drill, you’ll need a fence that is at least 4-5 feet taller than yourself. Go over to the fence and set up as if you were going to serve towards it.</p>
<p>You’ll want to be close to the fence, so your lead foot should only be about a foot away. You’ll need a racket and one tennis ball.</p>
<p>Toss the ball as you normally would, doing all the fundamentals we discussed. Then initiate the serve motion and swing your racket into the ball.</p>
<p>You’ll want to swing less than 100% speed. The point of this drill is to trap the ball between your racket and the fence with your right arm extended to the ideal height.</p>
<p>Your right arm should be fully extended during the trap, but not directly over your head. It should be a bit out to the side, at about the one o’clock position.</p>
<p>Once you trap the ball, let it down, and begin the next rep in the same way. The point of this drill is to find the correct height to hit the toss.<br />
This is a great drill to do for kids. While it doesn’t directly improve the toss, it does help give a great visual for how high the toss needs to be in order to extend the right hitting arm up to contact.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Summary</h2>
<p>Go through all the steps I outlined in this post. These are the same steps all the top servers do.</p>
<p>Then put them all together and practice your serve toss at least a hundred times 3-4 times per week for the next 2-3 weeks. I guarantee you’ll see positive results after that time if you do the reps.</p>
<p>Most people never improve their toss because they don’t follow the fundamentals. Even if they know them, they don’t practice them or their tosses.<br />
You can add the serve toss drills to fast-track your progress. By being one of the few who practice your toss, you’ll fly past your competition in terms of toss accuracy and serve quality.</p>
<p>Once you feel comfortable and have the toss down pat, you can forget about it and focus more on your serve motion. Building the perfect serve is a step-by-step process and takes time.</p>
<p>But it need not take you more than a few weeks to develop a great serve toss. I hope you actually follow my advice, use the information I provided, and practice.</p>
<p>If you have any questions for me, leave them in the comment section below. I’ll be glad to answer them for you.</p>
<p>The post <a href="/how-to-have-a-reliable-serve-toss-in-tennis/">How To Have A Reliable Serve Toss In Tennis</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/how-to-have-a-reliable-serve-toss-in-tennis/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>3</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>5 Steps To A Great Tennis Serve For Beginners With Pics And Video</title>
		<link>/5-steps-to-a-great-tennis-serve-for-beginners-with-pics-and-video/</link>
					<comments>/5-steps-to-a-great-tennis-serve-for-beginners-with-pics-and-video/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chad Walner]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 18 Nov 2018 07:33:57 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Theory]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[serve]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1354</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>For any level player, the serve is the most complicated shot in tennis. This is especially true for beginners. This is because the serve requires a complex series of movements executed with precision timing in a matter of seconds. It’s &#8230; <a class="kt-excerpt-readmore" href="/5-steps-to-a-great-tennis-serve-for-beginners-with-pics-and-video/" aria-label="5 Steps To A Great Tennis Serve For Beginners With Pics And Video">Read More</a></p>
<p>The post <a href="/5-steps-to-a-great-tennis-serve-for-beginners-with-pics-and-video/">5 Steps To A Great Tennis Serve For Beginners With Pics And Video</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>For any level player, the serve is the most complicated shot in tennis. This is especially true for beginners.</p>
<p>This is because the serve requires a complex series of movements executed with precision timing in a matter of seconds. It’s the only shot in tennis where you have control from start to finish.</p>
<p>All other shots are started by your opponent and finished by you. For that reason, the serve is a special shot and often requires long periods of time to master.</p>
<p><strong>An advanced serve that can be hit over 100 mph, can take years to learn. As a beginner in tennis, you likely don’t want to spend years learning the serve.</strong></p>
<p><strong>Never fear! Follow the 5 step plan below which will show you exactly how you can learn a beginner serve in tennis.</strong></p>
<p><strong>I call this the abbreviated serve motion. It’s actually not a total beginner’s serve. It’s a shortened version of an advanced serve. If you’re going to learn to serve in tennis, might as well do it right, don’t you agree? These steps will show you how to actually serve in tennis, and build a foundation that you can use immediately or that you can build on.</strong></p>
<p>In this post, you’ll find pictures that illustrate the various steps to take. I also made a video that clearly demonstrates the steps.</p>
<p>These steps make it easier to learn the serve. Think of them like checkpoints to make sure you’re serving correctly.</p>
<p>In order to learn this serve, we need to follow 5 basic steps. They are:</p>
<ol>
<li>Set up in the ideal serve stance with the ideal serving grip.</li>
<li>Position our hitting arm in the perfect place to begin the serve.</li>
<li>Toss the ball in a spot we can hit with the racket.</li>
<li>Swing up to contact.</li>
<li>Follow through in the ideal position.</li>
</ol>
<p>These 5 steps can be learned quickly if you are coordinated and practice them. Even if you’re not athletic or coordinated, don’t worry. You can still learn to serve but it may take a bit more practice.</p>
<p>The most difficult part of learning to serve in tennis is putting all the steps together into one fluid motion. The second most difficult part is contacting the ball at the ideal location and time.</p>
<p>However, if you follow the 5 simple steps I outline here, you’ll be well on your way to serving and playing tennis.</p>
<p>Whether you’re a total beginner or an intermediate player with a subpar serve, this program will work if you give it a chance. So let’s get started.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="video-container"><iframe class="size-full aligncenter" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/wqDXwBvpg8Q?rel=0&amp;modestbranding=1&amp;" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen"></iframe></div>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Step 1 – The Ideal Serve Stance and Serve Grip</h2>
<div id="attachment_1421" style="width: 810px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1421" class="size-full wp-image-1421" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/stance.jpg" alt="Use the Platform Stance for our advanced beginners serve." width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/stance.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/11/stance-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/11/stance-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /><p id="caption-attachment-1421" class="wp-caption-text">Use the Platform Stance for your advanced beginners serve.</p></div>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>In order to hit a good tennis serve, we need to set up properly. All great servers set up in the same way on every service motion. This routine makes it a lot easier to serve consistently.</strong></p>
<p>Additionally, it positions our body and hand in the correct positions to achieve maximum leverage and power into the ball.</p>
<p>We’ll start with the feet first. I am going to assume everyone is right-handed. If you are a lefty, perform the opposite actions.</p>
<p>Your left foot is going to be positioned close to the baseline at a 45-degree angle. The toe should be pointed to the right net post.</p>
<p>The right foot is to be set parallel to the baseline and 6-10 inches behind the left foot. The toe of the right foot should be in line with the heel of the left.</p>
<p>Setting up in this position will orient your shoulders away from the court and to the right. This is exactly where we want them. It will provide us with torque and power on the serve.</p>
<p>The serving hand will be in the continental grip. This is also known as the hammer grip. The index finger knuckle will be on the second bevel of the racket. If possible, move the index finger slightly away from middle finger. See picture and video for visuals.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<blockquote><p>By using the continental grip, we can achieve pronation and get more power on the serve. The continental grip is the same grip used by all the top professional players. Don’t you feel special now?</p></blockquote>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Congratulations, you’ve completed step 1. That wasn’t so difficult, right? It gets a little more difficult as we proceed, so brace yourself.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Step 2 – Position Hitting Arm</h2>

<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/Position-Hitting-Arm-1.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="450" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/Position-Hitting-Arm-1.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/Position-Hitting-Arm-1.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/11/Position-Hitting-Arm-1-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/11/Position-Hitting-Arm-1-768x432.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/11/Position-Hitting-Arm-1-732x412.jpg 732w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/11/Position-Hitting-Arm-1-366x206.jpg 366w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></a>
<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/Position-Hitting-Arm-2.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="450" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/Position-Hitting-Arm-2.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/Position-Hitting-Arm-2.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/11/Position-Hitting-Arm-2-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/11/Position-Hitting-Arm-2-768x432.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/11/Position-Hitting-Arm-2-732x412.jpg 732w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/11/Position-Hitting-Arm-2-366x206.jpg 366w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></a>
<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/Position-Hitting-Arm-3.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="450" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/Position-Hitting-Arm-3.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/Position-Hitting-Arm-3.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/11/Position-Hitting-Arm-3-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/11/Position-Hitting-Arm-3-768x432.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/11/Position-Hitting-Arm-3-732x412.jpg 732w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/11/Position-Hitting-Arm-3-366x206.jpg 366w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></a>

<p>This is a very easy step. It will only take a few seconds to learn and do. I could have combined it with step 1 but decided to make it separate. Small chunks equal easier learning.</p>
<p><strong>Once we’re set up in our ideal serve stance and grip, we’re going to position our hitting arm (the one holding the racket), into an “L” shape behind our body.</strong></p>
<p>The “L” shape is akin to a throwing motion. You’ll see baseball and football players assuming the same motion with their arms before throwing a ball.</p>
<p>The angle of the arm should be 45-75 degrees to the forearm. I like to keep my arm more at a 45-50-degree angle. It’s really a personal preference.</p>
<p>Your upper arm should be almost parallel to the ground. Your shoulders will be in line with the hitting hand behind your head; not to the side.</p>
<p>This is important. The palm of your hitting hand will be facing to the right, or away from you.</p>
<p>Hold the racket with a medium firmness grip. If you hold the racket too hard, it will cause too much tension in your muscles and severely reduce power.</p>
<p>We need to be fluid on the serve. For that reason, don’t worry about the results (where the ball goes) in the beginning.</p>
<p>For now, and the following steps, focus on just hitting the ball with solid contact. Alright, we’re ready for step 3.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Step 3 – The Serve Toss</h2>

<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/toss1.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="400" height="363" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/toss1.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/toss1.jpg 400w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/11/toss1-300x272.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" /></a>
<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/toss3.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="400" height="363" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/toss3.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/toss3.jpg 400w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/11/toss3-300x272.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" /></a>

<p>The toss is made with the left hand. Now, since you’re right-handed, this may be a little tough at first. But I assure you it gets easier with practice.</p>
<p><strong>Hold the ball in the fingertips of your left hand. Think of the ball as a fragile egg that can crack. For that reason, never let it touch your palm.</strong></p>
<p>Now place your left arm on or close to your left leg. From here we are going to lift the arm with the palm facing to the right.</p>
<p>When lifting the arm, it’s important not to raise the arm too fast. If you raise too fast, you won’t have any control of the ball and the toss will be inaccurate.</p>
<p>If you raise the arm too slowly, the ball won’t have enough air time once it leaves your hand. As a result, we need to move our arm somewhere in the middle (between slow and fast).</p>
<p>It’s also crucial that you keep your arm completely straight the whole time. As you raise the arm, keep the wrist and hand positioned the same way.</p>
<p>Once the arm reaches top of head height, release the ball by opening your fingers. Upon doing so, keep your wrist and hand in the same position and keep raising your arm until it is fully extended over your head.</p>
<p>The ball should go 5-6 feet above your head on the toss. This will allow enough time for us to swing the racket and comfortably hit with the ball.</p>
<p>The toss should be slightly to our right and slightly in front of our body. I would say 6-8 inches to the right of our body and 8-12 inches in front of us.</p>
<p>Keep in mind we can’t step on or over the baseline during the serve. If you toss to far forward, it could force you to do that.</p>
<p>The key is to toss forward enough to get our body weight into the serve, but not so far that we cross the baseline.</p>
<p>Right after you toss do the following. Keep your eyes up, tilt your shoulders (left shoulder should be higher than right) and bend your knees. This will set you up in a great position for step 4.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h4>Caveat About The Toss</h4>
<p>This step can be the most troublesome for beginners. I often see people struggle heavily with the toss. I find that beginners and intermediate players are divided into two camps with the toss.</p>
<p>Either they get it and the toss is no issue for them. Or, they find the toss to be very difficult and can’t place it in the right spot.</p>
<p>I can tell you right now, if the toss is not somewhere in the ideal spot, you won’t be able to serve.</p>
<p>For that reason, if you fall into the second camp and have trouble with the toss, you’ll need to practice it before moving on.</p>
<p>My suggestion would be to isolate the toss and practice it dozens, or even hundreds, of times until it is right. I have a drill for you in my accompanying video that will help, so check it out.</p>
<p>Hopefully you’ll have no issues with the toss and this will be just another step. Even if you think you toss well, you should work on it every practice session.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Step 4 – Swing To Contact</h2>

<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/swingtocontact1.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="150" height="150" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/swingtocontact1-150x150.jpg" class="attachment-thumbnail size-thumbnail" alt="" /></a>
<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/swingtocontact2.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="150" height="150" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/swingtocontact2-150x150.jpg" class="attachment-thumbnail size-thumbnail" alt="" /></a>
<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/swingtocontact3.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="150" height="150" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/swingtocontact3-150x150.jpg" class="attachment-thumbnail size-thumbnail" alt="" /></a>
<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/swingtocontact4.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="150" height="150" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/swingtocontact4-150x150.jpg" class="attachment-thumbnail size-thumbnail" alt="" /></a>
<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/swingtocontact5x.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="150" height="150" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/swingtocontact5x-150x150.jpg" class="attachment-thumbnail size-thumbnail" alt="" /></a>
<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/swingtocontact6.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="150" height="150" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/swingtocontact6-150x150.jpg" class="attachment-thumbnail size-thumbnail" alt="" /></a>
<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/swingtocontact7.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="150" height="150" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/swingtocontact7-150x150.jpg" class="attachment-thumbnail size-thumbnail" alt="" /></a>
<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/swingtocontact8.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="150" height="150" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/swingtocontact8-150x150.jpg" class="attachment-thumbnail size-thumbnail" alt="" /></a>

<p><strong>As the ball reaches its apex on the toss and begins to drop, that’s when you’ll begin your swing.</strong></p>
<p>The tennis swing can be a little complicated for people not used to a throwing motion. For that reason, we can simulate it with the tennis ServeMaster. This is a tennis aid for the serve.</p>
<p>I’ll get back to it later. For now, we’re going to swing the racket up to the ball using a throwing motion. There are a lot of nuances that go into the swing. I’ll point out a few here and in the video.</p>
<p>For one, a good throwing motion leads with the elbow. Your elbow will actually be traveling to the ball before any other part of your arm. At a certain point in the swing, your hand will overtake the elbow.</p>
<p>When you begin the swing motion the palm of your right hand should be facing away from you. As you initiate the swing, the palm will turn to face you.</p>
<p>Keep your hand in that position as you move the racket up towards the ball. Just before you strike the ball, you’ll pronate your forearm so that the racket impacts the ball head on.</p>
<p>This is a very critical part of the serve. If done right, it will generate a lot of pace with little effort. To get the timing and movements correct, I suggest using the Serve Doctor and the ServeMaster training devices.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h4>The ServeMaster To The Rescue</h4>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1464" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/ServeMaster-To-The-Rescue.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/ServeMaster-To-The-Rescue.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/11/ServeMaster-To-The-Rescue-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/11/ServeMaster-To-The-Rescue-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p>We can use the ServeMaster to simulate the serve motion dozens and dozens of times before we ever try to hit a real serve. This will teach the proper swing path on the serve, including pronation.</p>
<p>Instead of holding a racket, simply substitute with the ServeMaster. If you don’t have one, use a long sock with a couple of tennis balls inside (towards the bottom of the sock).  I like the ServeMaster, and I wrote a <a href="/learn-how-to-serve-in-10-minutes-with-the-servemaster/">full post</a> all about how it helps with the serve.</p>
<p>We can start in step 3 and simply toss an imaginary ball (or a real ball) and practice the swing path with the ServeMaster or sock. If you can video your swing, that would be ideal.</p>
<p>What I like about the ServeMaster is that it has a continental grip on the handle. It’s also good for righties and lefties, plus has weighted balls on the end of it to simulate the weight of the racket head.</p>
<p>Practice your swing with the ServeMaster or sock as much as you need. Remember to swing upwards, as well as outwards. Many students I see extend too far in front and are therefore hitting the ball too low.</p>
<p>If you are still having difficulty, I suggest you watch the video to see how I do it. Alright, now we’re ready for the last step in the beginner serve.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Step 5 – The Follow Through</h2>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1432" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/stepin1.jpg" alt="Step into the serve." width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/stepin1.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/11/stepin1-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/11/stepin1-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p><strong>Once contact is made with the ball, the body will rotate forward. The arm should continue to extend out as far as possible after contact.</strong></p>
<p>After full extension of the arm is completed, the arm will travel downwards and to the left. It will cross in front of the body and should finish around the hip area of the left side of the body.</p>
<p>Upon finishing the swing, the right shoulder will be higher than the left shoulder. The result is a cartwheel effect that adds power to the serve.</p>
<p>This is what the upper body does. How about the lower body?</p>
<p>For advanced servers, both feet come off the ground on contact, sometimes as much as 8-10 inches in the air. This jump propels the server into the court where he or she lands on their left foot only.</p>
<p>To do this requires much training and a perfect swing. So we are going to follow through differently but still get our body weight into the shot.</p>
<p>Here’s how it will work with our feet. On contact, your feet may or may not leave the ground. This depends on how athletic you are, etc.</p>
<p>Let’s assume your feet stay on the ground, which is perfectly fine. You’re left foot is going to remain where it is during the entire serve.</p>
<p>However, the right foot is going to step forward upon striking the ball. This will cause you to put your body weight behind the serve.</p>
<p>You can think of your left foot as a hinge and your right foot as the one that steps forward, into the court. You can watch the video to see how I do it.</p>
<p>I like this follow through for beginners for several reasons. One is that it’s much easier to perform than jumping. Second, it’s good for players who are older or have joint issues. Third, it keeps you on balance better and is easier to recover.</p>
<p>You can practice the follow through with the ServeMaster or the sock. Once you do that dozens of times (or even hundreds), then practice for a few minutes with just the racket (and no ball).</p>
<p>Once you complete the shadow swings, you can pick up a tennis ball and try out the complete serve. You’ll now have to put together all 5 steps to hit the ball.</p>
<p>At first, the serve might feel very awkward and uncomfortable. You need to realize that tennis is not the most comfortable sport to play correctly unless you learn it young.</p>
<p>If you can get through the initial few practice sessions, you’ll grow more acclimated to the serve. I suggest swinging slowly at first and then building up your racket speed.</p>
<p>If you come out of the gate trying to hit 100 mph serves, you’re likely to miss, injure yourself and grow discouraged. So start slowly, video your serve, practice with the teaching aids I recommended, and watch your serve bloom.</p>
<p>With consistent practice, you can have a fairly good tennis serve in several weeks or months. How good you’ll serve depends on a lot of factors.</p>
<p>If you’re athletic and have a good throwing motion, serving in the 90-100 mph range is easily achievable. I can serve around 100 mph using this serve motion.</p>
<p>Although I covered a lot here, I understand you may still have questions. If so, leave them in the comment section and I’ll get back to you shortly. Thanks.</p>
<p>The post <a href="/5-steps-to-a-great-tennis-serve-for-beginners-with-pics-and-video/">5 Steps To A Great Tennis Serve For Beginners With Pics And Video</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/5-steps-to-a-great-tennis-serve-for-beginners-with-pics-and-video/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Best 5 Tennis Rackets For Serve And Volley In 2018</title>
		<link>/the-best-5-rackets-for-serve-and-volley-in-2018/</link>
					<comments>/the-best-5-rackets-for-serve-and-volley-in-2018/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chad Walner]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 30 Oct 2018 08:42:53 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Reviews]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[serve]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[volley]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=904</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>If you really wanted the best vehicle for cornering, would you waste time researching the best Jeep?  Of course not!  You need the tennis racket that will fit your level and your game more than the &#8220;best&#8221; all-purpose racket. So &#8230; <a class="kt-excerpt-readmore" href="/the-best-5-rackets-for-serve-and-volley-in-2018/" aria-label="The Best 5 Tennis Rackets For Serve And Volley In 2018">Read More</a></p>
<p>The post <a href="/the-best-5-rackets-for-serve-and-volley-in-2018/">The Best 5 Tennis Rackets For Serve And Volley In 2018</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>If you really wanted the best vehicle for cornering, would you waste time researching the best Jeep?  Of course not!  You need the tennis racket that will <strong>fit your level and your game</strong> more than the &#8220;best&#8221; all-purpose racket.</p>
<p>So in tennis, there are basically two types of broad styles. You’re either a baseliner or a net crasher (serve and volleyer). Each style has very different needs.</p>
<p>Baseline players have more margin for error. A racket with power that can produce topspin is their main need.</p>
<p><strong>For the serve and volley player, rackets with more control and maneuverability are more important. The top rackets for serve and volley players are definitely different from those for baseline players, and we&#8217;ve gathered all the data together here with this very specific player in mind.</strong></p>
<p><strong>In this post, you’ll find our selection of the top 5 rackets of 2018 for serve and volley players. We broke each racket down in detail and listed their strong points and weaknesses.</strong></p>
<p>This is what we chose to be the best of the best for S&amp;V:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="#babolat">Babolat Pure Strike – 16 x 19</a></li>
<li><a href="#wilson-pro">Wilson Pro Staff RF97 Autograph</a></li>
<li><a href="#prince">Prince Phantom Pro 100</a></li>
<li><a href="#wilson61">Wilson Six One 95 &#8211; 18 x 20</a></li>
<li><a href="#yonex">Yonex EZONE DR 98 Blue</a></li>
</ul>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>How We Determined The Best Rackets For Serve And Volley</h2>
<p>We determined the best serve and volley rackets in three different ways:</p>
<ol>
<li>Through personal experience, trying out each racket.</li>
<li>Studying the specs of each racket to make sure they are ideal for serve and volley.</li>
<li>Reviewing a very detailed study that <a href="https://tenniscompanion.org/best-tennis-racquets/">tenniscompanion.org</a> did on the 22 best rackets and then we used the study to narrow down the 5 best rackets for serve and volley.</li>
</ol>
<p>The tenniscompanion.org study was compiled using six key attributes. Each attribute was scored on a 1-10 scale for every racket they reviewed. These attributes are power, control, maneuverability, comfort, touch/feel, and stability.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-921 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/racketPriorities.png" alt="" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/racketPriorities.png 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/racketPriorities-300x169.png 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/racketPriorities-768x432.png 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p>Let’s quickly look at each attribute in order of importance and determine its significance to a serve and volley racket.</p>
<p><strong>Control</strong> – Control is very important to the serve and volley player, especially when placing shots. Typically, smaller head sizes and thinner beams offer more control but less power. Control was an attribute we deemed important for our selected rackets to score well in.</p>
<p><strong>Maneuverability</strong> – This is a measure of how easily the racket can be maneuvered to hit a shot, particularly a volley. Most good maneuvering rackets have more weight in the handle than the head. This makes them feel lighter and allows them to be moved quicker. We feel this is important for volley players, so we looked for rackets that scored high in this attribute.</p>
<p><strong>Touch/Feel</strong> – Interestingly, rackets that offer touch are very similar to rackets built for comfort – heavy and flexible. The main exception is touch rackets have smaller head sizes. Since touch is very important to the volley player, this is an attribute our rackets had to score well in.</p>
<p><strong>Stability</strong> – A stable racket is one that is responsive and delivers a consistent, accurate strike of the ball. These rackets tend to be heavy with wider beams and less flexible frames. This attribute is semi-important to the serve and volley player but it wasn’t one of the key attributes for our rackets.</p>
<p><strong>Comfort</strong> – This is a measure of how comfortable your arm and body feel when hitting the ball. If there is less vibration and stiffness in the frame, that is deemed a comfortable racket. Comfort is an attribute we feel is not very important to the serve and volley player. However, one of the rackets on our list has comfort as an added bonus.</p>
<p><strong>Power</strong> – Except on the serve, power is not the most important attribute for a serve and volley player; and it may even be the last. Serve and volley players are more concerned with touch and maneuverability. For that reason, most of the rackets on this list are not the most powerful.</p>
<p>Overall, the most important attributes for selecting a great racket for serve and volley are control, maneuverability and touch/feel. Keep in mind that all the rackets we selected have power as well, but not as much as the rackets made for baseliners.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>The 5 Best Serve And Volley Rackets Of 2018</h2>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="babolat"></a></p>
<h3><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-911 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/r_bab1.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/r_bab1.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/r_bab1-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/r_bab1-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></h3>
<h3>Babolat Pure Strike – 16 x 19</h3>
</div>
<p>This racket ranked first on the tenniscompanion.org list of all the rackets they reviewed. It’s an all-court racket but at 11.3 oz and 98 sq inches, excellent for serve and volley. Its light weight allows for great maneuverability at net and quick reaction times.</p>
<p>The frame of this racket is slightly more flexible than the other members of the Babolat racket family. This affords more control and touch, perfect for the serve and volley player.</p>
<p>The only drawback I saw of this racket is slightly less power than most of the other Babolats I’ve used. But there are always trade-offs. With the Babolat Pure Strike you sacrifice a bit of power for more control. However, it’s also a fantastic racket for groundstrokes and returns.</p>
<p>Overall, this racket scored high marks across the board. Though unchanged since 2017, we still endorse it as one of the best serve and volley rackets for 2018. If you’re an all-court player who serves and volleys part of the time, few choices are better for a racket.</p>
<p><a href="https://amzn.to/2DYriCy" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Check the current price of this racket on Amazon.com</a> (affiliate link to Amazon for the exact model I’m reviewing here).</p>
<p>I personally played with the Babolat Pure Drive for years and had great success with Babolats. In the last couple of years, I switched to the Head Prestige MP, but I’d easily buy another Babolat for my next racket.</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="wilson-pro"></a></p>
<h3><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-913 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/r_rf.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/r_rf.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/r_rf-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/r_rf-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></h3>
<h3>Wilson Pro Staff RF97 Autograph</h3>
</div>
<p>The original Wilson Pro Staff from the 1980s and 90s was made popular by Pete Sampras. The new model for 2018 was popularized by Roger Federer, hence his initials in the title.</p>
<p>This racket is quite unique to other rackets in its design. It makes use of braided graphite construction with thin beams and a light head.</p>
<p>At 97 square inches, it has a great head size for serve and volley. Surprisingly, the racket weighs 12.6 ounces, which is one of the heaviest strung rackets on the market. The heavy weight gives the racket great control, but maneuverability is compromised.</p>
<p>Still, the Wilson Pro Staff makes up for the heavy weight in every other way. It feels stable, solid, and affords excellent control. Whether at the baseline, net, or serving, the Wilson Pro Staff handled solidly.</p>
<p>We picked this racket because it scored very well on volleys, slices, and net play according to tenniscompanion.org, which stated:<br />
“One of our favorite places to hit with Roger’s Pro Staff was up at the net. It felt solid in our hands and allowed us to hit crisp and controlled volleys with little effort. Combined with a heightened sense of touch and it gave us the feeling that we were in control when we approached the net.”</p>
<p><a href="https://amzn.to/2Q7AlZc" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Check the current price of this racket on Amazon.com</a> (affiliate link to Amazon for the exact model I’m reviewing here).</p>
<p>We endorse this racket for serve and volley, especially if you’re an advanced player who can handle a heavier stick. Hey, if it works for Roger Federer, it can work for you, right?</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="prince"></a></p>
<h3><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-914 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/r_prince.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/r_prince.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/r_prince-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/r_prince-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></h3>
<h3>Prince Phantom Pro 100</h3>
</div>
<p>Prince has long been known as of the best racket manufacturers. They really nailed it with this racket. With a 100 square inch head, 11.3 oz strung weight and a frame stiffness of only 54, you couldn’t ask for a racket with more control.</p>
<p>Arm friendly and responsive, you can be confident coming to net with the Prince Phantom Pro 100. This is a racket ideal for intermediate and advanced players who like to attack the net and desire control.</p>
<p>Most of the 11.3 ounces of weight is in the handle of the racket. This translates to a low head weight, giving it exceptional maneuverability at the net. On groundstrokes, the racket proved capable but doesn’t give as much spin and power as some of the other rackets on this list.</p>
<p>The main drawback of this racket is lack of power. But power is the main sacrifice when designing a racket for control. Overall, I thought this racket performed well when I hit with it. Players who swing fast won’t have power issues.</p>
<p><a href="https://amzn.to/2QdeEaf" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Check the current price of this racket on Amazon.com</a> (affiliate link to Amazon for the exact model I’m reviewing here).</p>
<p>As a hack, you could string a bit looser than normal, which should make up for some of the lost power. I believe giving up some power for all the control the Prince Phantom Pro 100 offers, is worth the trade-off. Especially if you attack the net consistently.</p>
<p>For that reason, I highly endorse this racket as one of the best serve and volley sticks of 2018.</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="wilson61"></a></p>
<h3><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-915 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/r_61.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/r_61.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/r_61-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/r_61-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></h3>
<h3>Wilson Six One 95 18 x 20</h3>
</div>
<p>For the pure serve and volley players out there that love control, this is your racket. The head size is only 95 square inches yet it weighs 12.3 ounces strung, making it almost as heavy as the Wilson Pro Staff RF 97 Autograph.</p>
<p>The heavy frame allows for comfortable contact and moves through the ball with ease. A light head balance, thin 22 mm beams all the way around it, and added it weight at the 3 and 9 o’clock positions, give this racket superior control.</p>
<p>This racket also boasts Wilson’s parallel drilling technology, which creates a more forgiving string bed and increased sweet spot. The racket performed great from the baseline and at the net in tests.</p>
<p><a href="https://amzn.to/2Pf7PPX" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Check the current price of this racket on Amazon.com</a> (affiliate link to Amazon for the exact model I’m reviewing here).</p>
<p>The main drawbacks of the Wilson Six One is the heavy weight and reduced power. This is a common theme among some serve and volley rackets. Maneuverability and power are not this racket’s forte.</p>
<p>But if you can get past that part, you have a stick that will provide you a ton of control and stability on your shots. We’re sure you’ll love coming to net with this racket.</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="yonex"></a></p>
<h3><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-916 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/r_yonex.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/r_yonex.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/r_yonex-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/r_yonex-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></h3>
<h3>Yonex EZONE DR 98 Blue</h3>
</div>
<p>This racket is a great choice for all-court players. It will still be a valuable addition to the serve and volley player with it’s excellent control and touch.</p>
<p>Yonex made this racket with Nanometric DR carbon graphite composition. This allows the frame to flex while snapping back into place on contact. The EZONE also features Yonex’s signature square head shape.</p>
<p>The square head increases the sweet spot of the racket compared to other rackets of its size (98 square inches). This racket also has technology that dampens vibrations from the ball, offering increased comfortability.</p>
<p>Like most of the other rackets on this list, the Yonex offers superior control and good maneuverability. While the racket lacks a bit of power, we feel it more than made up for it with its other attributes.</p>
<p>You should be able to hit good serves with this racket and have plenty of feel on the volleys. From the baseline you’ll hit good, consistent groundstrokes, especially with the larger sweet spot on the racket.</p>
<p><a href="https://amzn.to/2Q9ohXm" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Check the current price of this racket on Amazon.com</a> (affiliate link to Amazon for the exact model I’m reviewing here).</p>
<p>If you’ve never played with a Yonex before, you’ll find them to be very comfortable. My first racket was actually a Yonex, but that was back in the day. If you’re an intermediate to advanced player who swings relatively fast, this racket is a great choice.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Other Factors That Affect The Racket For S&amp;V</h2>
<p>Other factors will affect the way the racket plays. These are grip size, choice of string, string gauge, and string tension. Here are some quick guidelines on ways to determine these choices.</p>
<p><strong>Grip Size:</strong> The size of the grip is largely dependent on the person. Rafael Nadal uses one of the smallest grips on the men’s professional tour, while Juan Martin Del Potro favors a larger one. It comes down to a personal choice.</p>
<p>Most grips start at 4 inches (on the small side) and up to 4 5/8 inches on the large size. We recommend trying out different size grips before selecting one. Going too small or too large is usually a detriment. Try to choose a grip that is comfortable for your hand size.</p>
<p>As a helpful tip, if you’re already playing with a grip that’s too small, you can add an over grip to make it larger. Grips that are too large cannot be made smaller unless you change the entire grip.</p>
<p><strong>Choice Of String:</strong> Nowadays, players generally have two different choices for string material – synthetic gut or polyester. Synthetic gut is easier on the elbow and usually costs less. The feel of the string will also last longer.</p>
<p>Consequently, synthetic gut is a good choice if comfort and durability is your main concern. You’ll also spend less in restringing costs.</p>
<p>On the flip side, polyester will give more feel and bite on the ball. This results in more spin and power, which is helpful to both baseline and serve and volley players.</p>
<p>The drawbacks are that polyester loses feel after playing with it much quicker and stringing costs will be higher. Polyester is also harder on the arm, especially when strung with a high tension.</p>
<p>I personally need to restring with polyester every 3-4 weeks in comparison to 7-8 weeks with synthetic gut. Almost all professional players use polyester and there are a ton of options to choose from.</p>
<p>For serve and volley players, either string, synthetic gut or polyester, will do the job. But polyester gives more bite on the ball.</p>
<p><strong>String Gauge:</strong> This is another important factor in playability. Tennis string gauge refers to the thickness of it. The gauges vary in size from 15 to 18, with 15 being the thickest and 18 being the thinnest. Most players use a 16 or 17-gauge string.</p>
<p>The lower the gauge, the longer the string will last, but the less playability it will have. The opposite is true. The higher the gauge, the shorter the string will last but the more playability it will have.</p>
<p>I use a 16L and 17-gauge string and love it. In the past, I used regular 16-gauge string and played fairly well with it. However, the increased feel of the 17-gauge string is worth the extra time and money for me.</p>
<p>For serve and volley players, either string will work, but polyester provides more feel and spin. If you can afford the extra money, go with polyester.</p>
<p>You can try my string recommendation if you like. If you’re an avid player, the difference is a few hundred dollars a year more for using good polyester strings. Remember, all the pros use polyester.</p>
<p><strong>String Tension:</strong> This refers to how tight or loose the strings are tensioned when put into the racket. Most rackets have a recommended string tension listed on it. It may say something like “Recommended Tension: 55-65”.</p>
<p>I personally favor higher string tensions because they give more control. They’ll also last a little longer, as even when the tension drops from playing, they’ll still remain fairly tight.</p>
<p>Keep in mind that tighter tensions are not very friendly on the elbow. So if comfort is important, string lower. Most rackets give you a 10-point spread in the recommended tension. You can’t go wrong with a tension in the middle. For example, if between 55-65, string at 60.</p>
<p>After you string your racket and play with it for a few weeks, you’ll know if you need to adjust up or down. Keep in mind that small bits of tension are lost every time you play.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>I find that the first few times of play don’t necessarily give a good indication of the strings. If you string tight, you need to hit with the racket a few times before the strings “break in” and you can honestly assess them.</p>
<p>If you use polyester and play often with the same strings, you may notice they ultimately become unresponsive and have a “dead” feel. That’s when you need to restring. If you continue playing with such strings, you’re likely to hurt your elbow and be an unhappy camper.</p>
<p>I personally favor polyester and go with a hybrid 16L and 17-gauge string with a high tension (around 63-65).</p>
<p><strong>Main Strings:</strong> Signum Pro Plasma HEXtreme Pure 16L String &#8211; <a href="https://amzn.to/2PjmI3I" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Check the current price on Amazon.com</a> (affiliate link to Amazon for the exact model I’m recommending here).</p>
<p><strong>Cross Strings:</strong> Diadem Evolution 17 (1.25) String (Azure Blue) &#8211; <a href="https://amzn.to/2PePqTq" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Check the current price on Amazon.com</a> (affiliate link to Amazon for the exact model I’m recommending here).</p>
<p>The post <a href="/the-best-5-rackets-for-serve-and-volley-in-2018/">The Best 5 Tennis Rackets For Serve And Volley In 2018</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/the-best-5-rackets-for-serve-and-volley-in-2018/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The 5 Unique Spins For A Winning Tennis Serve</title>
		<link>/the-5-unique-spins-for-a-winning-tennis-serve/</link>
					<comments>/the-5-unique-spins-for-a-winning-tennis-serve/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chad Walner]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 27 Oct 2018 08:07:52 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Theory]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[serve]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=851</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>If you’re looking to turn your serve into a weapon, it’s critical you know the different types of serve spins and how to execute them. I wrote this post to give you exactly that information – as well as explain &#8230; <a class="kt-excerpt-readmore" href="/the-5-unique-spins-for-a-winning-tennis-serve/" aria-label="The 5 Unique Spins For A Winning Tennis Serve">Read More</a></p>
<p>The post <a href="/the-5-unique-spins-for-a-winning-tennis-serve/">The 5 Unique Spins For A Winning Tennis Serve</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>If you’re looking to turn your serve into a weapon, it’s critical you know the different types of serve spins and how to execute them. I wrote this post to give you exactly that information – as well as explain when to use these spins and their benefits and drawbacks.</p>
<p>With this knowledge, your serve can become a true asset to your tennis game &#8211; a shot that is difficult to return and hard to read. First, I want to dispel all the confusion between the spins, so you are completely clear on them.</p>
<p><strong>There are five possible types of spins on a tennis serve. You can think of spin as the direction the ball rotates.</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Flat Serve – No spin or very little spin.</strong></li>
<li><strong>Slice Serve – The ball has side-spin – either to the left or right – depending on if a righty or lefty hits the serve.</strong></li>
<li><strong>Kick Serve – The ball rotates diagonally, a combination of side-spin and topspin.</strong></li>
<li><strong>Topspin Serve – The ball rotates forward.</strong></li>
<li><strong>Underspin – The ball rotates backwards. This type of spin is generally not effective on the serve and used mainly by beginners.</strong></li>
</ul>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Why Learn The Different Spins?</h2>
<p>As you advance in tennis, the play becomes more difficult. Serves with the same spin on every point can be easily anticipated and returned. Hence the need for spin variation on your serves.</p>
<p>The different spins cause the ball to bounce off the ground in different ways. Some spins cause the ball to bounce low, with others to the side or high off the ground. If your opponent cannot read your spin, they’ll be left to guess, which is preferable.</p>
<p>Each type of spin has benefits and drawbacks. For example, kick serves are safer to hit than flat serves when trying to get into the serving box. That’s why most advanced players favor it on the second serve. However, flat serves are better if you are going for high pace and a nice ace. Wow, I like that rhyme!</p>
<p>In tennis, you only get two chances to get the serve into the box. The first serve can be more aggressive. The second serve should be more conservative, as the point will be lost if the serve misses the box. It’s therefore important to know which spins to use on first and second serves.</p>
<p>It’s undoubtedly true that using a variety of spins on both the first and second serve will make you a better and more effective server. You’ll add a new dimension to your game that will cause the returner to be off-balance while keeping you off the defensive.</p>
<p>Some court surfaces work better with certain spins. For example, hard courts and grass courts work well with flat serves, while red clay works better with kick serves. Knowing when to use the spins, and on which side of the court (deuce or ad), is also important.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>A Word On Beginner Vs. Advanced Serve In Relation To Spin</h2>
<p>If you have a beginner serve (commonly referred to as a waiter’s serve), I must warn you that it will be difficult to impart spin variation on the ball. This is because the eastern forehand grip, most commonly used in beginner serves, does not allow for kick and topspin serves.</p>
<p>For this reason, I urge you to learn the advanced serve. I have an article on this blog that shows you <a href="/beginners-serve-vs-advanced-tennis-serve-what-are-the-differences/">how to perform the advanced serve</a> – and the differences between the two serves: beginner and advanced.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>Once you know the advanced serve, execution of the four major spins (flat, slice, kick, and topspin) will be possible. If you have an advanced serve and use the continental or eastern backhand grip, then you’re in business. But whether you’re a beginner or advanced player, the following information could be invaluable to your tennis serve.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>The Flat Serve</h2>
<p>The flat serve is called “flat” because it has almost no spin. <strong>The less spin the ball has, the faster it moves through the air</strong>. For this reason, the flat serve is the most powerful serve in tennis. Only flat serves can reach speeds in excess of 100-110 mph – unless you&#8217;re John Isner or Nick Kyrios.</p>
<p>Balls hit without spin take a more direct path to their target than balls hit with spin. For this reason, the fastest serves in tennis are all hit flat.</p>
<p>That’s not to say all flat serves have zero spin. The ball could spin in any direction on a flat serve, but not with much rotation. When the flat serve bounces off the court, it tends to move in the same direction and stay low.</p>
<p>Most aces in tennis are the result of flat serves. For that reason, it is commonly used for first serves but not so much on second serves. Even the best professional players in the world can struggle to get more than 50-60% of their first serves in.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-92" style="margin-bottom: 0px; padding-bottom: 0px;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/benefits220x40.png" alt="" width="220" height="40" /></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Learnability</strong>: The flat serve is the easiest serve to learn and the one all beginners hit first. It doesn’t require any special technique with the hand, wrist or arm to hit.</li>
<li><strong>Velocity</strong>: Flat serves are ideal for hitting at high speeds. A flat serve moving at fast speed can be difficult to return, even if hit near the returner.</li>
<li><strong>Low Bounce</strong>: Because flat serves are usually struck hard with little spin, the ball stays low off the bounce. This has a skidding effect, which can make it difficult to return, especially on hard court and grass surfaces.</li>
</ul>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-92" style="margin-bottom: 0px; padding-bottom: 0px;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/Drawbacks-220x40.png" alt="" width="220" height="40" /></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Low Margin of Error</strong>: As the ball is typically struck hard with little spin, it has a much lower chance of making it into the service box than a serve hit with topspin.</li>
<li><strong>Energy</strong>: Flat serves with high pace require more effort than the other four serve types to hit. It can take a lot of energy to hit hard, flat serves consistently over a whole match.</li>
<li><strong>Serve and Volley</strong>: Flat serves are not ideal if you serve and volley. Due to their velocity, returns come back quicker, not allowing the server to get close enough to the net for a good first volley. Serves with spin are preferable for serve and volley play.</li>
</ul>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-92" style="margin-bottom: 0px; padding-bottom: 0px;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/execution-220x40.png" alt="" width="220" height="40" /><br />
<strong>Grip: Continental or Eastern</strong> – This depends on if you are using an advanced or beginner serve. The advanced serve uses the continental grip. The beginner serve uses an eastern forehand grip. Beginner serves with the eastern forehand grip can still be hit with good velocity but typically not more than 80-90 mph.</p>
<p><strong>Toss Placement</strong> – Toss the ball 12-15 inches in front of you and 6 inches to the right of your tossing arm shoulder when the ball is at its zenith. This is for right-handed players. Lefties will toss 6 inches to their left.</p>
<p><strong>Racket Contact Point</strong> – Since no spin is required for this serve, we can hit it directly from behind with the racket face completely squared to the ball at moment of contact. Remember, it’s fine if there is a bit of spin on the ball.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>The Slice Serve</h2>
<p>The slice serve rotates sideways. A righty hits slice serves that rotate to the right. When these serves strike the ground, the ball will sharply move to the left (from the server’s perspective). For a lefty, the opposite scenario will happen – sidespin to the left will yield bounces to the right.</p>
<p>The slice serve is produced by brushing on the ball. It can be a very effective serve and should be part of your serve arsenal. It’s much easier to learn than the kick serve or topspin serve. I believe everyone can learn the slice serve, and it doesn’t take long to become proficient with it.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>Slice serves are effective on any court surface and tend to bounce low off the court. They have a higher chance of going into the box than flat serves due to their spin. However, they often do not travel through the air as fast due to the heavy spin on them.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-92" style="margin-bottom: 0px; padding-bottom: 0px;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/benefits220x40.png" alt="" width="220" height="40" /></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Learnability</strong>: The slice serve is the second easiest serve to learn behind the flat serve. I believe kids and adults can learn it quickly.</li>
<li><strong>Velocity</strong>: The slice serve has less velocity than a flat serve but more than kick or topspin. It is good to use as a medium speed serve to throw off the timing of your opponent.</li>
<li><strong>Bounce</strong>: The main benefit of the slice serve is that it moves to the side after hitting the ground. If applied right, it can bounce away from the returner or directly into the body, which is difficult to return. The bounce is usually low, which also creates difficulty in returning.</li>
</ul>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-92" style="margin-bottom: 0px; padding-bottom: 0px;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/Drawbacks-220x40.png" alt="" width="220" height="40" /></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Low Margin of Error</strong>: Because the slice serve does not have topspin, it has a lower margin of error than a topspin or kick serve. Most players tend to overhit the slice, and thus it misses the box. It should, therefore, be used on first serves.</li>
<li><strong>Telegraphing</strong>: Most players toss the ball too wide on the slice serve. This can easily telegraph you are using it, which your opponent can key in on.</li>
<li><strong>Velocity</strong>: The slice serve has a lower velocity than a flat serve. For that reason, placement is vital to its success. If the placement is not ideal, it could be easily returned for a winning shot</li>
</ul>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-92" style="margin-bottom: 0px; padding-bottom: 0px;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/execution-220x40.png" alt="" width="220" height="40" /><br />
<strong>Grip: Continental or Eastern</strong> – This is contingent on if you are using an advanced or beginner serve. The advanced serve will use the continental grip. The beginner serve can get away with hitting a slice serve with an eastern forehand grip.</p>
<p><strong>Toss Placement</strong> – Toss the ball 12-15 inches in front of you and 6-8 inches to the right of your tossing arm shoulder when the ball is at its zenith. This is for right-handed players. Lefties will toss 6-8 inches to their left. Note, that if you toss more than 8 inches away from your hitting shoulder, you will be telegraphing the serve. Tossing in the same location as the flat serve is ideal.</p>
<p><strong>Racket Contact Point</strong> – The racket needs to be at a slight angle when contacting the ball – perhaps 10-15 degrees. This means a 10-15 degree difference from a flat serve, where the racket is dead center onto the ball.</p>
<p>Contact with the ball is made on the outside edge of it to produce the sidespin – at three o’clock for righties and nine o’clock for lefties. A slight adjustment of your hand at contact (with the palm facing slightly more to the left for righties and vice versa for lefties) is required for hitting the slice serve. Try to resist tossing the ball wide to produce the spin. Instead use an angle change on the racket.</p>
<p>The slice serve can be used effectively to serve and volley. It’s best application is to hit into the body of the returner. The slower velocity of the serve (in comparison to flat) will allow you to get closer to the net as well.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>The Kick Serve</h2>
<p>The kick serve and topspin serve are often confused for each other. A lot of my students ask me the difference As I stated earlier, the kick serve has diagonal spin (forward and side) while the topspin serve has forward spin only. In this segment, we’re talking exclusively about the kick serve.</p>
<p>The kick serve is absolutely essential to master if you want to move up the ranks in tennis. Once you get past the 5.0 level, every player can hit a kick serve – with varying levels of kick. As a side joke, I once asked my friend if a kick serve I hit was kicking. He said, “Man, that mother wasn’t even walking!”. I’ll never forget his remark, as it made me laugh. That was early in my playing days, before I knew all I do now.</p>
<p>The kick serve is used by all professional tennis players and is the serve of choice for the second serve. It is also used on first serves for various reasons. Many clay court specialists prefer to use it on their first serve. This is because it has a high chance of going into the service box and bounces high on clay.</p>
<p>Kick serves also have sidespin, making them difficult to read. Most good kick serves move up and away (or up and towards) the returner. This forces the returner to hit the ball over their shoulder, raising the difficulty level of the return.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-92" style="margin-bottom: 0px; padding-bottom: 0px;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/benefits220x40.png" alt="" width="220" height="40" /></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>High Margin Of Error</strong>: Due to the topspin on the kick serve, it often arcs down quickly, making it a high percentage serve. For this reason, it’s a great serve to use to ensure it will land in the service box.</li>
<li><strong>High Bounce</strong>: The kick serve bounces high, which has two benefits. One, it prevents the returner from attacking the serve inside the court. Second, it forces the returner to hit a high return, which is more difficult to handle than lower returns.</li>
<li><strong>Control</strong>: As the kick serve is hit with less velocity than a flat or slice serve, it’s placement can thus be controlled better – at least in theory. This means you can move it around the service box easier than you would a flat serve.</li>
<li>Serve and Volley: The kick serve is an optimal choice for the serve and volley. Many advanced players like to use it because it allows the necessary time to get into net while forcing the returner to hit a high-bouncing shot.</li>
</ul>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-92" style="margin-bottom: 0px; padding-bottom: 0px;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/Drawbacks-220x40.png" alt="" width="220" height="40" /></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Learnability</strong>: The kick serve can be very difficult to learn, especially for older players who are used to hitting only flat and slice serves. The kick serve is simply not possible to hit for players with a beginner serve and an eastern forehand grip.</li>
<li><strong>Slower Pace</strong>: Kick serves are slower than flat or slice serves. For this reason, they are vulnerable to attack if not hit with enough spin or placement. Even if good spin and placement are used, if the ball lacks pace, it can easily be attacked.</li>
<li><strong>Telegraphing</strong>: To hit the kick serve, the ball must be tossed more over the head than a flat or slice serve. For this reason, it is often a telegraphed serve. Most players know a kick serve will be hit on the second serve, but if used on the first serve, most players can see it coming a mile away.</li>
</ul>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-92" style="margin-bottom: 0px; padding-bottom: 0px;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/execution-220x40.png" alt="" width="220" height="40" /><br />
<strong>Grip: Continental or Eastern Backhand</strong> – The continental grip can be used on all spins, with the possible exception of underspin, which is really not used for advanced serves. However, I find that the eastern backhand grip is easier to generate a kick serve. The index knuckle is on bevel one, instead of bevel two (continental grip).</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p><strong>Toss Placement</strong> – Toss the ball 12-15 inches in front of you. The toss should be over your right ear (for right-handed players) at its zenith. This will allow you to hit up on the ball (imparting topspin) but also allow for some sidespin.</p>
<p><strong>Racket Contact Point</strong> – Unlike the flat serve and the slice serve, you’ll be striking the ball from the bottom edge of the ball, and slightly to its left side. If you think of the ball as a clock, the racket should contact the ball at approximately the seven o’clock position. This creates topspin and some sidespin.</p>
<p><strong>Kick Serve Tips</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>It helps generate spin if the toss drops a little further before hitting the ball. For this reason, a slightly higher toss on the kick serve is advised.</li>
<li>Hit up on the ball. This means the racket head will be moving upwards when striking the ball, as opposed to forward or to the side.</li>
<li>High racket head speed is essential to a good kick serve. Wrist snap in the way of ulnar deviation and pronation are necessary to generate that kind of racket head speed. Most professional players swing just as fast on the second serve as the first serve.</li>
<li>A more extreme bend of the knees with a more vertical jump (as opposed to into the court) will result in more spin.</li>
</ul>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>The Topspin Serve</h2>
<p>The topspin serve is almost all forward rotation. While there may be some degree of side spin, it is 90-100% forward spin. This will cause the ball to bounce slightly higher than the kick serve. The velocity of the topspin and kick serve are about the same, since the RPM on the ball is similar as well.</p>
<p>The topspin serve is a little more difficult to execute than the kick serve, as the ball must be tossed slightly more over the head. This requires flexibility, athletic ability and good timing to hit. While the kick serve is good enough to learn as a reliable second serve for most club players, more advanced players may want to add the topspin serve to their arsenal.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-92" style="margin-bottom: 0px; padding-bottom: 0px;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/benefits220x40.png" alt="" width="220" height="40" /></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>High Bounce</strong>: The topspin serve provides the highest bouncing ball of all the serves. For this reason it is very effective on clay and har-true.</li>
<li><strong>High Margin of Error</strong>: Due to the heavy topspin of this serve, it is the highest percentage serve of all five spins. For this reason, it can be reliably used on all second serves.</li>
<li><strong>Serve and Volley</strong>: Like the kick serve, the topspin serve is ideal for serve and volley due to its high bounce. Even more than the kick serve, the topspin serve can push the returner further back beyond the baseline. A topspin serve hit with heavy rotation is extremely difficult to attack.</li>
</ul>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-92" style="margin-bottom: 0px; padding-bottom: 0px;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/Drawbacks-220x40.png" alt="" width="220" height="40" /></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Learnability</strong>: Like the kick serve, the topspin serve is difficult to learn. It is even more difficult to hit than the kick serve because of the extreme placement of the toss. Again, beginner serves with eastern forehand grips have no chance of hitting kick or topspin serves.</li>
<li><strong>Pace</strong>: If not enough spin or pace is used on this serve, it can fall short and be easily attacked.</li>
<li><strong>Direction</strong>: Since the topspin serve is primarily bouncing forward, unlike the kick serve which bounces forward and to the side, it’s a bit easier to read and return. This should not be a detriment that causes you not to use it though. It is still very effective.</li>
</ul>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-92" style="margin-bottom: 0px; padding-bottom: 0px;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/execution-220x40.png" alt="" width="220" height="40" /><br />
<strong>Grip: Continental or Eastern Backhand</strong> – The information I stated for the kick serve in terms of grip applies the same for the topspin serve. The continental grip will work fine. But I find the eastern backhand grip works better for me on both the kick and topspin serves. Most professional players use the continental grip, with some using the eastern backhand grip. I feel the latter makes it easier to put spin on the ball. The drawback is less power.</p>
<p><strong>Toss Placement</strong> – Toss the ball 12-15 inches in front of you. At the zenith of the toss, the ball should be directly over your head. The toss can be placed over your left ear. It depends on your flexibility and knee bend. This is for right-handed players. Lefties will do the opposite.</p>
<p><strong>Racket Contact Point</strong> – The contact point is ideally at the 6 o’clock position on the tennis ball. This will give the ball the maximum amount of topspin. In other words, you want to brush up on the ball, striking it from the bottom side first.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>The Underspin Serve</h2>
<p>The underspin (also known as backspin) serve is not used in professional tennis. This is because it generally requires an eastern forehand grip to hit. The pace is also too slow to be effective. However, for players at the club level with a beginner, or waiter’s tray, serve and using the eastern forehand grip, it can be quite effective.</p>
<p>Serves hit with underspin typically stay low and skid through the court, similar to slices on groundstrokes. The underspin serve doesn’t require a long learning curve and it’s just another spin variation that can be added to your arsenal.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>If you use an advanced serve, I would skip the underspin serve. It’s not necessary to know and the four other spins are all you need to be a great server. However, if you’re a club player with a beginner serve, I recommend learning this serve, if nothing more than to change the variety. I know a decent club player that only ever hits with backspin and his serves can be difficult to return.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-92" style="margin-bottom: 0px; padding-bottom: 0px;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/benefits220x40.png" alt="" width="220" height="40" /></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Learnability</strong>: Fairly easy to learn but requires an eastern forehand grip.</li>
<li><strong>Rarely Seen</strong>: Few players ever hit with backspin, or at least backspin with high RPM. If you can manage to serve with tight backspin, you can hit with a spin your opponenent is unfamiliar returning.</li>
<li><strong>Low Bounce</strong>: Serves hit with backspin typically skid low through the court, making them difficult to return.</li>
</ul>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-92" style="margin-bottom: 0px; padding-bottom: 0px;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/Drawbacks-220x40.png" alt="" width="220" height="40" /></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Low Margin of Error</strong>: Without topspin, this serve has a much lower margin of error than a kick or topspin serve. For that reason, it only good for first serves.</li>
<li><strong>Vulnerability</strong>: If not hit with enough pace and spin, this serve can be easily attacked. The returner can also return it inside the baseline, putting you on the defensive right away.</li>
<li><strong>Serve and Volley</strong>: The underspin serve is not difficult to return for a good player. For that reason, it is a poor choice to serve and volley on.</li>
<li><strong>Placement</strong>: The underspin serve is best hit over the low part of the net. It is difficult to hit out wide, as it has no topspin. It is therefore difficult to place and easy for your opponents to read.</li>
</ul>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-92" style="margin-bottom: 0px; padding-bottom: 0px;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/execution-220x40.png" alt="" width="220" height="40" /><br />
<strong>Grip: Eastern Forehand</strong> – As I stated a few times already, the underspin serve should only be used with beginner serve motions. The eastern forehand grip is the only one that can hit underspin. Since advanced players use continental grips with pronation, it is not possible to hit with underspin.</p>
<p><strong>Toss Placement</strong> – Toss the ball 12-15 inches in front of you and 6 inches to the right of your tossing arm shoulder when the ball is at its zenith. This is for right-handed players. Lefties will toss 6 inches to their left.</p>
<p><strong>Racket Contact Point</strong> – The racket will be angled up (towards the sky) slightly more than on a flat serve. You’ll want the contact point to be at about the six o’clock position on the ball. The hitting hand should be aligned directly under it. Remember, we are producing backspin, so the racket has to brush from above to below, opposite of a topspin serve.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Summary</h2>
<p>In summary, there are four major spins to choose from for advanced players: flat, slice, kick and topspin. I recommend beginners try to learn the advanced serve so topspin and kick serves are an option. Otherwise, if you have a beginner’s serve you’re limited to flat and slice serves, with the odd exception of the backspin serve.</p>
<p>If you have an advanced serve and wish to add the kick serve to your game, I have posts on this blog that will help. If it seems difficult at first to learn, keep at it. Practice until you get it, as the kick serve is integral to developing a solid all-around game in tennis. No good player can serve without some type of forward spin on the serve.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>Once you have the flat, slice and kick serves in your arsenal, you can take your game up to the next level. Having the kick serve to fall back on for your second serve, you can be more confident and take more chances on your first serve. This will translate into more winning service games.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Here are some ways you can use the serves:</p>
<ul>
<li>Hit the kick serve to the body or backhand of your opponent and come into the net.</li>
<li>Hit the slice serve so it moves away or into the body of your opponent.</li>
<li>Flat serves can be hit anywhere but are most effective to the body and to the backhand.</li>
<li>Hit the topspin serve to the backhand of your opponent and come to net.</li>
<li>For beginners, hit the underspin serve to your opponents backhand and stay back or try coming to net.</li>
</ul>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>My favorite serve out of them all is the slice serve out wide on the deuce side. I can hit a very sharp angle that takes the player completely off the court when I hit my spot. About half the time, it goes as an ace. This is the one serve in my arsenal that is impossible to return for most players if I hit it right.</p>
<p>The other serve I really like is a flat serve out wide on the deuce side. About half the time I come in on this serve. Since it’s going to the opponent’s backhand (as most players are righties), I can expect a defensive shot coming back 95% of the time.</p>
<p>Experiment with the different spins and placements in the box. In general, either try to serve out wide, into the body or up the middle. Vary your spins, speeds and locations for best results. Always keep your opponent guessing and practice your serve religiously.</p>
<p>I hope this post was of help and answered your questions on the serve. If you have any comments or questions for, drop them in the comment box below and I’ll be sure to respond. Thank you for reading.</p>
<p>The post <a href="/the-5-unique-spins-for-a-winning-tennis-serve/">The 5 Unique Spins For A Winning Tennis Serve</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/the-5-unique-spins-for-a-winning-tennis-serve/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>10 Common Second Serve Issues And How To Fix Them</title>
		<link>/10-common-second-serve-issues-and-how-to-fix-them/</link>
					<comments>/10-common-second-serve-issues-and-how-to-fix-them/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chad Walner]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 24 Oct 2018 08:03:57 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Theory]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[serve]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=839</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>I’m sure you’ve heard the old adage in tennis, “you’re only as good as your second serve.” Well, that’s because it’s true. If your second serve is meat, the lions of tennis will feast on it and you’ll quickly be &#8230; <a class="kt-excerpt-readmore" href="/10-common-second-serve-issues-and-how-to-fix-them/" aria-label="10 Common Second Serve Issues And How To Fix Them">Read More</a></p>
<p>The post <a href="/10-common-second-serve-issues-and-how-to-fix-them/">10 Common Second Serve Issues And How To Fix Them</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I’m sure you’ve heard the old adage in tennis, <strong>“you’re only as good as your second serve.”</strong> Well, that’s because it’s true. If your second serve is meat, the lions of tennis will feast on it and you’ll quickly be torn asunder. And if you can’t hold serve, you can’t win in tennis, period.</p>
<p>You’re probably reading this post because your second serve is weak. You know it needs to get better. But despite all your efforts, it’s not getting any better in the time you’ve been playing. Maybe it doesn’t have spin, or it has spin but no pace, or maybe you can’t get it in the box.</p>
<p><strong>Whatever your issue is, this article will likely resolve it for you. I’ve put together the 10 most common second serve issues and how to fix them. For years, I struggled with hitting a good topspin serve until I slowly began to correct my form by addressing these 10 specific points:</strong></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<ol>
<li><a href="#correct-grip">Not holding the correct grip</a> (Continental or Eastern Backhand)</li>
<li><a href="#tossing-over-head">Not tossing over the head</a></li>
<li><a href="#tossing-high">Not tossing high enough</a> – must allow the ball to drop</li>
<li><a href="#no-racket-drop">Not using a racket drop</a></li>
<li><a href="#radial-ulnar">Not using ulnar and radial deviation</a></li>
<li><a href="#left-to-right">Not swinging from left to right</a></li>
<li><a href="#remaining-to-side">Not staying to the side</a> – orienting to the court too soon</li>
<li><a href="#keep-head-up">Not keeping the head up</a></li>
<li><a href="#arm-into-position">Not pulling the tossing hand to the right of the body</a></li>
<li><a href="#not-swinging-fast">Not swinging fast enough</a></li>
</ol>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Additionally, I studied the serves of the pros while watching hundreds of videos and reading dozens of blog posts. I ultimately identified 10 areas of the second serve that were crucial to its execution. I thought it would be very beneficial to list them all in a single article.</p>
<p>As I bettered my game and started coaching others, I used the knowledge of these 10 areas to improve the second serve of my students. It was rewarding to see them get the same good results. After years of experience playing and coaching, I now feel confident I can help you achieve the second serve you’ve always wanted.</p>
<p>One caveat before we get into it. You can improve one or two areas, but that’s not going to yield outstanding results. If you want to hit a great second tennis serve, you’ll need to be proficient in all areas. Putting them all together in a fluid manner with good timing is the key to an effective second serve in tennis. Of course, it goes without saying, you’ll need to practice.</p>
<p>Some of these ideas will be contrary to what you are currently doing on your serve. You’ll need to break out of your comfort zone to adapt to some new concepts. However, if you’re a newbie to tennis, it may even be easier, as you have no bad habits to break. If you’re an old dog trying to learn new tricks, take your time and start slow. Focus on the process, not the results.</p>
<p>One more thing. If you have a beginner’s serve with an eastern forehand grip, you’ll need to change your serve motion to an advanced one. There are basically only two types of serve motions in my opinion: <a href="/beginners-serve-vs-advanced-tennis-serve-what-are-the-differences/">beginner and advanced</a>.</p>
<p>The beginner motion is commonly referred to as the waiter’s serve with the body and racket strings oriented to the court. There’s no way you can possibly hit with spin with it. If you’re not willing to change, this article won’t help much. I implore you to at least give the advanced serve a try though.</p>
<p>If you already have an advanced serve motion using the continental grip, your ahead of the pack. This article might be the final piece of the puzzle for you in terms of building a quality second serve. So let’s dive in!</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="correct-grip"></a></p>
<h2>Not Holding The Correct Grip</h2>
</div>
<p>If you’re using the <strong>eastern forehand</strong> grip for your serves, you’ll need to scrap it. The eastern forehand grip requires the index knuckle to be on the third bevel. You’ll need to move the index knuckle down to the second bevel, home of the <strong>continental</strong> grip. This is the grip most advanced and professional tennis players use for their first and second serves.</p>
<p>When switching from the eastern to the continental grip, you’ll notice the racket will make about a 90-degree change in the orientation of the face. If you have a beginner’s serve, you may be wondering how you can hit the ball. Don’t concern yourself with that for now. Just make sure you set up for all serves with the continental grip and feel comfortable holding the racket with it.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>It’s important that you trust the grip and not try to change it during the stroke. That was one of my issues early on. I’d set up with the continental grip and in mid-swing, I’d shift into the eastern forehand grip. If you begin the serve with the continental grip, check your hand after you finish your swing to make sure it’s in the same position. Many players are totally oblivious of shifting their hand on the serve – if they do.</p>
<p>Once you begin practicing the serve (after you read this entire post, you’ll be able to do that), you may notice that you’re not getting enough spin with the continental grip. In that case you could move your hand to the <strong>eastern backhand</strong> grip. This will provide more spin but a bit less power.</p>
<p>To find the eastern backhand grip, position the hand so that the index knuckle is now resting on the top bevel, which is bevel number one. A lot of professional tennis players prefer this grip for their second serve. I believe Patrick Rafter (a former two-time U.S. Open champion) preferred the eastern backhand grip for both first and second serves.</p>
<p>This is because Rafter was hitting kick serves most of the time, being he was a serve and volley player. The cool thing about using the eastern backhand grip on your first serve is that you’re most likely to get it in. If you’re not coming to the net, I advise you to stick with the continental grip for your first serve.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="tossing-over-head"></a></p>
<h2>Not Tossing Over The Head</h2>
</div>
<p>I see so many club players trying to hit kick serves with tosses a foot or more to their right (assuming they’re right-handed). Lefties do the opposite. It’s physically impossible as the racket cannot brush on the ball. The proper toss is one that can be struck over the right ear (for righties) and slightly inside the court.</p>
<p>I’ve watched videos of some of the best servers of all time, like John Isner, Pete Sampras, Rafter, etc. Every one of them is tossing the ball over their head on second serves, most by their right ear. This is the only way to impart topspin or kick spin on the serve; slice serves can be tossed a bit more to the side.</p>
<p>For those who toss out to the side, tossing over the head will be a bit of a challenge. This is because a strong racket drop and proper orientation of the body is required to hit a toss above the head. We’ll go into that later. Just trust what I’m saying here first.</p>
<p>I also want to point out a question that comes up often, which is, “Should I arch my back on the second serve?” The answer is no. Don’t arch your back. It’s unnecessary and can hurt your back. Most players bend their knees 90 degrees or further, which makes it look like they’re arching their back.</p>
<p>Lastly, you need to toss so that the ball is slightly into the court. You should be moving up and slightly forward to make contact with the ball. This will allow you to put some power into the shot, as most of the racket head speed will be directed into generating spin.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="tossing-high"></a></p>
<h2>Not Tossing High Enough</h2>
</div>
<p>This is a common error that many club level players make. Most club players have no idea of this and toss both the first and second serves at the same height. Not tossing high enough will kill your chances of hitting with massive spin. The second serve needs to be tossed higher than the first serve for a couple of reasons.</p>
<p><strong>The first is that you’ll want to allow the ball to drop some before contacting it.</strong> The downward speed of the ball (though slight) adds to the velocity of the impact when struck by the racket. This is also due to the racket moving up towards the ball at the same time. On the first serve, where spin is not as important, you can hit the ball with a slightly lower drop from the zenith to contact.</p>
<p><strong>The second reason is that you need a bit more time to hit the second serve.</strong> On second tennis serves, the knees should bend more, the shoulders rotated greater and the hitting arm will be slightly more to the left (for right handed players). You want to allow enough time to hit these important positions before contact.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>Consider this: If you hit the ball near the apex of the toss, how will you generate spin on the ball? Your racket needs some space to brush on the ball, and so a higher toss is necessary. Only when the ball is on its way down can this happen. In contrast, first serves with a lower toss can be hit at the zenith (though not advised) because they don’t require a lot of spin.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="no-racket-drop"></a></p>
<h2>Not Having A Racket Drop</h2>
</div>
<p>The racket drop is when the racket moves into the inverted position where the butt cap is facing the sky. The racket drop comes directly after hitting the power position of the serve. When this occurs, the serving hand of the player drops and the racket falls into the “scratch your back” position some of you know.</p>
<p>Most beginner serves do not have a good racket drop. Some have no racket drop at all. This was my big problem early on with my serve. As a result, I never could develop a second serve until I changed to the advanced serve. If you have a beginner or waiter’s serve and have been banging your head against the wall on why you can’t impart spin, this is the main reason (besides your grip).</p>
<p>Check out my video devoted to how to achieve a proper racket drop:</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="kad-youtube-shortcode videofit"  ><iframe loading="lazy" width="600" height="400" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/yvL5mXGEkuo?autoplay=0&controls=1&fs=1&modestbranding=1&theme=dark&rel=0&loop=0&showinfo=1" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="true"></iframe></div>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Additionally, I wrote an article on how to use a <a href="/learn-how-to-serve-in-10-minutes-with-the-servemaster/">tennis serving device called the ServeMaster</a> to achieve an effortless racket drop. You can also see the video I created on the ServeMaster as well. All of these resources will help you develop a good, deep racket drop. It’s absolutely critical to hitting an effective second serve.</p>
<p>Your racket really needs to move in a clockwise fashion to hit the second serve. The racket will eventually achieve a 6 o’clock position and hit the ball at approximately 12:30 or 1:00 o’clock (with your head being the center of the imaginary clock). Again, this assumes your right-handed. Lefties will be making contact at 11:00-11:30.</p>
<p>There’s another benefit of the racket drop. It allows the racket to generate momentum on its way up to the ball. This momentum translates into racket head speed, which will impart more spin on the ball.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="radial-ulnar"></a></p>
<h2>Not Using Radial And Ulnar Deviation</h2>
</div>
<p>This one added a big boost to my racket head speed. First, let me explain what radial and ulnar deviation are. You can also see the picture I added for a good visual.</p>
<p>Hold your hand out in front of you, palm away, so that you see only the back of your hand. Now move only your hand to the thumb side until it can’t go any further. That’s radial deviation. Now move only your hand in the opposite way, to the side with the little finger. That’s ulnar deviation.</p>
<p>Now that you understand, let me explain how to use it in your second serve. At the point of the deepest part of your racket drop (6 o’clock position), you should achieve radial deviation with the hitting hand. This will also allow you to have a deeper racket drop, which is very good.</p>
<p>As you move your racket up to contact the ball, your hand will remain in the radial deviation position. Just before the racket contacts the ball, you’ll quickly transition to ulnar deviation. This allows for a “snap” of the racket, giving it more speed. You should experience a noticeable difference in racket head speed if done correctly.</p>
<p>Keep in mind this may not be easy to pull off at first. Practice with just the racket in slow motion before using it with an actual serve. You could also hurt your wrist if not done correctly, so start easy. Again, this only works if you use an advanced serve and correct the previous errors I mentioned in this post.</p>
<p>Right after you strike the ball and go into ulnar deviation, you’ll start to pronate. I talked a lot about pronating in other blogs on this post. It’s basically a twisting of the forearm that causes the racket head to face the opposite side. I didn’t mention it as one of the main common errors because it’s actually possible to achieve spin and go through all the steps mentioned in this post without pronating.</p>
<p>Of course, it’s optimal if you do pronate, as it maintains racket speed and all advanced servers use pronation. One question I get asked a lot about is the difference between pronation on the first and second serve. On the first serve the pronation is more violent. On the second serve it is less violent and a bit more elongated, as the swing path is traveling out the side rather than into the court.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="left-to-right"></a></p>
<h2>Not Swinging From Left To Right (For Right-Handed Players)</h2>
</div>
<p>Most beginners and some club players are unaware the first and second serve have totally different swing paths. On the first serve, the racket swings into the court. This is how every beginner serve (whether first or second) hits the ball.</p>
<p><strong>The second serve, however, has a very different swing path.</strong> The swing travels from left to right (for right-handed players). One good way to demonstrate this is to stand at the service line slightly on the ad side. For righties, your first serve swing path will basically follow the path of the midline. However, on the second serve, the swing path will travel along the service line out to the right, never really going forward.</p>
<p>To summarize, on the first serve you swing into the court. For the second serve, you swing out to the side. There’s no getting around it if you want to hit a good topspin serve. Look at all the pros hit their serves in slow motion. You’ll see their rackets move way out to the side after contact.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>This may sound illogical. But trust me, it’s correct. You may be wondering how the ball can go forward if you’re only swinging to the side. Try it. The ball will go forward with no problem, even though you are swinging to the side. This is a concept that is difficult to impress upon someone who has only ever swung into the court.</p>
<p>I recommend a good drill to help you with this. Stand at the baseline, in proper serve stance, with your racket dropped into the 6 o’clock position. This will result in the butt cap of your racket facing the sky.</p>
<p>Toss the ball and move the racket from left to right, finishing the swing path along the baseline. You should see the ball go forward to your target on impact. If you think about it, the strings are aligned to your target the entire time anyway, so it makes sense.</p>
<p>When you hit your second serve, really keep in mind the swing path out to the side. Resist the temptation to hit forward into the court. This should help your second serve out immensely. Again, it can only be done with the advanced serve motion.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="remaining-to-side"></a></p>
<h2>Not Remaining To The Side (Orienting To The Court Too Soon)</h2>
</div>
<p>This error is one of the most common I see at the club level. If you have a beginner’s serve, it won’t mean much. But if you serve with an advanced serve and use the continental grip, then it’s very important. Fortunately, this is one of the easiest errors to fix as well.</p>
<p>The more we can stay oriented to the side (to the right for righties and to the left for lefties), the better we can impart spin on the ball. I think the reason so many players orient to the court (or net) when hitting their second serves is that they learned the first serve initially. On the first serve, it’s important to orient into the court. It also feels natural to do so. But the second serve is different.</p>
<p>To fix this error we need to exaggerate the orientation toward the side. For righties, keep your chest facing to the right during the entire serve motion. You can skip the jumping into the court and just keep your feet planted on the ground while doing this drill.</p>
<p>At first, it will feel uncomfortable and you may not get much pace on the ball. Stay with it. We’re exaggerating the motion at first so you feel what it’s like to stay to the side. Once you become adept at not orienting into the court, you can then go back to your normal serve motion.</p>
<p>When performing your normal serve motion, stay to the side until the racket flares all the way out. Only then should you allow your body to begin facing the court. If you orient to the court too early, you can kiss your topspin serve goodbye.</p>
<p>I recommend you video yourself on a few serves or have a coach or friend watch you. Have them make sure you stay closed (to the side). We can’t see ourselves when we play so video and a coach are crucial to our development.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="keep-head-up"></a></p>
<h2>Not Keeping The Head and Tossing Hand Up</h2>
</div>
<p>This is a bugaboo that afflicts many players. If you watch a professional tennis player serve and then look at most club players, you’ll see a huge difference in form. One major difference I see all the time is the premature dropping of the tossing hand for those club players. Fortunately, this is something that can be corrected quickly.</p>
<p>All great servers leave their tossing hand in the air until the racket begins to ascend upwards out of the racket drop. This is done for a couple of reasons. One, it allows the server to hit the ball higher, which increases the chances of it going in the box. It also creates a higher bouncing ball off the court, which is more difficult to hit.</p>
<p>Two, it keeps the body in one linear line. If the hand is dropped too soon, it breaks the posture or integrity of the body into two units (legs and upper body) and does not allow the kinetic chain to move from the feet up to the ball.</p>
<p>It may feel uncomfortable at first but keep that tossing hand up until you start moving the racket to contact. A good drill I have my students do is to practice the toss alone. Stand in a serve position (with or without the racket) and toss the ball.</p>
<p>Don’t swing at all. Instead keep the tossing hand up and just catch the ball as it comes down – with the tossing arm still fully extended. Keep repeating until you feel comfortable with the drill.</p>
<p>This will get you used to keeping the tossing arm up. As for the head, it will follow the tossing arm somewhat, so lowering the arm will lower the head a bit too. Still, you need to keep your chin up and eyes on the ball throughout the serve.</p>
<p>I see a lot of players looking straight ahead when they serve, hitting the ball by feel. Keep your eyes on the prize and hand to the sky for serving success!</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="arm-into-position"></a></p>
<h2>Not Bringing The Tossing Arm To The Correct Position After It Drops</h2>
</div>
<p>You may have never even thought about this common mistake. While there is no one perfect spot for the tossing arm to move to, there is an ideal location. The tossing arm will begin to drop as soon as you initiate the leg drive upwards. At the same time the racket should be coming around to hit the ball.</p>
<p>The ideal place for the tossing arm to move on the second serve for righties is the right side of the body. I’ll explain how to do this in a minute. Let me tell you the why first. By moving to the right side of your body, the arm stabilizes it, keeping the shoulders from orienting to the court too soon.</p>
<p>Now, for the how. After the tossing arm drops, it should bend at the elbow. Bring the arm across your body so that the forearm is a little higher than the belly button. The right hand should be all the way to the right of your body. Hold that position as long as possible during the serve.</p>
<p>One way to tell if you are doing this correctly is if the hitting arm finishes over, or on top of, the tossing arm. If so, congratulations, you’re on the way to hitting a great second serve. If not, keep practicing.</p>
<p>You’ll probably feel like you’re lacking power by serving this way. It’s a slight exaggeration from a real serve but great practice. When you go back to your regular service motion, you do not have to finish exactly in this position. But you shouldn’t be far off. If you watch Roger Federer hit a second serve in slow motion, you’ll see he keeps his tossing arm across his body after dropping it.</p>
<p>I feel like this is another common serving mistake that can easily be corrected. It does not require intricate timing or a complicated maneuver. Practice slow shadow swings with the tossing arm finishing across the body, in the correct position. Then shadow swing faster until you feel you’re ready to hit real serves.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="not-swinging-fast"></a></p>
<h2>Not Swinging Fast Enough</h2>
</div>
<p>If you don’t have great second serve mechanics, I’m willing to bet the house that you slow your racket speed down on your second serve. You think, “If I swing slower, I’ll have more control. If I swing too fast and the ball will hit the net or fly out.” Unfortunately, that’s how most beginner and club players approach the second serve on big points – and maybe most points.</p>
<p>There’s no way you can generate big spin unless you push your racket speed to its upper limits. And the more spin you achieve, the greater the likelihood you’ll get the serve in the box. But this only applies if you have the right serve mechanics.</p>
<p>This article can set the foundation for you to hit with proper serve mechanics. Once you have worked them all out (no easy chore, I’m sure), only then will you feel confident swinging at full speed. This is how the pros approach their second serve. You’ll rarely see them slow their racket speed on the second serve. If they do, they’ll typically double fault.<br />
Racket head speed is essential to hitting a good second serve. Remember, since your swing path is moving out to the side, you’ll only be grazing the ball, not hitting it head-on. You therefore need as much racket speed as possible to generate sufficient forward velocity.</p>
<p>I find that when I couple ulnar deviation with pronation around contact, I get an explosive movement of the head that really adds extra rpm to the ball. It’s just something you have to experience to understand. Of course, athleticism, age, and flexibility will determine your maximum level of racket head speed. But technique can go along way towards improving it.</p>
<p>Now, if you don’t have all the fundamentals for an advanced serve in place, I have a small hack that can work for you. If you stay absolutely oriented to the side and swing as fast as possible, there’s a chance you may get the serve in routinely with some practice.</p>
<p>I found this to be true for myself, but the serve will certainly lack power. Give it a try. Even if your serving technique is not perfect, it can work as a short-term hack.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Summary</h2>
<p>You might be wondering the best way to apply this information. I would start by videoing your second serve just the way it is. Once you have it on video, play it in slow motion and look at all 10 areas I brought up this article. For example. Is your toss high enough? Is it over your head? Do you keep your tossing arm up long enough? Do you stay oriented to the side?</p>
<p>Once you understand what to look for, you can begin to make corrections. Work on one thing at a time. It all starts with the correct grip, so make sure you’re using the continental or eastern backhand grip off the bat. Then go through each area, making sure each one is resolved. If you get stuck, try using the ServeMaster to help out your swing path.</p>
<p>After you feel you have made progress, video your serve again and then review. What are you doing correctly? What are you not doing correctly? Keep going out to the court alone with a hopper of balls to practice. Have a definite and specific goal for your practice sessions.</p>
<p>For example, for one of your practice sessions, you may want to only work on swinging from left to right (if you’re right-handed). For the practice session, you would start with shadowing the serve with the correct swing path.</p>
<p>When you begin to actually serve, focus on the swing path only. Make sure you swing from left to right, with the racket finishing all the way to the right side with arm extended. Start slowly and build up until you are going full speed.</p>
<p>Sometimes it takes several sessions of doing this until you feel comfortable. Once you do and are swinging correctly, you can then attack the next area, which might be, for example, bringing the tossing arm across your body.</p>
<p>Look, acquiring a great second serve doesn’t come overnight. You’ll need some time, so cut yourself some slack right from the beginning. Hey, Rome wasn’t built in a day, right? If you practice several times a week, and are diligent in your sessions, in a few months you can realistically expect to see the blossoming of an effective topspin serve. I think it’s worth putting in the time if you truly love playing tennis.</p>
<p>In my experience, I like to experiment on the court in my practice sessions. If something’s not going right, I make a slight change and try that. I might get nowhere after an hour, but I don’t despair. Soon after I may notice that one of the changes I made resulted in something great. So I repeat it over and over again. I then make note of it and carry it into my next practice session. This is how progress is made.</p>
<p>Stay with it and believe you can do it. I feel like any able-bodied person can ultimately learn the topspin serve. And once you have it locked in, and your second serve is no longer a detriment, you’ll enjoy tennis a lot more. Not only that, you’ll win a lot more too!</p>
<p>Thanks for coming this far with me. If you have any questions about the second serve, feel free to drop me a comment below.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>The post <a href="/10-common-second-serve-issues-and-how-to-fix-them/">10 Common Second Serve Issues And How To Fix Them</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/10-common-second-serve-issues-and-how-to-fix-them/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Learn How To Serve In 10 Minutes With The ServeMaster</title>
		<link>/learn-how-to-serve-in-10-minutes-with-the-servemaster/</link>
					<comments>/learn-how-to-serve-in-10-minutes-with-the-servemaster/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chad Walner]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 23 Oct 2018 18:46:28 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Reviews]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[serve]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=831</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The serve is the most complicated stroke in tennis. It’s also one of the most difficult to teach. Until now. If you’re not familiar with the ServeMaster by Total Serve, this article could potentially be your gateway to the serve &#8230; <a class="kt-excerpt-readmore" href="/learn-how-to-serve-in-10-minutes-with-the-servemaster/" aria-label="Learn How To Serve In 10 Minutes With The ServeMaster">Read More</a></p>
<p>The post <a href="/learn-how-to-serve-in-10-minutes-with-the-servemaster/">Learn How To Serve In 10 Minutes With The ServeMaster</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The serve is the most complicated stroke in tennis. It’s also one of the most difficult to teach. Until now. If you’re not familiar with the <strong>ServeMaster by Total Serve</strong>, this article could potentially be your gateway to the serve you’ve always wanted. Whether you are a beginner learning how to serve in tennis, or if you have been playing for years but never properly learning the effective serve mechanics, this post is for you.</p>
<p><strong>This post could even save years of time and a lot of cash on expensive lessons. Keep reading if you want to learn how to serve or how to improve your serve in just 10 minutes! The results I’ve seen with the Total Serve never cease to impress me. In this article, I’m going to show you how to use it and a few great drills you can use it for on improving your serves and even your overheads. </strong></p>
<p>In my years of coaching and playing, I’ve seen many kids and club players struggle with their serve for all kinds of reasons. Often, the problem is a bad toss coupled with poor serve mechanics. I can often narrow it down to a much more specific hitch like not hitting up on the ball or a lack of knee bend.</p>
<p>There are so many things that could go wrong with a serve and they are typically difficult pinpoint and then to correct. If you address one issue, it creates another one. I honestly don’t even know how players learned to serve quickly before the ServeMaster was invented. It’s such a useful tool for both adults and kids. Anyone, no matter what their level, can use it.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>What Is The ServeMaster?</h2>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1456" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/smWhat-Is-The-ServeMaster.jpg" alt="What is the servemaster?" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/smWhat-Is-The-ServeMaster.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/smWhat-Is-The-ServeMaster-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/smWhat-Is-The-ServeMaster-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p>The ServeMaster is a teaching tool for the serve and overhead strokes in tennis. It was created by a former professional tennis player named Lisa Dodson. It’s made entirely of rubber. It includes a rubber handle attached to a rubber rope with options for one, two, or three rubber balls at the end. The grip was created for both righties and lefties and teaches the continental grip, which is used on all advanced tennis serves. There are three options to choose from when purchasing the ServeMaster. I’ll go over all three here.</p>
<ul>
<li>The device with one ball is excellent for young children up to ages 10-12.</li>
<li>The device created with two balls will work for kids 12 and up. Adults can easily use this device as well. I personally use the two-ball ServeMaster to warm up before a match.</li>
<li>The third device is made with three balls and is ideal for stronger or bigger adults. The three-ball device, at about 16 oz (or one pound), is great for using as a warm up before serving. Use it for a minute and your racket (typically 10-13 oz) will feel super light when you serve. This is the heaviest of the three ServeMasters.</li>
</ul>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="kad-youtube-shortcode videofit"  ><iframe loading="lazy" width="600" height="400" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/PA5rfvjj7L4?autoplay=0&controls=1&fs=1&modestbranding=1&theme=dark&rel=0&loop=0&showinfo=1" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="true"></iframe></div>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>If you’re an adult new to tennis, I would recommend you purchase the two-ball ServeMaster, as it’s easier to work with than the three-ball model.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.thetotalserve.com/?aff=17" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Check the current price of the ServeMaster here.</a></p>
<p>The ServeMaster is simple, durable, and fun to use. Many tennis coaches, as well as myself, use it with their students. When I teach the tennis serve to a child or beginner, it’s the first thing I use with my students. We’ll get into why next.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Why Is The ServeMaster Effective?</h2>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1457" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/smWhy-Is-The-ServeMaster-Effective.jpg" alt="Why is the ServeMater effective?" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/smWhy-Is-The-ServeMaster-Effective.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/smWhy-Is-The-ServeMaster-Effective-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/smWhy-Is-The-ServeMaster-Effective-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p>In my opinion, The ServeMaster is the most effective training tool for the serve on the market, period. First and foremost, it teaches the student to feel and use the continental grip, which is extremely important for advanced serves. It does this with check marks on the grip.</p>
<p>The advanced tennis serve requires the continental grip. If not used, an advanced serve is just not possible. I also like that both righties and lefties can use the ServeMaster. I’ve personally seen both righties and lefties benefit from the tool equally well.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>The ServeMaster is designed to simulate the feel of the racket with most of the weight being on the end. This gives the user the feeling or experience of how to move the arm and coordinate the body so that it’s in motion the entire time – just like a racket would be while in play. If the practitioner stops or slows their arm, the balls at the end of the device will hit their back. This lets the practitioner know that the swing is not the one fluid motion which it should be.</p>
<p>This amazing device will simulate every part of the serve, including the all-important racket drop. The racket drop is an essential technique which so many adult club players struggle with in their serve. It is when the racket drops into what many players know as the “scratch your back” position. <strong>The ServeMaster can cure this flaw quickly and forever!</strong></p>
<p>Cleverly, the ServeMaster also teaches pronation! How the heck can it do this? I didn’t think that was possible to do with such a simple device. But yet it does. <strong>Pronation is one of the most confusing and misunderstood concepts in tennis.</strong> If you want to know exactly what it is, I wrote about <a href="/beginners-serve-vs-advanced-tennis-serve-what-are-the-differences/">pronation in a recent article</a>.</p>
<p>It can be difficult to apply the concept of pronation in your serve. The cool thing about the ServeMaster is that you don’t even need to know what pronation is, but by using the ServeMaster, it automatically forces you to pronate. For this reason alone, it’s worth the buy.</p>
<p>The weight and length of the ServeMaster makes it a bit cumbersome to use at first. But once the practitioner learns the proper swing path, it’s very easy to use. We’ll go over how to use it a little later on. Once the proper swing path is learned, the practitioner can then incorporate the other components of the serve. These are the toss, the knee bend, the drive up, and the follow through.</p>
<p>I know this next part may sound like hyperbole. But I’ve taught kids as young as eight to have a beautiful serve motion within half an hour. To swing the ServeMaster, proper serving mechanics are essential. Once the kids master the swing, all you need do is put a racket in their hand and they’ll mimic the perfect swing mechanics with the racket. While it’s true, that doesn’t guarantee kids or adults will have an awesome serve in one day. This is because of the other components of the serve.</p>
<p>The player who wants to master their serve must work hard on the other basics, like the toss. And the timing of racket hitting the ball is very crucial as well. That’s where a lot of practice is necessary. But at least the most difficult part of teaching the serve is done, which is the basic motion.</p>
<p>Before learning of the ServeMaster, I tried to manually teach kids and adults how to serve. I did this in a variety of ways. One of my favorite tricks was to have them toss a tennis ball in one hand and throw it with the other (simulating the toss and racket motion). However, none of my training tactics were nearly as effective as the ServeMaster.</p>
<p>I can literally teach a kid how to use the ServeMaster in 5-10 minutes, then take it away and place a racket in their hand. I then ask the child to toss an imaginary ball and swing with the racket. Voila! The perfect serve motion in 10 minutes! It never ceases to amaze me when I see it. From there, we can work on the toss and their timing.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>How A Beginner Can Use The ServeMaster</h2>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1458" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/smHow-A-Beginner-Can-Use-The-ServeMaster.jpg" alt="How can a beginner use the ServeMaster?" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/smHow-A-Beginner-Can-Use-The-ServeMaster.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/smHow-A-Beginner-Can-Use-The-ServeMaster-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/smHow-A-Beginner-Can-Use-The-ServeMaster-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p>To use the ServeMaster all you need is a tennis court. No ball, racket or special equipment is needed. If you don’t have access to a tennis court, you can use your backyard or an outdoor area that allows a radius of 25 feet from the user. Here is how Lisa Dodson, the creator of the ServeMaster, advises beginners to use it. Later in this post, I talk about the advanced version.</p>
<ol>
<li>Start by gripping the ServeMaster. The ServeMaster is labeled “R” on one side of the grip. This is for righties. The other side is labeled “L” for lefties. Each side has two “V” shapes on it that indicate where the hand is to be placed. See the picture on the side for a visual. Basically, the crease between your thumb and index finger will be on the V. The key here is to have the base or bottom of your hand hanging off the grip. Keep a light grip on the ServeMaster – avoid tensing up and gripping hard.</li>
<li>Once you properly grip the ServeMaster, swing it gently at your side. You’ll feel how the weight of the balls shift your hand with the momentum they create. Do this for 30-60 seconds just to feel it.</li>
<li>Next, set up in the proper serve stance with feet in a platform position. The lead foot should be at a 45-degree angle to the baseline and the back foot parallel to the baseline. For righties, the toe of the back foot should be slightly to the left of the lead (left) foot. Lefties can do the opposite.</li>
<li>The hand that is holding the ServeMaster will be raised up so that the part of your arm containing your biceps and triceps is about parallel to the ground. Your arm will look like it’s in a throwing motion with your hand around the middle of your head and close to it. At this point the balls should be dangling behind your back.</li>
<li>If you’re a right-handed player, put your left tossing arm straight up in the air. Keep it there for now. Lefties, do the opposite of all the instructions I give here. Gracias.</li>
<li>Swing your right arm up by fully extending it upwards. At this point your left arm will begin to drop by your left side. Allow the swinging right arm to finish at the left side of your body. Don’t swing ultra-fast. A nice, controlled swing is what’s important here. If you do it right, you should be able to catch the balls with your left hand. That’s it!</li>
</ol>
<p>These six steps are how all beginners and children should start learning with the ServeMaster. This motion mimics the tossing arm staying high up in the air, which most club players and bad servers don’t do. It also trains the body to use the basic swing path of all advanced serves. It’s important the swing contains no hitches. If you stop the motion at any point, the balls will likely hit your body. You’ll then know you are not swinging correctly. Bam – instant feedback! Don’t worry it doesn’t hurt.</p>
<p>A couple of key points that Lisa mentions in her videos is the use of the left hand and right leg in the serve (for righties). The left arm’s purpose is not only for tossing but for creating momentum for the body to raise up. It does this by coming down and to the left side. At the same time, the right leg is pushing off the ground, propelling the hitting arm and body upwards.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>Not to burden you with a thousand things, but there are more key points Lisa mentions. Here are two: keeping your head up and hitting out in front. You’ll want to keep your head, or chin, up during the swing up to contact. If the head drops, the body will likely drop too, not allowing for contact at maximum height. It’s always best to hit the serve at maximum contact point within your abilities; some people jump higher than others.</p>
<p>Lisa also stresses hitting the serve out in front. During your swing, the highest point of the balls will be the contact point on the ball. In this exercise we’re not using a ball, so I just wanted to point that out. It’s vital to not just swing up, but out (meaning in the court) as well.</p>
<p>The last thing I’ll mention in this part of the instructions is pronation. I told you earlier that the ServeMaster teaches proper pronation naturally. For righties, when you begin the swing make sure your palm is facing to the left. As you swing up, your palm will turn to face the court directly at impact (the zenith of the swing). Right after you reach the zenith, your palm will start moving to the right. After it does, just continue your motion in that position, with the right arm finishing its follow through to the left side of the body.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Advanced Use Of The ServeMaster</h2>
<p>Once you master the basic swing path just explained, you can begin to practice the complete serve motion. This will incorporate an actual toss, take back, and knee bend. Follow these instructions for the advanced use of the ServeMaster. Remember, they are written for the right-handed player. Lefties just use the opposite hand or arm.</p>
<ol>
<li>Start with “rope” part of the ServeMaster in your left hand while holding the ServeMaster about waist height in front of you with your dominant hand on the grip.</li>
<li>Let go of the ServeMaster with your left hand and begin a tossing motion, with your left hand going straight up in the air.</li>
<li>At the same time, move the right arm back and into the same “L-Shape” position you started from in the last series of steps (for beginners).</li>
<li>Keep the right arm constantly moving after you begin the swing. Once the balls drop behind your back, you can then lower your left hand (the tossing hand).</li>
<li>As the tossing hand lowers to your left side, the right hand will extend upwards and outwards, like you’re tossing a football. From this point on, the swing path is the same as the beginner method. The main difference is that you’ll have more momentum here and should leave the ground slightly and move into the court.</li>
<li>Do this by jumping (a few inches off the ground is fine) onto your left foot. For those who can’t jump, you can just step forward with your right foot, using your left foot as a pivot.</li>
</ol>
<p>All the top professional players that serve with their right hand land on their left foot. So if you have no physical limitations, you should always land with your weight on the left foot.</p>
<p>When you first start this more advanced method, it’s acceptable to not do part 6 of the above instructions. Just practice steps 1-5 without the jump to get the feel of the swing. Once you have it, you can then incorporate step 6.</p>
<p>A few important key are to be noted here. One, bend your knees when you reach the L-Shape position with your arm. You should remain with bent knees (90 degrees is the ideal) while the dominant hand begins to drop out of the L-Shape. Once the arm begins the forward part of the swing, you should be uncoiling and slightly jumping forward and up. Your legs will obviously be extended at this point.</p>
<p>It’s also important to make sure your left shoulder is higher than your right shoulder while the tossing hand is at its zenith. At impact (if you were hitting a real ball) the right shoulder will be high and the left lower. After you complete the swing, the left shoulder will then be higher once again. This is a cartwheel motion and creates a lot of power on the serve.</p>
<p>One other important point is to keep looking up when you toss and don’t allow your body to sink down. Many club players drop their chins, not keeping their head up at impact, which causes them to hit lower than the maximum impact point. I know I said that earlier in the post, but I have to reiterate to make sure you do not lower your head.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Summary</h2>
<p>The beginning phase of the ServeMaster can be mastered relatively quickly. If you have coordination, 5-10 minutes should be good enough. The advanced method will take a little longer, maybe 10-15 minutes of practice a few times. Once you achieve the whole swing, there isn’t much room to deviate. No ball or racket is involved with the using the ServeMaster, so it really cuts down on the complexity.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.thetotalserve.com/?aff=17" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Check the current price of the ServeMaster here.</a></p>
<p>When you feel that you can complete the correct swing over-and-over and it doesn’t feel like a challenge anymore, you can begin to try with a racket and ball. You may want to try with the racket at first and no ball. Do this for a few minutes. Next, you can pick up a tennis ball and toss it during the motion. However, I have a little trick that will help you here.</p>
<p>Instead of tossing to hit the ball, clearly toss the ball far to your right and out of your reach. Complete the rest of your swing as if the ball was perfectly tossed. The reason for this is to allow your body the feel of tossing while still completing the perfect swing. With your mind not focused on hitting the ball, you can focus on the swing.</p>
<p>The final step is to actually toss into good position to hit the ball – just like a real serve. At first don’t worry where the ball goes. The most important thing here to continue the proper swing. Slowly you’ll make better contact and time your toss appropriately. The toss will really dictate how good your serve will be. You need to time your toss so that by the time your racket reaches the impact point, the ball will be at that spot. That’s really the tricky part of this whole deal.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>Keep practicing. If you find that your swing is falling off tossing a real tennis ball, go back to the advanced method, practice that, and then come back to the real serve. Even if you start to hit great serves, I still recommend using the ServeMaster to practice your form. If you had a terrible serve to begin with, you will now see a marked difference in your serve. And all this can happen in just a few sessions of using the ServeMaster. You should now have a good racket drop, pronate and reach up to the hit the ball. Don’t underestimate using video. Video your swing when you go out and compare as you progress.</p>
<p>Let me know how it goes. If you have any questions, drop them in comment box below. Thanks for reading!</p>
<p>The post <a href="/learn-how-to-serve-in-10-minutes-with-the-servemaster/">Learn How To Serve In 10 Minutes With The ServeMaster</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/learn-how-to-serve-in-10-minutes-with-the-servemaster/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Duds to Aces: 8 Must-Know Tips To Increase Tennis Serve Power</title>
		<link>/duds-to-aces-8-must-know-tips-to-increase-tennis-serve-power/</link>
					<comments>/duds-to-aces-8-must-know-tips-to-increase-tennis-serve-power/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chad Walner]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 07 Oct 2018 11:07:11 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Training]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[serve]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=667</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>We all want more power in our tennis serve. We see professional players on TV hitting serves 120 mph+ and they make it look easy. Yet the average club player has difficulty serving more than 90 mph. Why? It comes &#8230; <a class="kt-excerpt-readmore" href="/duds-to-aces-8-must-know-tips-to-increase-tennis-serve-power/" aria-label="Duds to Aces: 8 Must-Know Tips To Increase Tennis Serve Power">Read More</a></p>
<p>The post <a href="/duds-to-aces-8-must-know-tips-to-increase-tennis-serve-power/">Duds to Aces: 8 Must-Know Tips To Increase Tennis Serve Power</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>We all want more power in our tennis serve. We see professional players on TV hitting serves 120 mph+ and they make it look easy. Yet the average club player has difficulty serving more than 90 mph.</p>
<p>Why?</p>
<p><strong>It comes down to the fundamentals – but they’re often misunderstood. These little things can and do make all the difference. To add more power to our tennis serve, here we will isolate 8 elements and make small improvements in each, which together will give a huge boost to your serve power.</strong></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>We need to take a look at:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="#starting-stance">starting stance</a></li>
<li><a href="#body-rotation">body rotation</a></li>
<li><a href="#power-position">power position</a></li>
<li><a href="#shoulder-alignment">shoulder alignment</a></li>
<li><a href="#racket-drop">racket drop</a></li>
<li><a href="#pronation">pronation</a></li>
<li><a href="#forward-movement">forward movement</a></li>
<li><a href="#follow-through">follow through</a></li>
</ul>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>I’m going to touch on each fundamental in this post, explaining how you can use them to add power to your serve. Afterward, you’ll have a greater understanding of what produces a fast-paced tennis serve. Professional tour level players are simply combining all these fundamentals together into one fluid motion to produce their huge serves. While you may never serve 120 mph, you can certainly add 10-15 mph to your serve and possibly break the 100 mph barrier, which few club players achieve.</p>
<p>If you have a beginner’s serve, I have a series of videos detailing how to achieve an advanced serve on my youtube channel.  Reading this entire post then watching the videos will be very beneficial. I also have a great article on this blog explaining the differences between a <a href="/beginners-serve-vs-advanced-tennis-serve-what-are-the-differences/">beginner and advanced serve</a>.</p>
<p>While my videos are great for visual learning, the blog posts are excellent for relaying the longer technical details. I can provide a lot more information in these posts as opposed to a five-minute video. But the combination of both video and blog posts are by far the best way to learn, so stay tuned to each one.</p>
<p>Now back to the serve. We’ve all heard the saying “the serve is the most important shot in tennis”. It’s true. The serve starts off every point and if you can’t hold serve, you can’t win in tennis. A weak serve will cause you to be on the defensive most of the time. That’s no way to play tennis. So let’s dive into the eight ways you can optimize power on your serve.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="starting-stance"></a></p>
<h2># 1 &#8211; Starting Stance</h2>
</div>
<p>There are only two basic ways to stand when serving: the <strong>platform stance</strong> and the <strong>pinpoint stance</strong>. Let’s define each to make it easy to understand.</p>
<div id="attachment_1283" style="width: 810px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1283" class="size-full wp-image-1283" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0050.jpg" alt="Tennis platform stance." width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0050.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0050-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0050-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /><p id="caption-attachment-1283" class="wp-caption-text">Tennis platform stance.</p></div>
<p><strong>Platform Stance:</strong> The server starts the serve with both feet apart and jumps into the air off both feet. Most of the power on the jump comes from the front foot. The lead foot should be positioned at a 45-degree angle to the baseline. The back foot should be parallel to the baseline. The toes of the back foot should be near the heel of the front foot.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div id="attachment_1284" style="width: 810px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1284" class="size-full wp-image-1284" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0052.jpg" alt="Tennis pinpoint stance." width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0052.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0052-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0052-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /><p id="caption-attachment-1284" class="wp-caption-text">Tennis pinpoint stance.</p></div>
<p><strong>Pinpoint Stance:</strong> The serve starts with both feet apart but upon entering the power position, bring both feet together so they are touching, or nearly touching, and jump off both feet. The power from the jump is more evenly proportioned between both feet.</p>
<p>Let’s talk about the pros and cons of each stance. The platform stance is easier to learn, requires less timing and is better for serving and volleying than the pinpoint. This is because it has fewer moving parts and propels you forward into the court more than the pinpoint. I teach all new players and kids the platform serve first as it&#8217;s easier to learn. Its major drawback is that it&#8217;s less powerful.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>The pinpoint stance produces more power, as the force in the jump is distributed equally in both legs. The momentum of bringing the rear leg forward also provides additional power in the serve, as there is movement involved, rather than starting from a static position like in the platform stance. The pinpoint stance generates more of a vertical explosion in the jump, which will produce more pace on the serve.</p>
<p>If you play with a platform stance, try experimenting with the pinpoint. It may take a few practice sessions to get used to the timing. I have moved intermediate players from the platform to the pinpoint and they have seen good results.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="body-rotation"></a></p>
<h2># 2 – Body Rotation</h2>
</div>
<p>Many players with beginner and advanced serves orient their body way too straight-on to the court. This means they are facing the court, or net, rather than facing away from it. Ideally, your opponent should even see your back some of the time during your serve motion. The best examples of great body rotation on the serve I can think of are John McEnroe and Pete Sampras. Check out their service motions on youtube for examples. Play them in slow motion if you can.</p>

<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0106.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="450" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0106.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="Body rotation for the serve (starting position)." srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0106.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0106-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0106-768x432.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0106-732x412.jpg 732w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0106-366x206.jpg 366w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0106-538x302.jpg 538w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0106-269x151.jpg 269w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0106-560x315.jpg 560w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></a>
<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0107.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="450" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0107.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="Body rotation for the serve (power position)." srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0107.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0107-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0107-768x432.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0107-732x412.jpg 732w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0107-366x206.jpg 366w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0107-538x302.jpg 538w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0107-269x151.jpg 269w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0107-560x315.jpg 560w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></a>
<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0093.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="450" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0093.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="Body rotation for the serve (power position)." srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0093.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0093-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0093-768x432.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0093-732x412.jpg 732w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0093-366x206.jpg 366w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0093-538x302.jpg 538w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0093-269x151.jpg 269w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0093-560x315.jpg 560w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></a>
<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0100.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="450" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0100.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="Body rotation for the serve (with racket drop)." srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0100.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0100-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0100-768x432.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0100-732x412.jpg 732w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0100-366x206.jpg 366w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0100-538x302.jpg 538w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0100-269x151.jpg 269w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0100-560x315.jpg 560w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></a>

<p>If you have a beginner’s serve, you can orient slightly away from the court, but not too much because of your eastern forehand grip. You’ll definitely want to work on developing an advanced serve if you desire strong power on your serve. A beginner’s serve (or waiter’s serve) will only get you so far in tennis. There’s a reason why you won&#8217;t see a waiter’s serve from anyone (male or female) on the pro tour. It doesn’t generate enough pace or spin to compete with advanced service motions.</p>
<p>Advanced servers with a continental grip can orient away from the net to an extreme extent. The rotation of the shoulders will ideally be greater than 90 degrees (perpendicular to the net) but less so in the hips. This disparity between shoulders and hips creates torque in the core of the body, storing up kinetic energy. The uncoiling of the core during the serve motion is what triggers the arm, shoulder and wrist movements that come afterward. Doing it all correctly results in serve speeds in excess of 100 mph.</p>
<p>Without good rotation, the serve becomes more of an arm and shoulder shot. As I just demonstrated, it’s essential to create a coil with the body to add significant pace to your serve. If you have an advanced serve, turn your shoulders more than you normally rotate them. It may feel very uncomfortable at first, but that’s typical.</p>
<p>Get used to the increased shoulder rotation by turning slightly (10-20 degrees) more than normal at first. Continue practicing and shadow-stroking until your shoulders are 110-130 degrees away from the net. This will allow you to begin generating the higher serve speeds you crave.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="power-position"></a></p>
<h2># 3 – Power Position</h2>
</div>
<div id="attachment_1292" style="width: 810px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1292" class="size-full wp-image-1292" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0152.jpg" alt="The Power Position, also known as the Trophy Position." width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0152.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0152-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0152-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /><p id="caption-attachment-1292" class="wp-caption-text">The Power Position, also known as the Trophy Position.</p></div>
<p><strong>All groundstrokes and serves have a power position in tennis.</strong> This is the position you hold briefly before making your forward movement into the ball. I see a lot of club players with no power positions on their groundstrokes and serves. On the serve, the power position is often referred to as the “trophy position”.</p>
<div id="attachment_714" style="width: 410px" class="wp-caption alignright"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-714" class="size-full wp-image-714" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/3888716168_55398d3bc8_z.jpg" alt="" width="400" height="515" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/3888716168_55398d3bc8_z.jpg 400w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/3888716168_55398d3bc8_z-233x300.jpg 233w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" /><p id="caption-attachment-714" class="wp-caption-text"><a title="mathieu serve" href="https://flickr.com/photos/charliecowins/3888716168">&#8220;mathieu serve&#8221;</a> by <a href="https://flickr.com/people/charliecowins">chascow</a> is licensed under <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/">CC BY</a></p></div>
<p>I always recommend taking video of your serve. If you play back the video in slow motion, or even regular speed, you may notice you lack a power position. If so, it would benefit you to achieve it. Or, if you think you do hit a power position, it may be very weak compared to where it could be. If it doesn’t look athletic (knees bent, tossing hand straight up, racket in an L-shape to the forearm, shoulders slanted), you probably have a very poor power position.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>While I can’t go into extreme detail on the power position of the serve here, you can begin to make corrections simply by sight. If you pause the video of your serve in the power position and compare it to the current best servers in the world (or any pro in the top 20), you’ll see considerable differences. Notice those differences and begin to try and close the gap.</p>
<p>Once you identify how to achieve a better power position, begin practicing but without hitting the ball. You can do it with racket in hand or even without a racket. I often practice my serve form at home in front of a mirror with no racket or ball. Make sure you are hitting all the key points of the power position and then hold it for 3-5 seconds. Once you are done holding it, you can continue the rest of the serve motion. I find this really helps my service motion when I really serve.</p>
<p>Almost every great server achieves a great power position. They almost seem to pause there for just a few milliseconds before completing the remainder of their motion. I can all but guarantee you if you improve your power position, you’ll improve the power in your serve. Give it a try. It’ll be a challenge at first but keep working at it. If you have a coach or someone who can keep a trained eye on you while you serve, all the better.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="shoulder-alignment"></a></p>
<h2># 4 – Shoulder Alignment</h2>
</div>
<p>When I talk about shoulder alignment, I mean the angle of the shoulders relative to the ground. Think of a line that’s about 45 degrees in relation to the floor. I had shoulder rotation earlier in the post, but in relation to the court or net. What we are talking about here is different.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-1296 size-full" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0152angle.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0152angle.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0152angle-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0152angle-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p>I’ve studied many of the great servers of the last two generations. In case-after-case, I noted almost all of them have at least a 45-degree angle of alignment in their shoulders (to the ground) in the power position. One of the sharpest angles I saw was in Pete Sampras (nearly 60 degrees on some serves).</p>
<p>At the club level, most of the servers I see don’t even come close to a 45-degree angle on their shoulder alignment. For example, if you’re a right-handed player, your left shoulder should be much higher than your right shoulder in the power position. All you need do is take a video or picture in the power position and then draw a line through your shoulders. You’ll easily be able to see the angle in relation to the ground.</p>
<p>A big reason for a poor angle in club players’ serves is the early dropping of the tossing arm. If the arm drops too early, so do the shoulders. Another reason for a poor angle is that club players don’t achieve the stretch in their side obliques that make the correct shoulder alignment possible. If you ever notice, great servers flair out their hip (the one closest to the baseline) into the direction of the court. This makes their bodies appear like a bow, constricted and coiled. When uncoiled it unleashes massive power in comparison to not using the body properly.</p>
<p>If you want to gain effortless power on your serve, keep your tossing arm up longer than usual, flair out your front hip, and make sure your rear shoulder really dips much closer to the ground. I’m a big believer in exaggerating postures until they become habit. Try going through your service motion with these ideas in mind. You don’t even need to be on a court or use a racket or ball.</p>
<p>Check your form in a mirror and make sure you see a strong dip (the tossing shoulder much higher than the hitting shoulder) in the power position. Keep working on this until you become comfortable and then practice it in serves with a racket and ball. If you can achieve even a 10-15 degree increase in your dip, it will certainly add a few miles per hour to your serve.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="racket-drop"></a></p>
<h2># 5 – Racket Drop</h2>
</div>
<p>The racket drop is a very big deal when it comes to effortless serve power. This is the part of the serve where the racket inverts (even if for a millisecond) and the butt cap is facing the sky. Without exception, every top professional player has a deep racket drop (strong inversion).</p>
<div id="attachment_712" style="width: 410px" class="wp-caption alignright"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-712" class="wp-image-712 size-full" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/877694390_ba616ed92d_z.jpg" alt="" width="400" height="306" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/877694390_ba616ed92d_z.jpg 400w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/877694390_ba616ed92d_z-300x230.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" /><p id="caption-attachment-712" class="wp-caption-text"><a title="Andy Roddick serving at Wimbledon" href="https://flickr.com/photos/koltregaskes/877694390">&#8220;Andy Roddick serving at Wimbledon&#8221;</a> by <a href="https://flickr.com/people/koltregaskes">Kol Tregaskes</a> is licensed under <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/2.0/">CC BY-NC-ND</a></p></div>
<p>One of the deepest racket drops ever seen on the pro tour was that of Andy Roddick. If you have a chance to check out his serve in slow motion, I advise you to take note how deep is racket drop is. It was even deeper than Federer, which is why Andy averaged serve speeds about 10 mph more than Federer.</p>
<p>I find that club players either completely lack a racket drop or they have a very shallow one. Of all nine fundamentals mentioned in this post, the racket drop was my biggest problem for years. I corrected it using several drills that I recommend in this blog and my youtube channel. I’m sorry to say, but if you don’t have a deep racket drop, you’re likely never going to reach your potential in terms of serve speed.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>The reason for this is simple. A deep racket drop allows the racket to travel a longer distance to the target than no racket drop or a shallow one. A longer distance (for the racket to travel) translates into more momentum and a much stronger impact. I’ve noticed a huge difference when the racket drop is done correctly and when there is none.</p>
<p>The only way to tell what kind of racket drop you have is to video your serve. The racket typically moves to fast to tell, unless it’s blatantly obvious you have none. If your racket drop is non-existent or very poor, check out this video I made on <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=yvL5mXGEkuo" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">how to improve your racket drop</a>. By developing a deep racket drop, you’re sure to add good velocity to the serve. It may take time to develop, but it’s worth it. This is one of the most important factors in hitting powerful serves. It’s also crucial for being able to generate topspin serves.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="pronation"></a></p>
<h2># 6 – Pronation</h2>

<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/mSuppination1.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="450" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/mSuppination1.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="Supination" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/mSuppination1.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/mSuppination1-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/mSuppination1-768x432.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/mSuppination1-560x315.jpg 560w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></a>
<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/Pronation1.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="450" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/Pronation1.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="Pronation" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/Pronation1.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/Pronation1-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/Pronation1-768x432.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/Pronation1-560x315.jpg 560w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></a>

</div>
<p>I’ve said a lot about pronation in <a href="/10-tennis-drills-you-can-practice-without-a-court/#serve-pronation">previous articles</a>. It’s basically rotating the forearm 180 degrees. I’ll show you how to do it now. Put your arm straight in front of you with palm facing up (called supination). Now turn your palm down, twisting your forehand but keeping your arm in the same position. Congratulations, you just pronated.</p>
<p>This is what’s happening on the serve just before impact and just after impact. Pronation alone can gain you an extra 5-10 mph if timed perfectly right. It allows the racket face to move in two dimensions to the ball – towards it and turning into it. If you don’t pronate, then you’ll always be hitting the ball in one dimension and never be able to generate the kind of pace professional players do.</p>
<p>If you’ve been playing tennis a long time with a beginner’s serve or no pronation whatsoever, it’s going to be difficult to pick up. I can’t lie about that. Early on in my playing days, I didn’t pronate. I was never taught how to serve properly so I hit a waiter’s serve with an eastern forehand grip. When I learned about pronation and saw the great benefits, I decided to teach it to myself after years of playing without it.</p>
<p>It took me a couple of months of constant practice to get used to the continental grip and twisting the forearm at just the right time. I’m glad to say that now it has become as natural for me to use as driving a car or tying my sneakers. One easy way to learn pronation (and the racket drop) is to use the ServeMaster, created by Lisa Dodson. I have a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=PA5rfvjj7L4" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">ServeMaster video</a> on youtube devoted to using it. You should also <a href="/learn-how-to-serve-in-10-minutes-with-the-servemaster/">check out my post all about it</a> to see if it might be for you.</p>
<p>If you don’t pronate on your serve and you’re serious about tennis, I highly recommend you give it a try. Remember, it can take weeks or months to learn, so give it time. Or, who knows, maybe you’ll pick it up right away. I can guarantee you it will make a difference in your serve speed. But you’ll need to develop a racket drop and use the continental grip to make it work. So many of these fundamentals go hand-in-hand with each other it seems.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="forward-movement"></a></p>
<h2># 7 – Forward &amp; Upward Movement</h2>
</div>
<p>This section is what most people think of as a &#8220;jump into the serve&#8221;. After striking the ball on the serve, our momentum should cause our body weight to move upward and forward, following the path of the ball. Most professional tennis players get at least 4-5 inches off the ground. This is actually the result of momentum from a violent body motion rather than jumping.</p>
<div id="attachment_718" style="width: 385px" class="wp-caption alignright"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-718" class="size-full wp-image-718" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/235443062_af625f9a90_z.jpg" alt="" width="375" height="500" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/235443062_af625f9a90_z.jpg 375w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/235443062_af625f9a90_z-225x300.jpg 225w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 375px) 100vw, 375px" /><p id="caption-attachment-718" class="wp-caption-text"><a title="Leaning into serve" href="https://flickr.com/photos/75449583@N00/235443062">&#8220;Leaning into serve&#8221;</a> by <a href="https://flickr.com/people/75449583@N00">upabreak.com</a> is licensed under <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/">CC BY</a></p></div>
<p>If your mechanics are poor in the previous fundamentals, you’ll likely not experience this upward and forward movement. I almost feel it’s a very violent strike of the ball with the whole body. When I do it right, I can see and feel my opponents flinching on the other side of the net just before I hit the ball. If you never experience this, don’t worry. You can still hit fast-paced serves by trying to direct your body forward.</p>
<p>For sure, the upward movement comes mostly from bending your knees are pressing on the ground. If you lack a good knee bend or just can’t do it, you can at least initiate a forward movement by leaning forward the moment of contact. Just allow your body to fall forward a bit when you strike the ball. You’ll notice your serve is slightly faster and a bit heavier – meaning it doesn’t lose as much pace after hitting the ground.</p>
<p>On the serve, it’s best to land on the opposite leg of your dominant hand. A right-handed player will land on his left leg (and vice-versa for lefties). You typically want your weight slightly over the leg you land on. But if this doesn’t seem possible, just make sure you are finishing the serve inside the baseline. Even six inches of forward movement is better than none at all.</p>
<p>I honestly find this fundamental to be quite difficult if one doesn’t have that initial upward explosion. Whenever I serve and lack that explosion, jumping upward and forward always feels manufactured and forced. Even worse it throws my timing off the serve. Resist the temptation to jump only for the sake of jumping. You can still hit hard serves with forward movement. Before the modern era of tennis, the server was not allowed to jump or leave the ground, and they still hit fast serves – even with wooden rackets!</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="anchor">
<p><a name="follow-through"></a></p>
<h2># 8 – Follow Through</h2>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1347" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0111.jpg" alt="Follow through." width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0111.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0111-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0111-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
</div>
<p>When I talk about follow through, I’m talking about the hitting arm. I see many club players abruptly stop their arms after hitting the ball. It kind of looks like an invisible force field has frozen their arms, bringing them from a swinging motion to a dead stop. This kind of follow through, or lack of it, is caused by tensing the muscles of the arm way too tight.</p>
<p>The sooner you stop the hitting arm, the less racket speed you generate. The less racket speed you generate, the slower the serve. Make sense? This is also true on groundstrokes. That’s the reason why professional tennis players follow through so far; it keeps the racket speed high upon impact of the ball. When serving, follow through is just as important.</p>
<p>I like to follow through with my right arm slightly bent at the elbow and on the left side of my body – just like you’d see from a major league pitcher. This is especially true of first serves. On second serves, it’s also important to follow through, except the path of the racket is going out to the side. rather than into the court. I find that whether it be a first serve or a second serve, the follow-through is crucial to generating higher speeds and spins.</p>
<p>I know I might sound like a broken record, but the ServeMaster is an excellent tool for the serve and to get you following through. This is because the weighted balls at the end almost force your arm to keep going. It’s only natural that your arm will swing to the other side of your body.</p>
<p>If you are having difficulty with this during your real serves, practice swinging with only your racket. Try to keep your arm and grip super-loose on the serve motion and follow through. Just let the arm finish where it naturally wants to go. If this doesn’t help, swing slower.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>I can almost promise you that if you serve full speed, this will be a challenge for you to change. You must first start out using slow shadow swings (with and without the racket) and build up the muscle memory for it. This is the best way to elongate the follow through. I know this through my own experience and that of my clients. I always use slow swings first (in all strokes) to build the muscle memory before going full speed. Trust me on this.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Putting It All Together</h2>
<p>If you only use brute force to increase serve speed, you’ll tire yourself out, potentially injure your body, and never reach the speeds your capable of reaching. But by focusing on the fundamentals I outlined in this article, you can begin to see some nice changes pretty quickly. Pick one or two fundamentals that will be the easiest to change and start working on them. Perhaps you’ll soon notice the improvement in your serve pace and want to pick up the other fundamentals.</p>
<p>Building a great serve takes time, lots of practice, and sometimes going back to the drawing board before lasting improvement is made. Don’t ever give up. Video your serve every practice session if you can. Take a hopper of balls and practice serving on your own. Have a goal for the practice session. Maybe you’ll work on rotating your shoulders more or following through better. Pick one thing at a time and then work on it for a while.</p>
<p>Trying new things in a match usually doesn’t work. You need to set aside time to practice alone or with your coach. Consistent practice with specific and measurable goals are game-changers. If tennis is your passion, take your craft seriously and put in the work. I do. The most fun you can have in tennis is to see the fruit of your practice labors fulfilled in match play. Trust me, it’s well worth it.</p>
<p>The post <a href="/duds-to-aces-8-must-know-tips-to-increase-tennis-serve-power/">Duds to Aces: 8 Must-Know Tips To Increase Tennis Serve Power</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/duds-to-aces-8-must-know-tips-to-increase-tennis-serve-power/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Beginner Serve Vs. Advanced Tennis Serve – Simple Tips To Unlock Your Potential</title>
		<link>/beginners-serve-vs-advanced-tennis-serve-what-are-the-differences/</link>
					<comments>/beginners-serve-vs-advanced-tennis-serve-what-are-the-differences/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chad Walner]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 03 Oct 2018 10:35:33 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Training]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[serve]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=614</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>In the world of tennis, there are two types of serves: the beginner serve and the advanced serve. The beginner’s serve is often referred to as the “waiter’s tray serve” or just the &#8220;waiter&#8217;s serve&#8221;. The advanced serve is the &#8230; <a class="kt-excerpt-readmore" href="/beginners-serve-vs-advanced-tennis-serve-what-are-the-differences/" aria-label="Beginner Serve Vs. Advanced Tennis Serve – Simple Tips To Unlock Your Potential">Read More</a></p>
<p>The post <a href="/beginners-serve-vs-advanced-tennis-serve-what-are-the-differences/">Beginner Serve Vs. Advanced Tennis Serve – Simple Tips To Unlock Your Potential</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/checklist.jpg"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignright wp-image-629 size-full" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/checklist.jpg" alt="" width="400" height="688" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/checklist.jpg 400w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/checklist-174x300.jpg 174w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" /></a></p>
<p>In the world of tennis, there are two types of serves: the beginner serve and the advanced serve. The beginner’s serve is often referred to as the “waiter’s tray serve” or just the &#8220;waiter&#8217;s serve&#8221;. The advanced serve is the technique used by ALL professional tennis players. Which one do you have? After reading this post, you’ll have a very clear answer to that question.</p>
<p><strong>I’ve isolated six major elements that you can use to distinguish the beginner serve from an advanced serve: grip, body orientation to the court, racket drop, coming up with the racket flat or on edge, pronation, and jump. </strong></p>
<p><strong>We’ll look at these six categories and explore how they’re different in the two serves. If you have a waiter’s serve, don’t despair. You can still play tennis and serve quite effectively at the club level. At the same time, if you’re willing to make changes, you absolutely can develop an advanced serve. By knowing the differences, you’ll be able to start making those changes. </strong></p>
<p>This post is not a guide on exactly how to serve, but rather on the various options you have, and why some are better than others. I have videos on my youtube channel that take these points and show clearly how to put them into practice. Perhaps one of the easiest ways to learn the advanced serve is with the<a href="/10-common-second-serve-issues-and-how-to-fix-them/"> ServeMaster tennis training aid by Lisa Dodson.</a> It’s great for changing a beginner’s serve to an advanced one or teaching a new player the correct way to serve. If you currently have a beginner’s serve, it’s important to know the differences between it and an advanced serve. So without further delay, let’s get right into it.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Know Your Tennis Grip</h2>
<p>A rackets handle is shaped like an octagon and so has 8 faces around which your fingers find their grip. To describe the various tennis grips we begin by noting how your hand fits around the tennis racket handle and exactly which face you wrap your index finger around.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>The proper tennis grip for an advanced serve is the <strong>continental grip</strong>. The continental grip is a very natural grip, similar to how you hold a hammer. It has the position of the racket nearly perpendicular to the ground. Typically, the index knuckle is going to be on the second face with the heel pad on the bottom face. There is very little deviation in this grip for all advanced serves, as it allows for pronation (more on this below) and different types of spins.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div id="attachment_617" style="width: 404px" class="wp-caption alignleft"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-617" class="wp-image-617 size-full" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/RacketEndCapFaces.jpg" alt="Tennis racket end used to find grip." width="394" height="400" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/RacketEndCapFaces.jpg 394w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/RacketEndCapFaces-296x300.jpg 296w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 394px) 100vw, 394px" /><p id="caption-attachment-617" class="wp-caption-text">Tennis racket end cap.</p></div>
<p>The beginner&#8217;s serve utilizes what is called an &#8220;eastern forehand grip&#8221;. This grip rotates the hand around the racket so that the index knuckle grips around face three. Instead of the racket being perpendicular to the ground, the strings of the racket are directly facing the ground. This means there’s almost a 90-degree difference in the racket face in the two serve grips.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>The eastern forehand grip allows the beginner to keep the strings aligned with the ball all the way through the serve. This is the most logical way to hit a tennis ball. If you handed a racket to someone who never played tennis before, this is likely the grip they would use to hit the ball. The drawback of this grip is it does not allow for pronation and much variety of spin. The ball can only ever be hit “flat” with hardly any side or forward spin. However, I have seen club players use the eastern forehand grip to hit backspin on their serves, which I do not recommend.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>To develop an advanced serve, you absolutely MUST use the continental grip. That’s the first step. Doing so will open the floodgates to better tennis. Not only will you serve better, you’ll hammer out more effective overheads. If you have a beginner’s serve and change to the continental grip, at first you’re very likely to hit the ball off the court. This is because the extreme change in the racket face will cause you to hit the ball almost on the side of the racket. This is only an issue if you do not correct the other elements of the serve.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-92" style="margin-bottom: 0px; padding-bottom: 0px;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/practice-tips220x40.png" alt="" width="220" height="40" /></p>
<blockquote><p>Learn to use the <strong>continental grip</strong> in your server for much better ball control, power and spin.</p></blockquote>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Body Orientation To The Court</h2>

<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0089.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="400" height="400" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0089.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="Beginner stance." srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0089.jpg 400w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0089-150x150.jpg 150w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0089-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" /></a>
<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0087.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="400" height="400" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0087.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="Advanced stance." srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0087.jpg 400w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0087-150x150.jpg 150w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0087-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" /></a>

<p>Almost all beginners orient their body directly to the net post. This means their chest is facing the net. Again, they do this because it’s the most logical way to serve a tennis ball. There’s no easier way to hit than to align your body and racket face directly to the ball. That’s the way all kids and beginners hit until they properly learn to serve. The main drawback is it does not allow for maximum power, as there is no body torque.</p>
<p>In contrast, advanced tennis serves require you to face your body away from the court. Most professionals will angle their bodies at least 90 degrees from the net. Some players, like Pete Sampras and John McEnroe, will go well beyond 90 degrees. They’re almost at 150 degrees! This creates an excessive amount of body torque, which translates into serve power. When advanced players serve, their opponents can basically see their backs – if only for a second.</p>
<p>If a beginner player uses the eastern forehand grip (and they almost all do), he or she cannot orient away from the court. This type of player must face the court to hit with the eastern grip. Almost the same can be said for an advanced player. Almost no player using a continental grip can face the court and serve. It would feel very uncomfortable and limited on power.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-92" style="margin-bottom: 0px; padding-bottom: 0px;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/practice-tips220x40.png" alt="" width="220" height="40" /></p>
<blockquote><p>Face your body <strong>away from the net</strong> to effectively use the continental grip in your serve.</p></blockquote>
<p>As we now see, grip determines body orientation to the court. The serve can be compared to a chain. If the first link is broken, the rest of the chain will be compromised. An advanced serve starts with the proper grip (continental) and body orientation (away from the court). Once we have these first two steps down, which anyone can do, we can look at the third element.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Racket Drop</h2>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-1199 size-full" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0108.jpg" alt="Racket drop." width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0108.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0108-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0108-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p>The racket drop occurs after hitting the “trophy pose” during the serve. What I’m about to describe are the mechanics for the advanced serve. For righthanded players, the arm will move from right-to-left behind the player’s head and the opposite holds true for lefties.</p>
<p>As the arm moves to the left of the player’s head, the elbow will be high (shoulder level or higher) and the racket will invert so that the butt, or very bottom of the racket, faces the sky. This all happens very quickly but once the racket is fully inverted, it’s known as the <strong>racket drop position</strong>.</p>
<p>The deeper the racket drop, the more power one will achieve in the serve. If you look at any professional player, you’ll see deep racket drops. This allows for the racket to travel a longer path before striking the ball. Why is this important? It’s because the racket head can build up maximum momentum and speed before impacting the ball.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>In contrast, the beginner’s serve has a very slight racket drop or sometimes none at all. This results in much less power on the serve. Simply put, the grip and body orientation of the beginner serve doesn’t allow a proper racket drop to occur.</p>
<p>Throughout this article, I’ve been fairly simple in my use of tennis jargon. I like to take complex ideas and make them simple to understand. But I’m going to get a little technical here and mention wrist mechanics because I think it’s important to point out.</p>
<p>An advanced serve utilizes the wrist movement of radial flexion and ulnar flexion on the racket drop and swing up to contact. The beginner serve, however, uses hyperextension and flexion (with the wrist) on the same parts of the serve swing. This not nearly as effective as radial and ulnar flexion.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-92" style="margin-bottom: 0px; padding-bottom: 0px;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/practice-tips220x40.png" alt="" width="220" height="40" /></p>
<blockquote><p>Learn to use a deep <strong>racket drop</strong> to greatly increase power on your serves.</p></blockquote>
<p>In summary, if we can use the continental grip, orient away from the court and make a deep racket drop, we are well on our way to hitting an advanced tennis serve. As we can see, there is a marked difference between each element so far. Now we get into the swing-up-to-contact part of the serve.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="kad-youtube-shortcode videofit"  ><iframe loading="lazy" width="600" height="400" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/hMR18Pp-qrM?autoplay=0&controls=1&fs=1&modestbranding=1&theme=dark&rel=0&loop=0&showinfo=1" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="true"></iframe></div>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Racket Face Position – Flat vs On Edge</h2>

<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0098.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="400" height="400" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0098.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="Racket flat." srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0098.jpg 400w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0098-150x150.jpg 150w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0098-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" /></a>
<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0101.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="400" height="400" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0101.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="Racket on edge." srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0101.jpg 400w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0101-150x150.jpg 150w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0101-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" /></a>

<p>An advanced serve will have a deep racket drop so that the racket is inverted (butt cap to the sky) before it begins its swing path to the ball. Once the swing path initiates, the racket will move, or lead, to the ball with the racket edge facing first. To anybody watching, it looks like the server is trying to hit the ball with the side of his or her racket. This is very evident when we see the advanced serve in slow motion.</p>
<p>When the advanced server begins the forward swing to the ball, the palm of the hand will be facing in the opposite direction. For example, a righty’s palm will face to the left when swinging up. This causes the racket to lead on edge with the racket face perpendicular to the ground for some time.</p>
<p>In contrast, the beginner initiates the swing with his palm facing upward. This places the racket in the “waiter’s serve” position with the racket face parallel to the ground, like a waiter holding a tray. Again, this occurs because it is much easier to hit a ball square on by aligning the strings to the ball long before contact.</p>
<p>When the two serves are shown side-by-side in slow motion video, the differences become very obvious. I should point out that even players using an advanced serve can have difficulty with racket position on the serve. It is not uncommon for someone to use the continental grip, orient away from the ball and have a decent racket drop but still swing the racket straight on with no rotation, and all their hard work still leaves them with a waiter’s tray serve. This happens to players trying to use an advanced serve because they don’t trust the process of pronation.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-92" style="margin-bottom: 0px; padding-bottom: 0px;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/practice-tips220x40.png" alt="" width="220" height="40" /></p>
<blockquote><p>Imagine hitting the ball <strong>with the racket edge</strong>. Combine this with the next step, pronation, to develop a complete and powerful serve.</p></blockquote>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Pronation</h2>

<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0019.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="450" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0019.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="Supination" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0019.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0019-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0019-768x432.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0019-560x315.jpg 560w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0019-732x412.jpg 732w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0019-366x206.jpg 366w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></a>
<a class="thumbnail" href='/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0020.jpg'><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="450" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0020.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="Pronation" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0020.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0020-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0020-768x432.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0020-560x315.jpg 560w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0020-732x412.jpg 732w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0020-366x206.jpg 366w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></a>

<p>You’ve probably heard coaches and players telling you to “snap the wrist” for more spin and power on your serve but they don’t explain what it means in detail.  You are left wondering and you try to “snap your wrist” on your serve. But after doing so a few times, it hurts your wrist and doesn’t work. You then give up, mystified at the wrist snap and never understanding how pronation plays a part in the serve.</p>
<p>It took me months of study before I finally realized how advanced players are getting so much racket head speed in their serves. I’ll reveal the secret now:<strong> it’s a combination of radial and ulnar flexion with pronation.</strong></p>
<p>Still a mystery? Well don&#8217;t worry, you don&#8217;t need to be a doctor or a Latin scholar to master the tennis serve.</p>
<p>Basically, this just describes specific arm movements that you can use to generate that extra racket speed that is impossible to manufacture by swinging the arm from the shoulder alone. The arm is basically acting like a whip, and the wrist holding the racket finishes the job.</p>
<p>Now that we know that, we can move on to defining pronation, and along with it, supination. Here’s one of the clearest definitions I found on google:</p>
<blockquote><p>Pronation and supination are a pair of unique movements possible only in the forearm and hands, allowing the human body to flip the palm either face up or face down.</p></blockquote>
<p>So &#8220;twisting&#8221; seems like a more accessible word to use, right? Pronate by twisting a right arm counterclockwise, supinate by twisting clockwise.</p>
<p>To give you an easy visual, do the following easy exercise. Put your dominant arm straight out in front (not to the side) of you around shoulder level. Your palm should face up to the sky. Now turn your hand down so your palm is facing the floor. This rolling motion is called &#8220;pronation&#8221;. Rolling the hand back to the palm up position is called &#8220;supination&#8221;.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>All advanced serves are using pronation while striking the ball. But it’s occurring while the arm is extending upwards toward the ball. This allows the racket to move in a second dimension when contacting the ball. The racket is moving towards the ball from one angle (first dimension) and the face is rotating in another (second dimension). This speeds up the racket head and causes a stronger impact resulting in more spin and power.</p>
<p>In contrast, the beginner serve has zero pronation. The only wrist movement that can occur with a beginner serve is hyperextension and flexion, which again, is not good for the wrist. This is the main reason a lot of players with beginner serves hurt their wrist.</p>
<p>Since I moved to Florida almost 12 years ago, I’ve been playing an average of 2-3 hours per day. Some days I play 5-6 hours. Not once have I sustained a tennis related injury.</p>
<p>Good form begets an injury-free tennis life. There is no reason you should ever suffer injuries from the movement of your body if your form is ideal.</p>
<p>If you use a beginner serve, pronation is simply impossible. The player with the beginner serve cannot align their strings in the direction of the ball while simultaneously pronating. Pronation is only possible by approaching the ball with the edge of the racket. If a beginner player thinks he can snap his wrist with hyperextension and flexion, he is headed down a bad road. That limited movement can lead to injury and will never match the speed and efficiency of pronation.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-92" style="margin-bottom: 0px; padding-bottom: 0px;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/practice-tips220x40.png" alt="" width="220" height="40" /></p>
<blockquote><p><strong>Pronate</strong>, or twist, the racket face as it moves to contact the ball.</p></blockquote>
<p>Up to this point, we’ve discussed five components of the serve. Let’s look at the last one, which is the jump.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>The Jump</h2>
<p>The jump typically occurs in advanced serves and rarely in beginner serves. It’s the final part of the serve, where the server jumps for height and lands on the leg opposite his dominant arm. For example, a right-handed player will jump onto his left leg and the opposite is true of a lefty. Beginner serves usually have no jump, or at best, one foot stays on the ground and one shifts forward.</p>
<p>If an advanced server utilizes all five components, the end result is the jump. It’s produced by the forward and upward momentum of the stroke. This advanced serve has an explosive element that a beginner’s serve completely lacks. That explosive element naturally produces a motion that moves the player off the ground. Almost all good advanced servers will land on one foot inside the baseline from this jump.</p>
<p>You may not have ever realized this to be true. But look at the best servers in the game – or any professional players on TV. Notice how they all land on one foot inside the court, with their momentum going forward. However, when you watch a beginner’s serve, it looks like they start and finish their serve in the same spot. The forward movement of the body adds power to the serve, which makes advanced serves so difficult to return.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-92" style="margin-bottom: 0px; padding-bottom: 0px;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/practice-tips220x40.png" alt="" width="220" height="40" /></p>
<blockquote><p><strong>Jump into your serve</strong> for explosive power.</p></blockquote>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Summing It All Up</h2>
<p>If you’ve made it this far, you can see there are huge differences in the technicalities of a beginner serve and an advanced one. Truly, an advanced serve takes a long time to master. Most players using an advanced serve today started off learning it as children. If taught early and correctly, the advanced serve feels completely natural for the trained player later in life.</p>
<p>On the other hand, if you’ve been playing with a beginner’s serve your whole life and want to transition to the advanced serve, it’s going to take a lot of work. I’m not going to lie. I’ve worked with older players who have either complete beginner serves or many aspects of a beginner’s serve. It’s nearly impossible to change their muscle memory without doing thousands of reps of ingraining the new swing. Usually, though, older players don’t want to put in that time and effort. As a result, we work on improving their beginner or waiter’s serve.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>If you are absolutely intent on learning the advanced serve, whether you currently use a beginner’s serve or are new to tennis, it’s completely possible to learn, especially with the advanced tools available today. I think the ServeMaster is a great tool for learning the advanced serve. It will teach you to hold the correct grip, show you how to transition into a good racket drop and pronate. It does this for you naturally, without you having to think about it.</p>
<p>Once you feel comfortable with the Servemaster, you can replicate the swing with a racket. It should drastically improve your overall serve motion. In the future, I plan to make a long blog and video series on how to learn the advanced serve – so stay tuned. Thanks for reading and leave me a comment below if you have any questions.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>The post <a href="/beginners-serve-vs-advanced-tennis-serve-what-are-the-differences/">Beginner Serve Vs. Advanced Tennis Serve – Simple Tips To Unlock Your Potential</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/beginners-serve-vs-advanced-tennis-serve-what-are-the-differences/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>5</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
