<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>coaching Archives - Serve and Volley Tennis</title>
	<atom:link href="/tag/coaching/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/tag/coaching/</link>
	<description>Your secret weapon on the court.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 12 Jul 2019 09:38:48 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	

<image>
	<url>/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/cropped-ted_svt_favicon-32x32.png</url>
	<title>coaching Archives - Serve and Volley Tennis</title>
	<link>/tag/coaching/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>How Much Does It Cost To Play Tennis?</title>
		<link>/how-much-does-it-cost-to-play-tennis/</link>
					<comments>/how-much-does-it-cost-to-play-tennis/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chad Walner]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 16 Jan 2019 16:09:26 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Theory]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[coaching]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1931</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>I’ve been playing tennis for 25 years and I can tell you it does cost money to play. But it may surprise you how little it can cost in the right locations. The cost to play tennis varies depending on &#8230; <a class="kt-excerpt-readmore" href="/how-much-does-it-cost-to-play-tennis/" aria-label="How Much Does It Cost To Play Tennis?">Read More</a></p>
<p>The post <a href="/how-much-does-it-cost-to-play-tennis/">How Much Does It Cost To Play Tennis?</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I’ve been playing tennis for 25 years and I can tell you it does cost money to play. But it may surprise you how little it can cost in the right locations.</p>
<p><strong>The cost to play tennis varies depending on your location and several other factors. If you’re curious to know if tennis only a rich man’s sport, this post will spell it all out for you.</strong></p>
<p><strong>Tennis is like anything else in life. The more money you spend, the better quality you get. If you’re stretched for money though, I’ll show you a few ways to play tennis on the cheap.</strong></p>
<p>I already said location is a factor in cost. Here are some other factors that will influence your tennis budget:</p>
<ul>
<li>Tennis gear</li>
<li>Court time</li>
<li>Coaching</li>
<li>Tournaments and leagues</li>
</ul>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Unlike basketball or soccer, where you can just show up and play for free, tennis usually requires money to play. This is because of the factors I just mentioned.</p>
<p>But tennis need not break your budget. In this article, I’ll explain how you can keep your tennis costs low. For those who have the money to spend, I’ll discuss how you can create an awesome tennis lifestyle and really take your game to the next level.</p>
<p>Without further ado, let’s get into it, starting with location.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Cost Depending On Location</h2>
<p><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1942" src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/piggybank.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/piggybank.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/01/piggybank-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2019/01/piggybank-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>In my opinion, location is one of the most important factors to influence the amount of money you spend on tennis. I’ll give you an example from my life.</p>
<p>I was born and raised in New York. In the summertime, outdoor public and private courts are available. Some public courts were free but most required small fees ($5-$8 per hour per person). I was glad to pay those fees to play in the warm months.</p>
<p>But when the cold months come, tennis outdoors is virtually out the window. Nobody likes to play in 30-degree weather with snow on the ground – although I did it a few times.</p>
<p>The only option at that point is to play indoors. We called indoor courts “tennis bubbles”. The cost for indoor courts is considerably more than outdoor courts. The costs for indoor courts usually range from $40-$100 per hour per person!</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>If you live in a cold-weather state or country, indoor courts are your only option. If you play three times per week for one hour each day, at an average cost of $50 per hour, you’re looking at $600 per month.</p>
<p>That’s not cheap. And that doesn’t include the tennis gear and possible coaching. When I was living in New York, some of the indoor tennis courts offered deals where you could buy a seasonal membership.</p>
<p>In one club where I bought a membership, it allowed me to play any time the courts weren’t booked. In another club, I could only book court time during certain hours.</p>
<p>If you like to play a lot of tennis and your schedule is flexible, ask your local indoor tennis club if they have seasonal memberships. This is by far the cheapest way to go. Try to avoid peak hours, where the rates are sky high.</p>
<p>So that was life in New York. On average, I’d spend around $20-$30 per week during the outdoor season on court time and approximately $100 per month for indoor court time in the cold season.</p>
<p>But that was over 20 years ago, in the mid-‘90s. It’s probably more now. I also got great deals on indoor courts due to playing on the local college tennis team.</p>
<p>If you live in a cold-weather state, plan to spend at least several hundred dollars per month if you want to play a couple of hours per week. There’s really no getting around the cost of indoor court time.</p>
<p>In January of 2007, I moved to sunny South Florida. A lot of my decision had to do with the tennis down here. First, there are no indoor courts; all courts are outside and there is an abundance of them. This dramatically lowered my cost of playing tennis alone.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>Tennis can be played outdoors here year-round, with average temperatures in the 70s during the winter months. Second, there are more players here and the tennis is better than New York.</p>
<p>Currently, I spend zero money on court time. This is because I have private tennis courts in my community. Now you may be lucky and have that in your community as well. If so, it really cuts down on the cost of tennis.</p>
<p>One of my clients, an esteemed gentleman who compensates me nicely to hit with him, pays for my membership to a private club. This club has 8 har-true tennis courts. Additionally, I have a ton of tennis buddies who have access to tennis courts all around the area, so playing here in Florida is very cheap.</p>
<p>If you’re serious about tennis, moving to a warm climate will decrease your tennis costs substantially. You’ll also find more players to hit with, be able to play more often, and enjoy life more. No, seriously. Warm climates are awesome!</p>
<p>Some of you may live in remote locations where tennis courts are far. In that case, you’ll need to drive quite a distance, which requires gas money and time.</p>
<p>The bottom line is that your location will largely dictate how much you spend on tennis. In the best of cases, like mine, tennis will be virtually free. In the worst case, and if you’re an avid player, you could spend as much as $1000 per month on indoor court time in cold-weather areas and months.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>How Much Does Tennis Gear Cost?</h2>
<p>Tennis gear isn’t cheap. But it need not break your budget. Below is a list of the necessary tennis gear you’ll need when you start playing. As you get better, you may add more items to the list, but these are the bare essentials.</p>
<ul>
<li>Tennis sneakers</li>
<li>Tennis shorts, shirt, and hat (optional)</li>
<li>Rackets</li>
<li>String</li>
<li>Balls</li>
<li>Tennis bag</li>
<li>Grips</li>
</ul>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>The most expensive cost will be your tennis rackets. Now, you could go out and buy a $10 racket off eBay, but I’m assuming you’ll want to buy a new racket of good quality. Any decent adult tennis racket is going to cost you at least $100.</p>
<p>You’ll need at minimum two rackets but having three is optimal. The reason is that strings break unexpectedly. If you have only two rackets and the strings go on one, now you have just one racket left. That’s why I always carry three rackets in my tennis bag.</p>
<p>The next most expensive item will be your tennis sneakers. These can range from $40 up to over $100. The type I buy (Addidas Barricade) costs around $65. While you can practically wear any sneaker on court, tennis sneakers are best because they give you the best traction and ankle support of any kind of sneaker for tennis.</p>
<p>Next up is tennis apparel, which I put as optional. You can wear any sports related garb you want on court, but if you want to look and feel the part, you’ll want to purchase tennis shorts, shirt, and hat.</p>
<p>Tennis apparel is not cheap. But if you have the budget and are fashion conscious, spend the money to get yourself some good-looking clothing. Most tennis apparel is light, colorful, and made for tennis. If you don’t buy tennis shorts, always use shorts or pants with pockets. You’ll need pockets to hold the balls.</p>
<p>String can be another big expense, but only if you buy it in bulk. I usually spend about $100 on buying bulk string every three months. But I play often. When you break the strings on your racket, you’ll need to either restring the racket yourself or bring it to a professional stringer.</p>
<p>Most professional tennis stringers charge a minimum of $20-$25 for their labor and string. This usually involves cheap string. If you want a higher quality string, you’ll need to spend upwards of $35, maybe even $40 or $45. This is for one racket.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>It’s actually cheaper to buy string in bulk and give it to the stringer every time you string a racket. That’s what I do. I buy the string from Amazon and then hand it to my stringer, who charges me $15 per racket. In total, I pay around $25 per racket (for labor and string) when all is said and done.</p>
<p>How often will you string your racket? That totally depends on how much you play and your level of play. I know people that restring only a couple of times per year. I also know people that restring every week.</p>
<p>The one cost you can’t skimp on is balls. Playing with dead balls is no fun. So you’ll want to open a new can of tennis balls each time you play a match. If you’re just practicing, used balls can work fine.</p>
<p>The cost for balls ranges in price from $2.50 per can up to about $4. When you play tennis with friends, it’s customary for you to alter opening a new can. For example, if I play tennis Monday with Gary, I’ll open a new can. When we play again on Thursday, it’s his turn to open a new can.</p>
<p>The cost for balls isn’t exorbitant. It’s just an expense you’ll need to continually pay, unlike when you buy a racket and you’re good for several years. Figure on spending $10 per month for balls on the low side, and up to $30-$40 per month on the high side.</p>
<p>The tennis bag is essential. I see some people show up with a backpack or some other contraption and it looks awful. If you don’t have a tennis bag, do yourself a favor and buy one if you play tennis consistently. It’s a one-time expense for the most part.</p>
<p>A tennis bag is made to carry rackets and all your equipment. Not just that, but it makes you look like a real player and it’s very practical. New tennis bags usually start around $40. If you’re on a budget, you can probably buy a cheap, used tennis bag on e-bay for $10 or so.</p>
<p>The last piece of tennis gear I&#8217;ll mention is grips. Grips are fairly cheap, at about $2 each. A grip will last you on average 5-10 hours of play. It really depends on how warm it is when you play, how much you sweat, and how aggressively you grip the racket.</p>
<p>I like to buy the 12-pack of Wilson Tennis Overgrips. I find them to be comfortable and really absorb sweat well. It’s always best to have more grips than less.</p>
<p>Most people underestimate the importance of grips, but they can vastly improve your strokes. Ever try playing with a ratty, frayed grip on a hot humid day? If you have, you know what I’m talking about.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>How Much Does Coaching Cost?</h2>
<p>If you’re new to tennis, I recommend getting coaching, at least in the beginning. Tennis is a lot more fun when you know proper technique. I’ll go over the cost of coaching here, plus a few other alternatives for those more budget-minded.</p>
<p>If you’re an experienced player, you can probably skip the coaching if you enjoy playing at your level. Still, it never hurts to take a lesson from a qualified tennis coach to up your game. Even Roger Federer has a coach!</p>
<p>The fastest way to learn tennis is through private coaching. Private coaching rates vary by location and coach. Figure on paying $30 on the low side, and $100 or more for the very best coaches. In my opinion, $60 per hour should get you an excellent coach.</p>
<p>If you take a lesson once a week from a $60 per hour coach, your costs per month will be $240. As a beginner, you will likely need coaching for several months to get up to speed.</p>
<p>A cheaper alternative is to do group lessons or join a clinic. You won’t get the one-on-one attention that a private coaching lesson affords, but it’s your next best option.</p>
<p>For example, you could ask a private coach to teach you and one or two other friends at the same time. This would cut the cost down considerably. It might also make the lesson more fun with your friends involved.</p>
<p>On the other hand, clinics can range from several people up to a dozen. The costs vary depending on group size and duration. Most clinics I know charge $15-$20 per person. Most clinics are more for practice than technique though, so it’s a good option if you already know proper technique.</p>
<p>The next alternative option is an on-line course. Courses can range in price from around $20 up to $100, depending on the instructor and what the course involves. These courses will show you step-by-step how to hit each tennis stroke.</p>
<p>These tennis courses are great in that you have the lesson right there in video any time you want. However, there’s one huge drawback when compared to private coaching: there’s nobody there to watch and correct your strokes.</p>
<p>For this reason, you’ll need to video your strokes and compare them to the video lesson. Or, you can send your video to a qualified coach to critique. It will cost you, but it’s a lot cheaper to go this route than regular private coaching lessons.</p>
<p>The last option is to watch free tennis videos on youtube. I have a lot of great tennis tutorial videos on my youtube channel if you need help with your game. I have videos on the backhand, forehand, serve, volleys, and footwork.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Costs Of Tournaments And Leagues</h2>
<p>If you’re a competitive player and know the fundamentals of tennis, you may consider joining a tennis tournament or tennis league. What’s the difference you may ask? And how much does each cost?</p>
<p>A tennis tournament is a one-time event that is usually played on the weekend. Many tournaments are a one-and-done event, meaning if you lose, you don’t play another matche.</p>
<p>The USTA is the best place to look for local tennis tournaments. As of 2019, it costs $44 per year for an adult membership. As a member, you’ll be able to enter local tournaments at your level.</p>
<p>The average USTA tournaments costs $50 to enter. The cost covers court time, balls, and lights (if necessary). It’s not a bad deal and it will give you good experience. The drawback is that it can become costly if you enter tournaments every weekend and need to drive far to get to them.</p>
<p>That’s why I prefer to join tennis leagues. These are usually offered by your local tennis club (if you have one). In my area, I have a club about 10 miles from my home. The club offers singles and doubles leagues every week.</p>
<p>The cost for joining the league is $46 and includes court time, balls, lights, and 7 guaranteed matches. It’s quite a deal, I know. But then again, this is South Florida.</p>
<p>The leagues are a lot of fun because you usually play with the same people year-after-year and make good friends. My league has five flights with 8 people per flight. The line-up in each flight changes slightly after each season ends (a season is 8 matches).</p>
<p>If you enjoy tennis and have a tennis club near you, call them and ask if they offer leagues. To me, they’re far better than tournaments and a lot cheaper.</p>
<p>Now, if you’re goal is to make it to the higher levels of tennis (past 5.0 level), than you’ll want to play tournaments. If I wanted to see how high I can go in tennis, I’d start playing open tournaments all throughout Florida.</p>
<p>But due to my coaching and work schedule, it’s not practical. But if you’re young, hungry for success, and have great talent, tournaments are the only way to go. By playing tournaments you can rank state-wide, nationally, and even gain a world ranking. Oh, if only I could have been ranked 758 in the world. My life would be so much better now (LOL).</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Summing It Up</h2>
<p>If you’ve read this far, you now have a good idea of the costs associated with tennis. Just know, it’s entirely possible to play tennis year-round for free. I know a guy near me who plays virtually for free.</p>
<p>His name is Drew and he’s a very talented club player (5.0 level). He’s so good, that other players don’t mind paying for his court time and the balls. Drew just shows up and plays whenever he’s asked. The only tennis expense Drew has are for strings, grips, and a change of sneakers a couple of times per year.</p>
<p>This is an extreme example. On the high side, if you want to play at prestigious tennis clubs, take lessons from the best pros, and have awesome new gear, you can easily spend $15,000-$25,000 per year on tennis.</p>
<p>I didn’t mention it earlier, but if you’re a parent who has a child who wants to excel in tennis, you’ll need to pay for private lessons (or group lessons at least). In that case, budget several thousand dollars per year for 1-2 hours of lessons per week.</p>
<p>If you’re one of those crazed parents who want their child to become a tennis pro, you’ll want to send your child to a tennis academy. The prestigious academies down here in Florida, like Bollettieri, Macci, and Evert will cost your child a hefty $40,000 per semester!</p>
<p>If you have any questions about the costs associated with tennis, drop me a comment below. Thanks for reading. Check out the rest of my blog for cool tennis tips and info.</p>
<p>The post <a href="/how-much-does-it-cost-to-play-tennis/">How Much Does It Cost To Play Tennis?</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/how-much-does-it-cost-to-play-tennis/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>How To Become A Tennis Coach</title>
		<link>/how-to-become-a-tennis-coach/</link>
					<comments>/how-to-become-a-tennis-coach/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chad Walner]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 31 Dec 2018 10:07:45 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Training]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[coaching]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1763</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>If you’ve been thinking about becoming a tennis coach, you’re in the right place. In this blog post I’m going to outline the keys to becoming a successful tennis coach and why you should be one. I know you probably &#8230; <a class="kt-excerpt-readmore" href="/how-to-become-a-tennis-coach/" aria-label="How To Become A Tennis Coach">Read More</a></p>
<p>The post <a href="/how-to-become-a-tennis-coach/">How To Become A Tennis Coach</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>If you’ve been thinking about becoming a tennis coach, you’re in the right place. In this blog post I’m going to outline the keys to becoming a successful tennis coach and why you should be one.</p>
<p>I know you probably have a lot of questions on what it takes to be a paid tennis instructor. I’m going to give you a lot of answers here, so you can learn from my experience.</p>
<p>You may have been wondering if you have what it takes to coach tennis. The truth is, if you play tennis at a 4.5 level or higher and possess a friendly personality, you probably do.</p>
<p>I’ve been a tennis coach on and off for 25 years. Over the last four years, I’ve been consistently coaching part-time (average of 10 lessons per week) and it’s been incredibly rewarding.</p>
<p><strong>It’s an awesome feeling to use your tennis skill and knowledge to make someone’s game better. As a coach, you’ll be working with all kinds of people: kids, young adults, people aged 20s-50s, and even seniors.</strong></p>
<p><strong>In this post, I’ll tell you about my experience as a tennis coach in South Florida. I’m going to share how much money I make, how you much you can expect to earn, and the pros and cons of being a tennis coach.</strong></p>
<p>My hope is that you’ll have a much better understanding of it all by the time you finish this article. If you want a more comprehensive guide, check out my book on<strong> How To Be A Tennis Coach – The Definitive Guide For 2019</strong></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-1771 size-full" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/coaching-with-laptop.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/coaching-with-laptop.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/12/coaching-with-laptop-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/12/coaching-with-laptop-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Why Become A Tennis Coach?</h2>
<p>I got into coaching because I love tennis and I needed extra money. I thought, “Why not use my tennis skills to help other people become better while earning a living at the same time?”</p>
<p>I can honestly tell you I love working with all my students. As a result, the same students have been with me for years.</p>
<p>You know that you’re providing value and getting results for clients when they stick with you for the long-term. That’s the mark of a great coach.</p>
<p>Being a tennis coach has other benefits as well. You can set your own hours, choose the clients you work with, and not have to answer to a boss (if you coach privately).</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>One of my favorite parts of being a tennis coach is getting to meet different types of people. Most are successful, educated, and well-mannered. This also makes it a great way to network with people who have money and possible connections.</p>
<p>I love talking with my clients and discovering their stories, and sharing a passion for tennis.</p>
<p>Coaching is just fun. You travel to different courts, make connections, and generally brighten people’s day. If you have good tennis skills and like being around people, being a tennis coach is an awesome business.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>How Much Do Tennis Coaches Earn?</h2>
<p>How much a tennis coach earns depends on a lot of factors. On the low end, tennis instructors who work for a college or tennis camp can expect to earn about $15 per hour.</p>
<p>These are typically entry level coaching jobs. This is what I made when I used to coach at my college (I was in college and playing on the team at the time).</p>
<p>On the high side, and in the most lucrative markets, coaches can charge $300 per hour or more. In my county, the better coaches charge around $60-$75 per hour.</p>
<p>As you can see, there is quite a disparity in range. I don’t know of any private coaches who charge less than $30 per hour in my area (South Florida). I personally charge clients an average of $40-$50 per lesson, depending on several factors. I go in depth a lot more on pricing in my e-book and course.</p>
<p>The coaches who can charge and collect more than $100 per hour usually have decades of experience, work at famous tennis academies, and have coached young students to the pro ranks.</p>
<p>One such example is Rick Macci, who owns an academy in South Florida and charges $300 per hour for private lessons. He’s now a multi-millionaire and one of the most successful coaches in American tennis.</p>
<p>In my ebook and course, I break down how you should price your clients. Your skill level as a player will be a factor, as well as the gear you have and your experience and credentials.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>The Cost To Start Coaching</h2>
<p>Most businesses require a sizable amount of startup cash. But you can start off coaching for less than $50 and no formal training! This is another aspect of coaching tennis that I love &#8211; the small financial barrier to entry.</p>
<p>I would suggest you budget a bit higher though if you want to attract and retain clients. You definitely don’t need a huge investment to start coaching – a few hundred dollars will take you far at the start.</p>
<p>You can really scale up coaching too. And the more clients you have, the easier it is to attract more business. This is because clients will refer you to their friends, family, and associates if they like you.</p>
<p>When I started giving lessons again four years ago, all I had was a hopper and 75 used tennis balls. My total invest was $30, which was for the <a href="https://amzn.to/2SoTMtz" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">75-ball hopper</a> (Amazon link). I saved 75 balls from the matches I was playing, and bam, I was in business!</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>While I could coach effectively from my previous years of working with clients, it wasn’t until I began investing in needed tennis equipment that my coaching services became more valuable. In my ebook and course, I list out all the equipment you’ll need, from the bare minimum gear up to the gear needed for serious coaches.</p>
<p>Depending on how involved you want to get with coaching, you should budget from several hundred dollars to a couple of thousand to start. If you have the required gear, you’ll look more professional and you’ll be able to teach more effectively.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-1778 size-full" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/5a.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/5a.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/12/5a-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/12/5a-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Coaching Children</h2>
<p>While I like working with adults, it’s the children that motivate and inspire me the most. Their tennis future is dependent on my coaching expertise.</p>
<p>Most children come to you as blank slates and it’s up to you to mold them into competent players. Every child has different levels of ability.</p>
<p>Some pick tennis up quickly while others take a lot longer. If you like kids, you’ll love coaching, but you’ll need patience.</p>
<p>It’s always a thrill when you teach a new technique to a child and he or she can pick it up. It’s very rewarding to see a child make steady improvement under your wing.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1775" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/map-client.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/map-client.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/12/map-client-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/12/map-client-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>How Do I Find Clients?</h2>
<p>Finding clients as a private tennis instructor can be challenging in the beginning. This is especially true if you’re not familiar with the local tennis circuit in your area.</p>
<p>If you’re brand new to coaching or new to your area, posting ads on craigslist is a great place to start. There are also a half dozen tennis websites (like <a href="https://mytennislessons.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">mytennislessons.com</a>) where you can post free profiles.</p>
<p>In my e-book and course, I teach you how to create awesome profiles that stand out and attract customers. It took me a long time to figure out the best way to structure my profile. But once I did, I saw a 60% increase in sign-ups.</p>
<p>Posting on these websites is free, but the websites take a cut for every client they refer. For example, if a client signs up for six hours of lessons with you, the website takes a percentage of every hour you teach. That’s how they make money.</p>
<p>Of course, you can make business cards, post flyers, or do paid advertising. If you’re on a budget, this may not be an option. In my e-book and course, I’ll show you 10 unconventional methods for attracting new clients – most of which are free.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>How To Retain Clients</h2>
<p>The best clients you have are the ones that take lessons week-after-week and year-after-year. These are the clients that build the foundation of your business.</p>
<p>For me, these clients are a combination of kids and adults. Tennis is a sport that takes a long time to learn. Parents know this and the ones with money don’t mind investing in weekly or biweekly tennis lessons for their kids.</p>
<p>The adults who stick with me the longest are ironically not interested in lessons. They are only interested in hitting or playing matches. For this reason, it’s important you are consistent with your strokes, in good shape, and a level 4.5 player or better.</p>
<p>Just this morning I had three one-hour lessons with three different clients. All of them wanted to hit and play sets. This can be quite exhausting, especially in the heat of South Florida, where I teach.</p>
<p>For me, the most important way to retain clients is to be very consistent (hitting-wise), friendly, and professional. This means listening to them, complimenting them, and allowing them to win some points and games.</p>
<p>In my e-book and course, I have an entire subject discussing the dos and don’ts when dealing with clients. Not to toot my own horn, but I have an excellent rapport with my students.</p>
<p>I’ll tell you exactly how I do it. When your students like you, they’ll stick with you for years. This means cash in your pocket week-after-week.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1774" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/marissa1.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/marissa1.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/12/marissa1-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/12/marissa1-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>How To Actually Coach Clients</h2>
<p>When it comes to coaching tennis, I view it in two completely separate categories. The first category is everything but the actual coaching of the client. This involves the marketing of your services, the rates you charge, the markets you should target, how to deal with clients, billing, and scheduling.</p>
<p>I go over all of these in extensive detail in my e-book and course. The second category is the coaching and teaching. You may have played tennis for most of your life, but that doesn’t make you a good coach.</p>
<p>Since this is only a blog post, I can’t teach you how to best coach students from words. At best, I can give you some guidelines.</p>
<p>In my years of coaching, I developed a complete system for teaching every tennis stroke. This makes it so much easier to work with any level of client. These strokes include:</p>
<ul>
<li>Forehand</li>
<li>Backhand – one and two-handed</li>
<li>Backhand and forehand slice</li>
<li>Volleys</li>
<li>Overheads</li>
<li>First and second serve</li>
<li>Footwork</li>
<li>Mental aspect of tennis</li>
</ul>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>In my course, I’ll show you exactly how to teach each of these strokes. Now keep in mind that teaching beginners and intermediate/advanced players is quite different.</p>
<p>I explain the differences in my course. I also show you how to work with players who have a lot of tennis experience.</p>
<p>It’s one thing to take a player from scratch and show them how to hit a proper forehand. It’s a totally different thing to work with players who already know how to hit.</p>
<p>In my course, you’ll learn things like how to diagnose a player’s strokes and improve them. That’s the main reason people are paying you to coach them. They want results.</p>
<p>If you don’t know what to look for, or which drills will correct their issues, you’re not going to be very effective. We go over all of that in the course.</p>
<p>After taking my course, you’ll be able to diagnose any stroke from any level player. You’ll know exactly what the player needs to change to improve. You’ll also learn how to effectively make those changes.</p>
<p>These are all skills I learned from years of coaching. In the beginning, I was like a blind man. I’d see someone serve or hit and couldn’t figure out what their issue was. Two decades and thousands of tennis lessons later, it’s crystal clear.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1773" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/beginnertennisballs.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/beginnertennisballs.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/12/beginnertennisballs-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/12/beginnertennisballs-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Summary</h2>
<p>If you’re thinking about coaching tennis, I urge you to give it a try. As I said earlier, there’s a low barrier of entry in terms of money and you don’t even need qualifications or certificates.</p>
<p>While having a small budget and a few qualifications to your name helps, it’s not essential to start earning money as a local tennis coach. All you need is a hopper and balls to get started. That’s how I did it.</p>
<p>If you post an ad on craigslist today and put up several free profiles on the tennis websites, you might even get your first client within the next week or two. At a rate of $40 per hour, if you attract just one new client per month (that stays with you) you’ll have 12 paying clients after a year.</p>
<p>If these clients take a lesson with you once a week, that’s $480 per week – most of which is cash! You might be thinking $480 per week is not much. But remember, that’s only 12 hours of court time.</p>
<p>If you could earn $480 every week, that’s $2,000 per month. That money could be a huge difference-maker in your life.</p>
<p>From there, you could either scale up or keep coaching a part-time source of income. That’s the beautiful thing about coaching – you’re in control. If you want to stay part-time and work another job, that’s up to you.</p>
<p>I know another local coach who works full time. Last year he made around $75,000 for his efforts. He sets the hours he coaches, has plenty of time for his family, and just bought a new house with the money he’s earning.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>If you want to learn more about coaching, check out my e-book or course. There’s a ton of information in them that will make your coaching journey seamless.</p>
<p>In the beginning, I made mistakes that cost me clients and money. Once I figured out how to correct my mistakes, my revenue quadrupled. In my e-book and course, I’ll show you how to earn a full-time income from tennis coaching in less than six months.</p>
<p>If you want to learn my entire tennis coaching system, you’ll definitely want to sign up for my coaching course. In it, I show you everything you’ll need to know to be one of the best and highest-paid coaches in your area.</p>
<p>If you have any questions about becoming a tennis coach, feel free to ask. Thank you for coming to my blog. Don’t forget to sign-up to my newsletter for all the latest blog posts, videos, and offerings!</p>
<p>The post <a href="/how-to-become-a-tennis-coach/">How To Become A Tennis Coach</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/how-to-become-a-tennis-coach/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>3</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>How Do I Find A Great Tennis Coach?</title>
		<link>/how-to-find-a-great-tennis-coach/</link>
					<comments>/how-to-find-a-great-tennis-coach/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chad Walner]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 21 Sep 2018 07:33:01 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Theory]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[coaching]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=388</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>You want to learn tennis or improve your game but you’re uncertain how to find a great tennis coach. Or maybe you want your child to learn tennis and you want to be sure to find the right instructor. It &#8230; <a class="kt-excerpt-readmore" href="/how-to-find-a-great-tennis-coach/" aria-label="How Do I Find A Great Tennis Coach?">Read More</a></p>
<p>The post <a href="/how-to-find-a-great-tennis-coach/">How Do I Find A Great Tennis Coach?</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>You want to learn tennis or improve your game but you’re uncertain how to find a great tennis coach. Or maybe you want your child to learn tennis and you want to be sure to find the right instructor. It can be a challenge if you don’t know what to look for. We’re going to shed some light on the best ways to find the right tennis coach for you or your child.</p>
<p><strong>One of the best ways to find a great tennis coach is through a recommendation from a family member, friend or acquaintance. Next would be using the power of the Internet to locate a competent coach in your area. The third way would be to talk with tennis centers and academies in your region, as many have coaches on their staff. Other factors are important too. </strong></p>
<p><strong>When considering a coach, we should look at their coaching resume: how long have they been teaching, what are their credentials/qualifications, can the coach play well, do they use tools and video, and is the coach personable and patient?</strong></p>
<p>From my perspective, it seems there are two distinct challenges in finding a great coach.</p>
<ul>
<li>One is knowing where to find this coach.</li>
<li>The other is knowing if he or she is competent and can effectively teach.</li>
</ul>
<p>I put together this post to answer these questions definitively for you. Once you find the right coach, you can really accelerate your progress on the court. But if you choose the wrong coach, it can cost you a lot of money, waste your time and you won’t make much improvement. By reading and applying the information in this post, I’m confident you will avoid such a fate.</p>
<p>The second challenge is <strong>where</strong> to find a good tennis coach. This part is a lot easier. If you live in a moderately populated area, tennis coaches are abundant. It’s finding the right one that’s the tricky part.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>What Qualifications Should A Good Tennis Coach Possess?</h2>
<p>When considering a tennis coach you’ll want to know the answers to some important questions. Listed below are the most important questions to ask a new coach before hiring them. The answers to these questions might be in the “About Me” page on their website but it’s always good to ask in person or on the phone as well.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-401 alignright" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/findCoach8.jpg" alt="" width="400" height="289" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/findCoach8.jpg 400w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/findCoach8-300x217.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" /></p>
<ul>
<li>Are you <a href="https://uspta.com/default.aspx?menugroup=certification" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">USPTA certified</a>? If not, are you certified by any other tennis body? If they answer “yes” to any of these questions, ask them how long. If the answer is “no” ask them how long they have been coaching tennis.</li>
<li>What age range have you worked with? Are you currently coaching kids/people in this age range?</li>
<li>What level of player have you worked with previously? What is the highest level player you have coached (for example, club level, high school, college, semi-pro, pro).</li>
<li>What level of player are you? Ask the coach what’s the highest level of play they achieved in their lifetime. Some might say they were a decorated junior player while others played college tennis and some played semi-professionally.</li>
<li>What is your rate per half hour and per hour? Do you offer discounts for lessons paid in advance or packages (a number of lessons paid in advance). Do you offer group rates?</li>
<li>What is your availability?</li>
<li>Where will the lessons be given?</li>
<li>Will I need to pay for court time as well (if at a different court than your own)?</li>
</ul>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>You can gain a good sense of a coach’s credentials and teaching experience from their answers. But the coach’s personality, teaching style and compatibility with your game are just as important.</p>
<blockquote><p>While its true that some of the best coaches in sports were people who never excelled at the sport they chose to coach, in tennis it’s slightly different: <strong>You’ll want your coach to be an excellent player so he or she can demonstrate technique and rally with you.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Can The Tennis Coach Play?</h2>
<p>I would never recommend anyone receive coaching from someone lower than a 4.5 level player. This is because a coach needs to have a basic command of all the tennis strokes to effectively teach. If the coach cannot demonstrate basic technique, he or she should not be coaching tennis.</p>
<blockquote><p>Trust your first impressions when assessing the coach. Does it look like he or she can play tennis? Are they in shape? Does their form look smooth and natural? If the answers are all “yes” then you’re very close to finding the perfect coach for you or your child.</p></blockquote>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-394 alignright" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/findCoach1.jpg" alt="" width="400" height="267" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/findCoach1.jpg 400w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/findCoach1-300x200.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/findCoach1-272x182.jpg 272w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" />Keep in mind that most tennis coaches have never played professional tennis. Still, such coaches can be great ones, especially if they have solid fundamentals and are USPTA certified. If a coach has patience, makes the lessons fun and has many creative ways to teach, then give them strong consideration. Pricing and availability may be the only other factors stopping you from hiring the coach at this point. We’ll touch more on this soon.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Watch A Lesson Or Request An Intro Lesson</h2>
<p>If you are still uncertain about hiring the coach, ask to see 10 minutes of them coaching another client. If they allow you to watch, take note of how the coach interacts with the student. Does he or she use teaching props? How effective is he or she in the time you spend watching? Does the coach thoroughly explain things or is he or she silent the whole time? While 10 minutes won’t give you a perfect assessment of the coach, it will give you some idea.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-400 alignleft" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/findCoach7.jpg" alt="" width="400" height="320" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/findCoach7.jpg 400w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/findCoach7-300x240.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" />If you cannot watch an intro lesson, ask if you can be given one. Intro lessons are typically 10-15 minutes long and most coaches offer them free of charge. Additionally, the coach may hold clinics where several people or more are instructed at once. You may be able to watch or participate in one of these clinics at no charge. This is a better way to get an idea of the coach’s style than only watching.</p>
<p>The same can be said for children. See if they can participate in an intro lesson or group clinic. It’s important to see how your child interacts with the coach. At the end of the lesson, ask your child if they like the coach.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>Tennis coaches are people too, and they all have their own personalities and unique quirks. What makes a good tennis coach is the ability to work with people at all levels and ages. Some people have physical limitations so lessons should be based around the age and abilities of the person. A good coach is not going to teach an able-bodied 15-year-old boy the same way he would a 70-year-old man looking to learn tennis.</p>
<p>A good coach can also spot the flaws in your game. He or she will then point them out, demonstrate the correct technique and then have you practice without the ball. Once you gain a sense of the technique, the coach will use progressions to build up your muscle memory. Ultimately this allows you to learn and use correct technique. A good coach will also use any tool at their disposal to help a player improve.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>A Word On Teaching Tools and Video</h2>
<p>To me, the best tennis coaches are the ones using teaching tools and video in their lessons. It doesn’t matter so much if the coach creates the teaching tool or buys it. What matters is that the tools work. Many teaching tools are sold online and can help players improve fast. Such examples are serving aids, hitting aids and ball machines. I have some recommendations for tools I have used with success on my <a href="/recommended-gear/">Recommended Gear</a> page.</p>
<p>I personally incorporate video in my lessons; I feel it’s a great tool for instructing. by filming the student and playing oit back for them to review, I can point out things that I never could without it. My clients get a totally different perspective when they see themselves on screen. If a coach uses both tools and video, they are most likely very serious about improving their clients’ game. This type of coach is worth considering.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>How Much Does A Good Tennis Coach Charge?</h2>
<blockquote><p>A common question asked by people hiring a tennis coach for the first time is, “How much does it cost for a one hour tennis lesson?” There is no set fee. It depends on many factors, such as location, prestige and experience of the coach, the time of the year, and whether the lessons are group or individual. To give you a general answer, tennis lessons will range from a low of around $30 up to $100+ per hour.</p></blockquote>
<p>I personally charge $40-$50 for a lesson if the client comes to my courts. Again, the price depends on certain factors. I’ll touch on each briefly here.</p>
<ul>
<li>Location will matter. If you live in an expensive city like New York or London, expect to pay more than living in a rural area. And if you take lessons at an academy or tennis center, expect to pay more for lessons than from a coach working alone.</li>
<li>The prestige of the coach matters too. If you work with a world-renowned coach, expect to pay a lot more ($100+ per hour) than a regular coach ($40-$50 per hour). Some coaches are former professional players with great pedigrees and years of experience. These coaches will charge more too. In my area they typically charge $60-$80 per hour for a lesson.</li>
<li>Seasonality can affect the rate. During the peak season of the year (winter in the southern climates and summer in the northern climates), prices can increase by as much as 50%. This is due to more people wanting lessons during the peak season.</li>
</ul>
<p>If private lessons seem like an extravagance, consider group lessons&#8211;a lot of value can be had in this way too. If you and a friend want to learn tennis, both of you can learn at almost half the rate of private lessons. Often beginners can learn just as effectively in a group lesson of two or three people. The coach will be focusing primarily on basics anyway, so the two or three of you may benefit by learning together.</p>
<p>The next most affordable coaching classes are clinics. In clinics, you may get a few tips, but don’t expect a lot of one-on-one time. Clinics are mostly given to three or more people and focus on tennis drills and conditioning, rather than learning stroke mechanics. Still, clinics can be a good place to improve your game for a fraction of the cost of private lessons.</p>
<p>Perhaps the most inexpensive way to hire a coach is online. Some coaches have online courses that teach you all the strokes of tennis – from the most basic level up to advanced technique. In some of these courses, you can send in video of yourself and receive back feedback of your play. This can be a great resort if you do not have the time or money to devote to a personal coach.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Ask Around For Recommendations</h2>
<p>Now that you know what to look for in a good coach, how do you find one? Recommendations are the easiest way. As a tennis coach myself, some of my best students have come via recommendations. I like recommendations because you can ask people specific questions about their lessons and they’ll usually give you honest answers.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-399 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/findCoach6.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/findCoach6.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/findCoach6-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/findCoach6-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p>If you know someone who plays tennis, ask them if they can recommend a good coach. Ideally, they will have taken lessons with that coach as well. If nobody can recommend a tennis coach to you, the Internet may be your best bet. Nowadays people are doing everything online, so you may as well benefit from these advances in technology. In the last few years, many websites have popped up that are devoted to matching coaches and players for tennis lessons. I’ll go through the ones I think are worthwhile.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><a href="https://www.facebook.com/search/groups/?q=tennis" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Facebook Groups</a> – Search &#8220;tennis&#8221; on Facebook and you&#8217;ll find groups all over the world with people who will be glad to help you. Ask them something like: “I’m considering learning tennis. Can anyone recommend a great tennis coach near me?” You may be surprised how many people respond with a recommendation for a coach.</p>
<p><a href="https://mytennislessons.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Mytennislessons.com</a> – This is a great site to find a coach in your area. The level of coaching expertise varies widely, as do the rates, which are all posted under each coach. Read the short bio of the coaches and their student reviews. You can book one lesson or a package of lessons directly through the website, which handles the money transactions as well.</p>
<p><a href="https://uspta.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">USPTA.com</a> – On this site you can find a certified USPTA coach in your area. This site is simply a resource that will give you the name and phone number of the closest teaching pros to you. No other information about the coaches is offered and you’ll need to contact them directly to find out rates and book lessons.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.findtennislessons.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Findtennislessons.com</a> – Very similar to mytennislessons.com. If you don’t see a coach you like on mytennislessons.com or uspta.com, try this one.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.playyourcourt.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Playyourcourt.com</a> – Another site similar to mytennislessons.com and findtennislessons.com. This is a less popular site, but worth giving a try to as well.</p>
<p>Craigslist.org – Yup, I said it – craigslist. There is a different site for each city. If you go to the “lessons” or “activities” categories in your city and type in “tennis” you’ll likely find tennis coaches advertising. I advertise on craigslist and found some of my best clients on it, so I must recommend it.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Local Tennis Centers and Academies</h2>
<p>If you play at a local tennis club, often there is a club pro who gives lessons. Talk to the club pro and ask the questions I listed earlier in this post.</p>
<p>If you don’t play at a local tennis club, look up the ones near you and call to inquire about coaching. Often, but not all the time, the teaching pros at clubs are good coaches, as they have a lot of experience and work with many clients. You can learn at the club, which is great, but the main drawback is most tennis centers charge more than coaches who teach on their own. Availability may be limited as well.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-398 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/findCoach5.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="450" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/findCoach5.jpg 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/findCoach5-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/findCoach5-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></p>
<p>If you are really looking to accelerate your game or that of your child, tennis academies are your best bet. They’re really the crème-de-la-crème of places to learn – but mostly for children and teens. Almost all academies offer awesome programs for kids and have, at the least, several very experienced coaches on hand. Academies are a great choice as kids are in a learning-friendly environment with a proven system that works. Here kids will receive proper coaching, play against other kids their age/level, and work with different coaches on technique and conditioning.</p>
<p><script async src="https://pagead2.googlesyndication.com/pagead/js/adsbygoogle.js"></script><br />
<ins class="adsbygoogle" style="display: block; text-align: center;" data-ad-layout="in-article" data-ad-format="fluid" data-ad-client="ca-pub-1377479784047452" data-ad-slot="5908684722"></ins><br />
<script>
     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});
</script></p>
<p>Some of these academies have produced the world’s greatest players. Where I live in Florida, there exist over a dozen great tennis academies. The most famous of them are Nick Bollettieri-Img Academy, Everet Tennis Academy, and the Rick Macci Tennis Academy. Any of these venues will vastly improve your child’s tennis game. Most academies also have classes for adults. The main drawback of academies is the price. Unless you’re willing to shell out $100+ per hour, then this may not be the choice for you. If you are interested, you can easily search for academies in your area via google. If you live in a rural area, you may need to travel quite a distance to find the closest academy. On the flip side, few individual coaches can match the success of a good academy.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Summary</h2>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="wp-image-409 size-full alignright" src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/findCoach12.jpg" alt="" width="400" height="600" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/findCoach12.jpg 400w, /wp-content/uploads/2018/09/findCoach12-200x300.jpg 200w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" />Finding the perfect coach for you shouldn’t be difficult. Unless you receive a recommendation, it will take just a bit of research. You now have all of the resources you need to find that ideal instructor. I would recommend that you don’t pay for a “package” of lessons until you take at least one or two lessons with an instructor. See if they are worth it before committing to a series of lessons.</p>
<p>If you find a coach and take lessons, monitor your progress from the time you start. If you are not making progress after 3-4 lessons, you’re either not putting into practice what you learned, or you may need to find a new coach. Don’t be afraid to switch coaches if you must.</p>
<p>The main point of hiring a coach is to learn tennis and progress your game. I’m confident that if you use the rules of thumb outlined in this post, you’ll be able to find a coach who’s just right for you. Good luck and drop us a comment if you have any questions!</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>The post <a href="/how-to-find-a-great-tennis-coach/">How Do I Find A Great Tennis Coach?</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Serve and Volley Tennis</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/how-to-find-a-great-tennis-coach/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
