<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments for Serve and Volley Tennis	</title>
	<atom:link href="/comments/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Your secret weapon on the court.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sat, 04 Nov 2023 16:43:33 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	
	<item>
		<title>
		Comment on How Does A Tennis Tie-Break Work? by Adam		</title>
		<link>/how-does-a-tennis-tie-break-work/#comment-1300</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Adam]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 04 Nov 2023 16:43:33 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1575#comment-1300</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I believe some information in the section &quot;How Does The Serve Work In A Doubles Tie-Breaker?&quot; is incorrect: During regular games in a set, doesn&#039;t every serving double player always start their game &quot;on the deuce side&quot;? I believe the labels &quot;on the deuce side&quot; / &quot;on the ad side&quot; were meant to be in the second and not the first bullet point list of that section, i.e. once the tie-breaker begins.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I believe some information in the section &#8220;How Does The Serve Work In A Doubles Tie-Breaker?&#8221; is incorrect: During regular games in a set, doesn&#8217;t every serving double player always start their game &#8220;on the deuce side&#8221;? I believe the labels &#8220;on the deuce side&#8221; / &#8220;on the ad side&#8221; were meant to be in the second and not the first bullet point list of that section, i.e. once the tie-breaker begins.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		Comment on Why You Never Improve Your Tennis Game – And How You Can by Rashidah		</title>
		<link>/why-you-never-improve-your-tennis-game-and-how-you-can/#comment-1288</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Rashidah]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 06 Oct 2023 22:24:41 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1527#comment-1288</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;/why-you-never-improve-your-tennis-game-and-how-you-can/#comment-1281&quot;&gt;David Hopkins&lt;/a&gt;.

Older players can surprise you. I admire the 70 and 80 year olds at our local court who can still serve well and our volleys away. They don&#039;t move a lot, but with good stroke form, they can still be an asset on the doubles court. Tennis is a lifelong sport. I played 3 sets today, did the grocery shopping, and cleaned my house and I am 56! Yes, I&#039;m tired but as they say,&quot; there is plenty of time to sleep in the grave.&quot; Just get moving!]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="/why-you-never-improve-your-tennis-game-and-how-you-can/#comment-1281">David Hopkins</a>.</p>
<p>Older players can surprise you. I admire the 70 and 80 year olds at our local court who can still serve well and our volleys away. They don&#8217;t move a lot, but with good stroke form, they can still be an asset on the doubles court. Tennis is a lifelong sport. I played 3 sets today, did the grocery shopping, and cleaned my house and I am 56! Yes, I&#8217;m tired but as they say,&#8221; there is plenty of time to sleep in the grave.&#8221; Just get moving!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		Comment on Why You Never Improve Your Tennis Game – And How You Can by David Hopkins		</title>
		<link>/why-you-never-improve-your-tennis-game-and-how-you-can/#comment-1281</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[David Hopkins]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 02 Aug 2023 16:55:17 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1527#comment-1281</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Your comments about older club players lack of physical ability at being able to hit the ball really hard -&quot;they just don&#039;t have it in them&quot; inspired me. As a 64 year old who only started playing tennis a year ago your comments could have made me give up, put my racket on e-bay and take up Bowls or competitive  crochet. What I might lack in physical ability I make up for in guts and determination and I can still get around the court quicker than a lot of players half my age. As a new player its technique that&#039;s my issue, but I can fix that.  I&#039;m not looking to compete on the ATP tour so with respect I&#039;ll ignore your comments and keep playing, doing my best to prove you wrong.   I&#039;m also assuming that you don&#039;t coach and take the money from older clients that you know will never be any good.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Your comments about older club players lack of physical ability at being able to hit the ball really hard -&#8220;they just don&#8217;t have it in them&#8221; inspired me. As a 64 year old who only started playing tennis a year ago your comments could have made me give up, put my racket on e-bay and take up Bowls or competitive  crochet. What I might lack in physical ability I make up for in guts and determination and I can still get around the court quicker than a lot of players half my age. As a new player its technique that&#8217;s my issue, but I can fix that.  I&#8217;m not looking to compete on the ATP tour so with respect I&#8217;ll ignore your comments and keep playing, doing my best to prove you wrong.   I&#8217;m also assuming that you don&#8217;t coach and take the money from older clients that you know will never be any good.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		Comment on What Gym Exercises Will Improve My Tennis Serve? by Phil		</title>
		<link>/what-gym-exercises-will-improve-my-tennis-serve/#comment-1101</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 23 Aug 2022 02:58:53 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=2023#comment-1101</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I like the article and I will try this with a positive approach.
I am 69 and a bit heavy but I still play singles. Years back I beat the number one 4.5 singles player in USTA regionals so at best I was a so so 5.0 player but mostly 4.5 and at my age now a 4.0. I am tall (6&#039;3&quot; ) and I used to hit a 108 mph serve. I struggle to reach 80 mph now. Some older and shorter players hit bigger serves so I am a little annoyed.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I like the article and I will try this with a positive approach.<br />
I am 69 and a bit heavy but I still play singles. Years back I beat the number one 4.5 singles player in USTA regionals so at best I was a so so 5.0 player but mostly 4.5 and at my age now a 4.0. I am tall (6&#8217;3&#8243; ) and I used to hit a 108 mph serve. I struggle to reach 80 mph now. Some older and shorter players hit bigger serves so I am a little annoyed.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		Comment on Why Did The Serve And Volley Die Out? by Hoster		</title>
		<link>/why-did-serve-and-volley-die-out/#comment-822</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Hoster]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 05 Apr 2022 21:20:28 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=308#comment-822</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[What&#039;s next?  Ban one-handed backhand? :-)]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>What&#8217;s next?  Ban one-handed backhand? 🙂</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		Comment on 9 Plyometric Exercises For Explosive Tennis by Adrian		</title>
		<link>/9-plyometric-exercises-for-explosive-tennis/#comment-812</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Adrian]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 12 Mar 2022 06:56:26 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=636#comment-812</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[How’s it going? Great exercises which I’ve started incorporating into my workouts. I started the medicine ball throws and did 10 reps each variation, soon afterwards my left side of my back started aching, this was Thursday it’s now Saturday and it doesn’t feel like normal lower back pain, feels more internal. Is there a chance my core got overworked or twisted or something?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>How’s it going? Great exercises which I’ve started incorporating into my workouts. I started the medicine ball throws and did 10 reps each variation, soon afterwards my left side of my back started aching, this was Thursday it’s now Saturday and it doesn’t feel like normal lower back pain, feels more internal. Is there a chance my core got overworked or twisted or something?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		Comment on 10 Fun Tennis Drills You Can Practice Without A Court by Craig		</title>
		<link>/10-tennis-drills-you-can-practice-without-a-court/#comment-806</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Craig]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 16 Feb 2022 08:57:37 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=585#comment-806</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Thanks Chad for this - I posted a comment in response to another of your articles about plateu-ing... I think the above will help with my question there.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Thanks Chad for this &#8211; I posted a comment in response to another of your articles about plateu-ing&#8230; I think the above will help with my question there.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		Comment on How To Overcome A Plateau In Tennis by craig		</title>
		<link>/how-to-overcome-a-plateau-in-tennis/#comment-805</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[craig]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 16 Feb 2022 08:39:08 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1993#comment-805</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Hi - thanks for this article. Did the sprint session this morning :)

I am exactly as you mention here. Plateau&#039;d after 1.5yrs playing at average club level; and frankly really frustrated. For me the worst thing is losing technique. You briefly mentioned at the end there about consistently maintaining skills; but I&#039;ve been focusing on backhand for couple months and now can no longer seem to hit good forehand; or my serve flow/groove has just gone - not only flagging; but literally have lost it. Makes me want to quit. Do you have any tips on this for someone who does not have 2hrs/day to keep training all strokes? Some days I honestly feel like I am playing about the same as I was 1.5yrs ago!]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Hi &#8211; thanks for this article. Did the sprint session this morning 🙂</p>
<p>I am exactly as you mention here. Plateau&#8217;d after 1.5yrs playing at average club level; and frankly really frustrated. For me the worst thing is losing technique. You briefly mentioned at the end there about consistently maintaining skills; but I&#8217;ve been focusing on backhand for couple months and now can no longer seem to hit good forehand; or my serve flow/groove has just gone &#8211; not only flagging; but literally have lost it. Makes me want to quit. Do you have any tips on this for someone who does not have 2hrs/day to keep training all strokes? Some days I honestly feel like I am playing about the same as I was 1.5yrs ago!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		Comment on 7 Volley Types You Must Know To Master Your Net Game by Mary		</title>
		<link>/seven-volley-types-you-must-know-to-master-your-net-game/#comment-798</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Mary]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 06 Feb 2022 04:48:02 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=52#comment-798</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Excellent tips on mastering the net w/different volleys! Thank you!!!]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Excellent tips on mastering the net w/different volleys! Thank you!!!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		Comment on How Does A Tennis Tie-Break Work? by Ahmer		</title>
		<link>/how-does-a-tennis-tie-break-work/#comment-791</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ahmer]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 30 Jan 2022 23:36:27 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1575#comment-791</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[This is great article. Just missing side change rules for doubles. I’ve seen side changes on 1, 5, 9,… (every four points). What’s the definitive format for side change in doubles?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This is great article. Just missing side change rules for doubles. I’ve seen side changes on 1, 5, 9,… (every four points). What’s the definitive format for side change in doubles?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
